<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:x="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:exsl="http://exslt.org/common" xml:id="Paper-417">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Towards a Semantic Network of Dante’s Works and Their Contextual Knowledge</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Tavoni</surname>, <forename>Mirko</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Dipartimento di Filologia, Letteratura e Linguistica, Università di Pisa</affiliation>
          <email>mirko.tavoni@gmail.com</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Andriani</surname>, <forename>Paola</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Dipartimento di Filologia, Letteratura e Linguistica, Università di Pisa</affiliation>
          <email>paola.andriani@gmail.com</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Bartalesi</surname>, <forename>Valentina</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>ISTI-CNR</affiliation>
          <email>valentina.bartalesi@isti.cnr.it</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Locuratolo</surname>, <forename>Elvira</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>ISTI-CNR</affiliation>
          <email>elvira.locuratolo@isti.cnr.it</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Meghini</surname>, <forename>Carlo</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>ISTI-CNR</affiliation>
          <email>carlo.meghini@isti.cnr.it</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Versienti</surname>, <forename>Loredana</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>ISTI-CNR</affiliation>
          <email>loredana.versienti@isti.cnr.it</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
        <publisher>EPFL, Switzerland</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>EPFL Digital Humanities Laboratory</name>
          <address>
            <addrLine>GC D2 386</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Station 18</addrLine>
            <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
            <addrLine>frederic.kaplan@epfl.ch</addrLine>
          </address>
        </distributor>
        <pubPlace>Lausanne, Switzerland</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>EPFL</addrLine>
          <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="abstract">We present the “Towards a Digital Dante Encyclopedia” project, a three years Italian National Research Project, that aims at building a prototypical digital library endowed with services supporting scholars in creating, evolving and consulting a digital encyclopedia of Dante Alighieri and of his works.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
        <p>
          <date when="20140709"/>
          <time when="09:00:00"/>
        </p>
		<p n="session">1</p>
		<p n="room">415 - Amphimax</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
          <term>Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
          <term>Short Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
          <term>Digital Dante Alighieri Encyclopedia</term>
          <term>Knowledge Representation</term>
          <term>Semantic Network</term>
          <term>RDF</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
          <term>software studies</term>
          <term>computer applications in literary</term>
          <term>the creation of humanities digital resources</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="paper">
    <front>
      
      <div>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>1. Introduction</head>
        
        <p>In the field of digital humanities, scholars
are increasingly producing digital editions of texts and manuscripts. The
representation of knowledge included in literary texts is a complex issue,
requiring rich vocabularies, also called ontologies, for representing the many
different aspects that are investigated by scholars. In literature, there are many ontologies that
focus on different aspects of textual information but one single ontology representing all these aspects does
not exist.</p>
        <p>The “Towards a Digital Dante Encyclopedia” project
is a three years Italian National Research Project, started in 2012, that aims
at building a prototypical digital library endowed with services supporting
scholars in creating, evolving and consulting a digital encyclopedia of Dante
Alighieri and of his works. The digital library is based on a semantic
representation of Dante’s works and of the knowledge embedded in them in RDF
language <ref target="n1" rend="sup">1</ref>, a language recommended by the Web Consortium
for the representation of knowledge. In RDF, every piece of knowledge is
represented as a triple (subject predicate object), and a set of triples form
an RDF graph, generally called semantic network, in order to highlight the formal linguistic nature of the
representation. The services being developed address several tasks carried out
by the scholars building the encyclopedia, starting with the visualization of
references to primary sources (i.e., other authors’ works which Dante referred to his own works), their
types and their distribution both in time and in the works of Dante. The
overall goal is to shed light into the cultural context in which Dante wrote
his works and into the development of Dante’s reference library over time.</p>
        <p>This part of the project is divided in several
phases. The first phase regards the creation of an ontology for the knowledge
embedded in scholarly commentaries to Convivio <ref target="n2" rend="sup">2</ref>, the philosophical treatise which we choose
as initial case study. In the second phase, the ontological model is
generalized to represent the knowledge embedded in the scholarly commentaries
to other Dante’s works. In the third phase, Dante’s works along with their
attached commentaries are inserted into the digital library, as part of the
semantic network being built. In the fourth phase, the primary sources referenced
by Dante in his works, as reported by the commentaries, are inserted into the digital
library, following the same semantic approach. In the last phase, services are
developed, as web applications that allow scholars to browse the semantic
network of Dante’s work, of primary sources, or of references linking the
former to the latter. The references will be visualized in an intuitive way
through tables and charts, highlighting their distribution in Dante’s work and
over time.</p>
        <p>We present the structure of the semantic
network, as it currently stands and indicate how it will be further developed. Furthermore, we highlight the
benefits brought by the visualization service of primary sources to scholars.</p>
        
        <head>2. <hi rend="bold">Ontology for the representation of <hi rend="italic">convivio</hi></hi></head>
        
        <p>In order to detect the primary
sources used by Dante to write his Convivio,
we relied on the most recent and updated commentary to the text, that of Gianfranco Fioravanti (Mondadori, in the
press), and created an ontology for representing
the relevant knowledge carried by this commentary. In particular, our ontology
represents:</p>
        
        <list type="unordered">
          <item>the passage of Dante’s
text (e.g., “Sì come dice lo Filosofo nel principio della Prima Filosofia”) to
which a quotation from a source refers;</item>
          <item>the correspondent
book, chapter and paragraph of Dante’s text</item>
          <item>the author of the work
referenced in the commentary (e.g.,
Aristotle);</item>
          <item>the title of the work
referenced in the commentary (e.g., Metaphysics);</item>
          <item>the thematic area of
the work referenced in the commentary (e.g.,
Aristotelianism).</item>
        </list>
        
        <p>In order to create an ontology
for the semantic representation of the above information, we investigated
several existing ontologies (e.g. CIDOC-CRM <ref target="n3" rend="sup">3</ref>, FRBR <ref target="n4" rend="sup">4</ref> ,
FaBiO <ref target="n5" rend="sup">5</ref>, SKOS <ref target="n6" rend="sup">6</ref>), and we chose the classes and properties that we
considered the most appropriate to represent the above information. Furthermore,
we added our own classes and properties for the representation of the categories
of knowledge that were not addressed by the existing ontologies. Then, we
transformed the initial commentary into an RDF graph structured according to
the ontology <ref target="n7" rend="sup">7</ref>.</p>
        <p>On the basis of our ontology, we
are approaching the remaining phases of the “Towards a Digital Dante
Encyclopedia” project. To such aim, we are using the ontology developed so far in order to represent
other works of Dante (e.g. <hi rend="italic">De Vulgari Eloquentia</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Monarchia</hi>) as well as the knowledge carried by
commentaries to them. At the same time, we are collecting the primary sources
of Dante’s work in a digital format, for insertion into the semantic network
underlying the digital library. Our diachronic analysis, in fact, aims at
representing the evolution of Dante’s knowledge about primary sources.</p>
        
        <head>3. <hi rend="bold">The model population</hi></head>
        <p>In order to enrich our RDF graph, as we have
done for Convivio, we are collecting information for other
Dante’s works. In particular we are focusing on (i) the text of the work along
with the attached commentaries; (ii) the primary sources referenced in the
notes. We are currently storing the RDF triples generated according to our ontology
both for the notes and the primary sources. We are relying on the Virtuoso [8] technology for storing and accessing large RDF
graphs.</p>
        <p>It is important to note that the works of
Dante, as well as most of their primary sources, exist in some digital format. However, to the best of our knowledge, there is no
semantic representation that integrates this information
into a unique body of knowledge, expressed through a formal ontology. We do not expect the knowledge base that we build to give a coherent
view of Dante’s works. The knowledge in it may, and in general will be
incoherent and incomplete, and our ontology is flexible enough to allow both.</p>
        <p>

The creation of the semantic network is a very
time-consuming and knowledge-intensive process. It requires researching the
most appropriate ontologies for representing all aspects, and in several cases
it requires developing a new ontology to fill the gaps of existing ones. Once
the ontology is created, the works of Dante, the primary sources, and the knowledge
embedded in them will have to be expressed in this ontology, and this is also a
technically demanding task. But the benefits are enormous. The digital representation of
the knowledge can support scholars in several conceptually simple but time-consuming
tasks, allowing them to focus on the more intellectual aspects of their work.
The semantic network will be usable for a wide variety of purposes, which go
well beyond the specific services built by our project. It will constitute a
backbone that can be enriched with other knowledge about Dante and the
historical events, people, artistic movements, etc. that have come across Dante
and as such contribute to form the context in which Dante’s life and art took
place. In this sense, creating the semantic network is the most important
achievement of our project. Our project will build only one part of this network,
but will also lay the bases for the extensions and enrichments that will
complete what we have started.</p>
        <head>4. <hi rend="bold">Why this unified archive will be important tu study the culture of Dante</hi></head>
        <p>The importance of the archive and tools described above in order to
study how the culture of Dante developed in time is obvious. The fact of gathering the
current information on the primary sources used by Dante in his works, and the
fact of having this information available in digital format, will improve and
make more efficient the research of primary sources by the scholars. Having
all the information dispersed on paper books, in fact, makes impossible a
systematic overview of the culture of Dante and a well-ordered perception of
how it was gradually set up in time. On the contrary, the automatic visualization of data about primary
resources, according to different parameters (in chronological order, or by
type of source, or by author, by work, etc.), will allow to explore the
dynamics of the multi-faceted culture of Dante in relation to the diverse and
often conflicting stages of his biography and to study the evolution in time of
Dante’s cultural background.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="References">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>1. <hi rend="bold">Manola F., Miller, E.</hi> (2004). <hi rend="italic">RDF Primer</hi>. W3C Recommendation 10 February 2004. Available at: <ref type="url" target="http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-primer/">www.w3.org/TR/rdf-primer/</ref>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>2. <hi rend="bold">Alighieri, Dante</hi>. (1987). <hi rend="italic">Convivio</hi>, a c. di P. Cudini, Milano, Garzanti
          </bibl>
          <bibl>3. <hi rend="bold">Doerr, M.</hi> (2003). <hi rend="italic">The CIDOC CRM - an ontological approach to semantic interoperability of metadata</hi>. AI Magazine, vol. 24(3), 75-92
          </bibl>
          <bibl>4. <hi rend="bold">Tillett, B.</hi> (2004). <hi rend="italic">What is FRBR? A conceptual model for the bibliographic universe</hi>. Library of Congress Cataloging Distribution Service, vol. 25(5), 1-8.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>5. <hi rend="bold">Peroni, S., and Shotton, D.</hi> (2012). <hi rend="italic">FaBiO and CiTO: Ontologies for describing bibliographic resources and citations.</hi> J. Web Semantics: Science, Services and Agents on the World Wide Web.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>6. <hi rend="bold">Alistair, M., Matthews, B., Wilson M., amd Brickley, D.</hi> (2005). <hi rend="italic">SKOS Core: Simple knowledge organisation for the Web</hi>. In Proceedings of Dublin Core Conference.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>7. <hi rend="bold">Bartalesi, V., Meghini, C., Locuratolo, E., Versienti, L.</hi> (2013). <hi rend="italic">A preliminary study on the semantic representation of the notes to Dante Alighieri's Convivio.</hi> In Proceedings of the 1st International Workshop on Collaborative Annotations in Shared Environment: metadata, vocabularies and techniques in the Digital Humanities (DH-CASE '13). ACM, New York, NY, USA.
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
