<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:x="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:exsl="http://exslt.org/common" xml:id="Paper-925">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Active Authentication through Psychometrics</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Noecker Jr</surname>, <forename>John</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Juola &amp; Associates, United States of America </affiliation>
          <email></email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
        <publisher>EPFL, Switzerland</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>EPFL Digital Humanities Laboratory</name>
          <address>
            <addrLine>GC D2 386</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Station 18</addrLine>
            <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
            <addrLine>frederic.kaplan@epfl.ch</addrLine>
          </address>
        </distributor>
        <pubPlace>Lausanne, Switzerland</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>EPFL</addrLine>
          <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="abstract">In this article, we examine the application of computational stylometry to psychological profiling. We adapt several techniques which have proven useful for author identification to the problem of predicting various aspects of a user’s personality. In previous work, we were able to identify the user’s Myers-Briggs Type Indicator (MBTI) by analyzing an essay written by that user. Here, we adapt the MBTI prediction system to work by analyzing a user’s computer usage instead. We also introduce systems to predict the user’s most preferential Multiple Intelligences Developmental Assessment Scales (MIDAS) subcategories.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
        <p>
          <date when="20140711"/>
          <time when="09:00:00"/>
        </p>
		<p n="session">6</p>
		<p n="room">315 - Amphipôle</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
          <term>Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
          <term>Short Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
          <term>Psychological profiling</term>
          <term>stylometry</term>
          <term>active authentication</term>
          <term>computer security</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="paper">
    <front>
      
      <div>
        <p></p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        
        <p>What can your computer habits reveal about you?  The answer might surprise you.  Previous work (Juola, et al., 2013) has shown that just a few
minutes of computer usage can be used to identify who is at the keyboard and
their demographic and psychological attributes with a fairly high degree of
accuracy.  We expand upon this to show
that the same usage data can be used to thoroughly profile a previously-unknown
user to obtain valuable psychological information about the user.</p>
        <p>

Authorship attribution, the analysis of a document’s writing
style to infer the author’s identity, is a well-established problem in text
classification.  Previously, we used
classical authorship attribution techniques to identify “who was at the
keyboard” using the DARPA Active Authentication Corpus (Juola et al, 2013).  Researchers have successfully applied the
analysis of language usage to infer authorship of written documents (Juola,
2006. Koppel et al, 2009. Stamatatos,
2009. Jockers &amp; Witten, 2010), and stylometric analysis has also been
applied to things like gender (Argamon et al, 2006), personality (Luyckx &amp; Daelemans, 2008),
and even psychological disorders like depression (Rude et al, 2004).</p>
        <p>Here, we attempt to perform the same technique with groups
composed of individuals who share common psychological traits.  Previous work (Luyckx &amp;
Daelemans, 2008. Noecker &amp; Juola, 2013) on personality profiling has so far
focused on analyzing previously-written documents.  In contrast, our system provides a method for
real-time psychological profiling of a user based on his or her interactions
with a computer over a relatively short period of time (approximately 30
minutes).  The ultimate goal is two-fold:
to learn something about a previously-unobserved user (traditional stylometric
identification techniques require us to have training data on a user before we
can identify him) and to use psychological traits as an enhancement to current
user authentication methods.</p>
        <p>Currently, exact accuracy on the user-based authentication
is approximately 90%.  This task becomes
more difficult (and the accuracy becomes correspondingly lower) as the pool of
potential author models grows.  In order
to improve overall accuracy of the user authentication task, we propose to
include these psychological profiling tools in the authentication system.  If a given user can be identified as the most
likely candidate with 90% probability, and several facets of that user’s
personality can be confirmed with similarly high confidence, this will increase
the overall robustness of the authentication system.</p>
        <p>For our purposes, we used two personality/intelligence
measurement systems to profile users: Myers-Briggs Type Indicator (MBTI) and Multiple
Intelligences Developmental Assessment Scales (MIDAS).</p>
        <p>The Myers-Briggs type indicator (MBTI) assigns four binary
classifications to define personality (Myers &amp; Myers, 1980)

</p>
        <list type="unordered">
          <item>Extroversion
     vs Introversion</item>
          <item>iNtuition
     vs Sensing</item>
          <item>Thinking
     vs Feeling</item>
          <item>Judgement
     vs Perception</item>
        </list>
        <p>
The Multiple Intelligences Developmental Assessment Scales
(MIDAS) were developed by Dr. Howard Gardner in his 1983 book “Frames of Mind”
(Gardner, 1983).  He used a unique
definition of intelligence: “The ability to solve a problem or create a product
that is valued within one or more cultures” (MI Research and
Consulting).  He identified 8 primary
intelligent scales, each of which have several subscales (MI
Research and Consulting):

 

</p>
        <list type="unordered">
          <item>
            Musical
            <list type="unordered">
              <item>
                Vocal Ability
              </item>
              <item>
                Instrumental Skill
              </item>
              <item>
                Composer
              </item>
              <item>
                Appreciation
              </item>
            </list>
          </item>
          <item>
            Kinesthetic
            <list type="unordered">
              <item>
                Athletics
              </item>
              <item>
                Dexterity 
              </item>
            </list>
          </item>
          <item>
            Logical-Mathematical

            <list type="unordered">
              <item>
                Everyday Math 
              </item>
              <item>
                School Math 
              </item>
              <item>
                Everyday Problem Solving 
              </item>
              <item>
                Strategy Games 
              </item>
            </list>
          </item>
          <item>
            Spatial 
            <list type="unordered">
              <item>
                Space Awareness 
              </item>
              <item>
                Working with Objects
              </item>
              <item>
                Artistic Design 
              </item>
            </list>
          </item>
          <item>
            Linguistic

            <list type="unordered">
              <item>
                Expressive Sensitivity
              </item>
              <item>
                Rhetorical Skill
              </item>
              <item>
                Written-academic
              </item>
            </list>
          </item>
          <item>
            Interpersonal
            <list type="unordered">
              <item>
                Social Sensitivity
              </item>
              <item>
                Social Persuasion
              </item>
              <item>
                Interpersonal Work
              </item>
            </list>
          </item>
          <item>
            Intrapersonal
            <list type="unordered">
              <item>
                Personal Knowledge / Efficacy
              </item>
              <item>
                Effectiveness
              </item>
              <item>
                Calculations
              </item>
              <item>
                Spatial Problem Solving
              </item>
            </list>
          </item>
          <item>
            Naturalist
            <list type="unordered">
              <item>
                Animal Care 
              </item>
              <item>
                Plant Care 
              </item>
            </list>
          </item>
        </list>
        <p>We also include a 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> main scale, <hi rend="italic">Leadership</hi>, with its own subscales: <hi rend="italic">Communication, Management, and Social.</hi></p>
        <head>
          <hi rend="bold">Materials and Methods</hi>
        </head>
        <head>Corpus</head>
        <p>

 
In order to create the most accurate corpus possible, we set
up a simulated office environment and hired 80 temporary workers for one week
each.  Workers were tasked to perform a
long-term blogging project (research and write blog articles on topics “related
to Pittsburgh in some way”) over the course of a normal workweek.  For this study, we use the Free Key Logger
output, which provides the exact text typed by each user.  We do not include any information about the
applications being used or any data the user pastes from the clipboard.</p>
        <head>Feature Extraction</head>
        <p>

For our analysis, we used the Java Graphical Authorship
Attribution Program (JGAAP) (Juola et al, 2009).  JGAAP is a
Java-based, modular program for textual analysis, text categorization, and
authorship attribution.  It provides a
comprehensive framework, allowing us to rapidly test the effectiveness of
different analysis techniques on the recorded data.</p>
        <p>JGAAP divides analysis into several steps: Canonicization
(Preprocessing), Event Set (Feature) Generation, and Analysis.  In Canonicization, preprocessors are used to
standardize the text.  For this step, we
converted all input letters to lower case (“Unify Case”) and converted all
strings of whitespace characters into a single space character (“Normalize
Whitespace”).  At this stage, we also
processed a variety of special keyboard characters, converting these
non-printable characters into a printable placeholder (e.g. “backspace” was
replaced with “β”). 
Finally, we divided the input data into blocks of 1,000 characters, representing
about 30 minutes of computer usage.</p>
        <p>For the event set generation, we tested character N-grams
for all N from 1 to 15, and word N-grams for N from 1 to 5.  We then applied a number of analysis methods
for each experiment: Cosine Distance, Intersection Distance, Manhattan
Distance, and Matusita Distance.  For
each method, we used a centroid-based nearest neighbor classifier.  We performed leave-one-out cross-validation
to reach our final conclusion.</p>
        <head>Models</head>
        <p>For the MBTI classifiers, we built four binary classifiers
(i.e. E vs I, N vs S, T vs F, and J vs P). 
For the MIDAS classifiers, we first built a single 9-way classifier to
identify a user’s principle main scale.  This
was the scale along which the user scored highest (i.e. the scale for which the
user showed the highest preference).  For
example, a user might have a preference for “Musical” or “Linguistic”.  We also developed subscale classifiers, which
identify a user’s preference within each major scale.  For instance, a user might be identified as
“(Musical) Vocal Ability” and “(Kinesthetic) Dexterity”, etc.  Thus, each user was identified by a single
main scale preference as well as nine subscale preferences.

 

</p>
        <head>
          <hi rend="bold">Results</hi>
        </head>
        <head>MBTI</head>
        <p>For the MBTI classifiers, we averaged an accuracy of
81.5%.  The expected baseline average
(assuming we pick the most prevalent personality type for each category) is
55%. </p>
        <head>MIDAS</head>
        <p>For the MIDAS main category identification, our best
performing classifier had accuracy of 70.7%. 
This was using character 15 grams with Intersection Distance.  The expected baseline accuracy (achieved by
choosing the most common main scale, “Linguistic”) was 22.1%.</p>
        <p>For the MIDAS subscale identification, the best performing
classifiers used a variety of Character n-grams, again with Intersection
Distance as the top performing analysis method. 
The average subscale accuracy was 81%.</p>
        <head>
          <hi rend="bold">Conclusion</hi>
        </head>
        <p>We have shown here a method to reliably psychologically
profile a computer user based on only a short period (about 30 minutes) of
usage time.  In addition to providing
valuable information about the user in question, this method can also be used
to provide additional layers of security for the active authentication system
we have described previously.  Even in an
adversarial situation, the difficulty of imitating both an individual user’s
style, as well as mimicking the psychological profile of the user, will provide
additional security to the authentication system.</p>
        <p>Also interesting to note is the limited usage data required
to perform these analyses.  The initial
user psychological testing period took approximately 3 hours, but accurate
results were obtained for only 30 minutes of computer usage.  In addition, the three hours of testing were
completely lost time – the users were able to work only on the tests during
this time.  In contrast, the 30 minutes
of analysis can be done on whatever the user is working on at the time.  No downtime is required to perform these
analyses.  We believe this system could
be useful anywhere a non-intrusive analysis of a user might be beneficial (e.g. determining whether a potential
employee would be a good fit).</p>
        <p>For future work, we intend to focus on reducing the amount
of data needed even further.  Preliminary
results on as little as 500 characters (about 15 minutes of usage time) have
been promising.  Additional work is also
being done to integrate these methods into the broader active authentication
system in order to bolster the overall reliability of the system.</p>
    
       
       
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="References">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Argamon, S., Koppel, M., Fine, J., Shimoni, A. R</hi> (2006). <hi rend="italic">“Gender,
            Genre, and Writing Style in Formal Written Texts”. </hi>Interdisciplinary Journal for the Study of Discourse. Volume 23.
            Issue 3. pp. 321-346.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="italic">“Broad Agency Announcement: Active Authentication”.</hi> (2012). <hi rend="italic">DARPA.
            Solicitation No. DARPA-BAA-12-06</hi>. 12 Jan. 2012. &lt;http://www.fbo.gov/index?tab=documents&amp;t
            abmode=form&amp;subtab=core&amp;tabid=494b6b2c612c4 fd3db6cb018d4467e21&gt;.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Gardner, Howard</hi> (1983). <hi rend="italic">“Frames of Mind: The Theory of Multiple
            Intelligences”.</hi>  Basic Books.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Jockers, M. L., Witten, D.</hi> (2010) “<hi rend="italic">A Comparative Study of Machine
            Learning Methods for Authorship Attribution”.</hi>Literary and Linguistic
            Computing, vol. 25, no. 2. pp. 215–23.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Juola, P. </hi>(2006) <hi rend="italic">“Authorship Attribution”.</hi>Foundations and
            Trends in Information Retrieval, vol. 1, no. 3.  pp. 233–334.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Juola, Patrick, Noecker Jr., John, Ryan, Mike, Speer, Sandy </hi>(2009).</hi>
            “JGAAP 4.0 – A Revised Authorship Attribution Tool”. Proc. Digital Humanities 2009. pp. 357–359. Maryland Insitute. for
            Technology in the Humanities. University of Maryland.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Juola, Patrick, Noecker Jr., John, Stolerman, Ariel, Ryan,
            Michael, Brennan, Patrick, Greenstadt, Rachel </hi>(2013). <hi rend="italic">"Keyboard Behavior Based
              Authentication for Security"</hi>. IT Professional. 18 June 2013.
            IEEE computer Society Digital Library. IEEE Computer Society.
            &lt;http://doi.ieeecomputersociety.org/10.1109/MITP.2013.49&gt;.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Koppel, M., Schler, J., Argamon, S. </hi>(2009)<hi rend="italic">“Computational Methods
            in Authorship Attribution”. </hi>J. Amer. Soc. Information Science and Technology,
            vol. 60, no. 1. pp. 9–26.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Luyckx, K., Daelemans, W. </hi>(2008) <hi rend="italic">“Personae, a Corpus for Author and
            Personality Prediction from Text”.</hi>Proceedings
            of the Sixth International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation.
            Marrakech, Morroco.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">MI Research and Consulting, Inc</hi>. <hi rend="italic">“Multiple Intelligences
            Theory”. </hi> &lt;www.miresearch.org/mi_theory.html&gt;.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Myers I B, Myers P.</hi> (1980)<hi rend="italic">“Gifts Differing: Understanding
            Personality Type”. </hi>Palo Alto, CA. Consulting Psychologists Press.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Noecker Jr., J. Juola, P. </hi>(2013)<hi rend="italic"> “Psychological Profiling Through
            Textual Analysis”. </hi>Literary and Linguist
            Computing.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Rude, S., Gortner, E., Pennebaker, J. </hi>(2004) <hi rend="italic">“Language Use of
            Depressed and Depression-Vulnerable College Students”.</hi>Cognition and Emotion.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Stamatatos, E</hi>. (2009) <hi rend="italic">“A Survey of Modern Authorship Attribution
            Methods”</hi>. J. Amer. Soc. Information Science and Technology, vol. 60, no.
            3. pp. 538–556.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Zheng, N., Paloski, A., Wang, H. </hi>(2011) <hi rend="italic">“An Efficient User
            Verification System via Mouse Movements,”</hi>Proc. 18th ACM Conf. Computer and
            Communications Security (CCS 11). ACM. pp. 139–150.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
