<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:x="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:exsl="http://exslt.org/common" xml:id="Paper-472">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Cryptic Novel:  A Computational Taxonomy of the Eighteenth-Century Literary Field</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Algee-Hewitt</surname>, <forename>Mark</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
          <email>mark.algee-hewitt@stanford.edu</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Eidem</surname>, <forename>Laura</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
          <email>lmeidem@stanford.edu</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Heuser</surname>, <forename>Ryan</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
          <email>heuser@stanford.edu</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Law</surname>, <forename>Anita</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
          <email>anital@stanford.edu</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Llewellyn</surname>, <forename>Tanya</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Stanford University</affiliation>
          <email>tanya.llewellyn@gmail.com</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
        <publisher>EPFL, Switzerland</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>EPFL Digital Humanities Laboratory</name>
          <address>
            <addrLine>GC D2 386</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Station 18</addrLine>
            <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
            <addrLine>frederic.kaplan@epfl.ch</addrLine>
          </address>
        </distributor>
        <pubPlace>Lausanne, Switzerland</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>EPFL</addrLine>
          <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="abstract">This in this paper we present a project that uses machine learning and classification techniques to assess the underlying structure of fictional literature in the eighteenth century and to relate this structure to a taxonomic system based on genre labels in titles.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
        <p>
          <date when="20140711"/>
          <time when="14:00:00"/>
        </p>
		<p n="session">8</p>
		<p n="room">319 - Amphipôle</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
          <term>Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
          <term>Long Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
          <term>novels</term>
          <term>classification</term>
          <term>quantitative analysis</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
          <term>content analysis</term>
          <term>data mining</term>
          <term>data modeling</term>
          <term>English studies</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="paper">
    <front>
      
      <div>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        
        <head>Overview

 

</head>
        <p>This
project employs machine learning and other text-mining based clustering
techniques to study the relationship between taxonomic systems for categorizing
prose fiction in the eighteenth century. Our goal is to challenge narratives of
the so-called “rise” of the novel (Watt, 1957<ref target="n1" rend="sup">1</ref>; McKeon, 1987<ref target="n2" rend="sup">2</ref>; Richetti 1999<ref target="n3" rend="sup">3</ref>)
that trace a continuity between the prose fiction that emerged in the
eighteenth-century and the novel as a fully realized critical object in the
late nineteenth century. Our project instead uses statistical modeling methods
to theorize an alternate history for the novel: not, as proposed in Franco
Moretti’s Graphs, Maps, Trees<ref target="n4" rend="sup">4</ref>, as a history of genres, but instead as a
history of genre labels--that is, a history formed by the interaction between
paratextual, self-identified literary labels that circulated in the
eighteenth-century marketplace and the texts that they defined. Our project,
which is currently in its final stages at Stanford University’s Literary Lab,
bridges the historical and computational to enact a form of literary history
that puts pressure on traditional theories focused on charting the rise of the
novel. The project is deeply invested in using digital and statistical methods
to excavate the nuances in the ways in which eighteenth-century genres evolved.
Instead of analyzing texts via contemporary genre categorizations, we recover
the relationship between the self-applied taxonomy of eighteenth-century prose
fiction and the lexical and semantic features of the texts themselves to recuperate
a historically-determined literary field that has been largely overlooked (or
noted and elided) by modern criticism. Drawing from a corpus of 2,385 digitized
texts from the Eighteenth Century Collections Online (ECCO) database, we ask
how new computational methods can aid us in uncovering what kinds of work
self-identified genre labels in titles (specifically “story,” “history,”
“tale,” “letters,” “romance,” “life,” “adventure,” and “novel”) accomplished
within the literary marketplace of the long eighteenth-century, and how that
kind of work is distinct from critically- or retroactively-designated genres
(“gothic,” “jacobin,” “epistolary,” “historical,” “it-narrative,” “oriental
tale.”) </p>
        
        <head>Aims</head>
        <p>Our
project seeks to answer a series of critical questions about the taxonomic
systems of eighteenth-century fiction using computer generated models. Do
generic labels formally differentiate separate kinds of writing in a useful way
(such that a “novel” is lexically, semantically or formally different from a “romance”)
or do they merely function as signals within the marketplace itself, so that
there is no textual or formal differences between a “tale” or a “story” beyond
mere marketplace convention? How does the relationship between different genre
labels change over time, and how can it assist us in understanding the
evolution of titles as a representative labeling system? This approach takes
advantage of recent advances in probabilistic modeling to recover the meaning
of labels that have been homogeneously condensed under the rubric of novel; it
simplifies the complexity of the word “novel,” with all its attendant genres
and subgenres, to make the field that “novel” inhabits more complex. Developing
from these research questions, our method-driven aims are: (1) to detect and
assess large-scale trends in the development of and relation between genre
labels across time (2) to isolate formal differences in the corresponding full
texts identified under these categorical labels, and (3) to compare these
differences to a corpus of texts categorized according to modern genre
designations. </p>
        
        <head>Methods
and Narrative 

 

</head>
        <p>In
the early stages of our project, we began with an exploratory approach to our
data, using statistical, unsupervised learning techniques to identify word patterns
and clusters within the texts, prior to classifying the texts’ content onto the
label categories. Our initial approach sought to determine if some underlying
structure existed among these texts that we could then map onto a taxonomic
system, such as genre, or in our case, title labels. Using a series of
clustering techniques built off of different feature sets (most frequent words,
most distinctive words, etc), we found that the assumptions that provided the
foundation for our project were vindicated: not only did the titles under each
label cluster together based on the Most Frequent Words in each text, but there
were intriguing differences between clusters. For instance, though a coherent
cluster of “history” is present from the first quarter of the century,
definitively clustered labels “novel” and “romance” don’t emerge until later in
the century. These differences opened our research to a new set of concerns,
such as the relative stability of each category, or the ways in which the
labels individually and collectively change across time. Indeed, a major
finding of this phase was the dramatic influence time itself had over every
other variable we considered. Such a finding strengthened the presence of a
literary-historical component of our research and prompted us to pay closer
attention to the divisions of time we were employing.</p>
        
        <p>In
our current work, we have employed supervised learning techniques and machine
classification to specifically interrogate the relationship between text and
label: which labels have a high level of cohesion, and thus predictability, and
which labels are less cohesive, and were perhaps more tolerant of formal
deviation and experimentation? To answer this question, we employed a
discriminant function analysis to determine if texts could be reliably
algorithmically classified into their labels, treated in our analysis as a
taxonomic system. These results were validated through a leave-one-out cross
validation to determine the strength of our predictive model. . The results confirmed
the findings of the PCA: our model performed better than chance, categorizing
each of our labels, on average, 75% correctly. Another dimension of our study
was to investigate differences on a label-by-label basis: what does it mean,
textually, that a “life” is harder to algorithmically classify than a
“romance”? Did difficulties in categorization have anything to do with the
textual heterogeneity within the labels themselves? These questions prompted us
toward another set of analyses designed to evaluate the self-similarity of each
label. We divided each text in our corpus into ten equal parts, measuring the
distance from each part to the other in a matrix that, when averaged, resulted
in a distance score for each. The findings from this activity helped to both
clarify and complicate the story that was emerging regarding labels over the
course of the century.</p>
        
        <p>Our
most recent work has taken us in a more broadly comparative direction: to
examine the textual and larger structural differences between our current
corpus of texts, classified according to generic labels, and another corpus we
have compiled from modern, genre-focused bibliographies. Using the same
techniques of machine learning and self-similarity, we have started to
interrogate the logics by which generic labels organize and describe the
literary field of the eighteenth century in ways we have yet to discover.</p>
        
        <head>Results</head>
        <p>

 
Our
initial results proved the value and worth of studying this type of paratextual
literary categorization. The temporalization of data allowed by our method lets
us observe, first, the simultaneous dominance and differentiation of “novel”
and “tale” at the end of the century, leading us to speculate, as Anthony
Jarrells (2012)<ref target="n5" rend="sup">5</ref> has, on twin “rises” of genre in this century as opposed to one
rise; that is, the eighteenth-century appears to be as much a story of the rise
of “novel” as it is of the rise of “tale.” The result of our machine learning
classifications and self-similarity form a compelling argument for the ways in
which, throughout the eighteenth-century, the field of prose fiction underwent
a transformation through the processes of both differentiation and
consolidation. From these results, we argue that the novel can be viewed as
merely one branch, rather than the single formal end to which all
eighteenth-century prose fiction trends. Other important results, observed from
our PCA charts, indicate a general movement across all generically-labelled
texts from the usage of words that indicate exteriority (such as “law,” “city,”
“army,” “money,” “order,” and “public”) to words that indicate interiority (such as
“lover,” “marry,” “imagine,” “woman,” “write” and “read”). In the final stages
of the project, we are working to apply similar computational tools to genres
conventionalized by modern criticism -- such as the Gothic novel or Oriental
tale -- to examine how such categorizations relate to self-applied genre
labels.  Preliminary results indicate that, after sampling our texts and
controlling for time period and author, generic labels classify with a success
rate comparable to texts designated as such by critics. The question then
becomes not whether genre labels organize more successfully than conventional
genres, but whether and how they organize differently--if generic labels can
tell us something about the trajectory and organization of formal literary
history that genre cannot. Our presentation will include a more detailed
discussion of our methods and results and of the implications of the latter for
traditional teleological narratives of eighteenth-century prose fiction</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="References">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>1. <hi rend="bold">Watt, Ian</hi> (1957). <hi rend="italic">The Rise of the Novel: Studies</hi> in Defoe, Richardson, Fielding. London: Chatto and Windus.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>2. <hi rend="bold">McKeon, Michael</hi> (1987). <hi rend="italic">The Origins of the English Novel: 1600-1740</hi>. Baltimore: Johns Hopkins UP
          </bibl>
          <bibl>3. <hi rend="bold">Richetti, John</hi> (1999). <hi rend="italic">The English Novel in History, 1700-1780</hi>. London: Routledge.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>4. <hi rend="bold">Moretti, Franco</hi> (2004). <hi rend="italic">Graphs, Maps, Trees: Abstract Models for Literary History</hi>. New York: Verso
          </bibl>
          <bibl>5. <hi rend="bold">Jarrells, Anthony</hi> (2012). <hi rend="italic">After Novels: Short Fictional Forms and the Rise of the Tale.</hi> The Oxford History of  the Novel in English. 12 vols. Vol. 2. Eds. Peter Garside and Karen O'Brien. Oxford: Oxford UP.
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
