
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>gMan: Creating General-Purpose Virtual Environments for (Digital) Archival
                    Research</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-198.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-198.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: gMan: Creating General-Purpose Virtual Environments for (Digital) Archival
                    Research</h2><h4>
                    Blanke, Tobias, 
                    Centre for e-Research, King’s College London, 
                    <a href="mailto:tobias.blanke@kcl.ac.uk">tobias.blanke@kcl.ac.uk</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Connor, Richard, 
                    University of Strathclyde, 
                    <a href="mailto:richard.connor@cis.strath.ac.uk">richard.connor@cis.strath.ac.uk</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Hedges, Mark, 
                    Centre for e-Research, King’s College London, 
                    <a href="mailto:mark.hedges@kcl.ac.uk">mark.hedges@kcl.ac.uk</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Kristel, Conny, 
                    Netherlands Institute for War Documentation (NIOD), 
                    <a href="mailto:c.kristel@niod.knaw.nl">c.kristel@niod.knaw.nl</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Priddy, Mike, 
                    Centre for e-Research, King’s College London, 
                    <a href="mailto:priddy@mac.com">priddy@mac.com</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Simenoni, Fabio, 
                    University of Strathclyde, 
                    <a href="mailto:fabio.simeoni@cis.strath.ac.uk">fabio.simeoni@cis.strath.ac.uk</a>
                </h4><hr />
            

                <p class="noindent">This paper will present a critical analysis of our attempts to build Virtual
                    Research Environments (VREs) for everyday Humanities research tasks using
                    digital archives. Numerous specialised VREs have been developed for addressing
                    particular tasks in various humanities disciplines. The Silchester VREs
                    addressed data integration in archaeological excavations, the SDM VRE developed
                    services for sharing and annotating manuscripts, while TEXTvre is concerned with
                    TEI-based resource creation. Building on these experiences, gMan addressed the
                    issue of moving beyond support for specific, focused tasks, and instead building
                    services to enable more general-purpose humanities research activities, such as
                    integrating and organising the heterogeneous and often unstructured digital
                    resources, and support for ‘active reading’ processesBrockman et al.
                        2001. Scholarly work in the humanities and the evolving information
                        environment. Washington, DC. through advanced discovery facilities.
                    Such services regularly top the list of humanities user
                        requirementsBenardou et al. 2009. Understanding the Information
                        Requirements of Arts and Humanities Scholarship. International Journal of
                        Digital Curation.. This paper describes work to this end, firstly by
                    the DARIAH project, and subsequently consolidated by the gMan project, funded by
                    JISC’s VRE Rapid Innovation programme.</p>
                <p class="noindent">These experiments were based on use cases identified by the earlier LaQuAT
                    (Linking and Querying Ancient Texts) projectJackson et al. 2009. Building
                        bridges between islands of data—an investigation into distributed data
                        management in the humanities. Proceedings of the Fifth IEEE International
                        Conference on e-Science. Washington, DC., which investigated how to
                    integrate scattered, heterogeneous and autonomous data resources relating to
                    ancient texts, mainly databases but also XML corpora. LaQuAT attempted to solve
                    these issues by offering an integration framework based on the OGSA-DAI grid
                    middleware, which provided an integrated interface to the various data resources
                    that followed a relational database model. However, this approach had certain
                    limitations for our purposes, as such models are optimised for dealing with
                    datacentric resources - that is, resources consisting primarily of structured
                    data such as numbers, dates or very short text fields - rather than text-centric
                    resources containing significant quantities of unstructured text. The approach
                    worked well where the structural context of the information was clear and the
                    query aimed at exact matches. More commonly, however, humanities researchers
                    work with text-centric resources, perhaps enhanced with XML mark-up to capture
                    document structure and additional metadataNentwich, M. 2003.
                        Cyberscience. research in the age of the internet. Vienna., and they
                    look for resources for further investigation based on looser criteria of
                    relevance, e.g. by searching for all Roman legal texts in one resource
                    containing information on punishments that are also mentioned in papyri from
                    another resource.</p>
                <p class="noindent">These conclusions were further elaborated in the use cases that were developed
                    from them, which are the main drivers for the work described here. Complementing
                    this is a body of methodological investigation concerning scholars and their use
                    of sources, particularly their use of data and archives. Before describing our
                    current work, we will survey briefly these investigations.</p>
                <p class="noindent">The difference in scholarly practices between the sciences and the mainstream
                    humanities is highlighted in a studyPalmer et al. 2009. Scholarly
                        information practices in the online environment. that investigated
                    the types of information sources used in different humanities disciplines, based
                    on results from the US Research Libraries Group reports. Structured data is
                    relatively little used, except in some areas of historical research, and data as
                    it is traditionally understood in the sciences, e.g. the results of
                    measurements, even less so. It is true that the study is partly outdated, and
                    that data in the traditional sense is increasingly important in the humanities,
                    particularly in linguistics and archaeology where scientific techniques have
                    been widely adopted. Nevertheless, it is clear that in general humanities
                    research relies not on measurements as a source of authority, but rather on the
                    provenance of sources and peer-assessment, and that what data repositories are
                    for the sciences, archives are for the humanitiesDuff et al. 2004
                        Historians’ use of archival sources: Promises and pitfalls of the digital
                        age. The Public Historian.. Archival records are primary sources
                    about the past and may take many forms, including government papers, financial
                    documents, photographs, sound recordings, etc. All this information is
                    unstructured in nature.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Thus, our work is driven partly by the requirements fromDuff et al. 2004
                        Historians’ use of archival sources: Promises and pitfalls of the digital
                        age. The Public Historian., interpreted so as to relate to methods of
                    research in archives. Retrieval is to happen in real time, and traditional
                    finding aids are to be complemented by more sophisticated retrieval mechanisms,
                    including the ability to create relevance indexes on unstructured resources, as
                    well as the ability to combine resources in new ways. In particular, we aimed to
                    implement the personal copy of a finding aid that is often quoted as an
                    important prerequisite for specialised research in archives.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Our work investigated how (digital) archival content can be delivered to
                    humanities researchers more effectively, independently of the location and
                    implementation of that content, and with special facilities provided for
                    customising the retrieval, management and manipulation of the content. We
                    investigated how the UK and European research infrastructure (RI) can be
                    exploited to support data-driven, collaborative research in the humanities by
                    using the gCube environmentCandela et al. 2009. On-demand Virtual
                        Research Environments and the Changing Roles of Librarians. Library Hi
                        Tech., which was developed by the EU-funded D4Science project. gCube
                    allows virtual research communities to deploy VREs on demand by making use of
                    the shared resources of the European RI, and provides services that match
                    closely the sort of information organisation and retrieval activities that we
                    identified as being typical in humanities research.</p>
                <p class="noindent">D4Science provides an easy way of scavenging online data resources. It has a
                    consistent mechanism to import data for rich user interaction within the
                    deployed VREs. Its data resource staging framework, based on a well-defined
                    workflow of data analysis, data modelling and data generation, is one of the key
                    innovations of D4Science. The analysis and modelling phases define how data
                    collections are loaded into gCube compound objects using its simple but powerful
                    data model. In the data generation phase, descriptive metadata and provenance
                    information are added.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Using the gCube data staging framework, the following datasets were brought
                    together in our experiments:</p>
                <p class="noindent">
                        <li>The Heidelberger Gesamtverzeichnis (HGV) der griechischen
                            Papyrusurkunden Aegyptens, a collection of metadata records for 65,000
                            Greek papyri from Egypt.</li>
                        <li>Projet Volterra, a database of Roman legal texts, currently in the low
                            tens of thousands but very much in progress, stored in a series of
                            themed tables in Microsoft Access.</li>
                        <li>The Inscriptions of Aphrodisias, a corpus of about 2,000 ancient
                            Greek</li>
                    
                </p>
                <p class="noindent">These datasets were the same as those used in the LaQuAT project and thus and
                    allow a critical comparison of results. They overlap in terms of time, places
                    and people – specifically looking at the first five centuries or so of the Roman
                    Empire – although their contents are otherwise quite different. The provision of
                    an environment for working with this data in an integrated form would be highly
                    fruitful for the researcher.</p>
                <p class="noindent">The presentation will describe the use cases that we used for evaluating gCube.
                    Our approach was to break down the scenarios identified in interviews at KCL and
                    within DARIAH into a number of common, atomic actions. Specific instances of
                    these actions can be combined to model a variety of "real" research scenarios,
                    for example the ability to assemble heterogeneous resources (or parts of
                    resources) into a virtual collection, to share this virtual collection within a
                    specific community and to search across a virtual collection, where specific
                    search parameters (such as the importance of specific locations) can be set
                    according to preference. Specific communities also require specific search
                    services such as geo-referenced and date-range searches. Finally, the researcher
                    wants to share links between research objects and annotations (including related
                    documents publications) in her community.</p>
                <p class="noindent">In our experiments, we confirmed that most of these use cases could be supported
                    by the features already provided by the core D4Science systems. For the Digital
                    Humanities 2011 presentation, we will address our subsequent activities: the
                    analysis that we carried out to identify gaps in the existing service provision;
                    some results that demonstrate a clear distinction between the viewpoints of
                    humanities and science research, in respect of such features as image search;
                    our move to develop gMan as a production service for humanities researchers; and
                    the recently-funded European Holocaust Research Infrastructure project, which
                    aims to integrate Holocaust research material from archives across Europe. The
                    main aim of the project will be to make accessible existing Holocaust research
                    collections but the second priority will be to deploy virtual research
                    environments to make use of these resources. D4Science services were seen to
                    support initial requirements well.</p>
            

        <h2>References:</h2></div></div></body></html>