
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Detecting and Characterizing National Style in the 19th Century Novel</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-115.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-115.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: Detecting and Characterizing National Style in the 19th Century Novel</h2><h4>
                    Jockers, Matthew, 
                    Stanford University, 
                    <a href="mailto:mjockers@stanford.edu ">mjockers@stanford.edu </a>
                </h4><hr />
            

                <p class="noindent">In <i>Representative Irish Tales</i>, Yeats identified two basic categories of Irish
                    fiction characterized by what he called “two different accents, the accent of
                    the gentry and the less polished accent of the peasantry” (Yeats 1979). Writing
                    of this distinction, John Cronin notes in The <i>Anglo-Irish Novel</i> how “Maria
                    Edgeworth and William Carleton fit obviously enough the two extremes Yeats has
                    defined but a middle-class figure like Gerald Griffin belongs a little uneasily
                    somewhere in between” (Cronin 1980). Other critics including Thomas MacDonagh
                    (MacDonagh 1916), Thomas Flannagan (Flanagan 1959), and most recently Charles
                    Fanning (Fanning 2000) have all focused attention on the specific use of
                    language in Irish narrative and the extent to which linguistic style and choice
                    of theme and form reflects, or does not, the unique position of these Irish and
                    Anglo-Irish writers in a country where the use of English was to evolve in a
                    rather dramatic fashion. </p>
                <p class="noindent">Though Mark Hawthorne has written that the “Irish were not accustomed to the
                    English language and were unaware of its subtleties and detonations” (Hawthorne
                    1975), Charles Fanning has argued that the Irish in fact became masters of the
                    English language and employed a mode of “linguistic subversion” that allowed
                    them to comment upon and even satirize the British who all the while seem to
                    miss the point that the joke is on them (Fanning 2000). Cronin argues along
                    similar lines to Fanning when he writes that the. . . idiomatic unease in their
                    novels is not caused by any lack of ability on their part in the writing of a
                    standard English idiom. It derives, rather, from the tangled situation in which
                    they find themselves as novelists, directing their efforts towards an
                    English-speaking public but trying to give that public a creative insight into a
                    linguistically piebald area . . . they turned their very difficulties in regard
                    to idiom to constructive account by confronting head-on the blending of the two
                    idioms and two cultures. . . they turn this linguistic ragout to splendid
                    account, making use in the process of English, Irish, and Anglo-Irish” (Cronin
                    1980). </p>
                <p class="noindent">The subject of this research paper, then, is the matter of exactly how 19th
                    century Irish novelists uniquely employ style, setting, and theme. The critics
                    seem to agree that something specific is going on in terms of language, form,
                    and setting, and yet none gets to the heart of the matter, to the details of the
                    prose and to the specific uses of language. Leveraging the tools and techniques
                    from the authorship attribution and computational text analysis
                    literature—specifically natural language processing, machine learning, and topic
                    modeling—this paper compares and contrasts both linguistic style and narrative
                    theme in a corpus of over 500 British and Irish novels from the 19th century.
                    The results of this work show the precise extent to which Irish prose is
                    stylistically different from English prose, and I identify and explore those
                    linguistic and thematic features that mark the Irish novel as distinctly
                    different from the British. </p>
                <p class="noindent">Specifically, my research examines style through an analysis of sentence and word
                    level features. The results show, among other things, that Irish writers tend
                    toward expressions that are both longer and more indeterminate than their
                    British counterparts. Favoring the long sentence and greater use of the comma,
                    the Irish write in comparatively complex, flowing sentences that favor (as
                    measured by relative frequency) words denoting indeterminacy, words such as
                    “most,” “some,” “may,” and “yet.” British writers, on the other hand, show a
                    preference for shorter, more determinate sentences featuring words such as
                    “know, never, no, nothing, must, not, only, all, should, last, first, and
                    great.” This result tends to confirm anecdotal observations made by scholars,
                    including (Cronin 1980) who suggest that though the Irish may have sought to
                    imitate and appeal to the stylistic preferences of a British dominated industry,
                    they ultimately invented their own style of prose, which captured both the
                    rhythms of the local language and the anxieties of a country struggling with its
                    position vis-à-vis the colonizing presence of the British. </p>
                <p class="noindent">In addition to probing and comparing the stylistic habits of the two nations,
                    this work further analyzes the prose at the level of theme and argues that there
                    is an important link to be made between style and theme in Irish prose. To
                    harvest latent themes, I employed the unsupervised topic modeling tools of the
                    UMASS machine learning toolkit (McCallum 2002). A run of the model, which sought
                    to identify the 25 most prominent topics in the corpus, resulted in one
                    particular topic appearing with greater frequency in the Irish novels of the
                    corpus. This topic, which was labeled as “the big house theme,” is composed of
                    words clearly relating to tenant-landlord relations and the familial issues that
                    are so often explored by Irish writers attempting to characterize these troubled
                    relationships. The big house theme was found to be the most prominent topic in
                    35% of the Irish novels analyzed in this corpus, and it is present to a lesser
                    degree in many of the others. </p>
                <p class="noindent">My analysis concludes by tracing the links between distinctly Irish themes and
                    the elements of Irish style identified in the first part of the research. From
                    the macroanalytic data derived at the corpus level, I present a chronological
                    charting of Fanning’s notion of linguistic subversion, and then I move to the
                    micro level and offer a closer reading of several exemplary passages from works
                    in the chronology. I discuss how linguistic subversion is inherent to the
                    tradition of the "Irish Bull” and offer a brief discussion of Richard and Maria
                    Edgeworth’s 1835 essay on the subject in which they write with some humor that:
                    “English is not the mother tongue of the natives of Ireland; to them it is a
                    foreign language, and consequently, it is scarcely within the limits of
                    probability, that they should avoid making blunders both in speaking and writing
                    . . . Indeed, so perfectly persuaded are Englishmen of the truth of this
                    proposition, that the moment an unfortunate Hibernian opens his lips they expect
                    a bull, and listen with that well known look of sober contempt and smug self
                    satisfaction, which sufficiently testifies their sense of safety and
                    superiority.” (Edgeworth 1835) </p>
                <p class="noindent"> As early as <i>Castle Rackrent</i> (1800), Edgeworth had demonstrated her own command
                    of linguistic subversion and an acute awareness of how to form her narrative and
                    bend language to provide not simply a distinctly Irish novel but a seminal novel
                    within the larger novelistic tradition. My work provides quantitative evidence
                    of how, where, and why Irish style is different from British. </p>
            
        <h2>References:</h2>
            
                
                    <p>
                        Cronin, J.
                        1980
                        <i>The Anglo-Irish Novel</i>, 
                        Barnes &amp; Noble Books
                        Totowa, N.J
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Edgeworth, M.
                        1835
                        <i>Tales and Novels</i>, 
                        Harper &amp; brothers
                        New York
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Fanning, C.
                        2000<i>The Irish Voice in America : 250 Years of
                            Irish-American Fiction.</i>, 
                        Lexington, KY
                        University Press of Kentucky
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Flanagan, T. 1959
                        <i>The Irish Novelists, 1800-1850</i>, 
                        New York
                        Columbia University Press.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Hawthorne, M. D. 
                        1975
                        <i>John and Michael Banim (The "O'hara Brothers") : A Study in
                            the Early Development of the Anglo-Irish Novel, Romantic
                            Reassessment.</i>, 
                        Institut für Englische Sprache und Literatur, Universität
                            Salzburg
                        Salzburg
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Macdonagh, T. 
                        1916
                        <i>Literature in Ireland: Studies Irish and
                            Anglo-Irish</i>, 
                        T. F. Unwin.
                        London
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Andrew Kachites McCallum
                        2002
                        <i>"Mallet: A Machine Learning for Language Toolkit."</i>, 
                        
         (<a href="http://mallet.cs.umass.edu" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Yeats, W. B.
                        1979
                        <i>Representative Irish Tales</i>, 
                        Humanities Press
                        Atlantic Highlands, N.J.
                    </p>
                
            
        </div></div></body></html>