
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>The Time Machine: Capturing Worlds across Time in Texts</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-113.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-113.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: The Time Machine: Capturing Worlds across Time in Texts</h2><h4>
                    Juuso, Ilkka, 
                    University of Oulu, Finland, 
                    <a href="mailto:ilkka.juuso@ee.oulu.fi">ilkka.juuso@ee.oulu.fi</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Opas-Hänninen, Lisa Lena, 
                    University of Oulu, Finland, 
                    <a href="mailto:lisa.lena.opas-hanninen@oulu.fi">lisa.lena.opas-hanninen@oulu.fi</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Johnson, Anthony, 
                    University of Oulu, Finland, 
                    <a href="mailto:anthony.johnson@oulu.fi">anthony.johnson@oulu.fi</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Seppänen, Tapio, 
                    University of Oulu, Finland, 
                    <a href="mailto:tapio.seppanen@oulu.fi">tapio.seppanen@oulu.fi</a>
                </h4><hr />
            
                <h2>Introduction</h2>
                <p class="noindent">This paper describes a number of ways in which a temporally-sensitive electronic
                    dictionary resource, the Historical Thesaurus of the Oxford English Dictionary
                    (2 vols; Oxford, 2009 [=HTOED]), may be employed in the automatic dating of
                    words and entire texts. We investigate how the text captures time: most
                    expressly, how the residue of the present (or the different ‘presents’ of
                    language history) have managed to become trapped in the linguistic matrix of a
                    narrative so that we sense, for instance, the difference between a period being
                    represented and the narrator’s temporal positionality, or even the gap between
                    an author and his or her narrative stance. Through computer-assisted means we
                    analyze the impact of later historical and linguistic events on the reporting of
                    earlier events. To this end, we have developed an automatic system for
                    retrieving dating information and a colour-coded browsing interface for
                    searching and viewing the time-coded text, calling it the ‘Time Machine’. </p>
                <p class="noindent">Novels capture worlds, but however disparate the materials that may go into them,
                    something of the space-time in which they have been written remains as a
                    residue. This, in part, is a function of language itself: the instabilities,
                    changes and, above all, affordances at any one moment of that linguistic mesh
                    that Lotman (1990) might have called the semiosphere. In part, too, it is a
                    function of what, within Cultural Imagology, might more concretely be called the
                    texture of the iconosphere (Johnson 2005, 2006): the distinctiveness given to
                    the world at any particular moment by the concatenation of signifying objects
                    present within it. This is why it is an attractive idea to apply a tool such as
                    a time-coded dictionary to novels written at time t purporting to convey events
                    taking place at a time t-x. Within this frame of thought, the case of the
                    historical novel is a particularly pronounced one. By definition, the genre
                    tries to capture something of the iconosphere of a world that has passed us by
                    (even though its semiosphere may remain that of a contemporary reader). And even
                    in cases where the linguistic texture of the semiosphere is deliberately
                    archaized – or localized by the use of dialect forms – the residue of the
                    present remains. As a test case, we examine Diana Gabaldon’s Cross Stitch
                    (1991): a text which flaunts traditional temporal typologies by figuring a
                    protagonist who crosses from the iconosphere of the mid-twentieth century to
                    that of the seventeenth century and becomes trapped there: perceiving the past
                    in a lexis and syntax which palpably belong to a different age.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Time has previously been explored within documents in several ways. Some work has
                    concentrated on identifying expressions of time within text in an attempt to
                    build models of the succession of events. This has been particularly fruitful in
                    the case of, for example, medical discharge records and road accident reports,
                    where the sequence of events is of great importance (Hirschman 1981, Kayser and
                    Nouioua 2009). Other work has used a training set of time-associated words and a
                    Naïve Bayes Classifier to detect temporal concepts in blogs (Noro et al. 2006).
                    While this work is promising in analyzing writings about daily life in a compact
                    time frame, it seems ill-equipped for investigating iconospheres that deal with
                    spans constituting years or even decades. Thus a tool that can retrieve
                    time-related information from the HTOED automatically offers a very promising
                    way forward for the literary and linguistic scholar.</p>
            
            
                <h2>Methodology</h2>
                <p class="noindent">Using the ‘Time Machine’, we map out the iconospheric precision with which
                    Gabaldon represents different characters in her fiction (not to mention the
                    humour generated by the gradual blending of their discourses as the novel
                    progresses). But beyond this, by linking our tool with the powerful additional
                    resources which the HTOED has now opened up for those studying the ‘external’,
                    ‘mental’ and ‘social’ worlds of the novel from a historical and etymological
                    perspective, the project hopes to facilitate the achievement of a more nuanced
                    understanding of the interrelationship between ‘real’ and ‘fictional’ time in
                    the historical novel than has been possible before.</p>
                <p class="noindent">In order to better study iconospheres, we sought to develop a tool that would
                    automatically look up dating information and definitions for words, processing
                    entire texts at a time, thereby removing the need for manual queries using a
                    dictionary. Furthermore, we wanted the tool, on the one hand, to enable users to
                    specify time periods of interest for closer inspection while, on the other hand,
                    it left them free to browse the material through diverse visualization schemes
                    in order to discover trends or new time periods of interest.</p>
                <p class="noindent">At present the tool is a prototype, running inside a web browser, in order to
                    enable rapid experimentation with new visualization schemes using CSS. We use a
                    local SQL database to store the HTOED data. Texts can be uploaded via a browser
                    interface and are processed in any user-defined units tagged in the text, e.g.
                    page by page or speaker by speaker, or in the text as a whole. The tool reads
                    both XML and plain text. To finish verifying that the visualization schemes we
                    have chosen are useful, we wish to bring the tool to the digital humanities
                    community, in addition to the poetics and linguistics community (Johnson et al.
                    2010). Following this, we intend to develop the final tool in Java for inclusion
                    within the LICHEN toolbox.</p>
            
            
                <h2>Results</h2>
                <p class="noindent">What the HTOED is able to offer to the ‘Time Machine’ is the ability to isolate
                    different experiential modes within particular iconospheres at the same time as
                    it reveals the range of etymological meanings open to the reader at any given
                    moment. (This, of course, is an invaluable aid for critics who wish to avoid
                    anachronism in their own readings.) In our preliminary development of the ‘Time
                    Machine’ we concentrated on its capacity for isolating different lexical
                    categories within a given iconosphere and indicating the etymological choices
                    available for particular readings. At the top of the screen, the Source section
                    allows the user to choose either an entire text or some part of it (see Figure 1
                    below: a case in which the speaker Jamie has been chosen). In the Filter
                    section, the user can choose to narrow the search down to one particular word,
                    or to all words that were in use at a particular time (choosing either first use
                    date, last use date or both). To produce the present screen we started by
                    choosing all the words that entered the language after 1742, in other words
                    after the time period in which Jamie speaks. The Colour-coded text section then
                    highlighted all those words which entered the language after the given date, as
                    did our Wordlist section.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Our initial investigation found that the tool is able to pick out swathes of
                    temporal incongruities from this playful text or, further, search out instances
                    relating more specifically to the ‘external’, ‘mental’ and ‘social’ worlds of
                    the novel. It spots moments when the eighteenth-century clansman Jamie seems
                    prescient (mentioning ‘aesthetics’ for instance, or re-circulating the word
                    ‘sadist’, which has been bandied to him by his twentieth-century wife). It
                    detects instabilities not only in the iconosphere of the 1700s – which Gabaldon
                    has carefully researched – but also in the representation of
                    mid-twentieth-century England (which she appears to have taken more for
                    granted).</p>
                <p class="noindent">However, despite the manifest advantage of using even this approach to the ‘Time
                    Machine’ to spot faultlines and incongruities within the fictional world of a
                    novel, some teething-troubles remained: the most significant being that, unlike
                    human readers, the prototype cannot, of course, intuit the ‘correct’ lexical
                    choice from the range of possible meanings thrown up by a search. Accordingly,
                    we have tweaked the search and display capability of the ‘Time Machine’ so that
                    it can also narrow its lexical catchment area by trawling parts of speech (such
                    as substantives) in which cultural and temporal change exhibit their highest
                    visibility. <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-113.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Figure 1</a> demonstrates how,
                    using these restrictions, the prototype is able to flag up the way in which
                    Gabaldon has inadvertently endowed Jamie’s lexicon with three words
                    stereotypically associated with Scottishness (‘Sassenach, shinty, sporran’)
                    which were not, in fact, recorded until some time after the period in which
                    Jamie is meant to be speaking.</p>
                <p class="noindent">In sum, our study indicates that automated access to chronological information,
                    such as the date of first use for any given word, and full etymologies has
                    promising applications in literary and historical research that has until now
                    relied mostly on intuition and laborious manual methods to combine dating
                    information and texts. And beyond this, with some adaptation, it is also clear
                    that the ‘Time Machine’ could be of significance within areas such as forensic
                    linguistics, collocation studies, and the study of micro-linguistic change over
                    time in large corpora.</p>
            
            
                <p>
                    <h2>Figure 1</h2>
                    <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//113/figure1.PNG" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-113.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//113/figure1.PNG','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                </p>
            
        <h2>References:</h2>
            
                
                    <p>
                        Gabaldon, D.
                        <i>Cross Stitch</i>, 
                        Arrow Books Ltd.
                        1991
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <i>Historical Thesaurus of the Oxford English
                            Dictionary</i>, 
                        Oxford: OUP
                        2009
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Hirschman, L.
                        1981
                         “Retrieving time information from natural-language
                            texts, ” 
                        <i>Proceedings of the 3rd Annual ACM Conference on Research
                            and Development in Information Retrieval</i>, 
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Johnson, Anthony W.
                         “Notes Towards a New Imagology, ” 
                        <i>European English Messenger</i>, 
                        2005
                        14
                        1
                        50-58
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Johnson, Anthony W.
                         “New Methodologies: Imagology, Language and English
                            Philology, ” 
                        <i>Linguistic Topics and Language Teaching</i>, 
                        2006
                        Oulu University Press
                        7-27
                        Antilla, H.
                        Gear, J.
                        Heikkinen, A.
                        Sallinen, Riitta
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Johnson, Anthony W.
                        Opas-Hänninen, L.L.
                        Juuso, I.
                         “Stitches in Time and Switches in Text: Diana Gabaldon and
                            the Historical Thesaurus of the Oxford English Dictionary, ” 
                        <i>Paper presented at PALA2010</i>, 
                        2010
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Kayser, D.
                        Nouioua, F.
                         “From the textual description of an accident to its
                            causes, ” 
                        <i>Journal of Artificial Intelligence</i>, 
                        2009
                        173
                        12-13
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Lotman, Yuri M.
                        Ann Shukman
                        <i>Universe of the Mind: A Semiotic Theory of Culture</i>, 
                        1990
                        173
                        12-13
                    </p>

                    <p>
                        Noro, T.
                        Inui, T.
                        Takamura, H.
                        Okumura, M.
                        2006
                         “Time period identification of events in text, ” 
                        <i>Proceedings of the 21st international Conference on
                            Computational Linguistics and the 44th Annual Meeting of the Association
                            for Computational Linguistics (Sydney, Australia, July 17 - 18, 2006).
                            Association for Computational Linguistics</i>, 
                        
         (<a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3115/1220175.1220320" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                
            
        </div></div></body></html>