
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Evaluating Digital Scholarship: A Case Study in the Field of
                Literature</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-142.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-142.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: Evaluating Digital Scholarship: A Case Study in the Field of
                Literature</h2><h4>
                    Schreibman, Susan, 
                    <a href="mailto:susan.schreibman@gmail.com">susan.schreibman@gmail.com</a>
                    Digital Humanities Observatory, 
                </h4><h4>
                    Mandell, Laura, 
                    <a href="mailto:laura.mandell@gmail.com">laura.mandell@gmail.com</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Olsen, Stephen, 
                    <a href="mailto:SOlsen@mla.org">SOlsen@mla.org</a>
                </h4><hr />
            

                <p class="noindent">Evaluating and receiving credit for digital scholarship within traditional
                    disciplinary areas in the humanities has been a concern much discussed, not only
                    within the digital humanities community, but at think tanks on the future of
                    scholarly publishing, within institutions, at professional associations in the
                    various disciplines of the humanities, and in journal and newspaper
                        articles.For just a small sampling of recent postings and articles see
                        Scott Jaschik, ‘Tenure in a Digital Era’. Inside Higher Education (26 May
                        2010); ‘Evaluating Digital Scholarship, Promotion &amp; Tenure Cases’,
                        Office of the Dean, University of Virginia, 
         (<a href="http://artsandsciences.virginia.edu/dean/facultyemployment/evaluating_digital_scholarship.                         html" target="blank">link</a>)
   ; ‘Guidelines for Evaluating Work with Digital Media in the Modern
                        Languages’, Modern Language Association, 
         (<a href="http://www.mla.org/guidelines_evaluation_digital" target="blank">link</a>)
   ; Julia
                        Flanders, ‘The Productive Unease of 21st-century Digital Scholarship’.
                        Digital Humanities Quarterly (Summer 2009); Jeanne Glaubitz Cross,
                        ‘Reviewing Digital Scholarship: The Need for Discipline-Based Peer Review’.
                        Journal of Web Librarianship (December 2008); Joan F. Cheverie, et al,
                        ‘Digital Scholarship in the University Tenure and Promotion Process: A
                        Report on the Sixth Scholarly Communication Symposium at Georgetown
                        University Library’ Journal of Scholarly Publishing (April 2009)
                        219-230.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Over the past few years The Modern Language Association has taken the lead in
                    encouraging the recognition of digital scholarship in promotion and tenure
                    cases. Its 2006 <i>Report of the MLA Task Force on Evaluating
                        Scholarship for Tenure and Promotion</i> (
         (<a href="http://www.mla.org/tenure_promotion" target="blank">link</a>)
   ) offered unequivocal support
                    of digital scholarship. Among its recommendations are the following: <blockquote>The
                        profession as a whole should develop a more capacious conception of
                        scholarship by rethinking the dominance of the monograph, promoting the
                        scholarly essay, establishing multiple pathways to tenure, and using
                        scholarly portfolios . . . .[and] departments and institutions should
                        recognize the legitimacy of scholarship produced in new media, whether by
                        individuals or in collaboration, and create procedures for evaluating these
                        forms of scholarship.Report of the MLA Task Force on Evaluating
                            Scholarship for Tenure and Promotion. 
         (<a href="http://www.mla.org/tenure_promotion" target="blank">link</a>)
   </blockquote></p>
                <p class="noindent">This report and others (see "Our Cultural Commonwealth: The report of the
                    American Council of Learned Societies Commission on Cyberinfrastructure for the
                    Humanities and Social Sciences" etc.) make it clear that the Humanities must
                    broaden traditional definitions of scholarship and reconceptualize its methods
                    of evaluation. But it still falls to us in the digital humanities to articulate
                    the scholarly content and value of our work and to propose explicit procedures
                    for effectively evaluating it.</p>
                <p class="noindent">In 2008 the MLA’s Committee on Information Technology released an Evaluation
                        WikiThe Evaluation of Digital Work. 
         (<a href="http://wiki.mla.org/index.php/Evaluation_Wiki" target="blank">link</a>)
    (based
                    on the work of Geoffrey Rockwell who served as a member of the Committee from
                    2005-08) that provides a framework for departments to evaluate this new
                    scholarship. As a result of this work, the authors of this paper led a workshop
                    in evaluating digital work for tenure and promotion at the 2009 MLA convention
                    in Philadelphia. The workshop was designed to provide both a framework from
                    within which digital scholarship could be evaluated, as well as a forum for the
                    authors to evaluate just how difficult it was for non-specialists to come to
                    terms this new work. With this in mind, several themes were addressed in the
                    workshop design:</p>
                <p class="noindent">
                        <li>The impediments involved in evaluating digital scholarship,
                            particularly in terms of interdisciplinarity, authority, and use of
                            standards;</li>
                        <li>Issues of disciplinarity: digital scholarship does not fit comfortably
                            into the what is currently valued in the profession;</li>
                        <li>The absence of expertise at the departmental level in evaluating
                            digital scholarship handicaps both the evaluators and the
                            candidates;</li>
                        <li>The intellectual stakes of such work;</li>
                        <li>The value and credit accorded to interdisciplinary,
                            multi-institutional, collaborative work.</li>
                    
                </p>
                <p class="noindent">In the field of literary studies the gold standard for tenure and promotion is
                    the publication of the monograph. Editorial scholarship -- textual criticism,
                    book history, scholarly editing, the sociology and bibliography of texts
                    --particularly in North America, has been consistently devalued since the rise
                    of literary theory. That the digital is conducive to the kinds of projects that
                    have been denigrated by the academy (certainly since new literary criticism),
                    including pedagogy, public humanities, and the creation of scholarly editions,
                    has made the argument for including this work in tenure and promotion cases all
                    the more difficult. These aforementioned themes and questions were meant to
                    engage the group in questioning such values.</p>
                <p class="noindent">The workshop was structured around case studies based on the experiences of
                    individuals in the field. In some instances the case studies were anonymized (as
                    several of the workshop leaders created studies based on their own scholarship),
                    others were not (as when it was clear who the author was from the online
                    scholarship under discussion).</p>
                <p class="noindent">Attendees were seated at tables of eight and for each of three rounds had two
                    case studies to choose from. The first round of case studies were what might
                    term fairly traditional digital scholarly editions. This type of digital
                    scholarship was chosen because it most resembled analogue scholarship.
                    Nevertheless, when we opened the conversation up for discussion, the opening
                    remark by a Departmental Chair questioned that the edition under discussion
                    should be counted towards scholarship at all, as in her opinion, the creation of
                    scholarly editions fit squarely into the category of service. This became a
                    recurring theme of the workshop: individuals who did not understand the
                    theoretical and technical imperatives behind the scholarship consistently
                    categorized the work as service. It became clear that the production of
                    editions, whether distributed in analogue or digital form, were not viewed as
                    scholarship on par with critical theory.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Moreover, when the authors of case studies explained the theoretical methodology
                    implicit in their research in terms of the technologies used, non-technical
                    participants consistently complained that the authors were engaging in
                    techno-speak jargon. Participants also complained that the work was
                    undertheorized: however, when it was pointed out that theories common to digital
                    scholarship (for example, the limitations of particular metadata schemes, issues
                    arising from the hierarchical nature of XML, or the impediments to using a
                    standard such as TEI for genetic editing) were evoked and challenged, these
                    participants felt that it was not sufficient to rely on theoretical perspectives
                    not normative to the discipline of literature (i.e. coding was not satisfactory
                    as a basis for the field).</p>
                <p class="noindent">Subsequent case studies teased out issues of the implications of, in effect,
                    outsourcing the evaluation of scholarship to (scholarly) presses and journals,
                    the vast majority of which have not developed an economic model for publishing
                    digital scholarship. Discussions circled around alternative models of validating
                    digital scholarship, focusing on the work, for example, of NINES. Indeed, the
                    success of the NINES model was so apparent in these discussions that NINES has
                    committed its next two Summer Institutes (generously funded by the National
                    Endowment for the Humanities) to evaluating digital scholarship.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Although the writing is on the wall that our field must change to encompass new
                    scholarship and new scholarly forms as engendered by the new technologies, the
                    impediments to evaluating this scholarship by non-specialists are paramount. The
                    digital archive may have been the first form to challenge the primacy of print
                    scholarship, but new forms of scholarship are emerging that will even more
                    radically challenge the status quo.</p>
                <p class="noindent">It is clear from the research carried out by the authors in the preparation and
                    delivery of this workshop, the creation of the CIT Guidelines, and the
                    development of the NINES Summer Institutes, that it is imperative for the
                    Digital Humanities community to take a more proactive role in supporting
                    departments as they are increasingly called upon to evaluate digital
                    scholarship. This burden cannot continue to be borne solely by each individual
                    candidate, as is currently the norm. The overriding question for these
                    activities must be how do we provide a framework so that evaluators can evaluate
                    the research within the technological context within which the scholarship is
                    undertaken.</p>
                <p class="noindent">The discussion of the case studies by the participating department chairs, senior
                    faculty members, and junior faculty members revealed to us some of the specific
                    difficulties departments and institutions have in recognizing scholarly activity
                    in some of its new digital forms:</p>
                <p class="noindent">
                        <li>The evolving definitions of scholarship in language and literature
                            over the past 50 years (Eagelton Terry Eagelton. "The Functions of
                                Criticism," How To Read a Poem (Malden, MA: Basil Blackwell 2007),
                                1-24.), in particular the conflict between criticism and
                            philology as the dominant mode of scholarship;</li>
                        <li>The discounting of scholarly activities like textual editing and
                            translation, and the mislabeling of much digital scholarship as
                                serviceConnie Moon Sehat and Erika Farr. ‘The Future of
                                Digital Scholarship: Preparation, Training, Curricula Report of a
                                colloquium on education in digital scholarship’. (2009). 
         (<a href="http://www.clir.org/pubs/resources/articles.html" target="blank">link</a>)
    (McGann,McGann, Jerome. “A Note on the Current State
                                of Humanities Scholarship.” Critical Inquiry 30/2. 
         (<a href="http://criticalinquiry.uchicago.edu/issues/v30/30n2.McGann.html" target="blank">link</a>)
    GablerGabler, Hans Walter. "Theorizing the Digital
                                Scholarly Edition." Literature Compass 7/2 (2010)
                            43-56.);</li>
                        <li>The ongoing crisis in scholarly book publishing (Waters,Lidnsay
                                Waters. “A Modest Proposal for Preventing the Books of the Members
                                of the MLA from Being a Burden to Their Authors, Publishers, or
                                Audiences.” PMLA 115 (2000): 315–17. Guillory,Guillory,
                                John. "Evaluating Scholarship in the Humanities: Principles and
                                Procedures." ADE Bulletin 137 (Spring 2005), pp. 18–33.
                                GreenblattGreenblatt, Stephen. “A Special Letter.” 28 May
                                2002. 1 Nov. 2010 
         (<a href="http://www.mla.org/scholarly_pub" target="blank">link</a>)
   )</li>
                    </p>
                <p class="noindent">Our paper will summarize what happened at the workshop, in response to which we
                    will present action items to be undertaken by organizations such as MLA and
                    ACH.</p>
            

        </div></div></body></html>