
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Topic Modeling Historical Sources: Analyzing the Diary of Martha Ballard</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-173.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-173.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: Topic Modeling Historical Sources: Analyzing the Diary of Martha Ballard</h2><h4>
          Blevins, Cameron, 
          Stanford University, 
          <a href="mailto:cblevins@stanford.edu">cblevins@stanford.edu</a>
        </h4><hr />
      
        <p class="noindent">In 1991, historian Laurel Ulrich’s <i>A Midwife’s Tale</i> swept a little-known
          18th-century midwife named Martha Ballard into the national historical consciousness.
          Ulrich’s work centered on the analysis of nearly 10,000 diary entries penned by
          Ballard between 1785 and 1812, leading to an exploration of issues such as shifting family
          structures, the professionalization of obstetrics, and debtor patterns in a rural economy
          (Ulrich 1991). My research examines the same diary, but instead of a traditional close
          reading of the source, I use topic modeling to mine a digitized transcription, iterating
          through hundreds of thousands of words in order to search for textual patterns.</p>
        <p class="noindent">One of the fundamental challenges to applying text processing techniques to historical
          sources is one of data quality. Older, hand-written documents are often difficult to
          transcribe into a digital format, while the shorthand style of diary writing is often
          filled with abbreviations and misspellings. For instance, Ballard employs a vocabulary
          peppered with variations: the word “daughter” is spelled fourteen different
          ways: “daught,” “dagt,” “dat,” etc. One way to
          overcome this challenge is to use topic modeling, a method of computational linguistics
          that attempts to group words together based on their appearance in the text.</p>
        <p class="noindent">My short paper session focuses on an analysis of a historical source using topic modeling
          (Blei and Lafferty 2009). As a form of linguistic analysis, topic modeling has been
          employed over the past several years to examine large-scale, multi-author textual
          databases, including historical newspapers (Block 2006), journal articles (Gerrish et al.
          2010, Hall et. al. 2008), and social network data (Ramage et al. 2010). My application of
          topic modeling differs from many of these investigations by focusing on multiple, short
          texts by a single author: in this case, Ballard’s diary entries.</p>
        <p class="noindent">I employed the machine learning toolkit MALLET (McCallum 2002) in order to topic model
          each of Ballard’s entries as separate pieces of text. MALLET, identified thirty
          topics, which I then labeled for clarity. The following sample topics were some of the
          most coherent (my own labels in bold and uppercase):</p>
      
      
        <table border="1">
          <h2>Topics</h2>
          <tr>
            <td role="label">Topic Label </td>
            <td role="label">Topic Words </td>
           </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><b>MIDWIFERY</b> </td>
            <td>birth deld safe morn receivd calld left cleverly pm labour fine reward arivd
              infant expected recd shee born patient </td>
           </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><b>CHURCH</b> </td>
            <td>meeting attended afternoon reverend worship foren mr famely performd vers attend
              public supper st service lecture discoarst administred supt DEATH: day yesterday
              informd morn years death ye hear expired expird weak dead las past heard days drowned
              departed evinn </td>
           </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><b>GARDENING</b> </td>
            <td>gardin sett worked clear beens corn warm planted matters cucumbers gatherd
              potatoes plants ou sowd door squash wed seeds </td>
           </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><b>SHOPPING</b> </td>
            <td>lb made brot bot tea butter sugar carried oz chees pork candles wheat store pr
              beef spirit churnd flower </td>
           </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><b>ILLNESS</b> </td>
            <td>unwell mr sick gave dr rainy easier care head neighbor feet relief made throat
              poorly takeing medisin ts stomach </td>
           </tr>
         </table>
        <p class="noindent">Although topic modeling was useful for overcoming some of the challenges of spelling
          variations, its real value lies in its ability to quantitatively measure the relative
          thematic content of each piece of text. In the case of Ballard’s diary, MALLET
          assumes that each diary entry is compromised of some combination of thirty topics. An
          entry in which Ballard attended a sermon and purchased supplies from the general store
          might contain, for instance, scores of 50% for the CHURCH topic, 25% for the SHOPPING
          topic, and minimal or zero scores for the remaining twenty-eight topics. Associated
          temporal metadata (day, month, year, day of the week) allowed me to chart the behavior of
          certain topics over time.</p>
        <p class="noindent">As a simple barometer of its effectiveness, I used one of the generated topics that I
          labeled COLD WEATHER, which included words such as cold, windy, chilly, snowy, and air.
          Aggregating its entry scores by month shows exactly what one would expect over the course
          of a year ( <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-173.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Figure 1</a>).</p>
        <p class="noindent">
          <p>
          <h2>Figure 1</h2>
          <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//173/Blevins_Figure1.jpg" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-173.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//173/Blevins_Figure1.jpg','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
        </p></p>
        
        <p class="noindent">This approach also can chart patterns over the course of the diary, which covers the
          final twenty-seven years of Ballard’s life. Two topics tended to involve words
          related to HOUSEWORK. Aggregated by year, they demonstrate a steady increase in the
          frequency with which Ballard writes about daily chores ( <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-173.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Figure 2</a>).</p>
        
        <p class="noindent"> 
          <p>
            <h2>Figure 2</h2>
            <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//173/Blevins_Figure2.jpg" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-173.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//173/Blevins_Figure2.jpg','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
          </p>
        </p>
        <p class="noindent">Both topics moved in tandem and steadily increased as she grew older (excepting a curious
          divergence in the last several years of the diary). This is somewhat counter-intuitive, as
          one would assume the household responsibilities for an aging grandmother with a large
          family would decrease over time. Yet this pattern bolsters the argument made by Ulrich in
          <i>A Midwife’s Tale</i>, in which she points out that the first half of the diary was
          “written when her family’s productive power was at its height.” (Ulrich
          1991, pp. 285) As her children married and moved into different households, and her own
          husband experienced mounting legal and financial troubles, her daily burdens around the
          house increased. Topic modeling quantifies and visualizes this pattern, one not
          immediately visible to a human reader.</p>
        <p class="noindent">Topic modeling allows for patterns to crystallize that are imperceptible to a human
          reader. One topic was particularly intriguing, and included the words: feel husband unwel
          warm feeble felt god great fatagud fatagued thro life time year dear rose famely bu
          good</p>
        <p class="noindent">These were words that seem to cover EMOTION and spiritual reflection – an abstract
          topic that is difficult enough for a human reader to describe. Yet the computer did a
          remarkable job in identifying a cohesive group of words. The topic follows a fascinating
          trajectory in Ballard’s diary ( <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-173.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Figure 3</a>).</p>
        <p class="noindent">
          <p>
            <h2>Figure 3</h2>
            <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//173/Blevins_Figure3.jpg" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-173.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//173/Blevins_Figure3.jpg','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
          </p>
        </p>
        <p class="noindent">Not only did Ballard write about this topic more as she grew older, but there was a
          dramatic leap from 1803 to 1804-1805. This corresponds quite well to the period of intense
          family travail: Her husband was imprisoned for debt and her son was indicted by a grand
          jury for fraud, causing a cascade effect in Martha’s own life. Topic modeling not
          only reveals the trajectory of tangible themes (housework, births, gardening, etc.), but
          also begins to quantify and visualize abstract themes by charting Ballard’s
          emotional state of being.</p>
        <p class="noindent">My short paper session focuses on the results of my existing work on topic modeling
          Ballard’s diary while outlining some of the future paths this research could take.
          In particular, I am interested in pairing trends in topics with trends in Ballard’s
          social network. What topics correlate with what kinds of people? Are women or men
          described alongside particular themes? In what broad context do ministers, doctors,
          neighbors, or family members appear? In conjunction with traditional research and
          analysis, topic modeling presents a valuable methodology for examining historical
          sources.</p>
      
    <h2>References:</h2>
      
        
          <p>
            Blei. D.
            Lafferty, J.
            2009
             “Topic Models, ” 
            <i>Text Mining: Classification, Clustering, and Applications.</i>, 
            Srivastava, A. and Sahami, M. (ed.)
            Champan &amp; Hall
            Boca Raton
            pp. 71-94
          </p>
          <p>
            Block, Sharon
            2006
             “Doing More with Digitization: An Introduction to Topic Modeling
              of Early American Sources, ” 
            <i>Common-Place</i>, 
            6.2
            
         (<a href="http://www.common-place.org/vol-06/no-02/tales/" target="blank">link</a>)
   
          </p>
          <p>
            Gerrish, S.
             Llewellyn, C.
            2010
             “JSTOR Discipline Browser, ” 
            <i>JSTOR</i>, 
            
         (<a href="http://showcase.jstor.org/projects/discipline-browser" target="blank">link</a>)
   
          </p>
          <p>
            Hall, D.
            Jurafsky, D.
            Manning, C.
            2008
             “Studying the History of Ideas Using Topic Models, ” 
            <i>Proceedings of Empirical Methods of Natural Language
              Processing.</i>, 
            
         (<a href="http://nlp.stanford.edu/pubs/hall-emnlp08.pdf" target="blank">link</a>)
   
          </p>
          <p>
            McCallum, Andrew
            2002
            <i>MALLET: A Machine Learning for Language Toolkit</i>, 
            
         (<a href="http://mallet.cs.umass.edu" target="blank">link</a>)
   
          </p>
          <p>
            Ramage, D.
            Dumais, S.
            Liebling, D.
            2010
             ““Characterizing Microblogs with Topic Models.”, ” 
            <i>International Conference on Weblogs and Social Media.</i>, 
            
         (<a href="http://nlp.stanford.edu/pubs/twitter-icwsm10.pdf" target="blank">link</a>)
   
          </p>
          <p>
            Ulrich, Laurel Thatcher
            1991
            <i>A Midwife’s Tale: The Life of Martha Ballard and Her Diary,
              1785-1812.</i>, 
            Vintage
            New York
          </p>
        
      
    </div></div></body></html>