
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Discovering Land Transaction Relations from Land Deeds of Taiwan</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-120.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-120.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: Discovering Land Transaction Relations from Land Deeds of Taiwan</h2><h4>
                    Chen, Shih-Pei, 
                    Department of Computer Science, National Taiwan
                        University, 
                    <a href="mailto:gail@turing.csie.ntu.edu.tw">gail@turing.csie.ntu.edu.tw</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Huang, Yu-Ming, 
                    Department of Computer Science, National Taiwan
                        University, 
                    <a href="mailto:ming@turing.csie.ntu.edu.tw">ming@turing.csie.ntu.edu.tw</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Ho, Hou-Ieong, 
                    Department of Computer Science, National Taiwan
                        University, 
                    <a href="mailto:brent@turing.csie.ntu.edu.tw">brent@turing.csie.ntu.edu.tw</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Chen, Ping-Yen, 
                    Department of Computer Science, National Taiwan
                        University, 
                    <a href="mailto:champiyen@turing.csie.ntu.edu.tw">champiyen@turing.csie.ntu.edu.tw</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Hsiang, Jieh, 
                    Department of Computer Science, National Taiwan University;
                        Research Center for Digital Humanities, National Taiwan
                        University, 
                    <a href="mailto:jhsiang@ntu.edu.tw">jhsiang@ntu.edu.tw</a>
                </h4><hr />
            
                <h2>Abstract</h2>
                <p class="noindent"> Land deeds were the only proof of ownership in pre-1900 Taiwan. They are
                    indispensable for the studies of Taiwan’s social, anthropological, and economic
                    evolution. We have built a full-text digital library that contains more than
                    30,000 land deeds. The deeds in our collection range over 250 years and are
                    collected from over 100 sources. The unprecedented volume and diversity of the
                    sources provide an exciting source of primary documents for historians. But they
                    also pose an interesting challenge: how to tell if two land deeds are
                    related.</p>
                <p class="noindent"> In this paper we describe an approach to discover one of the most important
                    relations: successive transactions involving the same property. Our method
                    enabled us to construct over 3,300 such transaction pairs. We also introduce a
                    notion of <i>land transitivity graph</i> to capture the
                    transitivity embedded in these transactions. We discovered 2,219 such graphs,
                    the largest of which includes 103 deeds. Some of these graphs involve land
                    behavior that had never been studied before. </p>
            
            
                <h2>Introduction</h2>
                <p class="noindent">Until the turn of the 20th century, hand-written land deeds were the only proof
                    of transaction of lands in Taiwan. Such a deed may involve activities such as
                    selling/buying, lending of land to smaller farmers, dividing the land among
                    children or shareholders, and cultivation permits. The deeds usually follow,
                    depending on their types, a typical but not standard format, and are drown up in
                    ad hoc manner. Indeed, even the name of the location may be written in a local
                    convention unfamiliar to the outsiders.</p>
                <p class="noindent">While each land deed may have significance only to its owner, a large collection
                    of them provides a fascinating glimpse into the pre-modern Taiwanese grassroots
                    society. Historians have studied them to investigate the economic activities,
                    community development, and the relationship among the various ethnic groups
                    (Chen, 1997; Ka, 2001; Shih, 2001; Hong, 2005).</p>
                <p class="noindent">In the past few years we have built a full-text digital library of primary
                    historical documents of Taiwan called THDL (<i>Taiwan History
                        Digital Library</i>). Among its corpuses is a collection of over 30,000
                    land deeds, spanning from 1666 to the first decade of the 20th century, and
                    collected from over 100 sources of origin (Hsiang, Chen, Tu, 2009). This
                    collection is unprecedented in terms of volume, time span, geographic
                    distribution, and variety. While THDL presents an exciting source of primary
                    materials for historians, it also poses a challenge: how to find the
                    relationship between two land deeds, or, how to find all the land deeds
                    involving the same piece of land. Although it was customary to hand down earlier
                    deeds to the new owner during the transaction of land, most of these links were
                    broken when the Japanese, during their colonial rule of Taiwan between 1895 and
                    1945, modernized the land management system (Li, 2004). That is because the
                    officials only recorded the last deed as the proof of ownership but ignored the
                    previous ones. Consequently many of the older deeds were either destroyed or
                    (later) sold as collector’s items because they had lost their original value. </p>
                <p class="noindent">In this paper we present a semi-automated method to discover the transaction
                    relations among land deeds. We shall focus on two important relations: <i>successive transaction pairs</i> and <i>allotment agreements</i>. We further connect the transitive activities on
                    the same piece of land into a concept called <i>land transitivity
                        graph</i>, which captures the history of the land over time. The largest
                    such graph that we found has led to a discovery of a new type of land use that
                    had never been observed before.</p>
            
            
                <h2>Discovering Land Transaction Relations</h2>
                <p class="noindent">We start by describing the two relations among land deeds that our method tries
                    to capture.</p>
                <p class="noindent"><i>Successive transaction pairs</i>: A piece of land could be
                    sold from A to B, then from B to C. In this case there should be two land deeds
                    recording the two transactions. We call them a <i>successive
                        transaction pair</i>. Note that the situation could be rather complicated.
                    For instance it could have been B’s son who sold it to C. If B divided the land
                    among his descendents, the first selling transaction and the ensuing allotment
                    agreement (see below) also form a successive transaction pair.</p>
                <p class="noindent"><i>Allotment agreements</i>: An allotment agreement is a deed
                    that records how a land is divided among the owner’s descendants or among the
                    shareholders. In both cases the usual practice is to first divide the land into
                    several parts, then to have each participant drawing from the lot. Once the
                    decision is agreed upon, an agreement is written, and several copies are made
                    and given to each person involved. In the case of division among shareholders,
                    the allotment agreements should be preceded by a <i>cultivation
                        permit</i>, a permission from the government to allow a group of people to
                    cultivate the land. In this case, the cultivation permit and the ensuing
                    allotment agreement also form a successive transaction pair.</p>
                <p class="noindent">
                    <p>
                        <h2>Fig. 1 The process for discovering land transaction relations</h2>
                        <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//120/figure1.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-120.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//120/figure1.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                    </p></p>
                
                <p class="noindent">To tackle this problem of finding successive transaction pairs, we developed a
                    3-step semi-automatic process (Fig. 1). We first used text processing technology
                    to extract features of each land deed from its metadata and full text. Such
                    features include the transaction type, the general location of the land and the
                        <i>four reaches</i> (boundaries identifying the land via
                    some obscure way such as “bordering Lee’s house on the south,” “a large camphor
                    tree on the west,” etc), the names of the people involved in the transaction and
                    their roles (seller, buyer, scrivener), description of the source of the land
                    (how and when the current owner obtained it), the size, the price, and the
                    amount of taxes paid (Lu, 2008; Huang, 2009). Fig. 2 is an example of a typical
                    land deed. We designed an XML format to hold this information (Fig. 3). Second,
                    we defined rules to identify deeds that may be related. Fig. 4 shows the rules
                    we used for identifying the <i>successive transaction pairs</i>.
                    We then wrote a program to compare every pair of land deeds in THDL to see if
                    any pair satisfied the rules. Finally, we give all the pairs produced to human
                    expert to verify.</p>
                <p class="noindent">
                    <p>
                        <h2>Fig. 2 An example of a typical land deed of Taiwan</h2>
                        <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//120/figure2.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-120.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//120/figure2.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                    </p>
                </p>
                
                <p class="noindent"> 
                    <p>
                        <h2>Fig. 3 The features of a “selling” type of land deed, stored in XML</h2>
                        <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//120/figure3.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-120.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//120/figure3.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                    </p>
                </p>
                
                <p class="noindent">We further remark that a criterion that allows certain degree of fuzziness was
                    used when performing matching. This is because the names used in different deeds
                    may sometimes be slightly different even if they are the same place or person
                    (Huang, 2009).</p>
                
                <p class="noindent">
                    <p>
                        <h2>Fig. 4 The rules for identifying successive transaction pairs</h2>
                        <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//120/figure4.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-120.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//120/figure4.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                    </p>
                </p>
                <p class="noindent">The precision rate of the algorithm for successive transaction pairs is 63.9% and
                    that for allotment agreements is 94.4%. We have found 2,409 successive
                    transaction pairs and 878 sets of allotment agreements among the 30,820 land
                    deeds in THDL (Table 1). 
                    <p>
                        <h2>Table 1 The result of reconstructing land transaction relations among the
                            land deeds in THDL</h2>
                        <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//120/table1.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-120.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//120/table1.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                    </p>
                    Among the former, 358 are cross-generation (A sold to
                    B, and B’s descendent sold to C). Some of the pairs/sets are from different
                    sources (the “cross sources” column in Table 1), and are quite impossible to
                    find manually. Some others are from the same source but are not adjacent to each
                    other in their original order. These are also difficult to identify by hand.
                </p>
            
            
                <h2>Land Transitivity Graphs</h2>
                <p class="noindent">When further examining the transaction pairs, an interesting transitive
                    phenomenon emerged. There may be a deed of A selling a piece of land to B, and
                    some years later B divided the land among his sons, then one of them, C, rented
                    it to D to farm. Such transitive activities on the same piece of land could last
                    for decades. By connecting all these transactions into a graph, it may capture
                    the evolution of a property over time. </p>
                <p class="noindent">This is exactly what we did. We call these graphs land transitivity graphs. Using
                    the relations we discovered early, we came up with 2,219 such graphs. The result
                    is listed in Table 2. </p>
                <p class="noindent">
                    <p>
                        <h2>Table 2 The land transitivity graphs constructed among the land deeds in
                            THDL</h2>
                        <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//120/table2.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-120.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//120/table2.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                    </p>
                    </p>
                <p class="noindent">Fig. 5, the third largest graph, contains 36 deeds, dating from 1850 to 1910. The
                    head of the family, Liao Jiafu (廖佳福), was among the shareholders who received a
                    cultivation permit from the Qing government, and obtained this piece of land
                    through allotment in 1850 (the first deed). 
                    <p>
                        <h2>Fig. 5 The 3rd large graph, containing 36 deeds</h2>
                        <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//120/figure5.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-120.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//120/figure5.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                    </p>
                    Liao farmed the land for 50 years
                    and divided it among his descendents in 1901 (the second deed). The rest of the
                    deeds described the various activities such as further divisions or selling in
                    the next 10 years. By 1906, only 2 of the 8 divided pieces of land remained in
                    the Liao family.</p>
                <p class="noindent">
                    <p>
                        <h2>Fig. 6 The largest graph, containing 103 deeds </h2>
                        <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//120/figure6.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-120.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//120/figure6.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                    </p>
                </p>
                <p class="noindent">Fig. 6 is the largest land transitivity graph with 103 deeds. Tu, a historian,
                    studied this graph and discovered that the deeds involved demonstrated a unique
                    case of land use that had never been studied before (Tu, 2010). It is unlikely
                    for human to notice this possibility without the computer-generated transitivity
                    graph.</p>
                <p class="noindent">To help historians take advantage of these graphs, we developed an integrated
                    environment to analyze the information embedded in each graph (Fig. 7). In
                    addition to the graph itself and its zoomable navigation facility, we also added
                    tag cloud, chronological distribution, and a location map.</p>
                <p class="noindent">
                    <p>
                        <h2>Fig. 7 The integration environment for land transitivity graphs</h2>
                        <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//120/figure7.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-120.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//120/figure7.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                    </p>
                </p>
            
            
                <h2>Concluding Remarks</h2>
                <p class="noindent">Land deed research has been an important topic among historians of pre-1900
                    Taiwan. In this paper, we presented a method to discover the transaction
                    relations among the 30,820 land deeds in THDL, the largest existing full-text
                    database of land deeds. Our method discovered 2,049 successive transaction pairs
                    and 878 sets of allotment agreements. They, in turn, are transformed into 2,219
                    land transitivity graphs, each of which describes the transaction evolution of a
                    piece of land. One such graph has already led to the discovery of a unique
                    pattern of land development that had not been studied before (Tu, 2010). We feel
                    that our work demonstrates how IT tools can be used to help historians conduct
                    research that could not be done otherwise.</p>
            
        <h2>References:</h2>
            
                
                    <p>
                        Chen, C. K.
                        1997
                        <i>Taiwan’s aboriginal proprietary rights in the Ch’ing
                            period: Bureaucracy, Han tenants and the transformation of property
                            rights of the Anli Tribe, 1700-1895</i>, 
                        Academia Sinica
                        Taipei
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Hong, L.W. 
                        2005
                        <i>A study of aboriginal contractual behavior and the
                            relationship between aborigines and Han immigrants in west-central
                            Taiwan</i>, 
                        1
                        Taichung County Cultural Center
                        
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Hsiang, J., Chen, S. P., Tu, H. C. 
                        2009
                         “On building a full-text digital library of land deeds of
                            Taiwan, ” 
                        <i>Digital Humanities 2009
                            Conference</i>, 
                        Maryland, 
                        June 22-25, 2009
                        85-90
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Huang, Y. M. 
                        2009
                        <i>On reconstructing relationships among Taiwanese land deeds.
                            Master thesis</i>, 
                        National Taiwan University
                        Taipei, Taiwan
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Ka, C. M.
                        2001
                        <i>The aborigine landlord: Ethnic politics and aborigine land
                            rights in Qing Taiwan</i>, 
                        Academia Sinica
                        Taipei
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Li, W. L.
                        2004
                         “Land deeds and land administrative documents—Interpreting
                            the Archives of the Japanese Taiwan Governor-Generals, ” 
                        <i>Taiwanese History Research</i>, 
                        11 (2)
                        221-240
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Lu, C. C. 
                        2008
                        <i>Automated Classification of Taiwanese Land Deeds. Master
                            thesis</i>, 
                        Taiwan University
                        Taipei, Taiwan
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Shih, T. F. 
                        2001
                        <i>Local society in Qing Taiwan</i>, 
                        Cultural Affairs Bureau
                        Hsinchu
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Tu, F. E. 
                        2010
                         “Environmental Change, Land development and Dispute over
                            Property Rights in southern Taiwan (1890-1920), ” 
                        <i>The Sixth Conference of Taiwan Colonial
                            Government Archives</i>, 
                        Taiwan Historica, 
                    </p>
                
            
        </div></div></body></html>