
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Alma Cardell Curtin and Jeremiah Curtin: the Translator’s Wife's Stylistic
					Fingerprint</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-195.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-195.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: Alma Cardell Curtin and Jeremiah Curtin: the Translator’s Wife's Stylistic
					Fingerprint</h2><h4>
					Rybicki, Jan, 
					Pedagogical University of Kraków, Poland, 
					<a href="mailto:jkrybicki@gmail.com">jkrybicki@gmail.com</a>
				</h4><hr />
			
				<h2>The Problem</h2>
				<p class="noindent">Poland’s first literary Nobel Prize winner, Henryk Sienkiewicz (1846-1916), owed
					his great if short-lived fame to the very numerous if very mediocre translations
					by Jeremiah Curtin (1835-1906), diplomat, ethnographer, polyglot. Born in a
					Catholic Irish family in Wisconsin, he graduated from Harvard and was posted as
					a secretary to the American mission in St. Petersburg, Russia; his fluency in
					Russian made him a popular figure among the local aristocracy. Paradoxically, it
					might have contributed to his conflict with Ambassador Clay and precipitated the
					end of his diplomatic career (1869). Curtin switched to two professions he
					continued till the end of his life: that of the ethnographer (employed, for a
					time, by the Smithsonian Institution) and of the literary translator. In 1872,
					he met and promptly married Alma Cardell (1847-1938), who soon abandoned her
					post as a teacher in a Soldiers’ Orphans’ Home (for which her studies at the
					Barre Academy had made her more than qualified) to become her husband’s
					secretary, amanuensis and editor; until her peripatetic husband’s death, her
					life was to be led in hotels and boarding houses around the globe – especially
					after the Curtins stroke gold with Sienkiewicz’s international bestseller <i>Quo vadis</i> (1896). Alma devoted much work to virtually all
					publications signed by Jeremiah: his translations of Sienkiewicz and of other
					Polish authors (Orzeszkowa, Prus and Potocki); his translations from the Russian
					(Gogol, Zagoskin’s and Alexy K. Tolstoy); and his ethnographic studies on myths
					of Native Americans, Ireland and Slavic peoples. She also published and edited
					three books on Mongols after her husband’s death.</p>
				<p class="noindent">Yet the story of Sienkiewicz’s translator is most extensively told in <i>Memoirs of Jeremiah Curtin</i> (1940), published after the
					death of Alma Cardell Curtin. Although written in first-person narrative, they
					have been since proven to be the work of the wife. Michael Jacek Miko? has shown
					that Curtin’s alleged memoirs are in fact a compilation of “somewhat edited"
					fragments of Alma’s diaries and letters to her family (Miko? 1990). The same
					diaries (and not the <i>Memoirs</i>) show the extent of Alma’s
					contribution to Jeremiah’s translations: after a whole day of taking her
					husband’s dictation, he would go to sleep while she would copy and correct the
					day’s work (Miko? 1994). And although she knew no Polish and, at most, but a
					little Russian, it is not implausible to suspect that some traces of the
					translator’s wife’s hand might have been left on Sienkiewicz’s fiction in
					English. In the most radical hypothesis by Cheryl L. Collins, Alma, “held
					hostage by Jeremiah’s almost pathological restlessness," could have been “his
					full partner" in his literary work (Collins 2008).</p>
				<p class="noindent">This presents a nice authorship attribution problem. All that could have been
					done in this respect with traditional methods has been done by Miko?; the rest
					is the attributor’s nightmare, as all work published under Curtin’s name has
					been preserved in manuscripts in Alma’s hand alone. And while traces of the
					style of the <i>Memoirs</i> could perhaps be found in Alma’s
					editions of Jeremiah’s ethnographic works, it is highly uncertain if similar
					traces can at all be found in his translations.</p>
			
			
				<h2>The Method</h2>
				<p class="noindent">All hope there is lies in non-traditional methods of authorship attribution,
					developed at least since the seminal <i>Inference and Disputed
						Authorship: the Federalist</i> (Mosteller, Wallace 1964) and proven to be
					helpful in plagiarism detection (although Alma’s is plagiarism <i>a rebours</i>). This study applies Cluster Analysis to normalized word
					frequencies in texts; as shown by (to name but a few) Burrows (1987, 2002),
					Hoover (2004, 2004a) or Daren-Oskam (2007), this is one of the most precise
					methods of “stylistic dactyloscopy." A script by Maciej Eder, written for the R
					statistical environment, converts the electronic texts to produce complete
					most-frequent-word (MFW) frequency lists, calculates their z-scores in each text
					according to the Burrows Delta procedure (Burrows 2002); selects words for
					analysis from various frequency ranges; performs additional procedures for
					better accuracy (Hoover’s culling and pronoun deletion); compares the results
					for individual texts; produces Cluster Analysis tree diagrams that show the
					distances between the texts; and, finally, combines the tree diagrams made for
					various parameters (number of words, degree of culling) in a bootstrap consensus
					tree (Dunn et al. 2005, quoted in Baayen 2008: 143-147).</p>
				<p class="noindent">The analysis included all original works by Curtin (12 extensive studies) and a
					great majority of his translations (21 novels or long novellas).</p>
				<p class="noindent">Figure 1. shows the patterns of similarity and difference of word frequencies in
					all texts studied. The bootstrap consensus tree neatly divides Curtin’s <i>oeuvre</i> into two discrete groups: the upper branches are
					his translations while his <i>Memoirs</i> and his ethnography
					lie below. Yet the <i>Memoirs</i> are placed away from his
					ethnographic studies; also, what has been proven by Miko? to be Alma’s work,
					lies close to two of Jeremiah’s books on the Mongols, published by Alma after
					his death.</p>
				<p class="noindent">
					<p>
						<h2>Figure 1. Consensus tree for all texts</h2>
						<img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei/195/195_fig1.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-195.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei/195/195_fig1.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
					</p>
				</p>
				<p class="noindent">The length of the word list used in this study (all the way to the 5000th most
					frequent word in the corpus) can raise doubts as to the validity, in this
					context, of the term <i>stylistic</i> similarity: after all,
					words so far down the frequency-ordered word list are often quite meaningful and
					might reflect differences of content as well as of style. Any chance of finding
					traces of the translator’s wife’s hand in the translations as well as in the <i>Memoirs</i> has to rely on somewhat shorter lists
					(tentatively, from 10 to 150) from the top of the frequency-ordered
					most-frequent-word list; dominated as it is by functions words and aided by a
					100% culling rate (which limits the analysis to words that appear in all texts
					studied) and personal pronoun deletion, it might help purge any impact of the
					texts’ content to try to bring, say, a book on Irish myths and a translation of
					Sienkiewicz’s historical romance, to a common stylistic, or perhaps simply
					lexical, denominator.</p>
				<p class="noindent">The new result is presented in Figure 2. The texts attributed to Mrs Curtin
					either by Miko? or by Figure 1. are still immediate neighbours; more
					interestingly, the <i>Memoirs</i> (and the two “Mongol" works)
					now grow on the same branch with two translations: <i>Lillian
						Morris</i> and <i>For Bread</i>.</p>
				<p class="noindent">
					<p>
						<h2>Figure 2. Consensus tree for short most-frequent-word lists and a 100%
							culling</h2>
						<img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei/195/195_fig2.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-195.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei/195/195_fig2.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
					</p>
				</p>
			
			
				<h2>Conclusions</h2>
				<p class="noindent">So far, attempts at finding stylistic traces of the translator or the editor have
					been only partially successful. Word-frequency-based stylometric methods have
					shown that they are better at attributing the author of the original than the
					translator (Rybicki 2009, 2010; Rybicki, Eder 2010), or that Henry James’s
					switch from writing to dictation left no stylistic trace (Hoover 2010).</p>
				<p class="noindent">This time, however, it is possible that the translator’s wife has left her mark.
					First, Miko?’s attribution of the <i>Memoirs of Jeremiah
						Curtin</i> is visible in the consensus tree diagrams; second, the diagrams
					seem to validate the suspicions of Mrs Curtin’s significant contribution to <i>The Mongols: A History</i> and <i>The Mongols
						in Russia</i>.</p>
				<p class="noindent">Even more importantly, the most frequent words in two of the Sienkiewicz
					translations seem to exhibit a greater affinity to the <i>Memoirs</i>. It is hardly a coincidence that the two short stories depart
					from Sienkiewicz’s usual male- and Poland-dominated writing. Indeed, <i>Lillian Morris</i> and <i>For Bread</i> are
					two of Sienkiewicz’s so-called “American stories" (written during or immediately
					after his stay in America, 1876-1879) and both feature a strong female
					protagonist. If it ever made sense for Curtin to give his wife a somewhat freer
					hand at shaping the final version of the English version of this or that
					Sienkiewicz text, it would have been on the occasion of these two stories. After
					all, during the work on <i>Lillian Morris</i> and <i>For Bread</i> in the Irish summer of 1893, Jeremiah was busy,
					struggling with several other projects at the same time: he was collecting
					material for one of his Irish mythologies, translating a couple of other short
					works Sienkiewicz, and writing a lengthy “Translator’s Preface’ to the Polish
					writer’s another historical romance, <i>Pan Michael</i>.</p>
			
		<h2>References:</h2>
			
				
					<p>
						Baayen, R.H.
						2008
						<i>Analyzing Linguistic Data. A Practical Introduction to
							Statistics using R</i>, 
						Cambridge
					</p>
					<p>
						Burrows, J.F.
						1987
						<i>Computation into Criticism: a Study of Jane Austen’s Novels
							and an Experiment in Method</i>, 
						Oxford
					</p>
					<p>
						Burrows, J.F.
						2002
						 “Delta: A Measure of Stylistic Difference and a Guide to
							Likely Authorship, ” 
						<i>Literary and Linguistic Computing</i>, 
						17
						267-287
					</p>
					<p>
						Collins, C.L.
						2008
						 “Behind the Curtin, ” 
						<i>Milwaukee Magazine</i>, 
						1. April
					</p>
					<p>
						Curtin, J.
						1940
						<i>Memoirs of Jeremiah Curtin</i>, 
						Madison
					</p>
					<p>
						Dalen-Oskam, K. van
						Zundert, J. van
						2007
						 “Delta for Middle Dutch—Author and Copyist Distinction in
							Walewein, ” 
						<i>Literary and Linguistic Computing</i>, 
						22
						345-362
					</p>
					<p>
						Dunn, M. 
						Terrill, A. 
						Reesink, G. 
						Foley, R.A.
						Levinson, S.C.
						2005
						 “Structural Phylogenetics and the Reconstruction of Ancient
							Language History, ” 
						<i>Science</i>, 
						309
						2072-2075
					</p>
					<p>
						Hoover, D.L.
						2004
						 “Testing Burrows's Delta, ” 
						<i>Literary and Linguistic Computing</i>, 
						19
						453-475
					</p>
					<p>
						Hoover, D.L.
						2004a
						 “Delta Prime?, ” 
						<i>Literary and Linguistic Computing</i>, 
						19
						477-495
					</p>
					<p>
						Hoover, D.L.
						2010
						 “Modes of Composition in Henry James: Dictation, Style, and
							What Maisie Knew, ” 
						<i>Proceedings of the Digital Humanities
							2009 conference</i>, 
						College Park, MD, 
					</p>
					<p>
						Miko, M.J.
						1990
						 “Alma Cardell Curtin, the Woman behind Jeremiah
							Curtin, ” 
						<i>Milwaukee History</i>, 
						13
						53-68
					</p>
					<p>
						Miko, M.J.
						1994
						<i>W pogoni za Sienkiewiczem</i>, 
						Warszawa
					</p>
					<p>
						Mosteller, F.
						Wallace, D.L.
						1964
						<i>Inference and Disputed Authorship: The Federalist</i>, 
						Reading
					</p>
					<p>
						Rybicki, J.
						2009
						 “Liczenie krasnoludków. Troch? inaczej o polskich
							przek?adach trylogii Tolkiena, ” 
						<i>Ludzie i krasnoludki – powinowactwa z
							wyboru? Conference proceedings</i>, 
						Warszawa, 
					</p>
					<p>
						Rybicki, J.
						2009
						 “Translation and Delta Revisited: When We Read Translations,
							Is It the Author or the Translator that We Really Read?, ” 
						<i>Proceedings of the Digital Humanities
							2009 conference</i>, 
						College Park, MD, 
					</p>
					<p>
						Rybicki, J.
						Eder, M.
						2011
						 “Deeper Delta Across Genres and Languages: Do We Really Need
							the Most Frequent Words?, ” 
						<i>Literary and Linguistic Computing</i>, 
						26
						(forthcoming)
					</p>
				
			
		</div></div></body></html>