
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Knowing and Doing: Understanding the Digital Humanities Curriculum</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-251.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-251.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: Knowing and Doing: Understanding the Digital Humanities Curriculum</h2><h4>
                    Spiro, Lisa, 
                    Rice University, 
                    <a href="mailto:lisamspiro@gmail.com">lisamspiro@gmail.com</a>
                </h4><hr />
            
                <p class="noindent">As the digital humanities have become more visible, attracting attention both
                    from publications such as the <i> Chronicle of Higher
                        Education</i> and from universities eager to develop emerging areas of
                    research and teaching, commentators have been debating what qualifies as digital
                    humanities and whether the community is sufficiently inclusive. In part, as
                    Geoffrey Rockwell suggests, this debate reflects digital humanities’ failure to
                    provide multiple paths to entry. In the past, many entered the digital
                    humanities by apprenticing with established practitioners, but such
                    opportunities are not available to all (Rockwell 2010). New educational programs
                    such as the MA in Digital Humanities at University College London and the
                    proposed MA in Knowledge and Networks at Duke are being put forward to address
                    these needs, joining established programs at Kings College London, University of
                    Alberta, and other universities. As educational opportunities expand, the
                    digital humanities (DH) community should examine how digital humanists are being
                    trained (Hirsch &amp; Timney 2010). Based on this knowledge, the community can
                    create a more coordinated (though still flexible) approach to the DH curriculum
                    that reflects its own commitment to openness, collaboration, interdisciplinarity
                    and experimentation. Education is fundamental both to how the community
                    comprehends itself and how it brings in new members. As Melissa Terras observes,
                    curriculum “can be seen to define the field in the way the publication record
                    cannot,” serving as a “hidden history” that reveals what knowledge experts
                    believe to be crucial and how that knowledge is transmitted (Terras 2005, p.1).
                    By examining digital humanities education, we can participate in a concrete
                    conversation about how to make the field both more inclusive and more targeted
                    toward the core knowledge and skills that digital humanists need.</p>
                <p class="noindent">In order to understand how the digital humanities are taught at universities
                    today, I will look at both curriculum and courses.I am in the process of
                        collecting and synthesizing information related to this research,
                        particularly through my Zotero group, “Digital Humanities Education” (<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-251.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=http://www.zotero.org/groups/digital_humanities_education#X" target="_top">http://www.zotero.org/groups/digital_humanities_education</a>), and
                        posts on my blog, “Digital Scholarship in the Humanities” (<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-251.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=http://digitalscholarship.wordpress.com/#X" target="_top">http://digitalscholarship.wordpress.com/</a>). I am also working on a
                        related project for Brett Hirsch’s collection <i>Teaching
                            Digital Humanities: Principles, Practices, and Politics</i> proposing
                        an open certificate for digital humanities.  First, to get a broader
                    perspective on the digital humanities <i>curriculum</i>, I will
                    examine degree requirements and curriculum plans for digital humanities
                    undergraduate, masters, and Ph.D. programs. How are digital humanities degree
                    programs structured? What courses are deemed necessary, and how are they
                    sequenced? To what extent are projects and/or internships required? How do
                    explicitly digital humanities programs compare to more traditional programs that
                    include a digital humanities component? How are collaboration and
                    interdisciplinarity inculcated? Case studies of several programs will be offered
                    to elucidate different approaches. </p>
                <p class="noindent"> I am also analyzing a collection of over 200 DH <i>syllabi</i>All of these syllabi were found through web searches.
                        Almost all are from universities in the United States, Canada and the UK.
                        The earliest syllabus is from the late 1990s, but the bulk are from the late
                        2000s. for both graduate and undergraduate courses. These syllabi
                    represent a variety of approaches to digital humanities, such as media studies,
                    text encoding, programming, and information visualization, and come from a range
                    of departments, including history, English, digital humanities, library and
                    information science, and computer science. I am examining: </p>
                
                    <li>What do these syllabi say about how knowledge in the digital humanities is
                        categorized and conceptualized? </li>
                    <li> What are the course goals? How is learning assessed? </li>
                    <li> How do these classes balance theory and practice? </li>
                    <li> To what extent do the courses reflect “digital pedagogy,” the thoughtful
                        use of technology to foster learning? </li>
                    <li> To what extent are blogging, Twitter, or other forms of networked
                        communication part of the course? </li>
                    <li> What are the most frequently assigned readings? Is a DH “canon” emerging? </li>
                    <li> What are some typical—and atypical—assignments? To what extent are
                        projects required? How are projects structured and evaluated? </li>
                    <li> How does the course reflect the practices and norms of its departmental
                        home? For example, how do courses on digital history compare to those on
                        digital literary studies or digital media studies? </li>
                    <li> How is humanistic as well as technical knowledge woven into the course?
                        What scholarly values do these courses promote? </li>
                
                <p class="noindent">I plan to use a combination of manual and automated methods to analyze the
                    syllabi corpus. I am tagging the syllabi using a set of custom keywords so that
                    I can sort them easily and see emerging patterns. I am also compiling a linked
                    bibliography of readings assigned in DH courses. In addition, I will experiment
                    with methods such as topic modeling and word frequency analysis to categorize
                    the syllabi and extract key concepts. </p>
                <p class="noindent">Although my research is still underway, my initial analysis of a subset of
                    approximately 50 syllabi suggests that:</p>
                
                    <li>Digital humanities courses tend to use readings that are freely available
                        online, such as <i>A Companion to Digital Humanities</i> and
                            <i>Digital History: A Guide to Gathering, Preserving, and
                            Presenting the Past on the Web</i>, as well as blog posts by authors
                        such as Dan Cohen and Bill Turkel. Given its apparent interest in
                        up-to-date, openly accessible information, the community would benefit from
                        openly sharing educational resources such as syllabi, assignments,
                        exercises, and tutorials. </li>
                    <li>While many digital humanities courses do focus on text, as Melissa Terras
                        noted in 2006 (Terras 2006), they have expanded to include topics such as
                        geospatial scholarship, multimedia design, and information visualization. </li>
                    <li>Many courses require students to create scholarly digital projects,
                        whether as individuals or in teams. </li>
                
                <p class="noindent"> In a sense, this research updates Melissa Terras’ 2005 study of the curriculum
                    in humanities computing, charting how the field has changed in the last five
                    years. I am returning to Terras’ question about whether the digital humanities
                    curriculum reflects the field’s research agenda and whether DH has emerged as an
                    “ academic subject,” capable of standing on its own (Terras 2005). I also hope
                    my research helps to inform the digital humanities curriculum going forward.
                    While the digital humanities curriculum should be nimble enough to keep up with
                    the pace of technological change, diverse enough to encompass the variety of
                    approaches to “big tent” digital humanities, and flexible enough to reflect the
                    strengths of particular institutions, the community can benefit from greater
                    coordination and sharing of educational resources to save labor, spread ideas,
                    and provide greater coherence across programs. Of course, my analysis will focus
                    on the characteristics of current DH education programs rather than on emerging
                    areas of skill development, but I hope to document innovative educational
                    approaches as well as points of consensus. Developing a DH curriculum may make
                    it easier for departments (and individuals) to understand what they need to do
                    to beef up their digital humanities portfolio and how they can specialize in
                    particular areas of knowledge. Although my study will not define such a
                    curriculum (which should be worked out by the community rather than an
                    individual), I hope that it will illustrate trends and gaps in digital
                    humanities education.</p>
            

        <h2>References:</h2>
            
                
                    <p>
                        Hirsch, B. D.
                        Timney, M
                        2010
                         “The Importance of Pedagogy: Towards a Companion to Teaching
                            Digital Humanities., ” 
                        <i>Digital Humanities 2010</i>, 
                        London, 
                        July 7-10, 2010
                        303
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Rockwell, G.
                        DATE
                         “Inclusion In The Digital Humanities, ” 
                        <i>philosophi.ca</i>, 
                        June 22, 2010
                        
         (<a href="http://www.philosophi.ca/pmwiki.php/Main/InclusionInTheDigitalHumanities " target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>

                    <p>
                        Terras, M.
                        2005
                         “Disciplined: Using Curriculum Studies to Define 'Humanities
                            Computing', ” 
                        <i>ACH/ALLC 2005</i>, 
                        Victoria, BC, Canada, 
                        June 15 - June 18, 2005
                        
         (<a href="http://pear.hcmc.uvic.ca:8080/ach/site/program.xq#abs_43" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Terras, M.
                        DATE
                         “Disciplined: Using Educational Studies to Analyse
                            'Humanities Computing', ” 
                        <i>Literary and Linguistic Computing</i>, 
                        21(2)
                        229-246
                        
         (<a href="http://llc.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/21/2/229" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                
            
        </div></div></body></html>