
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Approaching the Coasts of Utopia: Visualization
                    Strategies for Mapping Early Modern Paratexts</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-206.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-206.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: Approaching the Coasts of Utopia: Visualization
                    Strategies for Mapping Early Modern Paratexts</h2><h4>
                    Galey, Alan, 
                    University of Toronto, Canada, 
                    <a href="mailto:alan.galey@utoronto.ca">alan.galey@utoronto.ca</a>
                </h4><hr />
            
                <h2>Introduction</h2>
                <p class="noindent">No one reads or writes a book alone. Proof may be found in the paratextual
                    letters and other prefatory material that often accompanies a book into the
                    world to meet its readers. This is especially true of early modern books, whose
                    prefatory letters stand as a threshold where the book’s material and symbolic
                    production come together—sometimes as a well-executed plan (ex.: the 1518
                    editions of More’s <i>Utopia</i>), and sometimes as a collision
                    of intentions (ex.: the 1590 edition of Spenser’s <i>Faerie
                        Queene</i>, or the 1623 Shakespeare First Folio). However, print-based
                    methods of representing paratextual networks—especially in their temporal
                    dimension, across multiple editions and translations—tend to emphasize the
                    published book as product, at the expense of the book as a process. This paper
                    takes the textual tradition of Thomas More’s <i>Utopia</i>, with
                    its unfolding process of paratextual change between editions, as a test case for
                    the design of an open-source interface component to help digital editors
                    visualize networks of paratexts in early modern books.</p>
                <p class="noindent">The study of paratexts has been reinvigorated in recent years, crossing national
                    and period boundaries in the tradition of Gerard Genette’s Paratexts, but more
                    recently drawing energy from intersections between book history and digital
                    humanities as interdisciplinary fields. Building on ongoing research on the
                    digital modelling and visualization of paratexts and similar materials (Fekete
                    &amp; Dufournaud, 2000; Monella, 2008; Johnson), this paper argues that creating
                    a digital visualization component for mapping has two benefits: first that a
                    well-designed digital visualization can represent the structured fluidity and
                    temporality of publication as a process that unfolds in time; and second, that
                    the process of creating such a visualization affords a reciprocal opportunity to
                    interrogate the digital tools and systems we use to represent the past.</p>
                <p class="noindent">This paper develops its argument in four sections: 
                        <li>Research context: archive and interface in digital textual
                            studies</li>
                        <li><i>Utopia</i> as a modelling challenge</li>
                        <li>Visualization strategies</li>
                        <li>Conclusion: visualization prototypes as essays</li>
                    
                </p>
            
            
                <p class="noindent">The small-scale project outlined in this paper is part of a larger project titled
                    Archive and Interface in Digital Textual Studies: From Cultural History to
                    Critical Design, funded by the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council
                    of Canada. This project is premised on two linked arguments. The first is that
                    we need to understand how the figure of the archive operates in the cultural
                    imagination, and how perceptions of digital archives are partly coded in advance
                    by historical fears and desires about the continuity of knowledge. The second
                    premise is that we need to develop traditions of digital interface design native
                    to the humanities, and which reflect the humanities’ uniquely valuable
                    understanding of the cultural histories and material complexities of texts
                    (Kirschenbaum, 2004; Drucker, 2011). The Archive and Interface project therefore
                    seeks to bridge between textual studies and the design of digital interface
                    tools in the humanities. It does so first by investigating the cultural history
                    of the humanities archive through case studies such as <i>Utopia</i>, and second by building an online library of interface
                    components designed to be part of that cultural history.</p>
                <p class="noindent">The interface library will focus on critical design strategies in four key areas:
                    textual variation (when sources diverge in significant ways); paratexts
                    (documents such as prefatory letters, often published with literary works in
                    complex configurations); materiality (the relation of physical documents to
                    digital versions); and performance (the relation of written texts to reading or
                    enactment in physical spaces). This project’s interface library focuses on
                    putting humanities-designed interface components in the hands of electronic
                    editors, and disseminating the methods by which those components may be created
                    and modified by the larger community of computing humanists (the open-source
                    model). </p>
                <p class="noindent">Granting that large-scale editing systems like Anastasia and Edition Production
                    &amp; Presentation Technology have their place in the digital humanities, this
                    paper will argue that small-scale and (relatively) rapidly prototyped interface
                    components, built by individuals or small groups with inexpensive tools, can
                    reflect the critical, experimental nature of humanities design in ways that
                    large projects cannot. Such experimental capacity and structural flexibility is
                    necessary in digital humanities projects if they are to learn from challenging
                    materials like <i>Utopia</i>, and not simply take their
                    representability for granted.</p>
            
            
                <h2>Utopia as a Modelling Challenge</h2>
                <p class="noindent">The specific nature of <i>Utopia</i>’s challenge to a digital
                    editor is that <i>Utopia</i>’s publication, as a collaborative
                    project between early modern humanists, thematizes the very ideals and anxieties
                    about the dissemination of knowledge that digital humanists have inherited. The
                    book form—and by extension, the emergent network of humanist print culture—is
                    not merely a delivery system for <i>Utopia</i>, but also one of
                    its chief objects of scrutiny. In particular, <i>Utopia</i>
                    simultaneously embodies and critiques the early modern archive with unusual
                    perspicacity. This paper’s analysis follows Warren Wooden and John Wall by
                    approaching <i>Utopia</i> “not as an object of knowledge but as
                    an occasion for an act of perception, an instrument for ‘seeing’ designed to
                    call attention to what is involved in perception” (1985, p. 233). In this light,
                        <i>Utopia</i> itself serves as a kind of visualization of
                    the early modern humanist archive of texts. </p>
                <p class="noindent">We know from correspondence that More began writing <i>Utopia</i>
                    with what is now the second book. From a reader’s perspective, the text was
                    written in reverse, with book 1 (written second) placed before book 2 (written
                    first), and various prefatory materials (written last) accumulating before book
                    1. These prefatory materials—the letters, verses, diagrams, and maps that
                    constitute the paratext of <i>Utopia</i>—increase and vary
                    across the four editions published from 1516 to 1518, and change even more
                    radically in subsequent early modern and modern editions. </p>
                <p class="noindent">It is common for modern editions to completely remove or reconfigure <i>Utopia</i>’s carefully constructed paratexts (Allen, 1963).
                    Yet, paradoxically, there may be no single ideal configuration of paratexts,
                    making the interpretation of <i>Utopia</i> as a material text
                    especially reliant on representational methods and tools (Jardine, 1993; Leslie,
                    1998; Vallée, 2004; Kinney, 2005). Those tools have tended to take printed form,
                    culminating in Terence Cave’s printed guide to <i>Utopia</i>’s
                    paratextual tradition. However, <i>Utopia</i> can be taken as an
                    early experiment itself in humanist print culture, no less than the digital
                    experiments we discuss at digital humanities conferences, which makes <i>Utopia</i> anything but passive material for representation
                    and editing.</p>
            
            
                <h2>Visualization Strategies</h2>
                <p class="noindent">Given <i>Utopia</i>’s playful, experimental nature, this paper
                    argues for the need for a visualization strategy based not on static
                    representation, as in traditional forms of data visualization that represents
                    the results of analysis, but based rather on the idea of modelling. Unlike a
                    static representation, a digital model embodies the process-friendly dynamism we
                    expect of digital visualizations, but also a certain “rough-and-ready” form and
                    heuristic flexibility (McCarty, 2004). These latter qualities we associate not
                    with commercial software but with the community-designed code libraries found at
                    SourceForge and similar places, which serve as the dissemination model for the
                    Archive and Interface project’s visualization components. (On humanities
                    approaches to visualization, see Drucker, 2010, and other articles in the same
                    special issue of <i>Poetess Archive Journal</i> on “Visualizing the Archive.”)</p>
                <p class="noindent">The design methodology for the interface library will be consistent with Ajax web
                    applications, a type of architecture that distributes processing between a
                    server and a user’s web browser, and which integrates well with XML databases
                    and object-oriented design. HTML 5’s new capabilities on the client side permit
                    animation and time-based interactivity to be incorporated into interfaces in
                    ways that used to be exclusive to Flash. This paper will include a brief
                    demonstration of a browser-based interface component that uses animation to
                    model paratextual change over time. The prototype presented here will rely on
                    the encoding structures proposed by Monella (2008), but will approach the topic
                    from the browser and interface side instead of drawing conclusions about the
                    encoding.</p>
            
            
                <h2>Conclusion: Visualization Prototypes as Essays</h2>
                <p class="noindent">The two strategies proposed above, modelling and browser-based design, will serve
                    to illustrate the paper’s broader conclusion that a digital humanities project
                    organized around many small interface prototypes may yield more publishable
                    components, respond more quickly to critical discourse about the material, and
                    involve less risk than a single, large interface project. The nature of
                    paratexts calls for an interpretive approach to digital representation,
                    especially with material as complex as More’s <i>Utopia</i>.
                    This paper concludes that the humanistic critical tradition, embodied by <i>Utopia</i> as a collaborative project in publishing
                    technologies of its own time, calls digital humanists to think of their
                    visualizations and interface prototypes not just as finished tools, which
                    emphasize utility, but also as essays that put forward arguments and serve as
                    pretexts for debate—like <i>Utopia</i> itself.</p>
            
        <h2>References:</h2>
            
                
                    <p>
                        Allen, P. R. 
                        <i>Utopia</i> and European humanism: The function of
                            the prefatory letters and verses, Studies in the Renaissance, 10:
                            91–107.
                        
                        
                        1963
                        
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Anastasia
                        31 October 2010
                        
         (<a href="http://anastasia.sourceforge.net/" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Cave, T. 
                        Thomas More's Utopia in Early Modern Europe: Paratexts and Contexts. 
                        Manchester
                        Manchester University Press
                        2008
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Drucker, J.
                         “Humanities approaches to interface theory, ” 
                        <i>Culture Machine</i>, 
                        2011
                        12
                        1–20
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Drucker, J.
                         “Graphesis, ” 
                        <i>Poetess Archive Journal</i>, 
                        2010
                        2.1
                        1–50
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Edition Production &amp; Presentation Technology.
                        
         (<a href="http://www.eppt.org/eppt/" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                        accessed 31 October 2010
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Fekete, J.-D., and N. Dufournaud.
                        2000
                        Compus: Visualization and analysis of structured documents for
                            understanding social life in the 16th century
                        Proceedings of the Fifth ACM Conference on Digital Libraries
                        47-55
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Genette, G.
                        1997
                        Paratexts: Thresholds of Interpretation, trans. J.E. Lewin.
                        Cambridge
                        Cambridge University Press
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Jardine, L.
                        1993
                        Erasmus, Man of Letters: The Construction of Charisma in
                            Print
                        Princeton, NJ
                        Princeton University Press
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Johnson, J.P.
                        Pale Tour
                        
         (<a href="https://pantherfile.uwm.edu/johnso73/www/paletour/" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                        [accessed 31 October 2010]
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Kinney, A.F.
                        2005
                        Utopia's first readers.
                        In Challenging Humanism: Essays in Honor of Dominic
                            Baker-Smith
                        T. Honselaars and A.F. Kinney
                        Newark, NJ
                        University of Delaware Press
                        23-53
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Kirschenbaum, M.G.
                        2004
                        "So the colors cover the wires": Interface, aesthetics, and
                            usability.
                        A Companion to Digital Humanities
                        S. Schreibman, R.G. Siemens, and J. Unsworth.
                        Oxford
                        Blackwell
                        523-42
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Leslie, M.
                        1998
                        Renaissance Utopias and the Problem of History.
                        Ithaca, NY
                        Cornell University Press
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        McCarty, W.
                        2004
                        Modeling: A study in words and meanings.
                        A Companion to Digital Humanities
                        S. Schreibman, R.G. Siemens, and J. Unsworth
                        Oxford
                        Blackwell
                        254-70
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Monella, P.
                        2008
                        Towards a digital model to edit the different paratextuality levels
                            within a Textual Tradition
                        Digital Medievalist
                        4
                        
         (<a href="http://www.digitalmedievalist.org/journal/4/monella/" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                        accessed 31 October 2010
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Vallée, J.-F.
                        2004
                        Printed voices and written friendships in More's Utopia
                        Printed Voices: The Renaissance Culture of Dialogue
                        D. Heitsch and J.-F. Vallée
                        Toronto
                        University of Toronto Press
                        42-62
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Wooden, W.W., and J.N. Wall, Jr.
                        1985
                        Thomas More and the painter's eye: Visual perspective and artistic
                            purpose in More's Utopia
                        Journal of Medieval and Renaissance Studies
                        15
                        231-63
                    </p>

                
            
        </div></div></body></html>