
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Enroller: A Grid-based Research Platform for English and Scots
                              Language</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-271.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-271.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: Enroller: A Grid-based Research Platform for English and Scots
                              Language</h2><h4>
                              Anderson, Jean, 
                              University of Glasgow, 
                              <a href="mailto:Jean.Anderson@glasgow.ac.uk">Jean.Anderson@glasgow.ac.uk</a>
                        </h4><h4>
                              Alexander, Marc, 
                              University of Glasgow, 
                              <a href="mailto:Marc.Alexander@glasgow.ac.uk">Marc.Alexander@glasgow.ac.uk</a>
                        </h4><h4>Green, Johanna, 
                              University of Glasgow, 
                              <a href="mailto:Johanna.Green@glasgow.ac.uk">Johanna.Green@glasgow.ac.uk</a>
                        </h4><h4>Sarwar, Muhammad, 
                              National e-Science Centre, UK, 
                              <a href="mailto:Muhammad.Sarwar@glasgow.ac.uk">Muhammad.Sarwar@glasgow.ac.uk</a>
                        </h4><h4>
                              Sinnott, Richard, 
                              University of Melbourne, 
                              <a href="mailto:rsinnott@unimelb.edu.au">rsinnott@unimelb.edu.au</a>
                        </h4><hr />
                  
                        <h2>Summary</h2>
                        <p class="noindent">This paper describes a collaboration between eScientists and humanists;
                              specifically Grid scientists and language and literature scholars,
                              working together to create a repository of data sets and tools,
                              combining our most advanced knowledge in all areas. </p>
                  

                  
                        <h2></h2>
                        <p class="noindent">Language and literature scholars make use of variety of language
                              resources to conduct their research. Such resources include
                              dictionaries, thesauri, corpora, images, audio and video collections.
                              At present most of these resources are distributed, non-interoperable
                              and license protected. As a result researchers typically conduct their
                              research through direct access to independent data sets using multiple
                              browser windows and multiple authorisations. This approach results in
                              non-scalable and less productive research, and often leads to
                              incomplete and/or non-verifiable results. </p>
                        <p class="noindent">The JISC funded project, <i>Enhancing Repositories for
                                    Language and Literature Researchers</i> (Enroller) is
                              addressing these issues through development of a targeted eResearch
                              environment. This paper presents the current state of progress and
                              outlines how secure access to distributed data resources with targeted
                              analysis and collaboration tools is supported. In the full paper we
                              will also describe how Enroller is exploiting high performance
                              computing infrastructures such as the UK National Grid Service and
                              ScotGrid, and discuss a problematic issue that has arisen through the
                              differing working practices of humanists and scientists.Consider a
                              typical language and literature scenario where a researcher wants to
                              search for a word such as "bonny" in the dictionary to find its
                              meaning; in a thesaurus to look up the concepts and categories it is
                              found in and in a corpus to find the documents containing it. The user
                              may also want to see the concordances and word frequency of the word
                              in each found document. In undertaking this process, they might want
                              to save the different results; share them with others and possibly
                              perform a comparison between many different resultant data sets. This
                              scenario becomes more challenging when multiple dictionaries, thesauri
                              and text corpora need to be cross-searched simultaneously, for example
                              when the researcher wants to lookup the word "bonny" in the Oxford
                              English Dictionary, in the <i>Scottish National
                                    Dictionary</i>, and in the <i>Dictionary of the
                                    Older Scottish Tongue</i>. The researcher may also want to
                              search for the word in the <i>Historical Thesaurus of
                                    English</i> to look up synonyms and related concepts and
                              categories and then search for all of the matching concepts in further
                              corpus resources. </p>
                        <p class="noindent">Researchers will want to use the standard text analysis tools: e.g.
                              concordances, word frequencies, collocation clouds. They may well wish
                              to save and download the results for further analysis or use targeted
                              tools to investigate, e.g. variant spellings of the word 'bonny'. The
                              problem is further exacerbated if the researcher decides to search for
                              multiple, possibly hundreds, of words at once and do all of the
                              mentioned tasks at once. Most of the language and literature data
                              environments do not permit scholars to do any of these activities,
                              instead researchers are left with individual level data sets, coded
                              differently (e.g. with different metadata and data formatting),
                              accessible through individual web-based resources with individual
                              access codes and methods. </p>
                        <p class="noindent"> The challenge for the project is to maintain the data integrity of its
                              collaborators and the security of access-limited data, while
                              facilitating research across and between each dataset for the benefit
                              of researchers in multiple fields. Enroller provides an interactive
                              research infrastructure that provides seamless, secure access to all
                              of the different language and literature data sets in a user-oriented
                              environment. Furthermore, since many of the searching and analysis
                              efforts can be computationally intensive – especially when bulk
                              searching or building of indexes is required - we provide secure
                              access to high performance computing infrastructures such as the UK
                              e-Science National Grid Service (http://www.ngs.ac.uk) and ScotGrid
                              (http://www.scotgrid.ac.uk). In this project, language and literature
                              researchers, including an associated network of international
                              scholars, are now able to access large amounts of language and
                              literature data and analysis services from a single, easy-to-use
                              portal. Enroller is currently working with the following data sets: 
                                    <li>The EPSRC and AHRC funded <i>Scottish
                                                Corpus of Text and Speech</i> is a collection of
                                          text and audio files covering a period from 1945 to the
                                          present. The SCOTS corpus is available in TEI-compliant
                                          XML. (http://www.scottishcorpus.ac.uk) </li>
                                    <li>The AHRC funded <i>Corpus of Modern
                                                Scottish Writing</i> offers a collection of texts
                                          and manuscript images from the period 1700 to 1945.
                                          (http://www.scottishcorpus.ac.uk/cmsw/) </li>
                                    <li>The AHRC funded <i>Newcastle Electronic
                                                Corpus of Tyneside English</i> provides a corpus of
                                          dialect speech from Tyneside in Northeast England. The
                                          NECTE corpus is encoded in TEI-compliant XML.
                                          (http://www.ncl.ac.uk/necte) </li>
                                    <li>The <i>Dictionary of the Scots
                                                Language</i> encompasses two major Scottish
                                          language dictionaries: the <i>Scottish
                                                National Dictionary</i> and the <i>Dictionary of the Older Scottish Tongue</i>. DSL
                                          data is available in XML format.
                                          (http://www.dsl.ac.uk/dsl) </li>
                                    <li> The <i>Historical Thesaurus of
                                                English</i> contains more than 750,000 words from
                                          Old English to the present in 250,000 categories. HTE was
                                          published in print form by Oxford University Press in 2009
                                          and is a new and significant development for historical
                                          language studies.
                                          (http://libra.englang.arts.gla.ac.uk/historicalthesaurus/) </li>
                                    <li> The <i>Oxford English Dictionary</i> is a
                                          commercial resource published by Oxford University Press
                                          and is the authority on English language vocabulary. It is
                                          accessible through our search interface by API.
                                          (http://www.oed.com) </li>
                              
                        </p>
                        <p class="noindent"> The inclusion of other data sets is underway, e.g. we have incorporated
                              Hansard, early C19th to late C20th, and are negotiating for the 1755
                                    <i>Dictionary</i> of Samuel Johnson. Many
                              scholars have no platform or assistance to put texts online and make
                              them accessible to others, far less can they make them interoperable
                              with other relevant data sets. Enroller provides a place where users
                              can deposit their own texts. Texts are wrapped in a basic, TEI minimal
                              XML envelope and indexed. The user can choose whether a text is
                              available to all or private. Once deposited a text can be searched
                              from the portal with the other data sets. </p>
                        <p class="noindent">The project has data at its heart, but it is also exploiting state of the
                              art high-performance computing and security solutions. In particular
                              the project is employing a Virtual Organisation Membership Service
                              (VOMS)-based solution in accessing the NGS where pooled Enroller
                              accounts are used by researchers accessing these resources through a
                              targeted project portal. This includes use and exploitation of the
                              Workload Management System (WMS) to provide resource broking based job
                              scheduling across all of the NGS nodes. This job scheduling is
                              targeted currently to supporting large-scale searching based upon the
                              Google MapReduce application. </p>
                        <p class="noindent"> The full paper will describe the Enroller project in more detail and
                              outline the capabilities that are supported and our experiences so far
                              in implementing this infrastructure. This includes a description of
                              how the portal has been made accessible through the UK Access
                              Management Federation; the easy to use search system and the reasons
                              for its human-computer interface choices; the advanced Grid-based
                              information retrieval system, capable of executing linguistic
                              workflows, taking advantage of HPC facilities such as NGS and
                              ScotGrid; how the system supports large-scale data indexes for fast
                              searching; support for tools for linguistic analysis, including
                              concordance, collocation and word frequency analysis; support for
                              seamless secure access to licensed data; support for data deposition
                              and automated indexing services; documented analysis of our user
                              experiences in using of the infrastructure provided thus far. We will
                              outline the plans for future adoption by the wider research community
                              and end with our reflections on this eScience/humanities
                              collaboration. </p>
                  
            <h2>References:</h2>
                  
                        
                              <p>
                                    J. Watt
                                    .O. Sinnott
                                    T. Doherty
                                    J. Jiang
                                    2008
                                     “Portal-based Access to Advanced Security
                                          Infrastructures, ” 
                                    <i>UK e-Science All Hands
                                          Meeting </i>, 
                                    Edinburgh, 
                                    September 2008
                                    17
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                    M.S. Sarwar
                                    R.O. Sinnott
                                    2010
                                     “Towards a Virtual Research Environment for
                                          Language and Literature Researchers, ” 
                                    <i>IEEE e-Science 2010 </i>, 
                                    Brisbane, Australia, 
                                    December 2010
                                    8
                              </p>

                              <p>
                                    <i> Java Database Connectivity (JDBC) API</i>, 
                                    15/03/2011
                                    
         (<a href="http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javase/tech/index-jsp-136101.html" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                    <i>The Internet2 Shibboleth framework </i>, 
                                    15/03/2011
                                    
         (<a href="http://shibboleth.internet2.edu" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                              </p>

                              <p>
                                    <i>Enroller</i>, 
                                    15/03/2011
                                    
         (<a href="http://www.glasgow.ac.uk/enroller/" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                              </p>

                              <p>
                                    <i>Oxford English Dictionary </i>, 
                                    15/03/2011
                                    
         (<a href="http://www.oed.com" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                    <i>Scotish Language Dictionaries </i>, 
                                    15/03/2011
                                    
         (<a href="http://www.dsl.ac.uk" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                    <i>The Scottish Corpus of Texts and Speech</i>, 
                                    15/03/2011
                                    
         (<a href="http://www.scottishcorpus.ac.uk/" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                    <i>Newcastle Electronic Corpus of Tyneside
                                          English</i>, 
                                    15/03/2011
                                    
         (<a href="http://research.ncl.ac.uk/necte/" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                              </p>
                              <p>
                                    <i>The Historial Thesaurus of English </i>, 
                                    15/03/2011
                                    
         (<a href="http://libra.englang.arts.gla.ac.uk/WebThesHTML/homepage.html" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                              </p>

                        
                  
            </div></div></body></html>