
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>The Cultural Impact of New Media on American Literary Writing: Refining a
               Conceptual Framework</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-258.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-258.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: The Cultural Impact of New Media on American Literary Writing: Refining a
               Conceptual Framework</h2><h4>
               Paling, Stephen, 
               School of Library and Information Studies, University of
                  Wisconsin-Madison, 
               <a href="mailto:paling@wisc.edu">paling@wisc.edu</a>
            </h4><hr />
         
            <h2>Introduction </h2>

            <p class="noindent"> This paper describes a survey study Data gathering is under way at the time of
                  this writing. The data gathering will be complete by the time of the
                  conference. that is part of an ongoing effort (Paling &amp; Martin, 2009;
               Paling, 2008; Paling &amp; Nilan, 2006) to extend Social Informatics(Kling, 1999) to
               the study of literature and art. This series of studies has focused on the emergence
               of new forms of literary expression offered by information technology, and whether
               and how those possibilities are finding a place alongside traditional forms of
               expression in American literary writing. The study is meant to be complementary to
               more discursive, hermeneutic views of literary work. Discursive discussion of
               literary work provides rich descriptions of work by selected authors. In contrast, a
               survey enables us to look at the actions of literary community members in the
               aggregate. This study is based, in part, on the idea that various forms of inquiry
               into emerging literary practices, taken together, will provide a more complete
               picture than any one form of inquiry alone can provide. Different approaches to
               inquiry need not be seen as oppositional. </p>
         

         
            <h2>The Previous Studies </h2>

            <p class="noindent">The previous studies in this series (Paling and Martin, 2009; Paling, 2008; Paling
               &amp; Nilan, 2006) developed, and found support for, a conceptual framework made up
               of four key values that typify American literary writing: </p>

            

               <li>Positive Regard for Symbolic Capital. </li>

               <li>Negative Regard for Immediate Financial Gain. </li>

               <li>Positive Regard for Autonomy. </li>

               <li>Positive Regard for Avant-garde-ism. </li>
            

            <p class="noindent"><i>Positive regard</i> was operationalized as responses that indicated admiration
               or desire for particular qualities, e.g., a desire to read an author's work based on
               previous work by that author. Similarly, <i>avant-garde</i> was operationalized as
               valuation of particular characteristics, e.g., a preference for literary work that is
               fresh or innovative, or electronic work that has characteristics that cannot be
               produced in print form. </p>

            <p class="noindent">The previous studies examined the ways in which literary authors could use
               information technology to change those key values. They posited, and found support
               for, the idea of <i>Intensifying Use of Technology</i>, which has three
               characteristics: </p>

            
               <li>Recognition of new forms of support for a value. </li>

               <li>Incomplete rejection of traditional forms of support for the value. </li>

               <li>Placement of greater emphasis on the newer forms of support. </li>
            


            <p class="noindent">For example, a fiction writer could use a hypermedia editor to produce non-linear,
               electronic fiction (recognition). She might prefer this newer form of fiction
               (greater emphasis on newer form of support), but also continue to write more
               traditional work (incomplete rejection). </p>

            <p class="noindent">The original study in the series (Paling &amp; Nilan, 2006) involved interviews with
               a purposive sample for heterogeneity (n=36) of editors of American little magazines.
               That study used primarily qualitative methods. The second study (Paling, 2008)
               involved the same sampling method (n=22), but focused on American literary authors.
               Paling (2008) used both qualitative data as well as quantitative data derived from
               Likert scales. The third study in the series (Paling &amp; Martin, 2009) was a pilot
               survey with a random sample (n=84), and that study led directly to the development of
               the current study. The original studies all showed the presence of intensifying use
               of technology, but differed in terms of how common that phenomenon seems to be.
               Because two of the three samples were non-random, and all three were relatively
               small, a larger, random sample will lead to firmer conclusions about the research
               questions. </p>
         

         
            <h2>The Current Study </h2>

            <p class="noindent">The current study concentrated on two research questions: 
                  <li>RQ1: Do members of the American literary community show support for Positive
                     Regard for Avant-garde-ism? </li>

                  <li>RQ2: Do the actions of members of the American literary community reflect
                     Intensifying Use of Technology with regard to Positive Regard for
                     Avant-garde-ism? </li>
               
            </p>
            <p class="noindent">Positive Regard for Avant-garde-ism was selected from the four key values that make
               up the conceptual framework because it is the most relevant to the use of information
               technology. It is directly relevant, for example, to how much participants value the
               use of information technology to produce innovative writing that cannot be done in
               print. However, the other key values play an important role in establishing the
               context within which a value such as Positive Regard for Avant-garde-ism comes into
               play, and they were retained as an important part of this study. </p>

            <p class="noindent">The current study represents a clear methodological progression along the line of
               research begun in the earlier studies. A total of 900 invitations for participation
               were sent out. The names were selected randomly from a sampling frame built based on
               publicly available lists from The Association of Writers and Writing Programs and the
               Modern Language Association, as well as print directories such the Council of
               Literary Magazines and Small Presses' <i>Literary Press and Magazine Directory</i>.
               This yielded a sample of exactly 400 participants. All of the potential participants
               live, work, or study in America, or work for a publisher whose primary presence is in
               America. An international sample would be desirable in the future, but was beyond the
               scope and funding level of this study. </p>

            <p class="noindent">The respondents were asked to complete a mail survey composed of brief yes/no or
               checklist questions, as well as questions that included Likert-type numeric scales.
               The questions were refined versions from the interviews in the earlier studies in the
               series. Data, and respondent comments, from the earlier studies uncovered minor
               problems with question wording, scaling, etc. Because of that, the data from this
               study cannot be combined with data from the earlier studies. Conclusions from the
               current study, though, should be given greater weight than conclusions from the
               earlier studies because of the larger, random sample and the refined questions. </p>
         

         
            <h2>Reconciling the Studies </h2>

            <p class="noindent">Much of the apparent difference between the previous studies seems to have resulted
               from the different sampling methods used in the studies in this series. The first two
               studies (Paling, 2008; Paling &amp; Nilan, 2006), as mentioned earlier, used
               purposive sampling for heterogeneity. In other words, an effort was made to seek out
               editors and authors who were actively involved in producing literature with a
               substantial electronic component. The strength of purposive sampling is that it
               allows this kind of effort to closely examine different segments of a community such
               as people who participate in American literary writing. The weakness of such
               sampling, though, is that it is very difficult to create a purposive sample that
               reflects not just the presence of particular phenomena, but also an accurate sampling
               of how widespread the phenomenon is. </p>

            <p class="noindent">The pilot survey (Paling &amp; Martin, 2009) did find limited demonstration of
               Intensifying Use of Technology. One respondent showed unambiguous evidence of
               Intensifying Use of Technology. A number of other respondents (8) demonstrated
               somewhat similar, but less pronounced, patterns of Intensifying Use of Technology.
               This would suggest that somewhere around 10% of the American literary community
               demonstrates Intensifying Use of Technology, although the conceptualization of that
               phenomenon may need to be altered to reflect the opinions of community members who
               place strong positive value on technological innovation in literature, but who do not
               actually place greater emphasis on such forms of literature. </p>

            <p class="noindent">Taken together, the previous studies suggest that we need to modify, but not reject,
               the concept of Intensifying use of Technology. Intensifying Use of Technology is a
               real phenomenon, but is not, to date, widespread in American literary writing. More
               importantly, the American literary establishment demonstrates very limited levels of
               the phenomenon. This conclusion is very similar to the conclusion reached by Rettberg
               (2009). Rettberg argued that electronic literature constitutes a literary
               avant-garde, but an avant-garde that is not part of any institutionalized mainstream.
               However, Rettberg's work represents the analysis of an individual directly involved
               in those efforts, and did not involve structured data gathering to address the
               actions of literary community members in the aggregate. The current study takes the
               contrasting approach, gathering data from respondents across the literary community
               to begin developing a larger picture of how information technology is influencing
               contemporary American literary writing. The size and type of the sample used in this
               study should help resolve any ambiguities raised in the previous studies. </p>
         
      <h2>References:</h2>
         
            
               <p>Kling, R
                  1999.  “What is Social Informatics and why does it
                     matter?, ” 
                  <i>D-Lib</i>, , vol. 5, no. 1.
                  Retrieved September 12, 2006. Available from 
         (<a href="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/january99/kling/01kling.html" target="blank">link</a>)
    [Accessed
                  November 15, 2009]. </p>

               <p>Paling, S &amp; Nilan, M
                  2006.  ““Technology, values, and genre change: the
                     case of little magazines”, ” , <i>Journal of the American
                     Society for Information Science and Technology</i>, , vol. 57, no. 7, pp. 862-872. </p>

               <p>Paling, S
                  2008.  ““Technology, genres, and value change:
                     literary authors and aesthetic use of information technology”, ” , <i>Journal of the American Society for Information Science and
                     Technology</i>, , vol. 59, no.
                     8, pp. 1238-1251. </p>

               <p>Paling, S &amp; Martin, C
                  2009.  ““Toward a theory of technological
                     transformation in artistic genres”, ” , paper presented at the <i>American Society for Information Science and Technology Annual
                     Meeting, Social Informatics Symposium</i>, , Vancouver, BC. </p>

               <p>Rettberg, S
                  2009.  ““Communitizing electronic literature”, ” ,
                     <i>Digital Humanities Quarterly</i>, , vol. 3, no. 1. Available from 
         (<a href="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/2/000046.html" target="blank">link</a>)
    [Accessed
                  November 15, 2009]. </p>
            
         
      </div></div></body></html>