
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Towards a Narrative GIS</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-388.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-388.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: Towards a Narrative GIS</h2><h4>
                    McIntosh, John, 
                    <a href="mailto:jmcintosh@ou.edu">jmcintosh@ou.edu</a>
                    University of Oklahoma, 
                </h4><h4>
                    De Lozier, Grant, 
                    <a href="mailto:ghaxed@gmail.com">ghaxed@gmail.com</a>
                    University of Oklahoma, 
                </h4><h4>
                    Cantrell, Jacob , 
                    <a href="mailto:jcantrell@ou.edu">jcantrell@ou.edu</a>
                    University of Oklahoma, 
                </h4><h4>
                    Yuan, May, 
                    <a href="mailto:myuan@ou.edu">myuan@ou.edu</a>
                    University of Oklahoma, 
                </h4><hr />
            
                <h2>Introduction</h2>
                <p class="noindent">Research in narrative intelligence applies artificial intelligence approaches to
                    study human ability to organize experience into narrative form (Mateas and
                    Sengers 2003). Narratives are traditionally defined as “a series of temporally
                    ordered clauses” (Labov 1972, p360-361). The time-centric approach leads to a
                    lesser consideration of space in narrative construction and analysis. In
                    contrast, we advocate a geospatial narrative in order to stress the importance
                    of space and time in understanding the ordering and spatial interaction of
                    events.</p>
                <p class="noindent">We define a geospatial narrative as a sequence of events in which space and time
                    are equally important. Narratives are stories that constitutes sequential
                    organizations of events (Franzosi 2010). Each event in a narrative relates
                    sequential or consequential occurrence in space and time. The conventional
                    Geographic Information Systems (GIS) center on information about spatial states
                    of reality, and temporal information is handled as add-ons to spatial objects.
                    Alternatively, we conceptualize a narrative GIS that emphasizes representing and
                    ordering events in space and time as well as functional abilities to construct
                    meaningful geospatial narratives. While an event is a complex, fuzzy term, we
                    start with one basic linguistic element of narratives: action, as the primitive
                    data construct to start building a narrative GIS. By relating action events
                    across space and time, a narrative GIS aims to discover spatiotemporal
                    correlates among actions and relate actions across scales.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Depending on the perspectives, there are many kinds of events, e.g. instantaneous
                    events, discrete events, cyclic events, transitional events, and others. In
                    contrast to TimeMaps (Farrimond et al. 2008), our vision of a Narrative GIS goes
                    beyond spatiotemporal visualization to spatial analytics. By using action events
                    as the primitive data constructs, a narrative GIS can support spatial queries of
                    sequential and consequential actions. A Narrative GIS is therefore capable of
                    revealing how time unfolds change and space unfolds interactions (Massey
                    2005).</p>
                <p class="noindent">We use two distinctive corpuses of histories in building narrative GIS databases
                    and narrative analytics as a proof of concepts: Dyer's <i>Compendium of the War of the Rebellion</i> and the <i>Richmond Daily Dispatch</i>. Frederick H. Dyers, a Civil War veteran
                    compiled the <i>Compendium</i> based on materials from the
                    Official Records of the Union and Confederate Armies and other sources. The
                    compendium lists organizations and movements of regiment cavalries mustered by
                    State and Federal Governments for services in the Union Armies. Collaborating
                    with the digital scholarship group at the University of Richmond, we have
                    started with four files from Dyer's Compendium: the 45th Massachusetts Infantry,
                    the 107th Pennsylvania
                    Infantry,the1stCaliforniaInfantry,andthe1stNewYorkCavalry. The <i>Richmond Daily Dispatch</i> was one of the primary news media in the south
                    during the Civil War. The newspaper was one of the most widely distributed
                    newspapers of the south and included news from the entire east coast. The <i>Richmond Daily Dispatch</i> retained the reputation as
                    politically unbiased was published throughout the Civil War.</p>

            
            
                <h2>Methodology</h2>
                <p class="noindent">Our idea of a narrative GIS consists of (1) semantic elements (who did what), (2)
                    temporal elements (when), and (3) spatial elements (where). A geospatial
                    narrative object integrates the three elements and enables search for and
                    analysis of spatial and temporal relationships among narrative objects. Input
                    data for narrative GIS vary widely from structured to unstructured sources. In
                    this study, both input data are texts, albeit in very different structures.
                    Dyer's Compendium concisely lists regiment movements. <i>Richmond
                        Daily Dispatch</i> consists of news articles. Spatial and temporal
                    connections among units in these texts are considerably different. Nevertheless,
                    the conceptual framework of a narrative GIS demands the identifications of
                    semantic, temporal, and spatial elements from the texts to form narrative
                    objects and relationships. As such, our workflow includes six key steps: (1)
                    extract text analysis units; (2) identify action verbs; (3) identify time for
                    words and text units; (4) identify locations for words and text units; (5)
                    combine all identified elements into a GIS database; and (6) build spatial and
                    temporal relationships among narrative objects. A schematic view of the workflow
                    is presented in <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-388.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">figure 1</a>
                    <p>
                        <h2>Figure 1</h2>
                        <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//388/figure1.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-388.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//388/figure1.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                    </p>
                </p>
                <p class="noindent">We begin with electronic versions of the historical documents. The texts are
                    split into subsets such as newspaper articles or book chapters for processing.
                    These subsets are typically written as a unit and need to be analyzed that way
                    for successful interpretation. For each processing unit, we apply natural
                    language processing to tokenize sentences and identify parts of speech (e.g.
                    verbs and nouns). The parts of speech provide important clues to extract
                    information.</p>
                <p class="noindent">The work presented here is centered on the location, time, and other
                    characteristics of events. The part of speech tagging is used to identify verbs.
                    We are most interested in “action” verbs and refine our list of potential
                    candidates by removing stative and modal verbs. Location referencing begins with
                    recognition of a standard grammatical structure to the way locations appear in
                    text. In general, locations are proper nouns that do not directly follow a
                    determiner (except for physical features).</p>
                <p class="noindent">Candidate words are matched to all their possible real-world geographic referents
                    in the “Gazetteer Matching” process. A number of different gazetteers are
                    utilized in the matching including the US Populated Places gazetteer and State
                    hydrography datasets from the USGS, historical counties, states, and territories
                    files from National Historical Geographic Information System, and the US Census
                    Bureau’s historical 100 largest cities dataset (US BGN; US NHD; NHGIS 2008;
                    Gibson 2008). These data are assembled in GIS and each location is identified
                    with a historically and spatially appropriate hierarchy. The names of geographic
                    locations are often highly ambiguous. For example “Georgetown” has over 70
                    possible locations among U.S. cities. Disambiguating a word to its true location
                    is an important and difficult task. A substantial amount of work has already
                    been done on location disambiguation under the heading of “Toponym Resolution”
                    (Leidner2007;Leidneretal2003). <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-388.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Figure 2</a>
                    illustrates the steps in the location referencing process.
                    <p>
                        <h2>Figure 2</h2>
                        <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//388/figure2.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-388.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//388/figure2.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                    </p></p>
                <p class="noindent">The temporal processing steps aim to extract dates, durations of events and the
                    relative temporal ordering between events. Historical texts contain temporal
                    information in a variety of formats. Most obvious are explicit dates that
                    include information such as the day, month and year. In addition, these texts
                    often include clues to derive dates and relative ordering of events. For example
                    words such as “yesterday“ or “last week” allow the date to be derived based on a
                    temporal relation to an anchor date (Han 2006). Similarly, relative temporal
                    expressions allow explicit dates to be determined based on temporal relations to
                    the current temporal focus (Han 2009).</p>
                <p class="noindent"><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-388.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Figure 3</a> outlines the steps in our
                    approach. 
                    <p>
                        <h2>Figure 3</h2>
                        <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//388/figure3.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-388.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//388/figure3.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                    </p>We begin by extracting anchor dates such as the date of publication
                    for a newspaper article and explicit dates found in the text. We use temporal
                    indicator words to refine the date of events and help establish temporal
                    ordering. Explicit dates contained in the text are modified by deictic or
                    temporal expressions. Semantic relationships between events are extracted based
                    on semantic indicators. When all of the temporal information is relative and
                    there are no explicit dates to give an explicit order, thirteen temporal
                    relationships are used to find the temporal ordering (Allen 1983).</p>
            
            
                <h2>Results and Concluding Remarks</h2>
                <p class="noindent">Thus far, our effort has been focused on extraction of events from the natural
                    language text sources, anchoring the events to geographical locations and in
                    time, and extracting information on the actors and objects involved in the
                    events. <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-388.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Figure 4</a> illustrates results from
                    Dyer's Compendium of the War of the Rebellion. 
                    <p>
                        <h2>Figure 4</h2>
                        <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//388/figure4.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-388.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//388/figure4.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                    </p>This figure shows the activity of
                    the 6th New York Regiment Calvary in Maryland and Virginia in September and
                    October of 1862. The processing identified the events including the regiment’s
                    movements and splitting off of a reconnaissance mission from Lovettsville to
                    Smithville while the main regiment moved to Kearnysville. While this example
                    from a single source, it illustrates the potential for the system to support
                    more complex geospatial narratives with the addition of information from other
                    sources.</p>
                <p class="noindent"><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-388.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Figure 5</a> shows a visualization of a
                    Richmond Daily Dispatch article. <p>
                        <h2>Figure 5</h2>
                        <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//388/figure5.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-388.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//388/figure5.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                    </p>
                    The article describes a letter
                    from a Union colonel to his family. It discusses the Union’s plan to move troops
                    to Alexandria Virginia the next evening. The article illustrates that in
                    addition to working with events that had already occurred the approach can also
                    be used to help investigate the thoughts and motivation leading to events that
                    had yet to occur.</p>
                <p class="noindent">These examples of preliminary results demonstrate the basic use of a Narrative
                    GIS. As we continue building the event narrative database, additional functions
                    will be built in for narrative analytics. For example, we are interested in
                    deciphering the local, regional and national processes on emancipation and to
                    identify scalar effects on military, political, and individual processes. One
                    approach will be extracting reports on battles and run-away slaves and analyze
                    spatial and temporal correlations among these events. When we extract events of
                    different categories in space and time, a Narrative GIS will allow us to analyze
                    spatial and temporal relationships among these kinds of events to draw insights
                    into the integration of multiple perspectives and interpretations of geospatial
                    narratives.</p>
            
        <h2>References:</h2>
            
                
                    <p>
                        Allen, J.
                        Waltz, D. 
                        1983
                        Maintaining Knowledge about Temporal Intervals
                        Communications of the ACM
                        26
                        11
                        32-843
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Bird, S.
                        Klein, E. 
                        Loper, E. 
                        2009
                        Natural Language Processing with Python --- Analyzing Text with the
                            Natural Language Toolkit
                        Cambridge, MA
                        O'Reilly Media
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Farrimond, B.
                        Presland, S.
                        Bonar-Law, J. 
                        Pogson, F. 
                        2008
                        Making History Happen: Spatiotemporal Data Visualization for
                            Historians
                        Second UKSIM European Symposium on Computer Modeling and
                            Simulation
                        Liverpool, UK
                        IEEE
                        424-429
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Fellbaum, C.
                        1998
                        WordNet: An Electronic Lexical Database
                        Cambridge, MA
                        The MIT Press
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Franzosi, R.
                        2010
                        Quantitative Narrative Analysis
                        Los Angelas, CA
                        SAGE Publications, Inc.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Gibson, C.
                        2008
                        Population Of The 100 Largest Cities And Other Urban Places In The
                            United States: 1790 to 1990. U.S. Census Bureau, Population
                            Division
                        
                        
         (<a href="http://www.census.gov/population/www/documentation/twps0027/twps0027.html" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Han, B.
                        Gates, D.
                        Levin, L.
                        2006
                        From Language to Time: A Temporal Expression Anchorer
                        Proc. 13th International Symposium on Temporal Representation and
                            Reasoning
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Han, B.
                        2009Reasoning about Temporal Scenario in Natural
                            LanguageIn the Proceedings of AAAI Workshop on Spatial
                            and Temporal Reasoning</p>
                    <p>
                        Jackendoff, R.
                        1992
                        Languages of the Mind
                        Cambridge, MAThe MIT Press
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Labov, W.
                        1972
                        Language in the inner cityPhiladelphia
                        University of Pennsylvania Press
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Leidner, J, L.
                        Sinclair, G.
                        Webber, B
                        2003
                        Grounding spatial named entities for information extraction and
                            question answering
                        Proceedings of the HLT-NAACL 2003 Workshop on Analysis of Geographic
                            References
                        Edmonton, CAN
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Leidner, J
                        2007
                        Toponym Resolution in Text: Annotation, Evaluation and Applications
                            of Spatial Grounding of Place Names. Diss.
                        University of Edinburgh, School of Informatics. Institute for
                            Communicating and Collaborative Systems
                    </p>
                    <p>Massey, D.
                        2005
                        For Space
                        Thousand Oaks, CA
                        Sage
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Mateas, M.
                        Sengers, P.
                        2003
                        Narrative Intelligence.
                            Amsterdam/Philadelphia
                        John Benjamins Publishing Company
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Miller, G.
                        Beckwith, R. 
                        Fellbaum, C.
                        Gross, D.
                        Miller, K.
                        1993
                        Introduction to WordNet: An Online Lexical Database (Revised)
                        Princeton University
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Pouliquen, B.
                        Kimler, M.
                        Steinberger, R.
                        Ignat, C.
                        Oellinger, T.
                        2006
                        Geocoding Multilingual Texts: Recognition, Disambiguation and
                            Visualisation
                        In Proceedings of The Fifth International Conference on Language
                            Resources and Evaluation(LREC)
                        
         (<a href="http://www.arxiv.com/ftp/cs/papers/0609/0609065.pdf" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        National Historical Geographic Information System
                        2008
                        Minnesota Population Center: University of Minnesota.
                        Minneapolis, MN
                        
                        
         (<a href="http://www.nhgis.org" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        U.S. Board on Geographic Names: Domestic and Antarctic Names – State
                            and Topical Gazetteer Download Files
                        United States Geological Survey
                        
                        
         (<a href="http://geonames.usgs.gov/domestic/download_data.htm" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        U.S. Geological Survey: National Hydrography Dataset
                        United States Geological Survey
                        
                        
         (<a href="http://nhd.usgs.gov/data.html" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                
            

        </div></div></body></html>