
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>The Digital Archaeological Record--an Analytic Data Repository for
                    Archaeology</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-329.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-329.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: The Digital Archaeological Record--an Analytic Data Repository for
                    Archaeology</h2><h4>
                    Brin, Adam , 
                    Digital Antiquity, 
                    <a href="mailto:abrin@digitalantiquity.org">abrin@digitalantiquity.org</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    McManamon, Francis, 
                    Digital Antiquity, 
                    <a href="mailto:fpm@digitalantiquity.org">fpm@digitalantiquity.org</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Lee, Allen , 
                    Arizona State University, 
                    <a href="mailto:Allen.Lee@asu.edu">Allen.Lee@asu.edu</a>
                </h4><hr />
            
                <p class="noindent">In the past 150 years, the discipline of archaeology has changed dramatically;
                    excavation procedures, field methods, and record keeping have both improved and
                    become formalized. Ahead of the digital era, the physical records of an
                    excavation (the papers, data tables, journals, and monographs) were preserved as
                    artifacts alongside the excavated materials in museums and repositories. More
                    recently, Archaeologists have been quick to adopt new technology from punch
                    cards in the 1960s to spreadsheets, databases, GIS, and 3D scanning. Yet, these
                    modern files, images, data sets, and documents, if not properly preserved, are
                    more fragile than the objects they describe. With the Digital Archaeological
                    Record (tDAR --<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-329.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=http://www.tdar.org#X" target="_top">http://www.tdar.org</a>), we hope to change this.</p>
                <p class="noindent">tDAR was designed as a domain-specific digital repository, focused on
                    preservation of, and access to archaeological documents, reports, data sets and
                    images. The most successful digital repositories provide additional value to
                    their users beyond the core mission of preservation. Examples including ArXiv
                        (<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-329.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=http://arxiv.org/#X" target="_top">http://arxiv.org/</a>)
                    or the University of Rochester's digital repository (<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-329.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=https://urresearch.rochester.edu#X" target="_top">https://urresearch.rochester.edu</a>) are successful because of
                    additional factors such as reputation or community. For tDAR, the additional
                    value is created through research tools developed on top of the repository.
                    These tools aim to promote new synthetic and comparative research using the data
                    sets stored within the repository.</p>
                <p class="noindent">tDAR's architecture includes three architectural components, a backend
                    preservation repository based on the California Digital Library's Micro-Services
                    model, an interactive web interface, and a research platform. Metadata is stored
                    within tDAR using a extension of the Library of Congress MODS schema, modified
                    to add archaeologically significant metadata. This includes descriptive metadata
                    about the site, location, culture, materials found, among other attributes. Data
                    sets ingested into tDAR function differently from data sets in a traditional
                    repository. Once a data set has been uploaded, users are guided through the
                    process of documenting their data set within the system. This process is
                    designed to focus on identifying non-machine discernible information such as,
                    whether numeric data represents a measurement or count and translating coded
                    values or lookup tables into human-readable values. Once complete, tDAR's
                    additional features provide unique opportunities to compare, contrast, and
                    analyze data within the system. </p>
                <p class="noindent">A significant challenge for many disciplines is the ability to perform synthetic
                    research. Data from archaeological excavations commonly include a mixture of
                    standardized observational data such as Munsell codes to record sediment color
                    and GPS/GIS readings are combined with more qualitative assessments about
                    artifact types, or the amount of "burning" on faunal elements. Within the
                    context of a specific site, this is easily reconcilable --as the team develops a
                    common understanding of these terms. However, utilizing these classifications
                    outside of a given site, region, or community of archaeologists, can be
                    challenging. Certain data may lend itself to the application of universal
                    classification schemes --including data that is either more scientific or is
                    derived from a well-documented period. However, more qualitative data may not be
                    as easily mapped to a universal classification model --as definitions of terms
                    will vary between archaeologists or over time. Instead, contributors may
                    provide, or develop a unique classification scheme (ontology) to describe their
                    data. These two approaches represent well-tread road within both research and
                    practice, with distinct benefits to each side. However, to perform any useful
                    comparison, a mapping must be developed.</p>
                <p class="noindent">tDAR does not force users to map data to universal data models or classification
                    schema. Instead, the application has developed a different approach --maintain
                    the data in its original, and capturing the intent of the archaeologist. The
                    application was been developed with reference ontologies available for certain
                    data elements including faunal species data among others. tDAR enables users to
                    create additional ontologies within the repository, or upload existing one using
                    the OWL format. Once a column of data is associated with an ontology, users are
                    presented with straightforward tools to map the unique data values to terms
                    within the ontology. We believe that this process serves a number of purposes,
                    not only does it maintain and represent the data as it was collected, but it
                    provides opportunities for collaboration and communication within the discipline
                    as archaeologists share data, and discuss intents.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Once data has been mapped, the application guides the user through the data
                    integration process of selecting data sets, identifying columns to compare, fine
                    tuning any mapping issues, and producing the new combined data set. In an analog
                    context, or outside of tDAR, this process can be time-consuming for one data
                    set, and overwhelming for multiple. Within tDAR, what would have been a complex
                    process taking days or weeks when performed manually becomes much more fluid,
                    taking hours. With the technology performing much of the heavy lifting, it
                    leaves the archaeologist to focus on the specific questions and details of their
                    research. </p>
                <p class="noindent">While tDAR is still developing, tDAR's data integration has already enabled
                    Archaeozoologists to ask novel questions about the cultural and ecological
                    circumstances under which species are overhunted or subsistence strategies
                    change. It is our hope that tDAR's core values of access, preservation, and
                    integration will enable us to ask, understand, and evaluate new questions and
                    ideas otherwise impossible within the field of archaeology.</p>
            
        </div></div></body></html>