
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Probabilistic Analysis of Middle English Orthography: the Auchinleck
                    Manuscript</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-346.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-346.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: Probabilistic Analysis of Middle English Orthography: the Auchinleck
                    Manuscript</h2><h4>
                    Thaisen, Jacob, 
                    University of Stavanger, 
                    <a href="mailto:jthaisen@gmail.com">jthaisen@gmail.com</a>
                </h4><hr />
            
                <p class="noindent">The bulk of the literary materials that survive from the Middle English period
                    are scribal copies, rather than authorial compositions. Such copies pose a
                    challenge to the stylometrist, the reason being that copies written in a single
                    scribal hand may have non-identical orthographic profiles. Their non-identity is
                    a product of their transmission history, as the typical copy will contain both
                    spelling forms originating in the exemplars and other such forms introduced by
                    the scribe. Historical dialectologists have developed methods for separating the
                    mix of scribal usage and exemplar usage typically recorded in a single scribal
                    copy. Although powerful, these methods rely on questionnaire-based interrogation
                    of text samples and subsequent visual analysis of spelling forms arranged in
                    tables. The arrival of digital transcripts has sped up the data collection
                    process and has led to compilation of fuller profiles, but the questionnaire
                    itself has stayed. Thus, these methods fail to take full advantage of the
                    digital medium. </p>

                <p class="noindent">This presentation demonstrates that a purpose of identifying and isolating
                    locations in which the makeup of the spelling system changes during the full
                    text of a longer Middle English literary manuscript may be met by
                    probability-based comparison of text samples. What spelling forms happen to be
                    attested in a given text is a function of what words happen to make up that
                    text. The direct comparison of texts is therefore not readily possible. It has
                    typically been made possible by considering profiles recording only the spelling
                    forms of those words which may reasonably be expected to occur in every text,
                    such as function words like "such", "that", and "these". The alternative
                    solution proposed in this paper is to base assessment of similarity on "models"
                    of text samples' spelling–exhaustive profiles of which letters and letter
                    sequences occur in them and with which frequency. I shall refer to single
                    letters as unigrams, ordered sequences of two letters as bigrams, etc. Such
                    models are easily compiled from electronic diplomatic transcripts. The
                    dissolution into n-grams is equal to identification of the between texts because
                    comparison of the building blocks is in itself relatively independent of the
                    word level. </p>

                <p class="noindent">Similarity is measured between a text sample (the test sample) and a model
                    derived from another text sample (the training sample). It is expressed as the
                    overall probability that the test sample is an instance of the same spelling
                    system as the system modelled. Computing this probability proceeds, with a
                    trigram model, from consideration of each unigram in the context of the bigram
                    preceding it–the reader may correctly recognise the "Markov assumption" in this
                    description. What is output, however, is the reciprocal of the average
                    probability per gram. This entity, called "perplexity", will conveniently always
                    be a positive number larger than 1 with the present type of data. Moreover,
                    techniques exist for "smoothing" a model, that is for reducing its dependence on
                    the words constituting the training sample. This reduction is achieved by
                    statistically manipulating the probabilities computed for the training sample
                    n-grams. Smoothing additionally leads to probability being assigned to spelling
                    forms unattested in the training sample. </p>

                <p class="noindent">It is these properties of these techniques that makes their application on n-gram
                    models based on Middle English texts further increase the comparability of those
                    texts. Probabilistic modeling techniques have, however, as far as I am aware,
                    rarely been applied for the stylometric analysis of Middle English materials,
                    and it has yet to be established which specific smoothing technique produces the
                    most satisfactory models of those materials. </p>

                <p class="noindent">A simple example may illustrate. The spelling forms &lt;suich, suyche, such&gt;
                    for the word "such" are found in text A, while the same word is spelt
                    &lt;suche&gt; in text B. Intuitively, the text B spelling form &lt;suche&gt;
                    falls within the range of variation characteristic of the spelling system of
                    text A but happens to be unattested in it, while other known Middle English
                    forms such as as &lt;swylke, suilk&gt; do not. The present methodology involves
                    dissolving &lt;suche&gt; into &lt;su, suc, uch, che, he&gt; and establishing
                    the smoothed conditional probability for each of these trigram building blocks
                    in text A (thus obtaining a intuition that the spelling form is possible in the
                    spelling system of text A. In practice, however, the quantification is not
                    effected for the individual form but for the whole of text B in relation to text
                    A. </p>

                <p class="noindent">To illustrate the adequacy of perplexity-based comparison in stylometry, I trace
                    changes in spelling in a large manuscript collecting several Middle English
                    literary works. The corpus is the Auchinleck manuscript, Edinburgh, National
                    Library of Scotland, Advocates' MS 19.2.1, produced in the London-Westminster
                    area in the first half of the fourteenth century. The potential influences on
                    the scribes include the literary structure, as the codex's total of almost
                    59,000 lines of text are divided between no less than forty-four literary works
                    representing a range of genres. A map showing locations in which the spelling
                    system changes during the full text of the Auchinleck manuscript may be expected
                    to reflect the literary structure only if the exemplars did so and the
                    Auchinleck scribes reproduced them slavishly. By contrast, it is the boundaries
                    of the scribal contributions that will be visible in the map if each scribe
                    thoroughly converted into his own spelling system when copying. Six scribal
                    hands are present. Of these, Scribe 4's contribution is too short (551 words) to
                    constitute a reliable sample, while the usages of the other five scribes should
                    be visible. They are distinct in terms of their typological classification on
                    the dialect continuum, although they fall into an eastern cluster and a western
                    one. Dialect analysis has thus placed Scribe 1 in Middlesex, Scribe 2 on the
                    Gloucestershire-Worcestershire border, Scribe 3 in London, Scribe 5 in Essex,
                    and Scribe 6 in Worcestershire (McIntosh, Samuels, et al 1986, I: 88; LPs 6510,
                    6940, 6500, 6350, and 7820). </p>

                <p class="noindent">To be able to compute and compare probability for sections of the Auchinleck
                    manuscript against one another, I obtained a digital transcript of its text from
                    the Oxford Text Archive (Burnley and Wiggins 2003). The transcript is suitable,
                    because rather than modernise the spelling forms found in its source, it
                    reproduces the source in conformity with standard practice of diplomatic
                    transcription. My tool for constructing models and computing perplexity is the
                    SRI Language Modeling Toolkit (SRILM; Stolcke 2002); this toolkit is freely
                    available for noncommercial purposes from the website of its SRILM constructed
                    and smoothed an interpolated model for every 200-line section; the smoothing
                    technique selected was that described by Witten and Bell (1991). This technique
                    was developed for purposes of text compression at the level of the word but it
                    is appropriate for application on Middle English spelling data too. The reason
                    is that the technique effectively assigns probability to collocating letters as
                    if they were a single letter, rather than a series of independent units. </p>

                <p class="noindent">The toolkit took the same modified transcripts of all the sections as the input
                    and computed their similarity with the models. The computation resulted in a
                    separate model for each section, and for every such model, a separate perplexity
                    for every section. I established the mean perplexity and standard deviation for
                    the perplexities obtained for each model. The box and whisker graph below shows
                    the results. In this graph the vertical axis gives perplexity and the horizontal
                    axis position in the text of the Auchinleck manuscript. The diamond represents
                    mean perplexity and the T-bar represents half a standard deviation, so that one
                    upright T-bar and its reverse together indicate an interval of one standard
                    deviation from the mean. A dashed vertical line appears for ease of reference at
                    the boundary of a scribal stint as established by palaeographers (Bliss 1951),
                    with the outlined numbers identifying the scribes. </p>

                <p class="noindent">As is apparent, the figure distinguishes the scribes of the Auchinleck
                    manuscript. The rises and falls in mean perplexity during the text strongly
                    correlate with the boundaries of the scribal stints, while mean perplexity is
                    relatively constant within every such stint. Repetion of the experiment with
                    other divisions of the text produced results sufficiently similar to <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-346.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Figure 1</a> to establish the pattern as being
                    a property of the data rather than an artefact of the method. </p>

                <p class="noindent">It would have been time-consuming indeed to conduct a questionnaire-based
                    interrogation of the full text of the Auchinleck manuscript. Visual analysis of
                    the resulting profile to identify and isolate locations in which the spelling
                    system changes would, moreover, have been complex, because of the amount of data
                    and difficulty of isolating the diagnostic features. Perplexity-based comparison
                    as illustrated above, by contrast, requires little preprocessing of the
                    transcript, is effected in an afternoon, and is based on all the available
                    data.</p>
            
            
                <p>
                    <h2>Mean perplexity and standard deviation in the Auchinleck manuscript
                        (trigram models, 200-line sections)</h2>
                    <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//346/figure1.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-346.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//346/figure1.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                </p>
            
        <h2>References:</h2>
            
                

                    <p>
                        Bliss, A. J.
                        1951
                         “Notes on the Auchinleck Manuscript, ” 
                        <i>Speculum</i>, 
                        26
                        652–58
                    </p>

                    <p>
                        Burnley, D.
                        A. Wiggins2003
                        The Auchinleck Manuscript
                        
         (<a href="http://www.nls.uk/auchinleck" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>

                    <p>
                        McIntosh, A.
                        M. L. Samuels
                        M. Benskin
                        1986
                        <i>A Linguistic Atlas of Late Mediaeval English</i>,  
                        4 vols
                        Aberdeen
                        Aberdeen University Press
                    </p>

                    <p>
                        Stolcke, A.
                        2002
                        SRILM: An extensible language modeling toolkit
                        Hansen, P. Pellom, B.
                        Proceedings of the 7th International Conference on Spoken Language Processing
                        Denver
                        Casual Productions
                        901–04
                    </p>

                    <p>
                        Witten, I. H.
                        T. C. Bell
                        1991
                        <i>The Zero-Frequency Problem: Estimating the Probabilities of Novel Events in Adaptive Text Compression</i>, 
                        <i>IEEE Transactions on Information Theory</i>, 
                        37
                        1085–94
                    </p>
                
            
        </div></div></body></html>