
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Geo-Temporal Argumentation: The Roman Funeral Oration</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-383.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-383.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: Geo-Temporal Argumentation: The Roman Funeral Oration</h2><h4>
                    Johanson, Christopher, 
                    UCLA Classics, 
                    <a href="mailto:cjohanson@gmail.com">cjohanson@gmail.com</a>
                </h4><hr />
            
                <h2>Overview of the Discipline-Specific Project</h2>
                <p class="noindent">The Roman aristocratic funeral of the Republic was an incredible show. It
                    packaged the Roman spectacular trifecta, the procession, the eulogy and the
                    subsequent games, which comprised gladiatorial and dramatic performances. While
                    each of these components of the funeral has received individual treatment—in the
                    case of the gladiatorial games, extensive—no detailed, comprehensive discussion
                    of the aristocratic funeral of the Republic exists. Moreover, before
                    gladiatorial games were held in the Colosseum and before dramatic performances
                    were staged in a monumental theater, they were first held in ad hoc venues in
                    the heart of Rome. No attempt has been made to situate the phenomenon within its
                    surrounding context, the Roman Forum. My current digital/analog manuscript
                    project, Spectacle in the Forum: the Roman Aristocratic Funeral of the Middle
                    Republic, offers the first attempt to study the mid-Republican funeral in its
                    totality and, in so doing, examines the most significant aspects of spectacular
                    stagecraft of the Roman Republic.</p>
            
            
                <h2>The Intellectual Problem</h2>
                <p class="noindent">Spectacle has received considerable attention in recent years, but its study has
                    been marred by deficiencies in method. Classics scholar Richard Beacham
                    pinpoints the problem: “Spectacle is three-dimensional and sequential, realized
                    by taking place over a period of time, and its place, circumstance, and
                    unfolding fundamentally shape what an audience both expects and experiences.” 
                    Ritual parades, political speeches, and religious rites are well described in
                    ancient texts and frequently depicted in art.  Yet, most spatial and spectacular
                    analyses attempt to reconstruct the monuments, imagery, actors and audience,
                    which are inherently kinetic and multi-dimensional (changing over space and
                    time), by means of textual description and two-dimensional plans.</p>
                <p class="noindent">The impact of monumental structures on Roman performers and their audiences, what
                    could and could not be seen during their performance, as well as the
                    significance of <i>monumenta memoriae</i>, directly affected the
                    shows when first performed, and the reading and interpretation of the records
                    subsequently examined by scholars. Performance “stages” of the mid-Republic were
                    ephemeral: extant temple podia, elevated balconies, and hillsides, might serve
                    as caveae. Simple temporary structures may have been all that was needed to
                    mount a production.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Three-dimensional digital models offer a partial solution. There are now a
                    growing number of projects that have used computerized reconstructions to
                    visualize Imperial Rome. There have been very few similar attempts to represent
                    the Republican city, and hardly any that make scholarly arguments set within the
                    digital reconstructions. Most reconstruction projects tend to focus on the
                    creation of a highly accurate, extraordinarily precise digital model informed by
                    scholarship as the ultimate goal. Instead, this project uses hypothetical
                    reconstructions as a digital laboratory. By injecting historical context—the
                    performers and the audience—into the digital environment, the digital
                    investigation transforms the quantifiable elements of the ephemeral experience
                    of ancient spectacle into a digital object fit for experiential analysis. It
                    uses the hypothetical reconstructions as a digital laboratory to explore the
                    staging of Roman spectacle and develop the digital toolset necessary for
                    scholarly interrogation and publication of spatial and experiential
                    arguments.</p>
            
            
                <h2>Geo-Temporal Argumentation: the Roman Funeral Oration</h2>
                <p class="noindent">The <i>laudatio funebris</i> of the mid-Republic was
                    genre-defying visual theater. While it is now generally agreed that the
                    persuasive techniques of oratory comprised verbal (the content and delivery of
                    the speech) and visual elements (gestures charged with meaning and explicit
                    visual and topographic references), the degree to which the choreography of the
                    funeral eulogy subordinated the words of the speech has not been fully examined.
                    For much of the audience, the visuality of the event eclipsed the aural content.
                    The <i>laudatio</i>, like the <i>pompa</i>
                    before it, relied on a basic set of quasi-formulaic visual cues to communicate
                    with the audience, or at least, to communicate some ideas to some of the
                    audience. To call the laudatio a speech alone, and to classify it within the
                    realm of oratory without qualification is to misunderstand much of the purpose
                    and the choreography of the event. In this presentation, I will put the event in
                    its proper place: the Forum. Through the use of textual analysis, experiential
                    investigation, and geo-temporal argumentation, I will demonstrate that the <i>laudatio funebris</i> was a multivariate theatrical event,
                    comprising two discrete elements targeted at two distinct audiences.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Though one can use a laboratory built out of virtual world infrastructure to
                    experiment, a researcher cannot (yet) “publish” the entirety of a laboratory
                    experience and call it scholarly communication. Rather, the laboratory is the
                    space where the research occurs; the results must be woven together into a
                    narrative in order to engage with the larger scholarly conversation.
                    Nonetheless, a text and image narrative is insufficient to convey the totality
                    of the kinetic and temporal subject matter. Geo-temporal argumentation presents
                    an innovative and more robust method of idea dissemination by offering:</p>
                
                    <li>Continuous and persistent spatial context.</li>
                    <li>Nodal points of departure for reader-based investigation</li>
                    <li>A refutable system embedded in a geographic context.</li>
                    <li>Narrative, perhaps <i>rhizomatic</i>, that enables
                        non-linear review and exploration</li>
                
                <p class="noindent">When the experience and creation of kinetic transitions are fundamental to an
                    understanding of an argument the reader must, quite simply, walk in the
                    footsteps of the authors in order to participate in the debate, critique the
                    result, and modify the conclusions. In this paper I aim to demonstrate that, for
                    space- and time-centric, phenomenological investigations, geo-temporal
                    argumentation is a new and superior form of scholarly communication.</p>
            
            
                <h2>The Technology and the Collaborative Project</h2>
                <p class="noindent">As is always the case, digital humanities projects are collaborative endeavors.
                    My “manuscript” project provides the domain-specific area of inquiry, but the
                    digital platforms that facilitate the research are part of two, larger
                    collaborative efforts of which I am but one of a number of co-investigators.</p>
                <p class="noindent"><b>GeoTemporal Publication Platform:</b> The research results and
                    assessment will be published within <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-383.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=http://www.hypercities.com#X" target="_top">HyperCities</a>, a geo-temporal content aggregation and publication
                    platform. Rather than create an entirely new digital humanities tool, “chapters”
                    from my manuscript are being used as case-studies to guide the development of 3D
                    narrative and mark-up tools within the HyperCities platform that will facilitate
                    exploration of the data and publication of this new form of scholarly inquiry.
                    We anticipate a mid-winter release of the working 3D system.</p>
            
            
                <h2>Project Samples</h2>
                
                    <li>
                        <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-383.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=http://www.etc.ucla.edu/research/projects/UCLAETC.kml#X" target="_top">For the
                            geo-aware 3D content, (Google Earth Required)</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-383.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=http://hypercities.ats.ucla.edu/#collections/8641#X" target="_top">For a rough,
                            sample narrative</a>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-383.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=http://caliber.ucpress.net/doi/abs/10.1525/jsah.2010.69.1.12#X" target="_top">An experiment in geo-temporal argumentation is now available in the
                            inaugural issue of a new hybrid print/digital issue of the JSAH</a>
                    </li>
                
            
        </div></div></body></html>