
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Googling Ancient Places</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-349.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-349.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: Googling Ancient Places</h2><h4>
					Isaksen, Leif, 
					Archaeology, University of Southamp, 
					<a href="mailto:leifuss@googlemail.com">leifuss@googlemail.com</a>
				</h4><h4>
					Barker, Elton, 
					Classical Studies, The Open University, 
					<a href="mailto:e.t.e.barker@open.ac.uk">e.t.e.barker@open.ac.uk</a>
				</h4><h4>
					Kansa, Eric C., 
					School of Information, University of California,
						Berkeley, 
					<a href="mailto:ekansa@ischool.berkeley.edu">ekansa@ischool.berkeley.edu</a>
				</h4><h4>
					Byrne, Kate, 
					Informatics, University of Edinburgh, 
					<a href="mailto:k.byrne@ed.ac.uk">k.byrne@ed.ac.uk</a>
				</h4><hr />
			
				<h2>Overview</h2>
				<p class="noindent">Our presentation about the Google Ancient Places (GAP) project will demonstrate
					new techniques to computationally identify places referenced in scholarly texts.
					We will also discuss deployment of simple Web services that use resulting place
					identifications to help bridge across online literary and material culture
					collections.</p>
			
			
				<h2>Project History</h2>
				<p class="noindent">Funded through the Google Digital Humanities Award program (July 2010-June 2011),
					GAP &lt;<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-349.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=http://googleancientplaces.wordpress.com/#X" target="_top">http://googleancientplaces.wordpress.com/</a>&gt; mines a portion of the
					Google Books Corpus &lt;<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-349.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=http://books.google.com/intl/en/googlebooks/history.html#X" target="_top">http://books.google.com/intl/en/googlebooks/history.html</a>&gt; to find
					books related to ancient locations identified by gazetteers of the Classical
					Mediterranean world.</p>

				<p class="noindent">GAP builds upon the Herodotus Encoded Space-Time Imaging Archive (HESTIA)
					project. HESTIA &lt;<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-349.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=http://www.open.ac.uk/arts/Hestia/#X" target="_top">http://www.open.ac.uk/arts/Hestia/</a>&gt; was a two-year
					collaboration (2008-2010) between The Open University and the Universities of
					Oxford and Birmingham, funded by the UK Arts and Humanities Research Council.
					Its aim was to explore new methods for visualizing relationships in Herodotus’
					Histories. The project explored multiple approaches, including: 
						<li>mapping the frequency of references to specific locations (both
							spatially and in terms of linear narrative)</li>
						<li>manually and automatically generating maps of the network connections
							between places. </li>
					 The project made use of Greek and English versions of the text from
					the Perseus Digital Library &lt;<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-349.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/#X" target="_top">http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/</a>&gt; which are marked up
					with the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) XML schema, including geographical
					locations based on automated string-matching with the Perseus internal gazetteer
					and Getty Thesaurus of Geographic Names. Closer analysis revealed that many of
					the locations were misidentifications, however, and a relatively labor-intensive
					process was required to correct them. </p>

				<p class="noindent">HESTIA’s use of Perseus Digital Library resources demonstrates the growing power
					of open infrastructure already established in Classical studies. HESTIA also
					helped to demonstrate the utility of visualizing locations within a narrative.
					However, could the approach be automated so as to scale beyond manually
					processing individual texts? GAP attempts to answer this question through more
					sophisticated computational methods and by using additional open infrastructure,
					especially new Semantic gazetteers (see below) such as GeoNames &lt;<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-349.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=http://www.geonames.org/#X" target="_top">http://www.geonames.org/</a>&gt;, and the Pleiades Project &lt;<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-349.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=http://pleaides.stoa.org/#X" target="_top">http://pleaides.stoa.org/</a>&gt;. </p>

				<p class="noindent">HESTIA’s focus lies in a seminal text, the <i>Histories</i> by
					Herodotus. While primary and secondary literary sources represent key resources
					for Classical Studies, Classics also draws upon diverse sources of material
					evidence gathered from art history, architecture and archaeology (Mahony and
					Bodard 2010:3-5). These different sources of evidence and their associated
					scholarship are often highly “siloed”. Reference to Perseus or Pleiades
					resources can improve their interoperability. To address this issue, GAP
					demonstrates how open digital humanities infrastructure together with the Google
					Books Corpus, can be used synergistically to bridge online literary and material
					culture collections. GAP uses Open Context &lt;<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-349.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=http://opencontext.org/#X" target="_top">http://opencontext.org/</a>&gt; to test such services. Open Context is an
					open-access archaeological data publication system offering wide-ranging
					documentation of architecture, archaeological contexts, and objects from
					multiple contributors (Kansa and Kansa 2007). Open Context provides a map and
					timeline on its splash page to enable both providers and users to quickly
					identify related research. The ability to identify relevant scholarly literature
					relating to Open Context’s material culture collections would be a
					ground-breaking extension to this service. </p>
			
			
				<h2>Approach</h2>
				<p class="noindent">Prior experience with Herodotus’ <i>Histories</i> informs GAP’s
					methodology. In developing the HESTIA Narrative Timeline, we learned that places
					referenced in narrative texts generally cluster together to maintain narrative
					coherency. Given a set of toponyms with multiple possible identifications, the
					set of identifications with the shortest overall path between them is likely to
					be correct. In addition, we can add weight to the importance of each toponym by
					the number of possible locations it could refer to. Somewhat
					counter-intuitively, this means that small, obscure places with unusual names
					are much better guides to location than well-known places with many namesakes.
					While a useful starting point, several additional factors complicate accurate
					place identification: 
						<li>The approach does not work well for fragments or with arbitrary
							higher-level structures such as the alphabetic organization of an
							encyclopedia. </li>
						<li>The author may assume that the anticipated audience will be able to
							contextualize by other narrative elements (such as well-known
							individuals) and thus mention only a single location (or even none at
							all). </li>
						<li>The author may contextualize by giving a territory in which the place
							is located. These can confuse point-based algorithms as there is no
							single ‘best’ point that represents them.</li>
						<li>The author may have confused the place they are discussing with
							another, especially if they are commenting on another work or reporting
							independent sources.</li>
						<li>Occasionally the pattern location clustering assumption simply does
							not hold. This is especially the case for places that do not perform an
							active function in the text such as personal names derived from places
							of origin (e.g. ‘Herodotus of Halicarnassus’).</li>
					</p>

				<p class="noindent">Fortunately, new open infrastructure, especially Semantic Gazetteers such as
					GeoNames and Pleiades, can improve the precision of place identification. Both
					GeoNames and Pleiades offer open, machine-readable data curated by dedicated
					communities. They provide unique HTTP URIs for each place to which multiple
					names (toponyms), locations (such as spatial coordinates) and categories (like
					‘settlement’ or ‘region’) can be assigned. These gazetteers make it much easier
					to handle the problem of synonymy and allow us to assign non-ambiguous and
					easily resolved public identifiers to places identified in the Google Books
					Corpus.</p>

				<p class="noindent">Nevertheless, even with the aid of gazetteers, the difficulties outlined above
					make place identifications highly probabilistic and uncertain, especially in
					cases where we find either insufficient or conflicting evidence. Hard cases can
					then be handled by a variety of methods, including more sophisticated but
					computationally expensive procedures or by manual effort of a scholar.
					Computationally, there are multiple levels at which we can look for clustering,
					including the chapter, book, and corpus (of the author or even genre). Looking
					at higher levels may provide us with broader contextual clues. A further
					advantage of working with massive digital corpora is that they frequently
					provide multiple translations and editions. In such cases we can use the linear
					chain of places in one edition to inform the processing of another and vice
					versa. Finally, as we process more books the system can record additional
					metadata about the places as well as the books. In particular it may see that in
					cases of homonymy, one location is much more frequently mentioned than all the
					others (such as the Egyptian Alexandria, as opposed to the many other cities of
					that name). This can help in cases where we have no other contextual clues to
					draw on. Google Books metadata and comparison of multiple editions found Google
					Books corpus may thus help resolve ambiguous place determinations in some
					cases.</p>

				<p class="noindent">It is also important to remember that there are some hard limits imposed on the
					process and some pragmatic aspects to our goals. First, we are only able to
					identify those places for which we have an entry in a gazetteer. Natural
					Language Processing available to us will not identify places previously unknown.
					Secondly, we are not looking for a ‘perfect’ set of results for the simple
					reason that natural language is ultimately indeterminate. Continued improvement
					of computational methods, as well as more traditional forms of scholarship will
					be required. </p>
			
			
				<h2>Outcomes</h2>
				<p class="noindent">Scaling and adapting text processing methods developed for HESTIA for the larger
					Google Books Corpus represents one of the key challenges for GAP. To help
					evaluate the effectiveness of our approach, we first reconciled local
					identifiers used by the HESTIA project with Pleiades URIs. We will report on how
					our algorithmic approach to place identifications compares with places manually
					identified in HESTIA using the same raw text of the Histories as used by HESTIA.
					We will then report on results of our algorithmic method on the 1828 translation
					of the Histories provided by Google. Finally we will discuss application of our
					algorithms for general use on the Google Books corpus, focusing on public domain
					texts with Library of Congress Headings DE-DG (Greco-Roman World; Greece;
					Italy).</p>

				<p class="noindent">GAP provides processing results in RDF-expressed annotations for each text. Such
					annotations are extremely useful to software but generally less helpful for
					humanities researchers who typically require a human interface. Thus, GAP also
					provides Web mapping tools, like those on the HESTIA and Open Context websites.
					These interfaces enable searches in both directions – from text to places, and
					from a place to the texts which reference it. To lower adoption barriers, we
					chose RESTful Web service (based on the Atom Syndication Format and GeoJSON)
					design patterns (see Blanke et al. 2009; Kansa and Bissell 2010). Such services
					enable other developers and digital humanists to incorporate our results into
					other research environments and applications.</p>

				<p class="noindent">As discussed above, the GAP project makes extensive use of existing digital
					humanities infrastructure, especially place gazetteers such as Pleiades. In
					doing so, GAP helps to demonstrate the growing maturity of digital scholarship
					in Classical studies. Rather than standing alone as isolated, one-off efforts,
					digital projects increasingly complement one-another and enable future work. In
					this light, we hope GAP will catalyze continued research (see Rosenzweig 2007)
					in the text processing methods, systems design, and semantic standards required
					to bridge gaps across literary and material culture collections. </p>




			
		<h2>References:</h2>
			
				
					<p>
						Barker ETE, Bouzarovski S, Pelling CBR, Isaksen L.
						2010
						 “Mapping an ancient historian in a digital age: the
							Herodotus Encoded Space-Text-Image Archive (HESTIA), ” 
						<i>Leeds International Classical Journal</i>, 
						9
						1-24
					</p>

					<p>
						Blanke, T., M. Hedges, and R. Palmer
						2009
						 “Restful services for the e-Humanities — web services that
							work for the e-Humanities ecosystem, ” 
						<i>Digital Ecosystems and Technologies,
							2009. DEST '09. 3rd IEEE International Conference on Digital Ecosystems
							and Technologies.</i>, 
						637-642
					</p>
					<p>
						Cohen, Daniel J. and Roy Rosenzweig
						2006
						<i>Digital History: A Guide to Gathering, Preserving, and
							Presenting the Past on the Web</i>, 
						Philadelphia
						University of Pennsylvania Press
						
         (<a href="http://chnm.gmu.edu/digitalhistory" target="blank">link</a>)
   
					</p>
					<p>
						Kansa, Eric C., and Ahrash N. Bissell
						2010
						 “Web Syndication Approaches for Sharing Primary Data in
							"Small Science" Domains., ” 
						<i>Data Science Journal</i>, 
						9
						42-53
					</p>
					<p>
						Kansa, E., and S. Whitcher Kansa
						2007
						 “Open Context: Collaborative Data Publication to Bridge
							Field Research and Museum Collections, ” 
						<i>International Cultural Heritage
							Informatics Meeting (ICHIM07): Proceedings [J. Trant and D. Bearman
							(eds)]</i>, 
						Toronto: Archives &amp; Museum Informatics, 
						
         (<a href="http://www.archimuse.com/ichim07/papers/kansa/kansa.html" target="blank">link</a>)
   
					</p>

					<p>
						Mahony, Simon and Gabriel Bodard
						2010
						 “Introduction, ” 
						<i>Digital Research in the Study of Classical Antiquity [Simon
							Mahony and Gabriel Bodard (eds.)]</i>, 
						London
						Ashgate
						1-14
					</p>

					<p>
						Rosenzweig, Roy
						2007
						 “Collaboration and the cyberinfrastructure: Academic
							collaboration with museums and libraries in the digital era, ” 
						<i>First Monday</i>, 
						12(7)
					</p>

				
			
		</div></div></body></html>