
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Computing in Canada: a History of the Incunabular Years</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-311.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-311.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: Computing in Canada: a History of the Incunabular Years</h2><h4>
					Rockwell, Geoffrey, 
					University of Alberta, 
					<a href="mailto:grockwel@ualberta.ca">grockwel@ualberta.ca</a>
				</h4><h4>
					Smith, Victoria Susan, 
					University of Alberta, 
					<a href="mailto:victoriassmith@gmail.com">victoriassmith@gmail.com</a>
				</h4><h4>
					Hoosein, Sophia, 
					University of Alberta, 
					<a href="mailto:shoosein@ualberta.ca">shoosein@ualberta.ca</a>
				</h4><h4>
					Gouglas, Sean, 
					University of Alberta, 
					<a href="mailto:sean.gouglas@ualberta.ca">sean.gouglas@ualberta.ca</a>
				</h4><h4>
					Quamen, Harvey, 
					University of Alberta, 
					<a href="mailto:hquamen@ualberta.ca">hquamen@ualberta.ca</a>
				</h4><hr />
			
				<h2>Introduction</h2>

				<p class="noindent">How were computers introduced to the public and how did humanities issues figure
					in the introduction of computing? The time has come in the digital humanities to
					think historically about computing in the humanities as Willard McCarty has
					pointed out in <i>Humanities Computing</i> and other venues.
					This paper describes a study of public representations of computing in Canada
					using the <i>Globe and Mail</i>, our major national newspaper.
					This paper restricts itself to what we call the incunabular years when computing
					was still a curiosity and business applications didn’t yet dominate the public
					discourse.</p>

				<p class="noindent">References to digital computers in the Globe and Mail start in 1950 with a report
					of the annual meeting in London, England of Ferranti Ltd. This report describes
					under the heading of “Instruments” the development of a digital computer that
					was probably the predecessor of the Ferranti Atlas which pioneers like Susan
					Hockey worked on.</p>

				<p class="noindent">"The instrument department has a design team of considerable strength working in
					conjunction with Manchester University on the development of an electronic
					digital computer." (Globe and Mail, Oct. 31, 1950, p. 21)</p>

				<p class="noindent">From this first reference to digital computers buried in a business report,
					interest in and then anxieties about computers grow steadily through the 1950s
					and early 1960s until by 1964 the Globe runs a full page story in “The Woman’s
					Globe and Mail” on “Will Computers Replace the Working Girl?” by Michelle
					Landsberg (Globe and Mail, May 21, 1964) that warns of the effects of automation
					on women who do most of the clerical work that can be automated. Computers go
					from being objects of curiosity in research labs at the University of Toronto
					with speculative utility to instruments that are changing the nature of office
					work, especially for women. It is this “incunabular” period that interests us,
					partly because it is a period when the academy is one of the major sites where
					computers are being installed and because academics are explaining computers to
					the broader community. This paper, using these early stories about computers,
					will tease out a history of early representations of computing in Canada.
					Specifically we will: 
						<li>Describe the content analysis methodology used in this study.</li>
						<li>Discuss the ways computers are presented to the public in the first
							decade and a half. Who is represented as having access to digital
							computers? What tasks are they presented as suitable for?</li>
						<li>Discuss how computing jobs like data-entry, training and programming
							are gendered in the public discourse of the Globe.</li>
						<li>Discuss the first references to the installation of computers at
							Universities and how these installations were presented to the
							public.</li>
						<li>How was research computing presented and how were humanities
							applications of computing presented?</li>
					</p>

			

			
				<h2>Methodology</h2>
				<p class="noindent">The Globe and Mail online archive, unabashedly titled “Canada’s Heritage from
					1844,” provides a full-text historical database of articles, ads, editorials and
					special features. In order to document the early discourse around computers we
					searched and collected all references to the word “computer” for content
					analysis coding and reading. The first reference we found dates back to 1897,
					though in this case it is not a reference to digital computers, but the computer
					as a type of job. The first reference to digital computers dates from 1950 and
					the number of references per year remains fairly low until the early 1960s when
					computing takes off as a subject of news, advertising and opinion.</p>

				<p class="noindent">Once gathered we coded the articles for content analysis. The coding rubric was
					developed iteratively as we read articles and developed hypotheses. For example,
					during the coding we became interested in gender and went back over the early
					stories to recode materials. Below is an example of the codes applied: 

						<li>Type of reference (i.e. news, classified ad, feature)</li>
						<li>Photos (i.e. were there photos and what do the photos show)</li>
						<li>Category of Application (University, Science, Military, Automation,
							Industry, Government, and Arts and Humanities)</li>
						<li>Gender of Named People (male, female, both, none)</li>
						<li>Discourse like “Brain” (Is the computer described as a giant
							“brain”)</li>
						<li>Types of computers mentioned in the references where applicable</li>
					</p>
			
			
				<h2>Themes Running Through the Early Years</h2>
				<p class="noindent">Close reading and content analysis led us to identify and follow a number of
					themes running through the stories in these incunabular years. For example,
					related to the Ferranti mentioned in the first reference, is a Canadian turn
					from being oriented towards computing in the UK to being oriented towards
					computing from the USA. This turn is obviously a much larger issue for Canada
					after the war than just a change in where computers are coming from, but you see
					the turn in the articles from the 1950s. Bylines from London dominate in the
					early 50s, but by the end of the 1950s New York begins to be source of
					information about computers outside of Canada. You can see the early orientation
					towards the UK in titles like the 1955 article “Britain Leads in Office
					Automation.” But, by 1961, in a comprehensive pair of articles on the computer
					industry, it is clear that US companies dominate. As the author Hugh Munro puts
					it, “Ferranti is the only company that designs and manufactures in Canada –
					specializing in big installations – which means the country is heavily dependent
					on the United States, where the other companies are based, not only for supplies
					but for technological advancement in the computer field.” (Munro, “Surging
					Computer Industry Confident It Has Only Begun”, December 6th, 1961, p. 23.)</p>
			
			
				<h2>Exclusionary Practices: Gender and Computing</h2>
				<p class="noindent">One theme that stands out in the early representations of computing in the Globe
					is how women were excluded from computing. Advertisements for programmers are in
					the “Help Wanted Male” section. It isn’t until 1960 that a woman is named in a
					story and then she is discussed as an exception. The exclusion of women gets
					discussed explicitly in 1964 when Michelle Landsberg writes the extraordinary
					feature “Will Computers Replace the Working Girl?” mentioned above (Globe and
					Mail, May 21, 1964). This feature confronts the effects of automation on women
					who happen to do most of the clerical work that is being automated. In the full
					paper we will contrast the exclusion with what we know of pioneers like Beatrice
					Worsley who was one two staff hired initially by the University of Toronto
					Computing Centre.</p>
				<p class="noindent">
					<p>
						<h2>Computers and the Working Girl; Title, Illustration and Text</h2>
						<img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//311/fig1.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-311.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//311/fig1.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
					</p>
				</p>
			
			
				<h2>Computing in the University</h2>
				<p class="noindent">The second story published about digital computers in the <i>Globe</i> is much more substantial than the Ferranti reference and it
					describes the first research computer installed in Canada at the University of
					Toronto. The story titled “Junior Electronic Brain Cost $100,000” dates from
					1951, was accompanied by two photographs, and is about the UTEC Jr. computer
					installed at the U of T’s Computing Centre. It is really the first significant
					story about computing in the <i>Globe</i>, which is significant.
					In the full paper we will go into some detail about this first significant
					representation of computing as it illustrates many of the other points we want
					to make.</p>

				<p class="noindent"> Much could be said about the U of T Computing Centre and the birth of academic
					computing in Canada. Here we will restrict ourselves to the way computing was
					presented to the public as starting at the University of Toronto. The U of T
					Computing Centre stayed in the news for decades, along with its director, Dr.
					Gotlieb, who was the most frequently mentioned expert of the period. But
					academic computing is not just about Gotlieb and research at his Centre. By 1955
					we see the first ads for computing courses at U of T and the first reports of
					computers at other universities. By 1957 we see an article about computing in
					the arts and humanities. This article, titled, “Strange Music Made By an
					Electronic Brain” reports about a music composition experiment. </p>
				<p class="noindent"> "To the casual observer, the squeaks, squawks, groans and hints of tunes were a
					harsh cacophony. To Professor C. C. Gotlieb and his colleagues, the sounds were
					the Iliac Suite, a string quartet composed by the electronic brain at the
					University of Illinois. It was an experiment in composition designed by Prof.
					Gottlieb and his fellow-workers with the university’s electronic brain to show
					that humans are not the only ones that can compose music."</p>

				<p class="noindent">What stands out about this and subsequent stories is that they are about the
					computer as an extraordinary device best understood as an “electronic brain”
					performing tasks that are human. The stories don’t really report humanities
					applications differently from scientific and engineering ones. Instead this
					research brain is presented as answering questions and completing tasks from all
					fields – it is a general purpose inquiry engine that the U of T Computing Centre
					is turning to questions and academic tasks from one field to the next. The brain
					is curious as we are, and the stories convey a sense of the discovery as
					Gotlieb’s team crosses disciplines discovering new uses for the computer. What
					remains to be seen (in a future study) is how the public discourse matches or
					reflects the evolving discourse within the academy and especially in humanities
					computing circles. We humanists, after all, are also reading the news; did we
					come to computing influenced by news of its promise or were we concerned about
					how it might affect our work?</p>
			
		<h2>References:</h2> </div></div></body></html>