<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:x="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:exsl="http://exslt.org/common" xml:id="Paper-718">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Chimeria Platform: User Empowerment through Expressing Social Group Membership Phenomena</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Harrell</surname>, <forename>D. Fox</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Comparative Media Studies Program, Massachusetts Institute of Technology</affiliation>
          <email>fox.harrell@mit.edu</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Kao</surname>, <forename>Dominic</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory, Massachusetts Institute of Technology</affiliation>
          <email>dkao@mit.edu</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Lim</surname>, <forename>Chong-U</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory, Massachusetts Institute of Technology</affiliation>
          <email>culim</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Lipshin</surname>, <forename>Jason</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Comparative Media Studies Program, Massachusetts Institute of Technology</affiliation>
          <email>lipshin@mit.edu</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Sutherland</surname>, <forename>Ainsley</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Comparative Media Studies Program, Massachusetts Institute of Technology</affiliation>
          <email>ainsleys@mit.edu</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
        <publisher>EPFL, Switzerland</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>EPFL Digital Humanities Laboratory</name>
          <address>
            <addrLine>GC D2 386</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Station 18</addrLine>
            <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
            <addrLine>frederic.kaplan@epfl.ch</addrLine>
          </address>
        </distributor>
        <pubPlace>Lausanne, Switzerland</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>EPFL</addrLine>
          <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="abstract">Categorization mechanisms in many digital media systems such as social networks and videogames are inadequate for representing the complexities of many social identity phenomena. To address such limitations, we built the Chimeria system - a platform built around a dynamic computational model of identity and more flexible group membership dynamics. Chimeria allows for the authoring of narrative experiences that parallel phenomena observed in real world social groups, like the notion of membership gradience and individuals shifting both within and between social groups. Our aim is to allow authors to make use of Chimeria 's underlying model to construct their own narratives pertaining to multiple types of group membership or identity related issues such as discrimination or marginalization. By granting control over the visual appearance, interaction mechanisms, and narrative content, we hope authors will use the platform along with their constructed narratives for both critical analysis and creative expression.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
        <p>
          <date when="20140711"/>
          <time when="14:00:00"/>
        </p>
		<p n="session">8</p>
		<p n="room">414 - Amphimax</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
          <term>Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
          <term>Long Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
          <term>identity</term>
          <term>artificial intelligence</term>
          <term>platform</term>
          <term>social networking</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
          <term>multilingual / multicultural approaches</term>
          <term>software design and development</term>
          <term>cultural studies</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="paper">
    <front>
      
      <div>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>1. Introduction
		
	
	
		
			
				
					</head>
        <p>Computational modeling of social categories can be found in a wide range of digital
media works. For example, within computer role-playing games (RPGs), racial categorization is
often used to style the visual appearance of a player’s avatar or trigger different canned
reactions when conversing with a non-player character (NPC). In social media, users might join
groups based on shared taste or categorize each other into groups such as “colleagues” or
“family members” using privacy settings. However, in most such systems, category membership
is determined in a top-down fashion. Members are often slotted into single, homogeneous
groups, with no possibility for hybrid identities, identities that exist at the margins of groups, or
identities that change over time. Taken holistically, such approaches have many limitations.
These deficiencies are particularly visible when trying to accurately model the nuance of social
category membership in the real world.

					</p>
        <p>Our Chimeria platform (hereafter Chimeria) addresses this deficiency. It create more
nuanced social categorization models in two primary ways: (1) by modeling the underlying
structure of many social categorization phenomena with our Chimeria engine; and (2) by
enabling users to build their own creative applications about social categorization, using the
engine as a backbone. Drawing on theories from sociolinguistics (Polyani, 1989), cognitive
science (Lakoff, 1987), and sociology of classification (Bowker and Star, 1999), the underlying
engine allows for the movement of individuals within, between, and across social categories. It
also allows for members to be more central to a group than others, to assimilate or naturalize in
relation to a hegemonic group, and to claim membership in multiple groups. In this paper, we
discuss the components of Chimeria and two sample applications built with it.
</p>
        <head>
          <p>2. The Chimeria Authoring Platform</p>
        </head>
        <p>Chimeria supports authoring narratives of group membership in any social identity
domain through a data-driven approach. Chimeria is divided into three components (Figure 2). </p>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="DH2014_2_chimeria1"/>
          <p>Fig. 1: The Chimeria Platform</p>
        </figure>
        <list type="ordered">
          <item>Chimeria Engine: A mathematical model of users’ degrees of membership across
multiple categories. It provides the functionality to calculate, modify, and simulate
changes to these memberships and serves as the logical processing component of the
system. It models users’ category memberships as gradient values in relation to the
membership values of more central members (Harrell, 2010; Bowker and Star, 1999;
Lakoff, 1987). This enables more representational nuance than binary statuses of
member/nonmember. Narratives processed by Chimeria are authored using a GUI or in
the XML file format with a narrative structure as described in (Harrell et al., 2013).
</item>
          <item>Chimeria Application Interface: A visual interface for user interaction and for
experiencing the narratives related to the category membership changes driven by the
Chimeria Engine. It provides freedom and flexibility over the aesthetic and visual
components of narratives. The interface can take on multiple forms (e.g., a text-only
interface or a 3D virtual environment).<ref target="n1" rend="sup">1</ref> The separation between the back-end (the
Chimeria Engine) and the front-end (Chimeria Application Interface) provides the
flexibility to go through the same narrative trajectory in relation to membership shifts but
with varying visual appearance.
</item>
          <item>Chimeria Domain Epistomologies: An “epistemology” is an ontology that describes
cultural knowledge and beliefs (Harrell, 2013). In Chimeria, they are the knowledge
representations describing the categories being modeled. The data utilized by Chimeria 		
	
	
		
			
				
					to present these categories to users include both author-contributed (e.g., artworks or
narratives) and data-driven (e.g., an API call to YouTube to query for a video) assets.</item>
        </list>
        <head>3. Chimeria Application Domains</head>
        <p>To better illustrate the capabilities of the components within our system we describe two
very different narratives created using Chimeria: 1) a fictional social networking application
which models social categories in the domain of musical preferences (Harrell, 2013); and 2) a
computer role-playing game (RPG) scenario which models a conversational narrative between
the player and a non-playable character (NPC).
</p>
        <head>3.1 Chimeria: Musical Identity Social Network
</head>
        <p>In Chimeria: Musical Identity Social Network, the Chimeria Engine models category
membership based upon musical preferences that are automatically constructed from a user’s
set of music “likes” (binary indications of positive valuation) on a social network profile. These
“likes” constitute a set of musical artists from which we extrapolate, using commercially
available musical classification data, moods (e.g., cheerful, gloomy, etc.), themes (e.g.,
adventure, rebellion, etc.) and styles (e.g., film score). This provides the context for non-binary
group membership and passing (the “ability of a person to be regarded as a member of social
groups other than his or her own...generally with the purpose of gaining social acceptance,”
Renfrow, 2004). Each user’s set of moods, themes and styles, then impacts the generated
narrative in fundamental ways. We construct a conversational narrative on a social network
structured by a model of conversation from sociolinguistics (Polanyi, 1989).
</p>
        <p>The Chimeria Application Interface consists of a procedurally generated photowall: a
dynamic collage of photos representing the user’s musical taste preferences. A feed of recent
updates, posts, and invitations appear in an adjacent vertical timeline (see Figure 2). The
system reacts to the user by generating interaction events from computer-controlled users who
make up the user’s social circle within the system.</p>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="DH2014_2_chimeria2"/>
          <p>Fig. 2: A screenshot of the Chimeria: Musical Identity Social Network application interface</p>
        </figure>
        <p>Figure 3 presents a screenshot of Chimeria: Musical Identity Social Network. Using
musical preferences from the user’s Facebook music likes or by manual entry, a hybrid
real/fictitious narrative experience progresses over time. A series of dynamically generated
posts by the user’s friends (non-player characters) comment on the user’s membership within
one or more musical affinity groups (i.e. “You’re a raucous rock fan now?” or “Want to hear
some airy jazz music?”). The user may “like,” “dislike,” or simply ignore these posts, resulting in
group membership changes illustrated by alterations to a self-updating “photowall.” Some
friends might question newly discovered interests, while others might pass judgment on prior
affiliations. The resulting narrative may describe passing or assimilating as a member of a new
group, reinforcing a prior group affiliation, or even being marginalized in every group. Some
groups are deemed oppositional, privileged, or marginalized relative to others. </p>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="DH2014_2_chimeria3"/>
          <p>Fig. 3: The Chimeria Platform Applied to Musical Identities in a Social Network</p>
        </figure>
        <head>3.2 Chimeria: Gatekeeper
</head>
        <p>Chimeria: Gatekeeper models a common RPG scenario – a player trying to gain access
to the inside of a castle. Within this sample application, we demonstrate the power of the
Chimeria Engine for enhancing this scenario by modeling more complex, adaptive, and nuanced
conversations between PCs and NPCs, overcoming limitations identified in other videogames
(Harrell et al., 2014). Figure 4 shows a preliminary visual design from Chimeria: Gatekeeper.</p>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="DH2014_2_chimeria4"/>
          <p>Fig. 4: Chimeria: Gatekeeper preliminary scenario visual design</p>
        </figure>
        <p>Drawing on the work of Erving Goffman (Goffman, 1963), Chimeria: Gatekeeper
attempts to model the effect of stigma on conversation. Within the scenario, the PC is initialized
to the ‘discredited’ category and the NPC to the ‘accepted’ category. The accepted category is
prototypically defined as the Brushwoods race – short, plain-spoken, and wearers of rough spun
clothing. The discredited category is prototypically defined as the Sylvanns race – tall, well-
spoken, and wearers of fine clothing.<ref target="n2" rend="sup">2</ref> To gain access to the inside of the keep, the player has
to convince the guard that she or he is among the accepted category, in effect “passing” as a
member of the category that has been instantiated as “accepted” (Harrell et al., 2014).</p>
        <p>User actions and responses (e.g., slouching to adopt the posture of a prototypical
Brushwood or displaying fine Sylvann clothing) incrementally shift the NPCs model of the PCs
membership with respect to the categories, bringing the player closer to gaining access to the
keep or to being rejected. Internal thoughts of the PC emphasize trade-offs between gaining
utilitarian access to the keep and the loss of self-identity that can occur in trying to pass. The
guard’s responses of approval or disapproval respond accordingly to chosen actions. A
transcript of a run-through of Chimeria: Gatekeeper is shown in Figure 5.</p>
        <p>Using Goffman's notion of impression management, we handle alternatives to the
common trajectory of intentionally passing by considering other player decisions such as
voluntary disclosure of stigma and slipping (trying to pass as a member of an accepted
category, but failing). The modeling of passing and social categorization membership in
Chimeria: Gatekeeper seeks to capture the stakes and power relationships often at play in real
world social interactions. </p>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="DH2014_2_chimeria5"/>
          <p>Fig. 5: Chimeria: Gatekeeper sample run-through</p>
        </figure>
        <head>4. Conclusion

			
				
					</head>
        <p>In this proposal, we have presented Chimeria, a platform for creating and analyzing
narratives related to social group membership. By modeling character identities in a dynamic
and nuanced fashion, we explore complex identity phenomena. By modeling social identity
phenomena related to categorization, we use Chimeria to suggest how to better critically
examine and express how identities are negotiated using digital media systems.</p>
        
        
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="References">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            1. We have additionally implemented a small demo showing the applicability of Chimeria to a 3D game interface built in Unity.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>
            2. We implement both “abstract” categories such as ‘accepted’ or ‘discredited’ and “concrete” categories that can instantiate them. This enables a great degree of flexibility for changing social dynamics within different contexts in games or different games altogether.
          </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">Bowker, G. C., &amp; Star, S. L.</hi></hi> (1999).<hi rend="italic"> Sorting Things Out: Classification and Its Consequences</hi>. Cambridge,
            MA:MIT Press. </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Goffman, E.</hi> (1963) <hi rend="italic">Stigma: Notes on the Management of Spoiled Identity.</hi> New York, NY: Simon and
            Schuster.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Harrell, D. F.</hi> (2010).<hi rend="italic"> Toward a Theory of Critical Computing: The Case of Social Identity Representation	in Digital Media Applications</hi>. CTheory. http://www.ctheory.net/articles.aspx?id=641 (accessed March 3,
            2014).
            <hi rend="bold">Harrell, D. F.</hi> (2013) <hi rend="italic">Phantasmal Media: An Approach to Imagination, Computation, and Expression</hi>.
            Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Harrell, D. F., Kao, D., &amp; Lim, C. U.</hi> (2013). <hi rend="italic">Computationally Modeling Narratives of Social Group Membership with the Chimeria System</hi>. In Proceedings of the 2013 Workshop on Computational Models
            of Narrative. pp. 123-128).
          </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Harrell, D. F., Kao, D., &amp; Lim, C. U., Lipshin, J., Sutherland, A., Makivic, J., and Olson, D.</hi> (2014).<hi rend="italic"> “Authoring Conversational Narratives in Games with the Chimeria Platform.”</hi> In Proceedings of Foundations of Digital Games 2014. Ft. Lauderdale, FL, USA, Apr 3 – Apr 7.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Lakoff, G.</hi> (1987). <hi rend="italic">Women, Fire, and Dangerous Things</hi>. University of Chicago Press, Chicago.
          </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Linde, C.</hi> (1993).<hi rend="italic"> Life Stories: The Creation of Coherence.</hi> Oxford, U.K.:Oxford University Press.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">Liu, H.</hi></hi> (2007). <hi rend="italic">Social Network Profiles as Taste Performances</hi>. Journal of Computer-Mediated	Communication, 13: 252–275.  </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Polanyi, L.</hi> (1989). <hi rend="italic">Telling the American Story: A Structural and Cultural Analysis of Conversational Storytelling</hi>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press. </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Renfrow, D. G.</hi> (2004).<hi rend="italic"> A cartography of passing in everyday life</hi>. Symbolic Interaction 27(4):485-506. </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
