<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:x="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:exsl="http://exslt.org/common" xml:id="Paper-77">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Metaphor, Popular Science and Semantic Tagging: Distant Reading with the Historical Thesaurus of English</title>
				<author>
					<name>
						<surname>Alexander</surname>, <forename>Marc</forename>
					</name>
					<affiliation>University of Glasgow</affiliation>
					<email>marc.alexander@glasgow.ac.uk</email>
				</author>
				<author>
					<name>
						<surname>Anderson</surname>, <forename>Jean</forename>
					</name>
					<affiliation>University of Glasgow</affiliation>
					<email>jean.anderson@glasgow.ac.uk</email>
				</author>
				<author>
					<name>
						<surname>Baron</surname>, <forename>Alistair</forename>
					</name>
					<affiliation>Lancaster University</affiliation>
					<email>a.baron@lancaster.ac.uk</email>
				</author>
				<author>
					<name>
						<surname>Dallachy</surname>, <forename>Fraser</forename>
					</name>
					<affiliation>University of Glasgow</affiliation>
					<email>fraser.dallachy@glasgow.ac.uk</email>
				</author>
				<author>
					<name>
						<surname>Kay</surname>, <forename>Christian</forename>
					</name>
					<affiliation>University of Glasgow</affiliation>
					<email>christian.kay@glasgow.ac.uk</email>
				</author>
				<author>
					<name>
						<surname>Piao</surname>, <forename>Scott</forename>
					</name>
					<affiliation>Lancaster University</affiliation>
					<email>s.piao@lancaster.ac.uk</email>
				</author>
				<author>
					<name>
						<surname>Rayson</surname>, <forename>Paul</forename>
					</name>
					<affiliation>Lancaster University</affiliation>
					<email>p.rayson@lancaster.ac.uk</email>
				</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<authority/>
				<publisher>EPFL, Switzerland</publisher>
				<distributor>
					<name>EPFL Digital Humanities Laboratory</name>
					<address>
						<addrLine>GC D2 386</addrLine>
						<addrLine>Station 18</addrLine>
						<addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
						<addrLine>frederic.kaplan@epfl.ch</addrLine>
					</address>
				</distributor>
				<pubPlace>Lausanne, Switzerland</pubPlace>
				<address>
					<addrLine>EPFL</addrLine>
					<addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
				</address>
				<availability>
					<p></p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<notesStmt>
				<note type="abstract">The present paper describes and implements the semantic analysis of analogy and metaphor in large textual corpora, using the recently-completed database of the _Historical Thesaurus of English_ (published in 2009 as the _Historical Thesaurus of the Oxford English Dictionary_). Using semantic annotation techniques and log-likelihood measures on a 600,000 word corpus of abstract popular science (including a mathematical exposition of number theory, a physics text on parallel universes, and two books on string and quantum theory), the paper digitally demonstrates the existence and the extent of significant analogical content in this corpus. In so doing, it applies Franco Moretti’s ‘distant reading’ programme in the analysis of literary history to non-narrative texts, as well as continuing work on integrating meaning into the methodologies of corpus linguistics.</note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
				<p>
				  <date when="20140709"/>
				  <time when="11:00:00"/>
				</p>
				<p n="session">2</p>
				<p n="room">413 - Amphimax</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
					<term>Paper</term>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
					<term>Long Paper</term>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
					<term>corpus linguistics</term>
					<term>distant reading</term>
					<term>semantics</term>
					<term>metaphor</term>
					<term></term>
				</keywords>
				<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
					<term>corpora and corpus activities</term>
					<term>semantic analysis</term>
					<term>linguistics</term>
					<term></term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text type="paper">
		<front>
			<div>
				<p></p>
			</div>
		</front>
		<body>
			<div>
				<head>1. Introduction</head>
				<p>This paper describes and implements a computational procedure for semantically analysing analogy in large bodies of text using a semantic annotation system based on the database of the <hi rend="italic">Historical Thesaurus of English</hi>.<ref target="n1" rend="sup">1</ref> In so doing, it demonstrates the value of a comprehensive and fine-grained semantic annotation system for English within corpus linguistics. Using log-likelihood measures on its semantically-annotated corpus of abstract popular science, the paper therefore demonstrates the existence, the extent, and the location of significant metaphorical content in this corpus. In so doing, it applies a version of Franco Moretti’s ‘distant reading’ programme in the analysis of literary history to non-narrative texts, as well as continuing work on integrating meaning into the methodologies of corpus linguistics.<ref target="n2" rend="sup">2</ref></p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>1.1. Analogy and Popular Science</head>
				<p>Following the 1980 publication of George Lakoff and Mark Johnson’s <hi rend="italic">Metaphors We Live By</hi>,<ref target="n3" rend="sup">3</ref> it has been frequently stated that human beings, as embodied minds perceiving the mental, social and physical worlds around them, understand abstractions in terms of concrete entities. While this is a well-explicated concept in cognitive linguistics and psychology, few studies have yet aimed to establish both the extent and operation of this in a large corpus of discourse. The standard methodology in cognitive linguistics tends to rely on introspection and the intuitions of native speakers, at the expense of empirical data.<ref target="n4" rend="sup">4</ref> This lack of rigour has resulted in results which, though "intuitively appealing", are criticized "for lacking a clear set of methodological decision principles".<ref target="n5" rend="sup">5</ref> Following earlier work we have undertaken on the investigation of analogy and metaphor in English from empirical groundings,<ref target="n6" rend="sup">6</ref><ref target="n7" rend="sup">7</ref> in this paper we discuss a methodology for identifying these textual phenomena automatically, and in so doing aim to open up cognitive linguistics to more digital humanities techniques, in addition to demonstrating the use of automated semantic annotation and disambiguation techniques at an unprecedented level of granularity.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>1.2. The Corpus</head>
				<p>We take as our initial data two book-length popular science texts which focus on explaining abstract concepts to a non-specialist audience, and therefore provide the greatest potential for the analysis of non-literary analogy - metaphor theory tells us that these should therefore be rich in non-abstract analogies. The corpus is therefore made up of Brian Greene's 2004 <hi rend="italic">The Fabric of the Cosmos</hi> and Marcus du Sautoy's 2003 <hi rend="italic">The Music of the Primes</hi>, although we have subsequently tested the methodology on other popular science texts.</p>
				<p>Through the procedure we describe in 3.1 below to analyse metaphor and analogy in these texts, we identify a range of domains which are unusually frequent in these texts and which are not pertinent to their subject matter (that is, not in the areas of physics, mathematics or general science). We then demonstrate in the remainder of section 3 that these domains are those analogies used systematically and consistently across the texts to elucidate and explicate the abstract concepts the books are focused on discussing. In order to do this, we identify all the semantic domains mentioned in these texts at very high levels of precision, using an annotation system built around the unprecedented detail found in the database of the <hi rend="italic">Historical Thesaurus</hi>. </p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>2. Semantic Annotation</head>
				<p>Semantic tagging and annotation is, we argue, the best solution we have to address the problem of searching and aggregating large collections of textual data: at present, historians, literary scholars and other researchers must search texts and summarize their contents based on word forms. These forms are highly problematic, given that most of them in English refer to multiple senses – for example, the word form "strike" has 181 <hi rend="italic">Historical Thesaurus</hi> meaning entries in English, effectively inhibiting any large-scale automated research into the language of industrial action; "show" has 99 meanings, prohibiting effective searches on, say, theatrical metaphors or those of emotional displays. In such cases, much time and effort is expended in manually disambiguating and filtering search results and word statistics. </p>
				<p>To resolve this problem, we use in this paper an early version of the Glasgow-Lancaster Semantic Annotation System, which we are currently developing at both of those universities. GL-SAS is a tool for annotating large corpora with meaning codes from the <hi rend="italic">Historical Thesaurus</hi>, enabling us to search and aggregate data using the 236,000 precise meaning codes in that dataset, rather than imprecise word forms. These <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus</hi> category codes are over one thousand times more precise than USAS, the current leader in semantic annotation in English corpus linguistics.<ref target="n8" rend="sup">8</ref> The system automatically disambiguates these word meanings using existing computational disambiguation techniques alongside new context-dependent methods enabled by the <hi rend="italic">Historical Thesaurus'</hi> dating codes and its fine-grained hierarchical structure. With our data showing that 60% of word forms in English refer to more than one meaning, and with some word forms referring to close to two hundred meanings, effective disambiguation is essential to GL-SAS. </p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>3. Results</head>
				<head>3.1. Methodology</head>
				<p>The 600,000 word corpus we outline above were lemmatised and then processed through our annotation system, resulting in texts with each word being annotated with a Historical Thesaurus meaning code. We then aggregated those codes into a dataset which summarised the frequency of each meaning code in the text, and took that frequency list and compared it to a reference corpus made up of a 14m word corpus of random selections from Wikipedia, to provide a comparison against standard expository text. Our comparison was based on a log-likelihood significance measure,<ref target="n9" rend="sup">9</ref> which identifies, to an acceptable degree, those semantic domains which are mentioned unusually frequently in our popular science texts by comparison to the reference corpus, and therefore indicates a text's "key" domains (where the log-likelihood values are greater than around 20)<ref target="n10" rend="sup">10</ref> - those domains which reflect what a text is "about".<ref target="n11" rend="sup">11</ref></p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>3.2. <hi rend="italic">The Fabric of the Cosmos</hi></head>
				<p>Brian Greene’s 2004 <hi rend="italic">The Fabric of the Cosmos</hi> discusses theoretical physics and its relation to the concepts of space and time. Its key semantic domains are given in Table 1:</p>
				<table>
					<row>
						<cell role="label"> HT Category</cell>
						<cell role="label">Category Name </cell>
						<cell role="label">Log-Likelihood Value </cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell role="data">01.05.07</cell>
						<cell role="data">Space</cell>
						<cell role="data">13655.8 </cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell role="data">01.05.07.01</cell>
						<cell role="data">Distance </cell>
						<cell role="data">6344.8</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell role="data">01.04.07.05.04.08 </cell>
						<cell role="data">Photon </cell>
						<cell role="data">4912.5 </cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell role="data">01.05.06.07 </cell>
						<cell role="data">Computation of time </cell>
						<cell role="data">3603.5 </cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell role="data">
							<hi rend="bold">01.02.09.15 </hi>
						</cell>
						<cell role="data">
							<hi rend="bold">Spinning textiles </hi>
						</cell>
						<cell role="data">
							<hi rend="bold">3193.5 </hi>
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell role="data">
							<hi rend="bold">03.11.03.01.08.02 </hi>
						</cell>
						<cell role="data">
							<hi rend="bold">Stringed instruments </hi>
						</cell>
						<cell role="data">
							<hi rend="bold">2277.7 </hi>
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell role="data">
							<hi rend="bold">03.11.03.02.09.14 </hi>
						</cell>
						<cell role="data">
							<hi rend="bold">Pattern/design </hi>
						</cell>
						<cell role="data">
							<hi rend="bold">1949.8 </hi>
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row>
						<cell role="data">
							<hi rend="bold">01.02.09.14.01.03 </hi>
						</cell>
						<cell role="data">
							<hi rend="bold">Woven fabric </hi>
						</cell>
						<cell role="data">
							<hi rend="bold">1922.2 </hi>
						</cell>
					</row>
				</table>
				<p>While the first four domains are within the <hi rend="italic">Thesaurus</hi> categories which refer to the text's topic, and therefore expected, the next four (in bold) are not immediately relevant to the book's topic. Looking for these domains in the text itself, chunked into 591 smaller files of 320 words each, we get a distribution like this:</p>
				<figure>
					<graphic url="DH2014_66_Figure 1 - FC Analogical Textual Clusters"/>
					<p>Fig. 1: Analogical textual clusters in The Fabric of the Cosmos, shown by frequency of key semantic domains</p>
				</figure>
				<p>(Here, the Thesaurus codes have been replaced by words representing those categories, for ease of reading.)</p>
				<p>The peak three-quarters of the way through the text indicates an area rich in mentions of textiles, and looking at this point in the text we find passages such as:</p>
				<p>Since we speak of the ‘fabric’ of spacetime, the suggestion goes, maybe spacetime is stitched out of strings much as a shirt is stitched out of thread. That is, much as joining numerous threads together in an appropriate pattern produces a shirt’s fabric, maybe joining numerous strings together in an appropriate pattern produces what we commonly call spacetime’s fabric. Matter, like you and me, would then amount to additional agglomerations of vibrating strings.<ref target="n12" rend="sup">12</ref></p>
				<p>The areas we have identified through the log-likelihood analysis are therefore those areas rich in metaphors of fabric and strings (as other examples show) which are used by the author to discuss physics. We can therefore use this technique to pinpoint areas of significant use of metaphor or analogy in a text.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>3.3. <hi rend="italic">The Music of the Primes</hi></head>
				<p>As a check of the methodology, the same technique shows that in this particular book, which discusses prime number theory, there are highly key domains of <hi rend="italic">travel </hi>and <hi rend="italic">landscape</hi> in use alongside mathematical terms. Going to sections particularly rich in these domains gives analogical content over a long stretch, introduced by the following extract:</p>
				<p>Gauss’s two-dimensional map of imaginary numbers charts the numbers that we shall feed into the zeta function. The north-south axis keeps track of how many steps we take in the imaginary direction, whilst the east west axis charts the real numbers. We can lay this map out flat on a table. What we want to do is to create a physical landscape situated in the space above this map. The shadow of the zeta function will then turn into a physical object whose peaks and valleys we can explore.<ref target="n13" rend="sup">13</ref></p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<head>4. Conclusion</head>
				<p>We therefore demonstrate in this paper the use of a very fine-grained semantic annotation system, and establish the utility of such detailed annotations by describing a digital technique for discovering not only the existence of systematic metaphorical content but also its location and where it clusters. We believe that this result is significant in its own right, particularly for scholars of metaphor or cognitive linguistics, but we will also show that this represents only one of the uses to which highly-granular semantically annotated data can be put.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="References">
				<listBibl>
					<bibl>1. <hi rend="bold">Kay, C., J. Roberts, M. Samuels, and I. Wotherspoon</hi> (eds). (2009). <hi rend="italic">Historical Thesaurus of the Oxford English Dictionary</hi>. Oxford: Oxford University Press. See also <ref type="url" target="http://historicalthesaurus.arts.gla.ac.uk/.">historicalthesaurus.arts.gla.ac.uk</ref>.
					</bibl>
					<bibl>2. <hi rend="bold">Rayson, Paul</hi>. (2008). <hi rend="italic">From Key Words to Key Semantic Domains</hi>. International Journal of Corpus Linguistics 13.4. 519-549.
					</bibl>
					<bibl>3. <hi rend="bold">Lakoff, George &amp; Mark Johnson</hi>. (1980). <hi rend="italic">Metaphors We Live By</hi>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.
					</bibl>
					<bibl>4. <hi rend="bold">Gibbs, Raymond W.</hi> (2006a). <hi rend="italic">Introspection and Cognitive Linguistics: Should We Trust Our Own Intuitions?</hi> Annual Review of Cognitive Linguistics 4(1). 135-151.
					</bibl>
					<bibl>5. <hi rend="bold">Evans, Vyvyan &amp; Melanie Green.</hi> (2006).<hi rend="italic"> Cognitive Linguistics: An Introduction</hi>. Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press. Page 780.
					</bibl>
					<bibl>6. <hi rend="bold">Alexander, Marc &amp; Christian Kay</hi>. (2011) [2010]. <hi rend="italic">Mapping Metaphors Across Time with the Historical Thesaurus</hi>. Conference paper at Helsinki Corpus Festival: The Past, Present, and Future of English Historical Corpora, University of Helsinki, Finland. Based on an earlier paper at The 3rd UK Cognitive Linguistics Conference, University of Hertfordshire.
					</bibl>
					<bibl>7. <hi rend="bold">Alexander, Marc</hi>. (2011).<hi rend="italic"> Meaning Construction in Popular Science An Investigation into Cognitive, Digital, and Empirical Approaches to Discourse Reification</hi>. University of Glasgow: Ph.D. thesis.
					</bibl>
					<bibl>8. <ref type="url" target="http://ucrel.lancs.ac.uk/usas/">ucrel.lancs.ac.uk/usas</ref>
					</bibl>
					<bibl>9. <hi rend="bold">Dunning, Ted.</hi> (1993). <hi rend="italic">Accurate methods for the statistics of surprise and coincidence</hi>. Computational Linguistics 19(1). 61–74.
					</bibl>
					<bibl>10. <hi rend="bold">Rayson, Paul, Damon Berridge, &amp; Brian Francis</hi>. (2004).<hi rend="italic"> Extending the Cochran Rule for the Comparison of Word Frequencies between Corpora</hi>. 7th International Conference on Statistical Analysis of Textual Data.
					</bibl>
					<bibl>11. <hi rend="bold">McIntyre, Dan &amp; Brian Walker</hi>. (2010).<hi rend="italic"> How can Corpora be Used to Explore the Language of Poetry and Drama?</hi> In Anne O’Keeffe &amp; Michael McCarthy (eds.), The Routledge Handbook of Corpus Linguistics. London: Routledge. 516-530.
					</bibl>
					<bibl>12. <hi rend="bold">Greene, Brian R</hi>. (2004). <hi rend="italic">The Fabric of the Cosmos: Space, Time and the Texture of Reality</hi>. Alfred A Knopf: New York. Page 486-7.
					</bibl>
					<bibl>13. <hi rend="bold">du Sautoy, Marcus</hi>. (2003). <hi rend="italic">The Music of the Primes: Why an Unsolved Problem in Mathematics Matters</hi>. London: Harper Perennial. Page 85.
					</bibl>
				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
