<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="paper_190_hoover"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Zeta and Iota and Twentieth-Century American Poetry</title><author><name reg="Hoover, David L.">David L. Hoover</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Field, Hana S.">Hana S. Field</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>paper</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>Delta</item><item>Zeta</item><item>Iota</item><item>poetry</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list><item>HSF: Created from David L. Hoover's text<date value="2007-04">April
                    2007</date></item><item>SAS: Revised <date value="2007-05">May 2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Zeta and Iota and Twentieth-Century American Poetry"><titlePart type="main">Zeta and Iota and Twentieth-Century American
                Poetry</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Hoover, David L.">David L. Hoover</name><address><addrLine>david.hoover@nyu.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">New York University</titlePart></front><body><div0><p>In his intriguing “All the Way Through: Testing for Authorship in Different
                    Frequency Strata”, John F. Burrows follows up his much-discussed Delta (Burrows,
                    2002a, 2002b, 2003; Hoover 2004a, 2004b, 2006) with two new measures of textual
                    difference: Zeta and Iota (Burrows 2006; see also Burrows 2005).</p><p>Both measures begin with a full word frequency list for a sample of Restoration
                    poetry (approximately 20,000 words) by a single primary author. The sample is
                    then divided into five sections of equal size, and word frequency lists are
                    created for them. Zeta deals with words of moderate frequency, words occurring
                    in at least three of the five sections. To compare two poets, the word list is
                    reduced further by removing any occurring more than three times in the second
                    poet’s sample. Where many authors are being compared, the list is reduced by
                    removing any words present in the text samples of most of the other authors.
                    Both methods remove from consideration the most frequent words of English that
                    have been the focus of so much recent work. Whether there are two or many
                    authors, the result is a list of words that are moderately frequent in the
                    primary author but much less frequent in the other author(s).</p><p>For Iota, the word list is first limited to words appearing in at most two of the
                    primary author’s sections. To compare two authors, the list is further limited
                    to words that are completely absent from the second author’s sample. Where many
                    authors are being compared, the list is further reduced by removing words that
                    appear in more than half the other authors. In either case, very frequent and
                    moderately frequent words are eliminated, leaving words that are not very
                    frequent in the primary author but are rare or non-existent in the other
                    author(s).</p><p>Zeta and Iota are remarkably effective in attributing poems as short as 1,000
                    words to the correct authors. Even more important, they allow the analyst to
                    concentrate on a relatively small subset of characteristic words, nearly all
                    content words. These lead back to the text and to important questions of
                    interpretation and style.</p><p>Both Zeta and Iota will require further testing before they can be confidently
                    applied to genuine questions of authorship and style, and we can begin with a
                    study of twentieth-century poetry. For these tests my corpus consists of samples
                    of 14,000 to 129,000 words of poetry by twenty-six poets as the primary set and
                    fifty-six independent poems from 900 to 21,000 words long as the secondary set,
                    thirty-six of these by poets in the primary set and twenty by other poets (poems
                    by primary authors are removed from their main samples). The texts were
                    downloaded from Chadwyck-Healey’s Literature Online and edited to regularize
                    hyphens and to remove prose sections and non-authorial text, such as publication
                    information, notes, section numbers, epigrams and other quotations. Delta tests
                    were used to determine which of the poems and poets are most difficult to
                    attribute, and these were analyzed using Zeta and Iota.</p><p>My head-to-head tests of Wallace Stevens vs Archibald MacLeish and Edwin
                    Arlington Robinson vs Robert Frost give even more definitive results than
                    Burrows achieves for Marvell vs Waller, though my much larger samples require
                    minor adjustments in technique). The new measures have no difficulty
                    distinguishing the two poets, whichever poet’s word list is used.</p><p>When Burrows tests Marvell and Waller (using each poet’s own primary word list)
                    against the samples and twenty-four independent poems by twenty-four other main
                    authors and twenty-one poems by other authors, Iota works very well for both
                    authors, and Zeta works based on Waller’s list. Marvell’s list produces a group
                    of failures which Burrows suggests are likely to be result from the contrast
                    between the political satires being tested and the largely pastoral nature of
                    most of Marvell’s poetry.</p><p>My tests using the primary word lists of eight different authors yields strong
                    results for Zeta on James Dickey, Vachel Lindsay, Robert Frost, and Wallace
                    Stevens, with all of their individual poems ranking higher than any poem or
                    sample by any other author. Zeta is very successful on two of William Vaughn
                    Moody’s independent poems, but the third ranks far below other author samples
                    and individual poems, and it fails badly when based on the word lists of Edwin
                    Arlington Robinson, Kenneth Rexroth, and Archibald MacLeish. For Iota, only the
                    lists of Stevens and Lindsay produce completely correct results, though those of
                    Moody and Rexroth produce good results except for a single poem by each author.
                    Further research into the causes of these poorer results is underway, but the
                    problems with Iota may be related to my larger samples. (The definition of
                    “rare” is obviously very different for 20,000-word samples and 120,000-word
                    samples.)</p><p>One alteration of Zeta that produces perfect results using Robinson’s word list
                    not only limits the word list to words that appear in at least three of the
                    author’s five sections, but also sets a lower limit on the word’s frequency in
                    the main set and limits the total frequency of the word in the twenty-five
                    counter-sets. Another, still under investigation, calculates the standard
                    deviation of the word’s frequency in the five base sections and divides it by
                    the mean frequency. Sorting the word list on the resulting Coefficient of
                    Variation (or Relative Standard Deviation) makes it easy to limit the list to
                    words that appear at relatively consistent frequencies in the five sections,
                    besides appearing in at least three of them and in a limited number of the
                    counter-set samples. A word appearing five times in each of a poet’s five
                    sections seems intuitively more “characteristic” of the author than one
                    appearing twenty-three times in one section and once in each of two others.</p><p>Whatever the outcome of further testing and modification may be, Zeta,
                    especially, is very effective in focusing attention on a poet’s characteristic
                    words, a useful task in its own right. In head-to-head tests on MacLeish and
                    Stevens, much more stringent stipulations than Burrows used produce fascinating
                    results: the twenty-six words occurring in all five sections of MacLeish’s
                    sample but with a frequency less than three in Stevens’s sample are good
                    potential MacLeish authorship markers, and the same stipulations produce forty
                    potential Stevens authorship markers. These words range in rank within their
                    word lists from about the 200th to the 1,400th most frequent. These two sets of
                    marker words return our attention to the texts:</p><p><emph rend="bold">Characteristic Stevens words rare in MacLeish:</emph><lb/>
                reality, except, centre, element, colors, solitude, possible, ideas, hymns,
                    essential, imagined, nothingness, crown, inhuman, motions, regard, sovereign,
                    chaos, genius, glittering, lesser, singular, alike, archaic, luminous, phrases,
                    casual, voluble, universal, autumnal, café, inner, reads, vivid, clearest,
                    deeply, minor, perfection, relation, immaculate</p><p><emph rend="bold">Characteristic MacLeish words rare in Stevens:</emph><lb/>
                answered, knees, hope, ways, steep, pride, signs, lead, hurt, sea’s, sons,
                    vanish, wife, earth’s, lifted, they’re, swing, valleys, fog, inland, catch,
                    dragging, ragged, rope, strung, bark</p><p>Stevens’s words are longer and more abstract, especially the nouns, and his list
                    is saturated with adjectives. MacLeish’s list has very few adjectives and more
                    verbs and concrete nouns. Searching for marker words in each poet’s work yields
                    a remarkable pair of short poems: MacLeish’s short poem “‘Dover Beach’–A Note to
                    that Poem” (215 words) contains seven of his twenty-six marker words, including
                    the three italicized in this brief passage:</p><lg><l part="F">. . . It’s a fine and a</l><l>Wild smother to vanish in: pulling down---</l><l>Tripping with outward ebb the urgent inward.</l><l>Speaking alone for myself it’s the steep hill and the</l><l>Toppling lift of the young men I am toward now . . .</l></lg><p>In his even shorter poem, “From the Packet of Anacharsis” (144 words), six of
                    Stevens’s forty marker words appear, including the three italicized in this
                    brief passage (internal ellipsis in the original):</p><lg><l>And Bloom would see what Puvis did, protest</l><l>And speak of the floridest reality . . .</l><l>In the punctual centre of all circles white</l><l>Stands truly. The circles nearest to it share</l><l>Its color . . .</l></lg><p>Preventing the huge numbers of items being analyzed from masking any meaningful
                    results is one of the most difficult challenges for quantitative analyses of
                    literature. By selecting for examination words that are particularly
                    characteristic of an author, Zeta and Iota are potentially very useful for
                    literary analysis as well as authorship attribution, no matter what further
                    refinements they may require.</p></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Burrows, John F.">John F. Burrows</name></author><title level="a">All the Way Through: Testing for Authorship in
                                Different Frequency Strata</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j"> Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr><note>Advanced Access published January 6, 2006</note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Burrows, John F.">Jonh F. Burrows</name></author><title level="a">Who Wrote <emph>Shamela</emph>? Verifying the Authorship of a
                                Parodic Text</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">20.4</biblScope><date value="2005">2005</date><biblScope type="pages">437-450</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Burrows, John F.">John F. Burrows</name></author><title level="a">Questions of Authorship: Attribution and Beyond</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">37</biblScope><date value="2003">2003</date><biblScope type="pages">5-32</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Burrows, John F.">John F.Burrows</name></author><title level="a">Delta’: A Measure of Stylistic Difference and a Guide
                                to Likely Authorship</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">17.3</biblScope><date value="2002">2002a</date><biblScope type="pages">267-287</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Burrows, John F.">John F. Burrows</name></author><title level="a">The Englishing of Juvenal: Computational Stylistics and
                                Translated Texts</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Style</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">36</biblScope><date value="2002">2002b</date><biblScope type="pages">677-99</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Hoover, David L.">David L. Hoover</name></author><title level="a">Testing Burrow's Delta</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">19.4</biblScope><date value="2004">2004a</date><biblScope type="pages">453-475</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Hoover, David L.">David L. Hoover</name></author><title level="a">Delta Prime?</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">19.4</biblScope><date value="2004">2004b</date><biblScope type="pages">477-495</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Hoover, David L.">David L. Hoover</name></author><title level="a">Word Frequency, Statistical Stylistics, and Authorship
                                Attribution</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m"> Advanced ICT Methods Guide to Linguistics</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="McEnery, Tony">Tony McEnery</name></editor><imprint><publisher/><pubPlace/><date>Forthcoming</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>