<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="paper_260_flanders"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Markup and the Digital Paratext</title><author><name reg="Flanders, Julia">Julia Flanders</name></author><author><name reg="Fiormonte, Domenico">Domenico Fiormonte</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>paper</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>metadata</item><item>encoding</item><item>theory</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Julia Flanders' email text <date value="2007-03">March
                    2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Markup and the Digital Paratext"><titlePart type="main">Markup and the Digital Paratext</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Flanders, Julia">Julia Flanders</name><address><addrLine>Julia_Flanders@brown.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Brown University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Fiormonte, Domenico">Domenico Fiormonte</name><address><addrLine>fiormont@uniroma3.it</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of Rome</titlePart></front><body><div0><head>Abstract:</head><p>According to the French rhetorician and literary critic Gerard Genette a paratext
                    is a transitional zone: a privileged space of a "pragmatics", of "strategy", and
                    of action over the audience (Genette 1997). In a digital environment, the idea
                    of the paratext may allow us to recognize the significance and the mode of
                    operation of certain crucial textual formations that might otherwise seem
                    inconsequential. These formations, unlike traditional paratexts, are not always
                    literally visible as part of the legible textual surface, but instead operate
                    through the representational and performative mechanisms of the digital
                    interface. Their separateness is demarcated through markup, which not only
                    creates a boundary between text and paratext but also makes the paratext into a
                    space of function and behavior: of meaning instantiated through action rather
                    than simply through textual signification.</p></div0><div0><head>Proposal:</head><p>According to the French rhetorician and literary critic Gerard Genette a paratext
                    is a transitional zone: a privileged space of a "pragmatics", of "strategy", and
                    of action over the audience (Genette 1997). This paratextual space—instantiated
                    in what are traditionally considered secondary or ancillary texts such as
                    footnotes, commentary, translation, and so forth—produces and ramifies the
                    "main" text, the object that is thus presented to our interest as primarily
                    significant. It is precisely through the paratexts that the concept of a "main"
                    text emerges at all: in a given historical moment, depending on social,
                    cultural, political, and other factors, a certain text emerges, and slowly
                    starts to circulate and acquire status through the effects of its paratexts:
                    comments, editions, translations, dedications, and so forth.</p><p>In a digital environment, the idea of the paratext may allow us to recognize the
                    significance and the mode of operation of certain crucial textual formations
                    that might otherwise seem inconsequential. An example of such a formation is the
                    information we might call "microtexts": that is, external, contingently visible
                    “microcontents” (Nielsen 2000) that describe, illustrate or complete information
                    within a web page or resource. These include also embedded alternate texts that
                    usually appear when you move the mouse over an image, link or any other semiotic
                    device (Zinna 2005). Another example is what we might call "metatexts", a
                    category embracing both formal metadata and also looser kinds of descriptive,
                    normative or regulative information, usually not directly visible to the user,
                    that is added in order to allow search engines and other processing to produce
                    coherent and useful results.</p><p>These terms arise from an external classification (one which could be extended)
                    emphasizing the different ways these paratexts function as part of a publication
                    architecture. But digital paratexts can be also organized, according to their
                    cognitive and semiotic functions, into at least three flexible (and mutually
                    permeable) categories: <list type="ordered"><item><label>1.</label> descriptive (syntagmatic and paradigmatic axes): those
                            paratexts which contain information about a text, including various
                            kinds of metadata;</item><item><label>2.</label> normative: those which constrain the behavior of the
                            text (for instance, schemas)</item><item><label>3.</label> pragmatic: those which mediate or represent the text
                            as a discursive object, and which produce its digital
                        phenomenology.</item></list></p><p>These formations, unlike traditional paratexts, are not always literally visible
                    as part of the legible textual surface: their "strategy" and "pragmatics"
                    operate through the representational and performative mechanisms of the digital
                    interface. In print, the paratext has (despite its marginality) a certain
                    visible presence on the page: its meaning may be wholly in relation to the text
                    it supports, but it is not different in kind from that text (Tomasi 2005). The
                    digital paratexts we are describing, however, occupy a different stratum and
                    have a different kind of visibility and functional effect. Their presence may be
                    felt primarily in what the text does or in how we discover it, rather than in
                    the words we see when we read it. Their separateness is demarcated through
                    markup, which not only creates a boundary between text and paratext but also
                    makes the paratext into a space of function and behavior: of meaning
                    instantiated through action rather than simply through textual signification. In
                    this respect, these categories of paratext (and in particular the last, which is
                    the realm of markup proper) are analogous to the punctuation, formatting, and
                    presentational conventions through which a printed text is realized for a
                    reader, or through which an oral text is concretized in print. As Genette
                    observes, any transcription, including the written transcription of an oral
                    speech, is a form of paratext, and we can usefully extend this idea to digital
                    forms by observing that any encoding—in effect, any transmediation—constitutes a
                    form of paratext as well.</p><p>Each of the three categories above illustrates a distinctive dimension of the
                    digital paratext, and raises a set of questions and issues that can help us
                    reach a clearer understanding of the role of markup and the nature of digital
                    texts. If we consider markup in Genette’s terms as a “privileged space” of
                    “action” and “pragmatics”, what effect does this have on our understanding of
                    text encoding as a transcriptional activity? To what extent do our disciplinary
                    expectations about documentary evidence run counter to the logic implied by
                    these terms? The boundary between transcription and authoring (and our sense of
                    where the distinction lies) may turn out to be harder to pin down than has
                    previously been suggested.</p><p>Similarly, to what extent does metadata operate as an active, rather than a
                    passive component of the textual ecology? If we understand metadata creation as
                    part of the authoring of the digital document, does this change our sense of who
                    should be creating it and what its sources should be?</p><p>Finally, if schemas and stylesheets can also be understood as paratexts (for
                    instance, as suggested in Pierazzo 2006), then we need to rethink our conception
                    of textual meaning and rhetoric to include not only the forms a text actually
                    takes, but also those which its constraints permit it to take: in other words,
                    the potential as well as actual forms through which we apprehend the text.</p></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Genette, Gerard">Gerard Genette</name></author><title level="m">Paratexts: Thresholds of Interpretation</title><respStmt><resp>Trans.</resp><name reg="Lewin, Jane A.">Jane A. Lewin</name></respStmt><imprint><pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace><publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher><date value="1997">1997</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Nielsen, Jakob">Jakob Nielsen</name></author><title level="m">Designing Web Usability: The Practice of Simplicity</title><imprint><pubPlace>Indianapolis, IN</pubPlace><publisher>New Riders</publisher><date value="2000">2000</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Pierazzo, Elena">Elena Pierazzo</name></author><title level="a">Just Different Layers? Stylesheets and Digital Edition
                                Methodology</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Paper presented at Digital Humanities 2006, Paris Sorbonne, 5-9 July 2006</title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Tomasi, F.">F. Tomasi</name></author><title level="a">Il paratesto nei documenti elettronici</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">I dintorni del testo: approcci alle periferie del
                                libro. Atti del Convegno internazionale. Roma, 15-17 novembre 2004;
                                Bologna, 18-19 novembre 2004</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Santoro, M.">M. Santoro</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Tavoni, M. G.">M. G. Tavoni</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Roma</pubPlace><publisher>Edizioni dell'Ateneo</publisher><date value="2005">2005</date><biblScope type="pages">712-722</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Zinna, A.">A. Zinna</name></author><title level="m">Le interfacce degli oggetti di scrittura</title><imprint><pubPlace>Roma</pubPlace><publisher>Meltemi</publisher><date value="2004">2004</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>