<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="paper_226_sinclair"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Reading Tools, or Text Analysis Tools as Objects of Interpretation</title><author><name reg="Sinclair, Stéfan">Stéfan Sinclair</name></author><author><name reg="Rockwell, Geoffrey">Geoffrey Rockwell</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>paper</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>text analysis</item><item>tools development</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Stéfan Sinclair's text <date value="2007-04">April
                    2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Reading Tools, or Text Analysis Tools as Objects of Interpretation"><titlePart type="main">Reading Tools, or Text Analysis Tools as Objects of
                    Interpretation</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Sinclair, Stéfan">Stéfan Sinclair</name><address><addrLine>sgsinclair@gmail.com</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">McMaster University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Rockwell, Geoffrey">Geoffrey Rockwell</name><address><addrLine>georock@mcmaster.ca</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">McMaster University</titlePart></front><body><div0><p>Computer-assisted text analysis has over 50 years of history in providing tools
                    to help scholars interpret texts (see, for instance, Potter, 1991, Burrows,
                    2004, Bradley, 2004). The tools themselves are the products of a large range of
                    circumstances in computing and text criticism, from the availability of certain
                    hardware to the fluctuating fortunes of structuralist approaches in literary
                    criticism. In this paper we will reverse the usual interpretive flow from tools
                    to text by attempting to interpret tools themselves as artifacts of human
                    creation. We will frame this interpretive exercise as a Gedankenexperiment; in
                    particular: if a scholar one hundred years from now were to study the TAPoR
                    Portal as cultural artifact, what would it reveal about its theoretical
                    presuppositions, the methodological practices of its times, its cultural value,
                    and even its authors?</p><p>This thought experiment is predicated on the assumption that tools can be studied
                    as cultural artifacts in ways similar to, say, literary texts. To examine this
                    assumption more closely, we will outline several ways in which tools may be
                    studied and interpreted, including: <list type="unordered"><item>as functional systems fulfilling an identified need</item><item>as code that corresponds to certain expectations in terms of
                            structure, brevity, creativity, etc.</item><item>as interfaces that may have an aesthetic appeal</item><item>as pedagogic tools that are intended to assist users in developing
                            skills</item><item>as artifacts that express an author's perspective</item><item>as artifacts that express characteristics about a community</item></list></p><p>Several differences are evident between literary texts and tools as objects of
                    study. For instance, tools manifest themselves at two (at leaset) layers of
                    visibility: the code layer, generally reserved for developers, and the interface
                    layer, generally intended for users. Literary texts, in contrast, have only one
                    layer of exposure. It may also be that text analysis tools are fundamentally too
                    different from texts to be considered using approaches of literary criticism. A
                    similar debate has raged in game studies for the past several years (see, for
                    instance Frasca, 1999): can games be studied as narratives (the literary camp)
                    or do they require an entirely different approach (the ludology camp)? We will
                    argue for a hybrid approach: while literary criticism can be useful to interpret
                    certain aspects of tools, other aspects require their own framework of study.
                    Moreover, this hybrid approach leads to certain practical consequences when
                    considering how to peer-review tools and their development (see Sinclair et al.,
                    2003). As a case study for interpreting tools, we will use the TAPoR Portal, an
                    initiative to build a web-based gateway to electronic texts and tools (see <xptr to="http://tapor.ca/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/> and Sinclair, 2002). The
                    TAPoR Portal is reaching the end of its development cycle, after approximately
                    five years. It serves as a convenient case study for several reasons, including
                    its duration (a five year project), its collaborative nature (involving several
                    dozen researchers at five Canadian universities, its development model (a blend
                    of academic and private sector contributions), its interdisciplinarity
                    (representing several branches of the digital humanities and computer science),
                    and, of course, its size and complexity (over 165, 000 new lines of code).
                    Indeed, given the size of this "corpus", examples can be found for just about
                    any interpretation that might be proposed, but such is the open-ended nature of
                    interpretation. </p></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Bradley, John">John Bradley</name></author><title level="a">Text Tools</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">A Companion to Digital Humanities</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Schreibman, Susan">Susan Schreibman</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Siemens, Ray">Ray Siemens</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Unsworth, John">John Unsworth</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace><publisher>Blackwell Publishing Ltd</publisher><date value="2004">2004</date><biblScope type="pages">505-522</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Burrows, John">John Burrows</name></author><title level="a">Textual Analysis</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">A Companion to Digital Humanities</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Schreibman, Susan">Susan Schreibman</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Siemens, Ray">Ray Siemens</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Unsworth, John">John Unsworth</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace><publisher>Blackwell Publishing Ltd</publisher><date value="2004">2004</date><biblScope type="pages">323-347</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Frasca, Gonzalo">Gonzalo Frasca</name></author><title level="a">Ludology Meets Narratology: Similitudes and Differences
                              Between (Video) Games and Narrative</title></analytic><monogr><imprint><date value="1999">1999</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-11-13" to="http://www.ludology.org/articles/ludology.htm" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Potter, Rosanne G.">Rosanne G. Potter</name></author><title level="a">Statistical Analysis of Literature: A Retrospective on Computers and the Humanities, 1966-1990</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">25.6</biblScope><date value="1991">1991</date><biblScope type="pages">401-429</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Sinclair, Stéfan">Stéfan Sinclair</name></author><author><name reg="Bradley, John">John Bradley</name></author><author><name reg="Ramsay, Stephan">Stephan Ramsay</name></author><author><name reg="Rockwell, Geoffrey">Geoffrey Rockwell</name></author><author><name reg="Siemens, Ray">Ray Siemens</name></author><title level="a">Peer Review of Humanities Computing Software</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">ACH/ALLC 2003 Conference Program</title><imprint><date value="2003">2003</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-11-13" to="http://www.english.uga.edu/webx/abstracts/final/sessions.pdf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Sinclair, Stéfan">Stéfan Sinclair</name></author><author><name reg="Butler, Terry">Terry Butler</name></author><title level="a">TAPoR - A Canadian Text Analysis Portal for Research</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Digital Resources in the Humanities</title><imprint><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Office for Humanities Communications</publisher><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><title level="m"><name reg="TAPoR Project">TAPoR Project</name></title><imprint/></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-11-13" to="http://www.tapor.ca/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>