<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="paper_250_porter"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Examples of Images in Text Editing</title><author><name reg="Porter, Dorothy Carr">Dorothy Carr Porter</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>paper</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>images</item><item>TEI</item><item>text encoding</item><item>medieval manuscripts</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Dorothy Carr Porter's doc <date value="2007-04">April
                    2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Examples of Images in Text Editing"><titlePart type="main">Examples of Images in Text Editing</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Porter, Dorothy Carr">Dorothy Carr Porter</name><address><addrLine>dporter@uky.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of Kentucky</titlePart></front><body><div0><p>In 2002, <title type="j">Computers and the Humanities</title> dedicated an issue
                    to “Image-based Humanities Computing” at a time when “a majority of first
                    generation image-based humanities computing projects have reached at least an
                    initial plateau of completion.” (Kirschenbaum, p. 3) Since that time interest in
                    incorporating primary source images into “text” editions has blossomed, as can
                    be attested by recent threads on the TEI listserv and work on the TEI council to
                    develop recommendations for specific methods for integrating image files – and
                    pointers to areas of image files – into traditional text encoding projects. The
                    number of image-based projects has multiplied in that time as well, although it
                    takes some effort to find who is working on such projects. There is not (yet) a
                    central listing of all image-based TEI projects under development.</p><p>Practical work has been done on tool development since 2002 as well. As of March
                    1, 2007 there are no less than six tools of which I am aware that serve to edit
                    or display images within the context of text editing. The majority of these
                    tools are for linking text and image for digital display.<note n="1">Edition
                        Production and Presentation Technology (EPPT), developed by Kevin Kiernan
                        under the aegis of the <title level="m">Electronic Boethius </title>project,
                            <xptr to="http://www.eppt.org/eppt-trial/EPPT-TrialProjects.htm" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/><lb/>Image processing services,
                        developed by Neel Smith and Christopher Blackwell through Harvard's Center
                        for Hellenic Studies, at <title level="m">Digital incunabula: a CHS site
                            devoted to the cultivation of digital arts and letters</title>, <xptr to="http://chs75.harvard.edu/projects/diginc/techpub/images" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/><lb/>Juxta, developed through the NINES
                        project (networked infrastructure for nineteenth-century electronic
                        scholarship), <xptr to="http://www.nines.org/tools/juxta.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/><lb/>Florian Thienel, “Konzept für einen editionsphilologischen
                        EDV-Arbeitsplatz auf der Basis von XML und verwandten Standards”
                        Diplomarbeit im Fach Informatik, Universität Würzburg</note> Add to these
                    additional tools for the simple annotation of images<note n="2">UVic Image
                        Markup Tool (1.3.0.3), <xptr to="http://www.tapor.uvic.ca/~mholmes/image_markup/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note> and tools for tagging multimedia.<note n="3">Doug
                        Reside at the Maryland Institute of Technology in the Humanities (MITH) at
                        the University of Maryland is developing still-unnamed tool to tag not only
                        images, but video and audio files as well</note> Undoubtedly, the
                    proliferation of tools focused on image editing and display reflects a growing
                    interest in incorporating images into digital editions.</p><p>The number of tools available for working with text plus image in digital editing
                    highlights a simple truth: projects and their sources are different, and
                    technologies that will work for one project might be incompatible with another.
                    On the other hand, technologies applicable in simple circumstances might be
                    expanded and combined with other technologies to suit much more complex
                    situations. In this presentation, I will describe the sources of two digital
                    projects with reference to their requirements for becoming viable digital
                    projects. One is quite simple and the other complex, but the same methods inform
                    both projects.</p><p>MS Cambridge, Pembroke College MS 25, the subject of the <emph>Digital Edition of
                        Cambridge, Pembroke College MS 25</emph> , (Pembroke 25 project) directed by
                    Paul Szarmach, Director of the Medieval Academy of America, and Thomas N. Hall
                    at the University of Notre Dame. Pembroke 25 is a collection of Anglo-Latin
                    homilies, copied at the scriptorium at Bury St. Edmunds in the late eleventh or
                    early twelfth century by a scribe – or perhaps two scribes – who used the round
                    English Caroline minuscule common there rather than the more pointed Norman
                    Caroline minuscule that came to prominence in England in the period immediately
                    following the Norman Conquest. Following the disillusionment of Bury St. Edmunds
                    in 1538, Pembroke 25 disappeared for a time, but it was given to Pembroke
                    College, Cambridge, at the end of the sixteenth century, and it still lives in
                    that library today. It has been well maintained, it is not damaged, and the
                    script is clear and easy to decipher.</p><p>For an edition of this sort, a single text from a single manuscript, the encoding
                    requirements are relatively simple. This manuscript is purely textual, not
                    illustrated or illuminated in any way, but we are noting all abbreviations and
                    distinctive paleographical aspects in the manuscript (including scribal
                    emendations), as well as marginalia. The TEI Header contains some descriptive
                    information, notably a descriptive list of all abbreviation types that are
                    linked to the individual abbreviations throughout the project. We are using the
                    EPPT for the text-image linking in this project, and I will give a brief
                    demonstration of the project as it stands at the time of the conference.</p><p>The <emph>Electronic Aelfric</emph> , directed by Aaron Kleist at Biola
                    University and developed by a large group of collaborators, seeks to edit eight
                    Old English homilies by Ælfric of Eynsham, who was arguably the most educated
                    and prolific writer of tenth century England. These homilies cover the period
                    from Easter to Pentecost, and trace their development through six phases of
                    authorial revision and then through nearly 200 years of transmission following
                    Ælfric’s death: twenty-four sets of readings or strands of textual tradition
                    found in twenty-eight manuscripts produced in at least five scriptoria between
                    990 and 1200.</p><p>The contrast between the <emph>Electronic Aelfric</emph> and Pembroke 25 is
                    great: while Pembroke 25 is one manuscript, the <emph>Electronic Aelfric</emph>
                    draws from twenty-eight manuscripts. Although no single homily out of the eight
                    occurs in more than ten of these manuscripts, it is still a great number of
                    textual variants to deal with. In addition to the text, the project also needs
                    to address the individual manuscripts – six of which are from the infamous
                    Cotton Collection (now housed in the British Library), damaged by fire in 1731.
                    Those manuscripts that are not damaged still have singularities, such as
                    marginalia, that we also wish to encode and link to image. We are using the EPPT
                    for this project, partnered with the TEI Apparatus tags, to bring together the
                    text and images of several different manuscripts. I will show examples of
                    corresponding manuscript pages, as well as sample code illustrating multiple
                    variants partnered with image-text linking.</p></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Carlquist, Jonas">Jonas Carlquist</name></author><title level="a">"Medieval Manuscripts, Hypertext and Reading. Visions
                                of Digital Editions</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">19.1</biblScope><date value="2004">2004</date><biblScope type="pages">105-118</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Cross, James E.">James E. Cross</name></author><title level="m">Cambridge Pembroke College MS. 25: A Carolingian
                                Sermonary Used by Anglo-Saxon Preachers</title><title level="s">King’s College London Medieval Studies, 1</title><imprint><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>King's College</publisher><date value="">1987</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Dué, Casey">Casey Dué</name></author><author><name reg="Ebbott, Mary">Mary Ebbott </name></author><title level="a">As Many Homers As You Please: an On-line Multitext of
                                Homer</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Classics @</title><imprint><date value="2004">2004</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://classics.furman.edu/classicsAt2/due-ebbott_2004_all.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Godden, Malcolm">Malcolm Godden</name></author><title level="m">Aelfric’s Catholic Homilies: Introduction, Commentary
                                and Glossary</title><imprint><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>Published for the Early English Text Society by the
                                    Oxford University Press</publisher><date value="2000">2000</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Kiernan, Kevin">Kevin Kiernan</name></author><author><name reg="Seales, W. Brent">W. Brent Seales</name></author><author><name reg="Griffioen, James">James Griffioen</name></author><title level="a">The Reappearances of St. Basil the Great in British
                                Library MS Cotton Otho B. x</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">36.1</biblScope><date value="2002">2002</date><biblScope type="pages">7-26</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Kiernan, Kevin">Kevin Kiernan</name></author><title level="a">Digital Facsimiles in Editing: Some Guidelines for
                                Editors of Image-based Scholarly Editions</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Electronic Textual Editing</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Burnard, Lou">Lou Burnard</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="O’Brien O’Keeffe, Katherine">, Katherine O’Brien O’Keeffe
                                </name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Unsworth, John">John Unsworth</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>Modern Language Association</publisher><date value="2005">2005</date></imprint></monogr><note>preprint at <xptr to="http://www.tei-c.org/Activities/ETE/Preview/kiernan.xml" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Kiernan, Kevin">Kevin Kiernan</name></author><author><name reg="Jaromczyk, Jerzy W.">Jerzy W. Jaromczyk</name></author><author><name reg="Dekhtyar, Alex">Alex Dekhtyar</name></author><author><name reg="Porter, Dorothy Carr">Dorothy Carr Porter</name></author><respStmt><resp>with</resp><name reg="Hawley, Kenneth">Kenneth Hawley</name><name reg="Bodapati, Sandeep">Sandeep Bodapati</name><name reg="Iacob, Ionut Emil">and Ionut Emil Iacob</name></respStmt><title level="a">The ARCHway Project: Architecture for Research in
                                Computing for Humanities through Research, Teaching, and
                            Learning</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">20 (Suppl 1)</biblScope><date value="2005">2005</date><biblScope type="pages">69-88</biblScope></imprint></monogr><note>doi:10.1093/llc/fqi018</note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Kirschenbaum, Matthew G.">Matthew G. Kirschenbaum</name></author><title level="a">Editor's Introduction: Image-based Humanities Computing</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">36.1</biblScope><date value="2002">2002</date><biblScope type="pages">3-6</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Lecolinet, Eric">Eric Lecolinet</name></author><author><name reg="Robert, Laurent">Laurent Robert</name></author><author><name reg="Role, Francois">Francois Role</name></author><title level="a">Text-image Coupling for Editing Literary Sources</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">36.1</biblScope><date value="2002">2002</date><biblScope type="pages">. 49-73</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>