<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="paper_251_wulfman"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Abbey Inside the Machine: The MonArch Project</title><author><name reg="Wulfman, Clifford Edward">Clifford Edward Wulfman</name></author><author><name reg="Mylonas, Elli">Elli Mylonas</name></author><author><name reg="Loyer, Anne">Anne Loyer</name></author><author><name reg="Bonde, Sheila">Sheila Bonde</name></author><author><name reg="Maines, Clark">Clark Maines</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>paper</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>archaeology</item><item>rhetoric</item><item>modelling</item><item>xml</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Clifford Edward Wulfman's xml <date value="2007-04">April
                        2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="The Abbey Inside the Machine: The MonArch Project"><titlePart type="main">The Abbey Inside the Machine: The MonArch Project</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Wulfman, Clifford Edward">Clifford Edward Wulfman</name><address><addrLine>Clifford_Wulfman@brown.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Brown University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Mylonas, Elli">Elli Mylonas</name><address><addrLine>elli_mylonas@brown.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Brown University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Loyer, Anne">Anne Loyer</name><address><addrLine/></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Wesleyan University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Bonde, Sheila">Sheila Bonde</name><address><addrLine/></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Brown University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Maines, Clark">Clark Maines</name><address><addrLine/></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Wesleyan University</titlePart></front><body><div0><head>Description of Project</head><p>MonArch (The Monastic Archaeology Project) is a collaborative project based on
                    the excavations at the Abbey of Saint-Jean-des-Vignes in Soissons, France under
                    the joint directorship of Sheila Bonde (Brown University) and Clark Maines
                    (Wesleyan University). The monastery at St.-Jean-des-Vignes remains with us
                    today in two media: in the physical remains of the abbey and in the textual
                    remains left behind by its inhabitants. The most significant of the latter are
                    the community's Customary, which describes the roles and activities of the
                    abbey's inhabitants over the course of the religious year, and the Abbey's
                    Obituary, which lists, by month and day of death, the members of the monastic
                    community and laics who had provided service or gifts to the monastery, with a
                    description of their donations.</p><p>Two websites have been developed as part of the MonArch Project. The first was
                    implemented at Wesleyan (<xptr to="http://www.wesleyan.edu/monarch/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>), and provides thorough documentation of the excavations,
                    annual field reports, and inventories of finds. The second, which is the focus
                    of this paper, is a research effort in its own right, one that explores the ways
                    in which encoded representations of archaeological data may be used enhance
                    their use. The often complex interrelationships among textual, architectural,
                    and archaeological evidence are difficult to represent and explicate in
                    traditional formats; the work described here attempts to use digital
                    representations to create a new form of scholarly expression.</p></div0><div0><head>Research Questions</head><p>MonArch has always focused beyond a simple description of concrete artifacts to a
                    thoroughgoing investigation and elaboration of a concept: from the outset, the
                    project was conceived as a multi-disciplinary endeavor that took
                        <emph>monasticism</emph> rather than the monastery as its object of
                        study.<note n="1">Sheila Bonde and Clark Maines, <title level="m">
                            Saint-Jean-des-Vignes in Soissons: Approaches to its Architecture,
                            Archaeology and History</title>, <title level="s"> Biblioteca Victorina
                            vol. XV</title> (Turnhout: Brepols Press, 2003).</note> Therefore, to
                    the extent that its digital manifestation is to be a direct reflection of the
                    project's aims, it too must take as its focus an abstraction and not a
                    collection of materials.</p><p>Such a focus makes designing the digital reflection more challenging. It cannot
                    be a simple linked, digital collection, because such an organization would put
                    undue emphasis on the monastery and its artifacts. And because the site needs to
                    be built around concepts and questions — about monasticism and the archaeology
                    of monasticism — the digital project cannot be conceived or designed without
                    considerable knowledge of those concepts or an understanding of medieval social,
                    economic, architectural, and religious history and the role of archaeology in
                    elucidating it all. It must, in other words, express the <emph>archaeological
                        definition of monasticism</emph> Bonde and Maines are deriving from their
                    work, a definition that is based on the following factors: <list type="unordered"><item>The monastic complex as the physical expression of spiritual, social,
                            and economic motives;</item><item>The functions of the abbey's structures;</item><item>The <foreign rend="italic">communitas</foreign> who used these
                            structures and the routine of their lives;</item><item>The economy of the surrounding region — the farms, mills, priories,
                            parishes, and other holdings that constituted the abbey's domain;</item><item>The place of the abbey (defined as both buildings and community) in
                            the local, regional, and inter-regional networks of power and influence;</item><item>The way these phenomena changed over time.</item></list></p><p>The relationship of the texts — both primary and secondary — to the
                    archaeological data is complex, because the archaeological material supports and
                    illustrates the texts at the same time that the texts contextualize the
                    archaeology and architecture. These two kinds of remains — &#128;&#148; the textual and
                    the physical — become two inter-referential and mutually reinforcing centers
                    from which the concepts of monasticism emerge. The research focus of the current
                    digital project is on designing an infrastructure and and an interactive
                    interface that simultaneously represent the authors' arguments and allow users
                    of the site to form their own interpretations.</p></div0><div0><head>Considering Use</head><p>We argue that it is most fruitful to conceive the digital manifestation of the
                    MonArch project as a <emph>reading</emph>. Insofar as its goal is to provide a
                    definition, the resource is fundamentally rhetorical: it has an argument, and it
                    supports its claims with evidence drawn from a variety of evidential sources.
                    That argument, generally stated, entails an archaeological definition of
                    monasticism, whose refinement is the ongoing and iterative task of the MonArch
                    project. The task of the digital resource, therefore, must be unusually subtle:
                    it must express this archaeological definition through an intricate blend of
                    textual and material evidence, and it must provide a way for readers to interact
                    with and question the argument and its claims.</p><p>In fact, insofar as the digital resource is the manifestation of this argument,
                    the mutually referential presence of both encoded texts and artefactual
                    simulacra constitutes a claim in itself, a claim that a
                    <soCalled>definition</soCalled> of monasticism can be manufactured through a
                    reading of monastic text, monastic space, and monastic time, and perhaps only in
                    this way. That is to say, the boundaries established by the site (and here the
                    web site and the excavation site perhaps begin themselves to lose their
                    boundaries) determine how monasticism is to be understood.</p></div0><div0><head>Research Goals</head><p> Our research, then, is focused on establishing a layered set of
                    <emph>models</emph> that enable researchers to articulate their understanding of
                    monasticism and allow scholars (students, readers, users) to interact with that
                    understanding. Underlying the whole project is a fundamental data model that
                    represents the characteristics of the texts, spaces, buildings and artifacts
                    that form the object of study. Overlaying the data model is another model, that
                    of the relationships that embody the intellectual connections that the
                    researchers have made as they work over their materials and which embody their
                    definition of monasticism. These connections are the evidence for their claims.
                    At the topmost layer is a model of user interaction, one consisting of visual
                    juxtapositions that illustrate the relationships among the historical evidence
                    and that enable further questioning. </p><p>The problem of structuring information in order to enhance argument is part of a
                    larger problem. One of the major powers promised by digital resources is the
                    instantiation of the kind of textuality envisioned by postmodern theorists like
                    Roland Barthes and Jacques Derrida, among others: the simultaneous availability
                    of vast amounts of information in a form that makes the interconnections, both
                    explicit and implicit, traversable. Yet benightedness is a clear danger: it is
                    all too easy to become lost: in <soCalled>hyperspace,</soCalled> in the library,
                    in the labyrinth, or in the wood of error. As digital resources grow in size and
                    complexity, the need for prospects — lookouts, overviews of the textscape —
                    becomes ever greater. Digital resources must therefore become responsive: when a
                    reader examines an argument or claim in a digital publication, the resource
                    should respond to her, helpfully putting on the virtual desk before her
                    materials that are relevant to her evolving inquiry. Thus, in loftiest terms,
                    our goal must be to assist, supplement, and augment a human agent&#128;&#153;'s
                    investigation of accumulated cultural knowledge, a goal congruent with the aims
                    of research over the past half-century in fields from information retrieval to
                    artificial intelligence.</p></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><monogr><title level="u"><name reg="The Abbey of St.-Jean-des-Vignes">The Abbey of
                                    St.-Jean-des-Vignes</name></title><imprint/></monogr><note><xptr to="http://dev.stg.brown.edu/projects/Monarch/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><title level="u"><name reg="Monarch. Monastic Archaeology Project">Monarch. Monastic
                                    Archaeology Project</name></title><imprint/></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.wesleyan.edu/monarch/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Bernstein, Mark">Mark Bernstein</name></author><author><name reg="Bolter, J. David">J. David Bolter</name></author><author><name reg="Joyce, Michael">Michael Joyce</name></author><author><name reg="Mylonas, Elli">Elli Mylonas</name></author><title level="a">Architectures for Volatile Hypertexts</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Hypertext '91 Proceedings</title><imprint><pubPlace>San Antonio, TX</pubPlace><publisher>Association for Computing Machinery</publisher><date value="1991">1991</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Bonde, Sheila">Sheila Bonde</name></author><author><name reg="Maines, Clark">Clark Maines</name></author><title level="a">The Archaeology of Monasticism, Ten Years of Work at
                                the Augustinian Abbey of Saint-Jean-des-Vignes, Soissons</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Medieval Europe, 1992 (Pre-printed Papers of the
                                Conference on Medieval Archaeology in Europe, York, 21-24.IX.1992)</title><imprint><pubPlace>York</pubPlace><biblScope type="vol">8</biblScope><date value="1992">1992</date><biblScope type="pages">83-88</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Bonde, Sheila">Sheila Bonde</name></author><author><name reg="Maines, Clark">Clark Maines</name></author><title level="m">Saint-Jean-des-Vignes: Approaches to its Architecture,
                                Archaeology and History</title><title level="s">Biblioteca Victorina vol. XV</title><imprint><pubPlace>Turnhout</pubPlace><publisher>Brepols Press</publisher><date value=" 2003">2003</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg=" McCarty, Willard"/></author><title level="m">Humanities Computing</title><imprint><pubPlace>Basingstoke</pubPlace><publisher>Palgrave McMillan</publisher><date value="2005">2005</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Unsworth, John">John Unsworth</name></author><title level="a">What is Humanities Computing and What Is Not?</title></analytic><monogr><imprint/></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.computerphilologie.uni-muenchen.de/jg02/unsworth.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><title level="a">The Rhetoric of Performative Markup</title><respStmt><resp>Organized by</resp><name reg="Flanders, Julia">Julia Flanders</name></respStmt><author><name reg="Wulfman, Clifford">Clifford Wulfman</name></author><title level="a">The Rhetoric of Digital Structure</title><author><name reg="Flanders, Julia">Julia Flanders</name></author><title level="a">The Rhetoric of Performative Markup</title><author><name reg="Mylonas, Elli">Elli Mylonas</name></author><title level="a">The Rhetoric of Performative Markup</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Digital Humanities 2006 Conference Abstracts</title><imprint><pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace><publisher>CATI, Université Paris-Sorbonne</publisher><date value="2006">2006</date><biblScope type="pages">248-251</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>