<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="paper_168_terras"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Researching e-Science Analysis of Census Holdings: The ReACH project</title><author><name reg="Terras, Melissa">Melissa Terras</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>paper</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>history</item><item>census</item><item>e-science</item><item>high performance computing</item><item>database analysis</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Melissa Terras's doc <date value="2007-04">April
                2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Researching e-Science Analysis of Census Holdings: The ReACH project"><titlePart type="main">Researching e-Science Analysis of Census Holdings: The ReACH
                    project</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Terras, Melissa">Melissa Terras</name><address><addrLine>m.terras@ucl.ac.uk</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">School of Library, Archive and Information
                Studies<lb/>University College London</titlePart></front><body><div0><p>e-Science technologies have the potential to enable large-scale datasets to be
                    searched analysed, and shared quickly, efficiently, and in complex and novel
                    ways. So far, little application has been made of the processing power of grid
                    technologies to humanities data, due to lack of available large scale datasets
                    which would warrant such high performance computing, and little understanding of
                    or access to e-Science technologies. The ReACH workshop series, funded by the
                    UK’s Arts and Humanities Research Council, was established in June 2006 at
                    University College London to investigate the potential application of e-Science
                    and high performance computing technologies to a large dataset of interest to
                    historians, humanists, digital consumers, and the general public: historical
                    census records.</p><p>The ReACH series consisted of various workshops undertaken over the summer of
                    2006 to investigate the academic, technical, and managerial aspects that would
                    have to be taken into account in order to set up a large scale project which
                    would utilise UCL’s high performance computing facilities to analyse large scale
                    historical census datasets from the UK’s National Archives, in conjunction with
                    the genealogy firm, Ancestry. By undertaking a scoping study in this manner, it
                    was hoped to determine the academic merits of such a proposal: it may be
                    feasible to undertake this analysis, but would it be useful to historical
                    researchers? What would the analysis do? What would the technical implementation
                    of such a project involve? What staffing and funding costs would be required?
                    The workshop series featured input from various project partners, and
                    interdisciplinary experts, to ascertain whether a full scale project would be
                    worthwhile to undertake. Moreover, the workshop series aimed to ascertain if and
                    how e-Science (defined as “a specific set of advanced technologies for Internet
                    resource-sharing and collaboration: so-called grid technologies, and
                    technologies integrated with them, for instance for authentication, data-mining
                    and visualization. (AHRC ICT 2006)”) can be applied to the arts and humanities.</p><p>Public interest in historical census data is phenomenal, as the overwhelming
                    response to mounting the 1901 census online at The National Archives
                    demonstrates (Inman, 2002). Yet the data is also much used for research by
                    historians (see Higgs 2005 for an introduction). There are many versions of
                    historical census datasets available, covering a variety of aspect of the
                    census, and digitised census records are one of the largest digital datasets
                    available in arts and humanities research. In the Arts and Humanities Data
                    Service repository collection alone there are currently 155 datasets pertaining
                    to historical census data (from the UK and abroad) created for research purposes
                    (AHDS 2006). Commercial firms dealing (or having dealt) in genealogy information
                    (such as Ancestry<note n="1"><xptr to="http://www.ancestry.com/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note>, Genes Re-united<note n="2"><xptr to="http://www.genesreunited.co.uk/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note>, QinetiQ <note n="3"><xptr to="http://www.qinetiq.com/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note>, British Origins<note n="4"><xptr to=" http://www.origins.net/BOWelcome.aspx" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note>, The Genealogist<note n="5"><xptr to="http://www.thegenealogist.co.uk/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note>, and 1837Online<note n="6"><xptr to="http://www.1837online.com/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note> ) have digitised vast swathes of historical census material (although to
                    varying degrees of completeness and accuracy). There is much interest from the
                    historical community in using this emerging data for research, and developing
                    tools and computational architectures which can aid historians in analysing this
                    complex data (see Crocket, Jones and Schürer (2006) for an advanced proposal
                    regarding the creation of a longitudinal database of English individuals and
                    households from 1851 to 1901, see also the work of the North Atlantic Population
                        Project<note n="7"><xptr to="http://www.nappdata.org/napp/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note>). However, there have been few opportunities for the application of high
                    performance computing to utilise large scale processing power in the analysis of
                    historical census material, especially analysing data across the spectrum of
                    census years available in the UK (7 different censuses taken at 10 year
                    intervals from 1841-1901). Although certain digitized datasets of the UK census
                    are in the public domain (1881<note n="8">The 1881 Census for England and Wales,
                        the Channel Islands and the Isle of Man (Enhanced Version) was deposited in
                        the Arts and Humanities Data Service repository by K. Schürer (University of
                        Essex. Department of History) in 2000, and is available from <xptr to="http://www.ahds.ac.uk/catalogue/collection.htm?uri=hist-4177-1" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note>) most were digitized by commercial
                    companies and are unavailable to the academic researcher. Most historians do not
                    have access to, or do not know how to use, high performance computing
                    facilities. </p><p>The aim of the ReACH series was to bring together disparate expertise in
                    Computing Science, Archives, Genealogy, History, and Humanities Computing, to
                    discuss how e-science scale techniques could be applied to be of use in the
                    historical research community. The project partners each brought various
                    expertise and input to the project: <list type="unordered"><item>UCL School of Library, Archives and Information Studies<note n="9"><xptr to="http://www.slais.ucl.ac.uk/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note>, who have expertise in digital humanities and advanced
                            computational techniques, as well as digital records management,</item><item>The National Archives<note n="10"><xptr to="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/                             " from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note>, who select, preserve and provide access to, and advice on,
                            historical records, e.g. the censuses of England and Wales 1841-1901
                            (and also the Isle of Man, Channel Islands and Royal Navy censuses)</item><item>Ancestry.co.uk<note n="11"><xptr to="http://www.ancestry.co.uk/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note>, who own a massive dataset of census holdings worldwide, and who
                            have digitized the censuses of England and Wales under license from The
                            National Archives. The input of Ancestry was central to this research to
                            gain access to the complete range of UK census years in digital format. </item><item>UCL Research Computing<note n="12"><xptr to="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/research-computing/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note>, the UK's Centre for Excellence in networked computing, who have
                            extensive high performance computing facilities available for use in
                            research. </item></list></p><p>The project aimed to investigate the reuse of pre-digitised census data:
                    presuming there was not funding available to be in the business of digitisation
                    of other record data for any pilot project. The project also wished to
                    investigate the use of commercial datasets (as many of the large census data
                    sets are owned by commercial firms: in this case, Ancestry), and the licensing
                    and managerial issues this would raise for future projects. The project also
                    wanted to establish how feasible, and indeed useful, undertaking such an
                    analysis of historical census data would be.</p><p>The results of the well attended workshop series was a sketch for a potential
                    project, and recommendations regarding the implementation of e-science (high
                    performance computing) technologies in this area. However, at this time, it was
                    not thought possible to pursue the potential project at this time in the
                    following e-Science call which emanated from the AHRC in October 2006 due to a
                    variety of reasons which are elucidated in this paper. Reasons for not taking
                    the project forward at this time were not technical or managerial, but
                    historical: it will be a few years before all the digitized data required to
                    make this project a success will be available (or be of high enough quality, see
                    Holmes 2006). Nevertheless, the scoping nature of this project did highlight
                    interesting aspects of the application of high performance computing to
                    humanities data: discussing the nature, size and quality of humanities datasets
                    (as opposed to scientific datasets), and managerial and technical expertise in
                    data management, security, and licensing. Importantly, the nature of working
                    with a commercial company on their sensitive data was also explored from a legal
                    aspect, highlighting issues regarding use and reuse of digital data for the arts
                    and humanities: who “owns” resulting datasets from collaborative projects?</p><p>This paper describes the methodology of the workshops, reporting on suggestions
                    made during the series regarding potential applications of high performance
                    computing which would benefit academic historians, sketching out a future
                    project regarding how historical census material can be analysed utilising high
                    performance computing, and extrapolates recommendations that can be applied in
                    general to the use of e-Science and high performance computing in the arts and
                    humanities research sectors.</p></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Arts and Humanities Data Service (AHDS)">Arts and Humanities Data Service (AHDS)</name></author><title level="u">Cross Search Catalogue</title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-10-31" to="http://www.ahds.ac.uk/catalogue/search.htm?nq=n&amp;q=census&amp;s=all&amp;coll=y&amp;item=y" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Arts and Humanities Research Council (AHRC)">Arts and Humanities Research Council (AHRC)</name></author><title level="u">e-Science, Backgound</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">AHRC ICT Programme Activities and Services</title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-11-13" to="http://www.ahrcict.rdg.ac.uk/activities/e-science/background.htm" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Crocket, A.">A. Crocket</name></author><author><name reg="Jones, C. E.">C. E. Jones</name></author><author><name reg="Schürer, K.">K. Schürer</name></author><title level="u">The Victorian Panel Study. Report Submitted to the ESRC (Award
                                Ref: RES-500-25-5001), May 2006</title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Higgs, Edward">Edward Higgs</name></author><title level="m">Making Sense of the Census Revisited: Census Records
                                for England and Wales 1801-1901: A Handbook for Historical
                                Researchers</title><imprint><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Institute of Historical Research</publisher><date value="2005">2005</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Holmes, R.">R. Holmes</name></author><title level="a">The Accuracy and Consistency of the Census Returns for
                                England 1841-1901 and their Indexes</title></analytic><monogr><edition>M.A. Dissertation</edition><imprint><publisher>School of Library, Archive and Information Studies,
                                    University College London</publisher><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Inman, Phillip">Phillip Inman</name></author><title level="a">Genealogy</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">The Guardian</title><imprint><date value="2002">Thursday September 26, 2002</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-11-03" to="http://www.guardian.co.uk/internetnews/story/0,,798781,00.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>