<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="paper_152_nowviskie"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Collex: Facets, Folksonomy, and Fashioning the Remixable Web</title><author><name reg="Nowviskie, Bethany">Bethany Nowviskie</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Field, Hana S.">Hana S. Field</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>paper</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>semantic web</item><item>faceted browsing</item><item>open archives</item><item>folksonomy</item><item>social bookmarking</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list><item>HSF: Created from Bethany Nowviskie's rtf<date value="2007-04">April
                    2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Collex: Facets, Folksonomy, and Fashioning the Remixable Web"><titlePart type="main">Collex: Facets, Folksonomy, and Fashioning the Remixable
                web</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Nowviskie, Bethany">Bethany Nowviskie</name><address><addrLine>bethany@virginia.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Applied Research in Patacriticism<lb/> University of
            Virginia</titlePart></front><body><div0><p>C<emph>ollex</emph> is an online toolset designed to aid students and scholars
                    working in networked archives and federated repositories of humanities
                    materials: a sophisticated <emph>COLL</emph>ections and <emph>EX</emph>hibits
                    mechanism for the semantic web. It allows users to search, browse, annotate, and
                    tag electronic objects and to repurpose them in illustrated, interlinked essays
                    or exhibits. By saving information about user activity (including the
                    construction of annotated collections and exhibits) as "remixable" metadata, the
                        <emph>Collex</emph> system writes current practice into the scholarly record
                    and permits knowledge discovery based not only on predefined characteristics or
                    "facets" of digital objects, but also on the contexts in which they are placed
                    by a community of scholars. Collex builds on the same semantic web technologies
                    that drive MIT's SIMILE project and social bookmarking systems like
                        <emph>Connotea</emph> and <emph>Zotero</emph>, but it also brings folksonomy
                    tagging to trusted, peer-reviewed scholarly archives and features an integrated
                    publication system. This exhibits-builder is analogous to high-end digital
                    "curation" tools currently affordable only to large institutions like the
                    Smithsonian. <emph>Collex</emph> is free, generalizable, and open source and is
                    presently being implemented in a large-scale pilot project under the auspices of
                    NINES.</p><p><emph>Collex</emph> is constructed with pragmatic scholarly needs in mind, and
                    under the assumption that "the general field of humanities education and
                    scholarship will not take the use of digital technology seriously until one
                    demonstrates how its tools improve the ways we explore and explain our cultural
                    inheritance – until, that is, they expand our interpretational procedures"
                    (McGann, Radiant <emph>Textuality</emph> xii; my emphasis). <emph>Collex</emph>
                    facilitates primary interpretive gestures of exploration and explanation in a
                    broad and socially-networked manner, and aims to form a locus for further
                    expansion of interpretive methods in digital humanities.</p><p>The first formal iteration of <emph>Collex</emph> (released in February 2007)
                    federates more than 60,000 digital objects of 19th-century literature, art,
                    culture and criticism from the most prominent and acclaimed online journals,
                    archives, and repositories in the field. This pilot project forms the core of
                    NINES, the <emph>Networked Infrastructure for Nineteenth-century Electronic
                        Scholarship</emph>, a trans-Atlantic federation of scholars and of
                    peer-reviewed primary and secondary materials constituting a federated
                    collective. Endorsed by the NINES steering committee and under development for
                    the past year at ARP, the University of Virginia's <emph>Applied Research in
                        Patacriticism</emph> lab, <emph>Collex</emph> is both the central
                    clearing-house for NINES and the interpretive hub around which we hope a vital
                    community of scholars and students will coalesce.</p><p>Humanists eager to develop new ways to integrate and explore digital works
                    currently lack crucial institutional and technical resources. Even the best
                    models that scholars of (for instance) nineteenth century literature and culture
                    now follow and imitate — the <emph>Whitman Archive, Romantic Circles</emph>, the
                        <emph>Rossetti Archive</emph>, the <emph>William Blake Archive</emph> — are
                    stand-alone projects that can only be loosely integrated through web browsers,
                    even when shared through OAI protocols. As a consequence, what you see now on
                    the web is what you get: an agglomeration of sites and projects whose content is
                    atomized and whose scholarly and educational value is indeterminate. While it is
                    possible for tech-savvy scholars, using ad-hoc tools and methods, to produce and
                    distribute annotated, re-organized, or selected versions of existing online
                    resources, they presently lack coordination within a peer-reviewed digital
                    publishing environment. Because of this, their productions — personal web pages
                    and online course packets — are difficult to maintain, are not readily
                    interoperable or standards-compliant, and are easily dismissed as heterogeneous
                    grab-bags of links. NINES was founded to work against this debilitating
                    situation.</p><p>The inherent complexity of available resources is a further obstacle to the
                    penetration digital humanities into the disciplines. <emph>Collex</emph> is
                    designed to aid humanities scholars doing research in complex digital
                    collections like the <emph>Rossetti Archive</emph>(its initial test case) or
                    within federated research environments like NINES. Such environments often
                    stymie their users through the sheer quantity of information made available to
                    them in top-level tables of contents, sitemaps, and idiosyncratic search
                    engines. Our tool operates under the assumption that the best paths through a
                    complex digital resource are those forged by use and interpretation. A
                        <emph>Collex</emph> approach works to assist scholars in recording, sharing,
                    and building on the interpretive purposes to which they put their online
                    teaching and research environments.</p><p><emph>Collex</emph> uses semantic web principles and technologies to explore and
                    develop the research potential of the digital scholarship aggregated in NINES.
                    Two critical concepts embodied in a NINES environment shaped by the
                    <emph>Collex</emph> application fall under the rubrics widely known as "faceted
                    classification" and "folksonomy." Facets and folksonomies structure an approach
                    to descriptive metadata. They generate an evolving interface between the
                    fully-integrated peer-reviewed electronic resources that constitute NINES and
                    the user communities that re-imagine NINES content through interpretation,
                    contextualization, and critical and creative re-fashioning.</p><p>"Full integration" means that each of our NINES-participating resources has
                    contributed a package of metadata representing all of the digital objects they
                    wish to make browseable, collectible, and available to users for re-purposing
                    within <emph>Collex</emph>. An important innovation of <emph>Collex</emph> lies
                    in the way these objects are defined by their contributing editors.
                    <emph>Collex</emph> uses a Dublin Core flavor of RDF, the "resource description
                    framework" of the semantic web, to define collectible "objects" without limiting
                    them to their expression as web pages. Where other social bookmarking tools are
                    designed to allow collection and annotation of whole web pages,
                    <emph>Collex</emph> allows contributors of resources to make finer-grained
                    distinctions, and users of the system to build collections and exhibits more
                    attuned to the patterns of attention in humanities scholarship.</p><p>A clear example of interpretive modeling through object definition is the
                        <emph>Collex</emph>representation of a book of poetry in the Rossetti
                    Archive. Using XSLT transformations, we have created RDF metadata for
                    intellectual and material objects at differing levels in this book. One RDF
                    object (typed as a secondary resource, with supplemental genre and date
                    identifiers) expresses the editor's commentary on the book as a concept. Another
                    object, also articulated in metadata, expresses one particular edition of the
                    book. Within that high-level expression, each page of the book has been shared
                    with <emph>Collex</emph>users as a collectible object, as has each poem on each
                    page. Such fine disambiguation ensures that <emph>Collex</emph> users can
                    locate, annotate, and exhibit objects specifically suited to the scholarship
                    they wish to perform – whether their attention is focused on bibliographic,
                    social, or textual matters. It also ensures that archive maintainers have the
                    fullest control, in the <emph>Collex</emph> environment, over the use of their
                    intellectual property and the artifacts they minister.</p><p>Because RDF objects share a common (and relatively simple) metadata scheme, they
                    are discoverable through "facets" in the <emph>Collex</emph> search and
                    faceted-browsing interface. Faceted classification is a non-hierarchical means
                    of expressing ontological relationships. Any given object will share a number of
                    facets with other objects – common dates, genres, authors, etc. Exposing these
                    facets makes it possible not only for users to manually "drill down" into
                    certain categories or explore lateral relationships, it also opens possibilities
                    for algorithmic serendipity in research. In other words, <emph>Collex</emph> can
                    exploit formally-expressed facets to offer more options and avenues to users
                    interested in a particular object: "more like this" – more objects in the
                    repository sharing one or more attributes with a researcher's subject of
                    attention. Even more interesting is the ability of <emph>Collex</emph> to record
                    and analyze user activity, and to translate the products of user interaction
                    into RDF objects within the system itself. In this way, in addition to "more
                    like this," <emph>Collex</emph> can suggest to recent collectors of a particular
                    object that they view the published collections and exhibits into which other
                    users have placed the object, or objects like it. Because this content can be
                    expressed as subscription-based RSS feeds, a web service, or an API, it is
                    possible for the maintainers of scholarly resources to patch into
                    <emph>Collex</emph> directly from their individual web page or listserv
                    interfaces, offering information about user annotations and re-mediations for
                    any given object without requiring users to visit <emph>Collex</emph> at all.</p><p>All <emph>Collex</emph> activity takes place within the ordinary web-browsing
                    environment that scholars presently use to access digital resources, and will
                    require nothing in the way of plugins or downloads. The overhead (in terms of
                    initial metadata production) for contributors of resources to the federated
                    collections in which <emph>Collex</emph> can operate has also been kept
                    purposely low, and is thoroughly compatible with Open Archives protocols. We
                    predict that both of these factors – combined with the strong endorsement and
                    example of NINES – will facilitate the adoption of <emph>Collex</emph> into
                    day-to-day practices of humanities scholars in networked research and publishing
                    environments.</p></div0><div0><head>Screenshots</head><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">paper_152_nowviskie_1.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>A Collex sidebar list view (user-collected objects in the "visual art" genre)
                        with the same constraint in the faceted browser</figDesc></figure><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">paper_152_nowviskie_2.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>A different constraints set, and a detail view of one object (for tagging,
                        annotation, and knowledge discovery) in the sidebar</figDesc></figure></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><analytic><title level="a">Access to the Literature: The Debate Continues</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Nature Web Focus</title><imprint><date value="2004">2004</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.nature.com/nature/focus/accessdebate/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Broughton, V.">V. Broughton</name></author><title level="a">Faceted Classification as a Basis for Knowledge
                                Organization in a Digital Environment; the Bliss Bibliographic
                                Classification and the Creation of Multi-Dimensional Knowledge
                                Structures</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">New Review of Hypermedia and Multimedia </title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">7</biblScope><date value="2001">2001</date><biblScope type="pages">67-102</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Golder, Scott">Scott Golder</name></author><author><name reg="Huberman, Bernardo">Bernardo Huberman</name></author><title level="a">The Structure of Collaborative Tagging Systems</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Information Dynamics Lab, HP Labs</title><imprint><date value="2005">2005</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.hpl.hp.com/research/idl/papers/tags/tags.pdf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Hammond, Tony">Tony Hammond</name></author><title level="a">Social Bookmarking Tools (I): A General
                            Overview</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">D-Lib Magazine</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol"/><date value="2005">April 2005</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="" to="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/april05/hammond/04hammond.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Lessig, Lawrence">Lawrence Lessig</name></author><title level="m">Free Culture</title><imprint/></monogr><note><xptr crdate="" to="http://www.free-culture.cc" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Lynch, Clifford A..">Clifford A. Lynch</name></author><title level="a">Institutional Repositories: Essential Infrastructure
                                for Scholarship in the Digital Age</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">ARL Bimonthly Report</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">226</biblScope><date value="2003">2003</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Mathes, Adam">Adam Mathes</name></author><title level="a">Folksonomies - Cooperative Classification and
                                Communication Through Shared Metadata</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Paper written for LIS590CMC Computer Mediated
                                Communication, Graduate School of Library and Information Science at
                                the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, December 2004</title><imprint><date value="2004">2004</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.adammathes.com/academic/computer-mediated-communication/folksonomies.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="McGann, Jerome">Jerome McGannl</name></author><title level="m">Radiant Textuality: Literature After the World Wide Web</title><imprint><publisher>Palgrave MacMillan</publisher><date value="2001">2001</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="McGann, Jerome">Jerome McGann</name></author><title level="a">Culture and Technology: The Way We Live Now, What is to
                                Be Done?</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Paper presented at the University of Chicago, April 23,
                                2004</title><imprint><date value="2004">2004</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="" to="http://www.nines.org/about/bibliog/mcgann-chicago.pdf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/> from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/&gt;</note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="MLA">MLA</name></author><title level="a">The Future of Scholarly Publishing: Report of the Ad
                                Hoc Committee on the Future of Scholarly Publishing</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Profession 2002</title><imprint><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>Modern Language Assocation of America</publisher><date value="2002">2002</date><biblScope type="pages">172-186</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Nowviskie, Bethany">Bethany Nowviskie</name></author><title level="m" type="WWW document">Collex: Semantic Collections and Exhibits for the remixable
                                Web
                            </title><imprint/></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.patacriticism.org/collex/about" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Nowviskie, Bethany">Bethany Nowviskie</name></author><author><name reg="McGann, Jerome">Jerome McGann</name></author><title level="m" type="WWW document">NINES: A Federated Model for
                                Integrating Digital Scholarship
                            </title><imprint/></monogr><note>White paper version available at
                            <xptr to="http://www.nines.org/about/9swhitepaper.pdf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Unsworth, John">John Unsworth</name></author><title level="a">Not-so-Modest Proposals: What Do We Want Our System of
                                Scholarly Communication to Look Like in 2010?</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Paper presented at the CIC Summit on Scholarly Communication, December 2,
                                2003</title><imprint><date value="2003">2003</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/~jmu2m/CICsummit.htm" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Unsworth, John">John Unsworth</name></author><title level="a">Tool Time, or 'Haven't We Been Here Already?' Ten
                                Years in Humanities Computing</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Paper presented at Transforming Disciplines: The Humanities and Computer
                                Science, NINCH conference, Washington, DC, January 18, 2003</title><imprint><date value="2003">2003</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/~jmu2m/carnegie-ninch.03.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Van de Sompel, H et. al.">H. Van de Sompel et. al.</name></author><title level="m">Rethinking Scholarly Communication: Building the System
                                that Scholars Deserve</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">D-Lib Magazine</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol"/><date value="2004">September 2004</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>