<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="paper_220_vanhoutte"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>A Descriptive Classification Generator for Electronic Editions</title><author><name reg="Vanhoutte, Edward">Edward Vanhoutte</name></author><author><name reg="Van den Branden, Ron">Ron Van den Branden</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                book</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>paper</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>electronic edition</item><item>classification</item><item>typology</item><item>modeling</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Edward Vanhoutte's txt <date value="2007-03">March
                    2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="A Descriptive Classification Generator for Electronic Editions"><titlePart type="main">A Descriptive Classification Generator for Electronic
                    Editions</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Vanhoutte, Edward">Edward Vanhoutte</name><address><addrLine>edward.vanhoutte@kantl.be</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Centre for Scholarly Editing and Document Studies<lb/>Royal
                Academy of Dutch Language and Literature</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Van den Branden, Ron">Ron Van den Branden</name><address><addrLine>ron.vandenbranden@kantl.be</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Centre for Scholarly Editing and Document Studies<lb/> Royal Academy of Dutch
                Language and Literature</titlePart></front><body><div0><head>Introduction</head><p>Electronic scholarly editions which mimick conventional models of scholarly
                    editions as prescribed by different theoretical and methodological schools
                    provide denotative models (Geertz, 1993, p. 93) which thrive on the otherness of
                    the digital medium but re-emphasize the computational aspect of the
                    'computer-based' (Steding, 2002), 'Computergestützte' (Kamzelak, 1999), or
                    computer-assisted scholarly edition. The isomorphism between the digital and the
                    print medium aimed at by the application of computational techniques to the
                    praxis of scholarly editing confirms what we already know. What is interesting,
                    however, is not the degree to which the computer can assist the editor in
                    digitizing, creating, and publishing an edition, but the intentional artefacts
                    which are built by using the computer as a modelling tool (Smith, 2002). They
                    are instrumental in two crucial activities of humanities research, that is, the
                    discovery of meaning and the making of meaning. As products of (experimental)
                    modelling, their purpose is 'to achieve failure so as to raise and point the
                    question of how we know what we know' (McCarty, 1999), 'what we do not know',
                    and 'to give us what we do not yet have.' (McCarty, 2004, p. 255) This paper
                    will address the role of experimental modelling and the assessment of exemplary
                    models of scholarly editions in the development of a useful classification,
                    typology, and description of electronic editions.</p></div0><div0><head>Classification</head><p>As psycholinguistic research has shown, categorization is innate in human
                    cognition (Giannakopoulou, 2003) and involves the formation and use of patterns
                    in a self-maximizing system (deBono, 1978, pp. 25-43). Operations which can be
                    classified under this scholarly primitive are naming, labelling, classifying,
                    cataloguing, indexing, sorting, etc. Categorizing as a mind process can result
                    in the production of formalized instruments such as bibliographies, indexes,
                    catalogues, classification schemes, and taxonomies for which advanced subject
                    analysis is needed. For the most part, however, it remains a culturally
                    determined mind tool particularly where it is used for the selection of
                    usefulness. This means that categorizing is not determined by how the world is,
                    but tries to develop convenient ways in which to represent it (Hacking, 1999, p.
                    33).</p></div0><div0><head>Traditions and Typologies</head><p>Textual scholarship is fragmented by the development of different theories,
                    methods, and praxes which are based on a diversity of attitudes and perspectives
                    (author, language, audience, function, format, etc.). This becomes especially
                    clear when studying current typologies and classification schemes for scholarly
                    editions. Heinrich Meyer (1992) surveyed the literature on textual scholarship
                    in Germany in the twentieth century and listed more than forty names for
                    different types of editions that were used. As he argued, the
                    'ausgabentypoligische Terminologiewirrwarr' (Meyer, 1992, p. 17) is the result
                    of a methodological pluralism both inside and across editorial traditions.</p><p>As a consequence, there is no one theoretical paradigm for textual scholarship
                    across all traditions, periods, languages, and authors and there is no one
                    universally applicable taxonomy of editorial types. Moreover, the existing
                    taxonomies are seldom internally consistent in their applied perspective. The
                    simplified representation in the German school, for instance, offers a taxonomy
                    which runs from the archive edition over the historical-critical edition to the
                    study and the reading edition (Kanzog, 1970, pp. 9-44). Where 'archive edition'
                    denotes the archival function of this type of edition and hints at the extent of
                    the documentary set presented, 'historical-critical' refers both to the method
                    used to create the edition and the format in which that edition comes before the
                    user. The study-edition and reading edition, on the other hand, identify the
                    envisioned function of the product and its intended audience in their naming. In
                    the Anglo-American tradition, the copy-text edition refers to a specific theory
                    of establishing a text whereas the types of scholarly editions David Greetham
                    mentions in his <title level="m">Textual Scholarship. An Introduction</title>
                    mainly refer to the format or appearance of the edition, such as 'parallel print
                    edition', 'variorum edition', or 'type facsimile edition', or to a combination
                    of format and method such as 'Eclectic Clear-Text Edition with Multiple
                    Apparatus'. (Greetham, 1994, p. 383)</p><p>The least useful typology of scholarly editions is based on the publication
                    medium. Here we have print edition, hybrid edition, and electronic edition.
                    Especially this last one is often presented as a meaningful class while it is
                    widely used to name almost anything which is available in an electronic format.
                    A sad example is, for instance, the édition électronique of the correspondence
                    of René Descartes which is nothing more than a 35 page MSWord file which has
                    been made available online <xptr to="http://classiques.uqac.ca/classiques/Descartes/correspondance/descartes_correspondance.doc" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/> . </p></div0><div0><head>Electronic editions</head><p>With respect to the classification of electronic editions, it becomes difficult
                    to maintain the application of conventional typologies and taxonomies, or ignore
                    them altogether. The danger of a normative typology and hence a rigid
                    theoretical frame for textual scholarship is that it establishes its principles
                    firmly without allowing the advancement of its theories, methodologies, and
                    practices. However, as a scholarly discipline, scholarly editing should be
                    interested in both. Especially when, in the case of electronic scholarly
                    editing, exemplary modeling is employed as a scholarly method to generate
                    electronic editions rather than the epigonuous application of rigid theory and
                    method to the electronic edition.</p></div0><div0><head>Classification Generator</head><p>For reasons of identification and bibliographic research on electronic editions
                    (Lavagnino, 1996; Dahlström, 2002; Kirschenbaum, 2002; Van der Weel, 2005),
                    there is a need for some integrated scheme by which editors of electronic
                    editions can describe their edition according to several parameters. With the
                    classification generator which we propose here, we believe we have developed a
                    tool which can be of aid to that purpose.</p><p>The classification generator is an on-line tool which allows the editor to input
                    the details of the electronic edition atomized in meta-information on the edited
                    text (language, period, genre) and information on the edition via a
                    user-friendly form. The latter minimally contains details about method, intended
                    audience, content, format, encoding, technology, function, and functionality of
                    the edition. Once the edition is described according to these parameters, a
                    descriptive classification code is generated that can be included in the
                    published edition. This classification code is an alphanumerical string that
                    exactly describes the electronic edition from multiple perspectives. The
                    classification generator serves at least three goals. First, it liberates the
                    field of electronic scholarly editing from the conventional text-editorial
                    theories with their rigid and inconsistent prescriptive typologies. Instead the
                    classification generator atomizes the different facets of the electronic edition
                    and presents the sum total of this documentation as a description of the
                    product. Second, the user confronted with an electronic edition gets a detailed
                    description of the kind of electronic edition one is using on inputting the
                    classification code in the classification generator. Third, the codes derived
                    from the classification generator can be of use for an (analytical) bibliography
                    of electronic editions. The description of an improved re-release of an
                    electronic edition will generate a different classification code which could be
                    collated against the codes of other releases of the same edition.</p><p>A last feature of the classification generator is the option to register an
                    edition's classification code together with a formal bibliographic description
                    in a database. This database will allow theorists of electronic scholarship and
                    bibliographers of new media to perform interesting forms of analysis on its
                    contents.</p></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Dahlström, Mats">Mats Dahlström</name></author><title level="a">Nya medier, gamla verktyg</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Human IT</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">6.4</biblScope><biblScope type="pages">71-116</biblScope></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.hb.se/bhs/ith/4-02/md.pdf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="deBono, Edward ">Edward deBono</name></author><title level="m">Lateral Thinking: A Textbook of Creativity</title><imprint><pubPlace>Harmondsworth</pubPlace><publisher>Peguin</publisher><date value="1978">1978</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Geertz, Clifford">Clifford Geertz</name></author><title level="m">The Interpretation of Cultures</title><imprint><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Fontana</publisher><date value="1993">1993</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Giannakopoulou, Anastasia">Anastasia
                                Giannakopoulou</name></author><title level="a">Prototype Theory: An Evaluation</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Ecloga Online Journal</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">3</biblScope><date value="2003">2003</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.strath.ac.uk/ecloga/Giannakopoulou.htm" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Greetham, D. C.">D. C. Greetham</name></author><title level="m">Textual Scholarship. An Introduction</title><imprint><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Garland Publishing</publisher><date value="1994">1994</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Hacking, Ian">Ian Hacking</name></author><title level="m">The Social Construction of What?</title><imprint><pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace><publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher><date value="1999">1999</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><editor role="editor"><name reg="Kamzelak, Roland">Roland Kamzelak</name></editor><title level="m">Computergestützte Text-Edition</title><title level="s">Beihefte zu Edition, 12</title><imprint><pubPlace>Tübingen</pubPlace><publisher>Niemeyer</publisher><date value="1999">1999</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Kanzog, Klaus ">Klaus Kanzog</name></author><title level="m">Prolegomena zu einer historisch-kritischen Ausgabe der
                                Werke Heinrich von Kleists. Theorie und Praxis einer modernen
                                Klassiker-Edition</title><imprint><pubPlace>München</pubPlace><publisher>Carl Hanser Verlag</publisher><date value="1970">1970</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Kirschenbaum, Matthew G.">Matthew G. Kirschenbaum</name></author><title level="a">Editing the Interface: Textual Studies and First
                                Generation Electronic Objects</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">TEXT: An Interdisciplinary Annual of Textual Studies</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">14</biblScope><date value="2002">2002</date><biblScope type="pages">15-51</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Lavagnino, John ">John Lavagnino</name></author><title level="a">The Analytical Bibliography of Electronic Texts</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Paper presented at ALLC/ACH 1996, Bergen, Norway, June
                                25, 1996</title><imprint><date value="1996">1996</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="McCarty, Willard">Willard McCarty</name></author><title level="a">Humanities Computing as Interdiscipline</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">A seminar in the series "Is Humanities Computing an
                                Academic Discipline?", held under the auspices of the Institute for
                                Advanced Technology in the Humanities (IATH), at the University of
                                Virginia, Guy Fawkes Day 1999</title><imprint><date value="1999">1999</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://ilex.cc.kcl.ac.uk/wlm/essays/inter/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note><note><xptr to="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/hcs/mccarty.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="McCarty, Willard">Willard McCarty</name></author><title level="a">Modeling: A Study in Words and Meanings</title></analytic><monogr><editor role="editor"><name reg="Schreibman, Susan">Susan Schreibman</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Siemens, Ray">Ray Siemens</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Unsworth, John">John Unsworth</name></editor><title level="m">A Companion to the Digital Humanities</title><imprint><pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace><publisher>Blackwell Publishing Ltd</publisher><date value="2004">2004</date><biblScope type="pages">254-70</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Smith, Brian Cantwell">Brian Cantwell Smith</name></author><title level="a">The Foundations of Computing</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Computationalism: New Directions</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Scheutz, Matthias">Matthias Scheutz</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace><publisher>MIT Press</publisher><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.jhfc.duke.edu/jenkins/courses/p256/readings/p256foc.pdf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Steding, Sören A.">Sören A. Steding</name></author><title level="m">Computer-Based Scholarly Editions: Context - Concept -
                                Creation - Clientele</title><imprint><pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace><publisher>Logos Verlag</publisher><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Van der Weel, Adriaan">Adriaan Van der Weel</name></author><title level="a">Bibliography for the New Media</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Qaerendo</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">35.1-2</biblScope><date value="2005">2005</date><biblScope type="96-108">96-108</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>