<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="paper_252_renear.xml"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Modeling, Explanation, and Ontology in the Cultural Sciences</title><author><name reg="Renear, Allen H.">Allen H. Renear</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>paper</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>modeling</item><item>explanation</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Allen H. Renear's doc<date value="2007-03">March
                2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Modeling, Explanation, and Ontology in the Cultural Sciences"><titlePart type="main">Modeling, Explanation, and Ontology in the Cultural
                Sciences</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Renear, Allen H.">Allen H. Renear</name><address><addrLine>renear@uiuc.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Graduate School of Library and Information Science,
                <lb/>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</titlePart></front><body><div0><head>Abstract</head><p>Humanities computing must make <emph>conceptual modeling</emph> one of its
                    defining activities. This is necessary not only to provide more effective
                    computational support for scholarship in the humanities, but also in order for
                    humanities computing itself to become something more than a “bag of tricks”.
                    This paper describes promising developments already underway in several areas
                    within humanities computing, generalizes from past, if partial, successes (text
                    encoding), draws parallels with recent work in bioinformatics, and argues that
                    the logical identity of conceptual modeling and theory-construction makes
                    conceptual modeling simply a computationally oriented variant of scientific
                    explanation, and, more broadly, interpretation and understanding in general. As
                    an example of how model development can provide fundamental insights into the
                    cultural world a case is described where a set of ontology evaluation criteria
                    developed within computer science is applied to an influential framework for
                    cultural entities and the result that a radical reconfiguration of that
                    framework is suggested.</p><p><emph>Acknowledgements</emph>: There is undoubtedly much here that is influenced
                    by seminal papers on these issues by Willard McCarty and John Unsworth; I
                    acknowledge a debt to them without of course any suggestion that they see things
                    as described here.</p></div0><div0><head>Introduction</head><p>The nature of humanities computing has long been problematic in the digital
                    humanities community. Part of the reason for this anxiety is that humanities
                    computing is struggling to move out of a pre-scientific phase. “Science” here is
                    of course intended to be taken in the broadest possible sense — the point is not
                    to separate disciplines such as physics on the one hand from, say, literary
                    studies on the other, but rather to distinguish practices that have primarily
                    non-epistemic non-theoretical objectives from those that have understanding,
                    explanation, and knowledge as their principal immediate goals. Nor is there any
                    implication of a clear boundary between scientific practices and non-scientific
                    practices, or that there isn’t a complex and essential mutual involvement — the
                    claim is only that some rough distinction of this sort is possible and useful.</p><p>If humanities computing is to mature as a coherent field of intellectual inquiry
                    it will need to make a transition from being an <emph>ad hoc</emph> set of
                    useful techniques, to more systematic general methods and theories that make
                    direct contact with the specific methods and theories of the disciplines it
                    supports. This theme is not new, but our progress has been modest so far and
                    some further discussion and elaboration is in order.</p><p>First, there are new reasons to be optimistic. For one thing this progress is
                    already occurring in other informatics fields—bioinformatics as an example—and
                    the specifics of these changes provide an indication of how things might go in
                    humanities computing as well. Moreover the growing significance of conceptual
                    models and ontologies that is already in evidence in humanities computing, and
                    the nature of the discourse around them, is a sign that this transition is
                    perhaps already underway. Finally one of the most theoretically productive areas
                    within the humanities computing community, namely text encoding, arguably has
                    been as successful as it has precisely to the extent that it has embodied the
                    features recommended here — and owes its limitations and disappointments to the
                    extent to which it has not. What all these things have in common is the
                    foregrounding of conceptual modeling, explicitly or implicitly.</p><p>I use the term “conceptual modeling” broadly, meaning any formally defined
                    abstract representation of a domain of interest. Typical examples of modeling
                    languages are the ER and UML diagrams used in business applications, logic-based
                    knowledge representation formalisms such as description logics or the frame
                    languages (such as the KL-ONE family) common in artificial intelligence, and the
                    various formal ontologies now used in computational biology and elsewhere</p><p>Science in the broad sense is the development of <emph>understanding</emph>.
                    Scientific understanding comes typically in the form of theories, and theories
                    are at least in part the systematic identification of objects and relationships
                    that are the salient features of some domain. Informatic disciplines must put
                    these theories, formalized as conceptual models that support computational
                    processing, at the center of their identity. And for informatic disciplines to
                    be sciences themselves they must not only exploit such conceptual models, but
                    participate in their development and exploration. This is true for informatics
                    in general, and for humanities computing in particular.</p></div0><div0><head>Modeling in Bioinformatics</head><p>Other areas that began as craft-like bag-of-tricks approaches to applying
                    computing to a scientific field have now begun to evolve a more coherent body of
                    method, theory, and metatheory. Perhaps the most dramatic case is
                    bioinformatics. Although initially a haphazard and opportunistic application of
                    computing techniques, there are now a considerable number of families of
                    well-theorized methods tightly tied to biological theory. Of particular interest
                    here is the role of so-called <emph>ontologies</emph> in contemporary
                    bioinformatics such as the Gene Ontology (Ashburner et al., 2000), the
                    Foundational Model of Anatomy (Rossee &amp; Mejino, 2003), and other
                    ontologies in genomics, molecular function, neuroscience, biodiversity, and
                    other areas of the life sciences as well. An enormous amount of effort is going
                    into the development and use of these formal models.</p><p>In some cases the influence on biological science <emph>per se</emph> has still
                    been modest, but generally the results are extremely promising and in a few
                    cases the influence has been stunning. The Gene Ontology in particular, has been
                    enormously successful and provides the overall framework for contemporary
                    genomics. Of special significance for us is the extent to which the fundamental
                    explanatory entities and properties of biological theories are explicitly
                    identified as the core constituents of these conceptual models, blending the
                    work of first order science with its bioinformatics support.</p></div0><div0><head>Modeling in the Cultural Sciences</head><p>Within the humanities computing community text encoding systems such as the TEI
                    can be seen as a step in the same direction as the new ontology-based models in
                    computational biology. Behind the methods of the TEI is at least arguably an
                    informal positing of text models, components, and relationships. However unlike
                    the bioinformatic ontologies the models being indicated by text encoding
                    techniques are only indirectly and implicitly identified. This has been pointed
                    out by a number of critics (Raymond &amp; Tompa, 1992; Raymond, Tompa,
                    &amp; Wood, 1996, 1998, 2001; Buzzetti, 2002), and projects to develop
                    remedies are underway (Sperberg-McQueen et al., 2002; Renear et al., 2003).</p><p>Another promising sign are the ontologies being developed in museum studies
                    CIDOC/CRM (Crofts et al., 2003) and library science (IFLA 1998). For the most
                    part these are being put forward as frameworks for designing digital information
                    management systems or shaping the development of standards, policies, and
                    procedures, but to the extent that they succeed at efficient, functional, and
                    interoperable systems they may be considered confirmed as substantive
                    theoretical proposals for how to understand the nature of the cultural world.
                    And where these models and ontologies appear to be applications of existing
                    explanatory theories of cultural objects and relationships that is more evidence
                    that they are achievements which advance our understanding of that world.</p></div0><div0><head>An Example: Revising FRBR</head><p>What follows is an example intended to support two claims. First that the
                    evolution of conceptual models intended to support information systems design
                    can in fact be an activity of first order science (in the broad sense), and
                    second that precisely the same techniques designed for general evaluation of
                    ontologies in natural science can be effectively employed in evaluating cultural
                    ontologies.</p><p>Several models for cultural objects identify such things as works, texts,
                    editions, and individual items as <emph>types</emph> of things, fundamental
                    kinds. Not only are various sorts of conceptual arguments advanced in favor of
                    such an analysis, but so is the relative success of such frameworks in guiding
                    the design of effective information systems that are effective, efficient, and
                    interoperable. That is, the conceptual and practical success of these systems
                    can be taken as indicating that they correctly represent <emph>how things
                    are</emph>. A well-known model of this sort is IFLA’s Functional Requirements
                    for Bibliographic Records (IFLA 1998), a framework designed primarily to support
                    library cataloguing, but which clearly has wider application — FRBR in fact
                    describes itself as a “conceptual model of the bibliographic universe”. </p><p>A puzzle recently emerged about an assignment of one particular cultural object
                    (XML documents, as defined in the W3C XML standard) to the appropriate FRBR
                    entity type. Some considerations argued for an assignment to the FRBR
                        <emph>expression</emph> (roughly: text) entity type, and other competing
                    considerations argued for assignment to the FRBR <emph>manifestation</emph>
                    (roughly: edition, or format) entity type. The proposed resolution was an
                    awkward and unsatisfying exception to the FRBR framework which preserved the
                    ontology of works, expressions, editions, at the cost of complexities elsewhere.
                    (Renear et al 2002, Renear 2005).</p><p>Two years later however it was noted that when a proposed criterion for ontology
                    evaluation which had been developed for scientific and general purpose
                    ontologies (Guarino &amp; Welty, 2000; Guarino &amp; Welty, 2002) was
                    applied to the FRBR framework the result was an anomaly that suggested
                    refactoring the four Group 1 entity types into new entities and corresponding
                    roles. (Renear, 2006). Under the resulting revised model the manifestation and
                    expression entity types are not treated as true entity types (fundamental
                    kinds), but rather <emph>roles</emph> (relationships) that entities of other
                    types have in particular circumstances—and in fact this revision was extended
                    to all four FRBR entities (Renear &amp; Dubin, forthcoming). We realized
                    that this new way of conceptualizing cultural objects appeared to be an
                    application of a more general approach developed by John Searle (1995) as well
                    as consistent with some work in aesthetics (Levinson 1980). In short, all four
                    FRBR “entities” can be reinterpreted not as entities but as roles that other
                    non-cultural things have under specific social contexts of “collective
                    intentionality”.</p><p>That this is not just a practical adjustment in a conceptual model for humanities
                        <emph>computing</emph>, but a substantive claim in the science of cultural
                    objects in general, can be established by comparing it to familiar claims about
                    cultural objects by scholars such as Ingarden, Wellek, Richards, Fish, Goodman,
                    Tanselle, Schillingsburg and others. In this comparison contradiction will serve
                    as well as convergence to make the point that these assertions fall within the
                    domain of humanist inquiry, and not merely within some auxiliary practice.</p></div0><div0><head>The Relative Neutrality of these Recommendations</head><p>It may be thought that putting conceptual modeling at the heart of humanities
                    computing and seeing the development of models as first order scholarship in the
                    humanities requires accepting some archaic and dubious philosophical view, a
                    positivistic scientism perhaps, or even philosophical realism. But this is not
                    so. It is possible to engage in ontology without taking a philosophical
                        <emph>meta</emph>-ontological position. Many different philosophical
                    positions (including constructivism and relativism) are all perfectly consistent
                    with taking conceptual modeling as the natural activity of humanities computing,
                    and at least part of humanities scholarship more generally. Of course the
                        <emph>results</emph> of modeling will not be neutral vis-à-vis other first
                    order theories, but the <emph>activity</emph> of modeling need not be
                    exceptionally controversial. Again the experience of bioinformatics, where
                    researchers with different philosophical views (or no philosophical views at
                    all) nevertheless often agree, or more importantly disagree, on specific issues
                    without rejecting the overall approach, is significant. </p><p>This is not to say that the position is entirely neutral. It may well conflict
                    with some general accounts of humanistic inquiry which hold that such inquiry is
                    radically different than the natural sciences, especially if those accounts are
                    understood as applying in general or without exception to the entire range of
                    humanistic scholarship — although I am not yet convinced that it does in fact
                    conflict with the traditions of hermeneutics and <emph>verstehen</emph>, despite
                    the differences in tone and direction. In any case that the recommendation is
                    not entirely uncontroversial cannot be taken as a decisive mark against it at
                    the outset. Whether it is sound or not will depend on how it fares against its
                    competitors in improving our knowledge and understanding of the cultural
                world.</p></div0><div0><head>Concluding Remarks</head><p>I have argued that humanities computing must make conceptual modeling its central
                    defining activity if it is to fully realize its promise to substantially advance
                    humanities scholarship, and that such modeling is an intrinsic part of first
                    order humanities inquiry, and not merely an auxiliary activity.</p></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Ashburner, Michael, et al">Michael Ashburner, et
                                al</name></author><title level="a">Gene Ontology: Tool for the Unification of
                            Biology</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j"> Nature Genetics</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">25</biblScope><date value="2000">2000</date><biblScope type="pages">25-29</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Buzzetti, Dino">Dino Buzzetti</name></author><title level="a">Digital Representation and the Text Model</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">New Literary History</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">33.1</biblScope><date value="2002">2002</date><biblScope type="pages">61-88</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Cover, Robin">Robin Cover</name></author><title level="a">Conceptual Modeling and Markup Languages</title></analytic><monogr><imprint><date value="2001">2001</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://xml.coverpages.org/conceptualModeling.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Cover, Robin">Robin Cover</name></author><title level="a">XML and Semantic Transparency</title></analytic><monogr><imprint><date value="1998">1998</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://xml.coverpages.org/xmlAndSemantics.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Crofts, Nick">Nick Crofts</name></author><author><name reg="Dionissiadou, I.">I. Dionissiadou</name></author><author><name reg="Doerr, Martin">Martin Doerr</name></author><author><name reg="Stiff, Matthew">Matthew Stiff</name></author><title level="m">Definition of the CIDOC Object-Oriented Conceptual
                                Reference Model, ISO/TC46/SC4/WG9/N2, International Organization for Standardization</title><imprint><date value="2003">2003</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Guarino, Nicola">Nicola Guarino</name></author><author><name reg="Welty, Christopher A.">Christopher A. Welty</name></author><title level="a">A Formal Ontology of Properties</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m"> Proceedings of the 12th European Workshop on Knowledge
                                Acquisition, Modeling and Management</title><title level="j"> Lecture Notes In Computer Science</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Dieng, Rose">Rose Dieng</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Corby, Olivier">Olivier Corby</name></editor><imprint><biblScope type="vol">1937</biblScope><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher><date value="2000">2000</date><biblScope type="pages">97-112</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Guarino, Nicola">Nicola Guarino</name></author><author><name reg="Welty, Christopher">Christopher Welty</name></author><title level="a">Evaluating Ontological Decisions with OntoClean</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Communications of the ACM</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">45.2</biblScope><date value="2002">2002</date><biblScope type="pages">61-65</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="International Federation of Library Associations">International Federation of Library Associations</name></author><title level="m">Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records:
                                Final Report</title><title level="s">UBCIM Publications-New Series</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Plassard, Marie-France">Marie-France Plassard</name></editor><imprint><biblScope type="vol">19</biblScope><pubPlace>München</pubPlace><publisher>K.G.Saur</publisher><date value="1998">1998</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Levinson, Jerrold">Jerrold Levinson</name></author><title level="a">What a Musical Work Is</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">The Journal of Philosophy</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">77.1</biblScope><date value="1980">1980</date><biblScope type="pages">5-28</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="McCarty, Willard">Willard McCarty</name></author><title level="a">Humanities Computing: Essential Problems, Experimental
                                Practice</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">17.1</biblScope><date value="2002">2002</date><biblScope type="pages">103-125</biblScope></imprint></monogr><note>doi:10.1093/llc/17.1.103</note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="McCarty, Willard">Willard McCarty</name></author><title level="a">Modeling: A Study in Words and Meanings</title></analytic><monogr><editor role="editor"><name reg="Schreibman, Susan">Susan Schreibman</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Siemens, Ray">Ray Siemens</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Unsworth, John">John Unsworth</name></editor><title level="m">A Companion to the Digital Humanities</title><imprint><pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace><publisher>Blackwell Publishing Ltd</publisher><date value="2004">2004</date><biblScope type="pages">254-70</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Raymond, Darrell R.">Darrell R. Raymond</name></author><author><name reg="Tompa, Frank Wm.">Frank Wm. Tompa</name></author><author><name reg="Wood, Derick">Derick Wood</name></author><title level="a">From Data Representation to Data Model: Meta-Semantic
                                Issues in the Evolution of SGML</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Computer Standards &amp; Interfaces</title><edition>[SGML Special Issue]</edition><imprint><biblScope type="vol">18.1</biblScope><date value="1996">January 1996</date><biblScope type="pages">25-36</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Raymond, Darrell R.">Darrell R. Raymond</name></author><author><name reg="Tompa, Frank Wm.">Frank Wm. Tompa</name></author><author><name reg="Wood, Derick">Derick Wood</name></author><title level="m">Markup Reconsidered</title><title level="s">Department of Computer Science, Technical Report No.
                                356</title><imprint><publisher>The University of Western Ontario</publisher><date value=" 1993">1993</date></imprint></monogr><note>Presented at the First International Workshop on the Principles of
                            Document Processing, Washinton DC, October 21-23 1992; an earlier
                            version was circulated privately as "Markup Considered Harmful" in the
                            late 1980s.</note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Renear, Allen H.">Allen H. Renear</name></author><author><name reg="Dubin, David">David Dubin</name></author><author><name reg="Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.">C. M. Sperberg-McQueen</name></author><author><name reg="Huitfeldt, Claus">Claus Huitfeldt</name></author><editor role="editor"><name reg="Furuta, R.">R. Furuta</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Maletic, J. I.">J. I. Malectic</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Munson, E.">E. Munson</name></editor><title level="a">Towards a Semantics for XML Markup</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Proceedings of the 2002 ACM Symposium on Document
                                Engineering. McClean, Virginia, November 2002</title><imprint><publisher>Association for Computing Machinery</publisher><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Renear, Allen H.">Allen H. Renear</name></author><author><name reg="Phillippe, Christopher">Christopher Phillippe</name></author><author><name reg="Lawton, Pat">Pat Lawton</name></author><author><name reg="Dubin, David">David Dubin</name></author><title level="a">An XML Document Corresponds to which FRBR Group 1
                                Entity?</title></analytic><monogr><editor role="editor"><name reg="Usdin, B. T.">B. T. Usdin</name></editor><title level="m">Proceedings of Extreme Markup Languages, Montréal,
                                Québec, August 2003</title><imprint><date value="2003">2003</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Renear, Allen H.">Allen H. Renear</name></author><title level="a">Text from Several Different Perspectives, the Role of
                                Context in Markup Semantics</title></analytic><monogr><editor role="editor"><name reg="Nicolas, C.">C. Nicolas</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Moneglia, M.">M. Moneglia</name></editor><title level="m">Atti della conferenza internazionale CLiP 2003,
                                Computer Literacy and Philology, Firenze, 4–5 December 2003</title><imprint><pubPlace>Florence</pubPlace><publisher>University of Florence Press</publisher><date value="2005">2005</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to=" http://people.lis.uiuc.edu/~renear/clip2005.pdf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Renear, Allen H.">Allen H. Renear</name></author><title level="a">Is An XML document a FRBR Manifestation or a FRBR
                                Expression? — Both, Because FRBR Entities are not Types, but
                            Roles</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Proceedings of Extreme Markup Languages, Montréal,
                                Québec, August 2006</title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.idealliance.org/papers/extreme/Proceedings/html/2006/Renear01/EML2006Renear01.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Renear, Allen H.">Allen H. Renear</name></author><author><name reg="Dubin, David">David Dubin</name></author><title level="a">The Four FRBR Group 1 Entities are Roles, Not
                            Types</title></analytic><monogr><imprint><date>Forthcoming</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Rosse, Cornelius">Cornelius Rosse</name></author><author><name reg="Mejino, José L. V., Jr.">José L. V. Mejino, Jr.</name></author><title level="a"> A Reference Ontology for Biomedical Informatics: the
                                Foundational Model of Anatomy</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j"> Journal of Biomedical Informatics</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">36.6</biblScope><date value="2003">2003</date><biblScope type="pages">478-500</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Searle, John R.">John R. Searle</name></author><title level="m">The Construction of Social Reality</title><imprint><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>The Free Press</publisher><date value="1995">1995</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.">C. M.Sperberg-McQueen</name></author><author><name reg="Huitfeldt, Claus">Claus Huitfeldt</name></author><author><name reg="Renear, Allen H.">Allen H. Renear</name></author><title level="a">Meaning and Interpretation of Markup</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Proceedings of Extreme Markup Languages, Montréal,
                                Québec, August 2000</title><imprint><publisher>Graphic Communications Association</publisher><date value="2000">2000</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.">C. M.Sperberg-McQueen</name></author><author><name reg="Dubin, David">David Dubin</name></author><author><name reg="Huitfeldt, Claus">Claus Huitfeldt</name></author><author><name reg="Renear, Allen H.">Allen H. Renear</name></author><title level="a">Drawing Inferences on the Basis of Markup</title></analytic><monogr><editor role="editor"><name reg="Usdin, B. T.">B. T. Usdin</name></editor><editor><name reg="Newcomb, S. R.">S. R. Newcomb</name></editor><title level="m">Proceedings of Extreme Markup Languages 2002, Montréal,
                                Québec, August 2002</title><imprint><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Unsworth, John">John Unsworth</name></author><title level="a">Scholarly Primitives: What Methods do Humanities
                                Researchers Have in Common, and How Might Our Tools Reflect
                            This?</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Paper presented at Symposium on Humanities Computing:
                                Formal Methods, Experimental Practice. King's College, London, May
                                13, 2000</title><imprint><date value="2000">2000</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/~jmu2m/Kings.5-00/primitives.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Unsworth, John">John Unsworth</name></author><title level="a">Knowledge Representation in Humanities
                            Computing</title></analytic><monogr><imprint><date>n.d.</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/~jmu2m/KR/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Unsworth, John">John Unsworth</name></author><title level="a">What is Humanities Computing and What is Not?</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Distinguished Speakers Series, Maryland Institute for
                                Technology in the Humanities, University of Maryland, College Park
                                MD, October 5, 2000</title><imprint><date value="2000">2000</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/~jmu2m/mith.00.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Unsworth, John">John Unsworth</name></author><title level="a">New Methods for Humanities Research</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">The Lyman Award Lecture, National Humanities Center,
                                November 11, 2005</title><imprint><date value="2005">2005</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www3.isrl.uiuc.edu/~unsworth/lyman.htm" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>