<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ab-294">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Interfaces for Crowdsourcing Interpretation</title>
<author>
<name><surname>Nally</surname>, <forename>Gwendolyn</forename></name>
<affiliation>University of Virginia Library, United States of America</affiliation>
<email>egn9b@virginia.edu</email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Peck</surname>, <forename>Chris</forename></name>
<affiliation>University of Virginia Library, United States of American</affiliation>
<email>cp3ee@virginia.edu</email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Lin</surname>, <forename>Shane</forename></name>
<affiliation>University of Virginia Library, United States of America</affiliation>
<email>ssl2ab@virginia.edu</email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Márquez</surname>, <forename>Cecilia</forename></name>
<affiliation>University of Virginia Library, United States of America</affiliation>
<email>cm2ug@virginia.edu</email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Maiers</surname>, <forename>Claire</forename></name>
<affiliation>University of Virginia Library, United States of America</affiliation>
<email>cdm6zf@virginia.edu</email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Walsh</surname>, <forename>Brandon</forename></name>
<affiliation>University of Virginia Library, United States of America</affiliation>
<email>bmw9t@virginia.edu</email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Boggs</surname>, <forename>Jeremy</forename></name>
<affiliation>University of Virginia Library, United States of America</affiliation>
<email>dw04@aub.edu.lb</email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Praxis Program Team</surname></name>
<affiliation>University of Virginia Library, United States of America</affiliation>
<email>praxis2012@collab.itc.virginia.edu</email>
</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority></authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
                        
<notesStmt><note type="abstract">Our research will explore problems related to the individual in crowdsourced interpretation projects. Agreeing that prototypes can have arguments, we will elaborate on a number of approaches to crowdsourcing interpretation through the development of several working prototypes for use in the Prism web service. The poster will demonstrate ways in which the user interface for Prism influences and is influenced by the roles individuals might play within the crowd.</note></notesStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Poster</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
<term>crowdsourcing interpretation</term>
<term>interface design</term>
<term>visualization</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>information retrieval</term>
<term>interface and user experience design</term>
<term>software design and development</term>
<term>user studies/user needs</term>  
<term>knowledge representation</term>
<term>information architecture</term>
<term>authorship attribution/authority</term>
<term>interdisciplinary collaboration</term>
<term>crowdsourcing</term>
<term>networks</term>
<term>relationships</term>
<term>graphs</term>
                    
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date when="2013-03-29"></date>
<name>Erin Pedigo</name>
<desc>Initial encoding</desc>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
<text type="poster">
<body>
<div>
<div>
    
    <p>Our research will detail a number of approaches to crowdsourcing
        interpretation &#8212; especially as these approaches relate to the ongoing development and
        design of <hi rend="italic">Prism,</hi> a tool that facilitates crowdsourced interpretation of texts. We take up the
        challenge detailed by Ramsay and Rockwell (2012) that the activity of building provides
        affordances as rich and informed as writing, and that it is important to to be aware of the
        nature and quality of the intervention that happens through building. Drucker (2009) and
        Ruecker et. al. (2011) demonstrate the importance of speculative prototyping as a way to
        explore humanities questions and make arguments through prototypes. In that spirit, our
        research will inform the creation of several interfaces that address problems related to
        the individual and crowdsourced interpretation.</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Background</head>  
    
    <p>In 2011, the Praxis team at the University of Virginia created <hi rend="italic">Prism</hi> as digital realization of
        the “Patacritical Demon” imagined by Drucker (2009), McGann (2004), and Nowviskie
        (2012). In its current form, <hi rend="italic">Prism</hi> allows multiple users to highlight a text based on certain
        predetermined categories. The tool then creates an aggregate visualization of individual
        responses. In this way <hi rend="italic">Prism</hi> diverges from current utilizations of crowdsourcing; where
        crowdsourced projects have traditionally asked users to compile data or do other
        mechanistic tasks, <hi rend="italic">Prism</hi> asks individuals to mark up a text with categories of meaning, to
        discern trends in the way a larger group of users reads the text. Although <hi rend="italic">Prism</hi> promises
        to bring individual experience into the fold, Bethany Nowiskie (2012) notes that <hi rend="italic">Prism</hi> “is
        not a device for rich, individual exegesis,” and the usefulness of <hi rend="italic">Prism</hi> lies in the
        overlapping and visualizing of all contributors, “generating spectra of similarity and
        difference.”</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Existing Approaches to Crowdsourcing Interpretation</head>    
    
    <p>Owens (2012) distinguishes between two approaches that are commonly lumped under
        the heading of crowdsourcing: “human computation” and “the wisdom of crowds.” Human
        computation projects ask participants to solve problems for which computational
        solutions are comparatively expensive to develop or perform. Such problems include
        transcription (Transcribing Bentham, Old Weather, reCAPTCHA), protein folding (fold.it),
        and image metadata tagging (ESP Game). Crowd-wisdom projects, on the other hand,
        engage participants in open-ended socially-negotiated tasks that may go further than
        processing information and actually create new knowledge. (This is the mode of Wikipedia
        or any website with comment or discussion forum functionality.)</p>
</div>
 
<div> 
<head>Directions for Research</head>    
    
    <p>We have begun to consider other ways to crowdsource interpretation, especially
        approaches that attend more closely to individual responses. In particular, we have
        identified two areas for exploration:
        
        <list type="simple">
        <item><hi rend="italic">Computation and Crowd Wisdom</hi> &#8212; Owens (2012) suggests that both existing modes of
        crowdsourcing are worth designing for and can work in tandem for Digital Humanities
        projects (Galaxy Zoo). In that spirit, <hi rend="italic">Prism</hi> presents the user with a task that is in both
        constrained in such a way that it produces information and somewhat open-ended and
        socially-negotiated through the user’s engagement with a text.</item>
            
         <item><hi rend="italic">Wisdom of the Individual</hi> &#8212; Crowdsourcing interpretation might offer an increased focus on
        individuals as a part of the collaborative process. Preserving the marks of each participant
        would better respect the human element at the core of crowdsourcing. This feature would
        also make <hi rend="italic">Prism</hi> a more powerful pedagogical tool, as an instructor could identify an
        individual student’s remarks for generating discussion. This would also be useful for the social sciences, which are inherently concerned with the individual as a member (and perhaps representative) of a particular group.</item></list></p>
    
    <p>Future design and development of <hi rend="italic">Prism</hi> must account for the many potential roles of
            individuals in crowdsourcing interpretation. For example, in order to better serve
            projects concerned with the wisdom of particular individuals <hi rend="italic">Prism</hi> would need to store
            user markings and interpretations, in a way that they are extractable and easily viewed in
            relation to the markings of the crowd. Similarly, in order to better facilitate social science
            research <hi rend="italic">Prism</hi> might include a way to separate out user interpretations according to
            demographic information (such as class, gender, age, etc.) or according to specific user
            responses. The poster will detail how the the design and development of <hi rend="italic">Prism</hi> has been
            and continues to be influenced by the different roles individuals might play within the
            crowd.</p>
</div>
    
</div>    
    
    
</body>
    
<back>
<div type="References">
<listBibl>
    
<bibl><hi rend="bold">Drucker, J.</hi> (2009). <hi rend="italic">SpecLab: Digital Aesthetics and Projects in Speculative Computing.</hi> Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2009.</bibl>
    
<bibl><hi rend="bold">Ford, P.</hi> (2011). The Web Is a Customer Service Medium. <ref type="url" target="http://www.ftrain.com/wwic.html">http://www.ftrain.com/wwic.html</ref>. (accessed 6 January 2011).</bibl>
    
<bibl><hi rend="bold">Galey, A., S. Ruecker, and the INKE team</hi> (2010). How a Prototype Argues. <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi> 25(4): 405–24.</bibl>
    
<bibl><hi rend="bold">McGann, J.</hi> (2001). <hi rend="italic">Radiant Textuality: Literature After the World Wide Web.</hi> New York: Palgrave MacMillan.</bibl>
    
<bibl><hi rend="bold">McGann, J.</hi> (2004). What is a Text? In Schreibman, S., R. Siemens, and J. Unsworth (eds). <hi rend="italic">A Companion to Digital Humanities.</hi>  Oxford: Blackwell.<ref type="url" target="http://digitalhumanities.org/companion/view?docId=blackwell/9781405103213/
9781405103213.xml&amp;chunk.id=ss1-3-4">http://digitalhumanities.org/companion/view?docId=blackwell/9781405103213/
9781405103213.xml&amp;chunk.id=ss1-3-4</ref></bibl>
    
<bibl><hi rend="bold">Meister, J. C.</hi> (2012). Crowd Sourcing ‘True Meaning’: A Collaborative Markup
Approach to Textual Interpretation. In Deegan, M. and W. McCarthy (eds). <hi rend="italic">Collaborative Research in the Digital
Humanities.</hi>  Ashgate. 105–122.</bibl>
    
<bibl><hi rend="bold">Nowviskie, B.</hi> (2012). A Digital Boot Camp for Grad Students in the Humanities. <hi rend="italic">Chronicle
of Higher Education.</hi> <ref type="url" target="http://chronicle.com/article/A-Digital-Boot-Camp-for-Grad/131665/">http://chronicle.com/article/A-Digital-Boot-Camp-for-Grad/131665/</ref> (29 April 2012).</bibl>
    
<bibl><hi rend="bold">Owens, T.</hi> Human Computation and Wisdom of Crowds in Cultural Heritage.
<ref type="url" target="http://www.trevorowens.org/2012/06/human-computation-and-wisdom-of-crowds-in-cultural-heritage/">http://www.trevorowens.org/2012/06/human-computation-and-wisdom-of-crowds-in-cultural-heritage/</ref></bibl>
    
<bibl><hi rend="bold">Ramsay, S., and G. Rockwell</hi> (2012). Developing Things: Notes toward an
Epistemology of Building in the Digital Humanities. In Gold, M. K. (ed). <hi rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
Humanities.</hi> Minnesota: University of Minnesota Press.</bibl>
    
<bibl><hi rend="bold">Ruecker, S., M. Radzikowska,  and S. Sinclair</hi> (2011). <hi rend="italic">Visual Interface Design for Digital
Cultural Heritage: A Guide to Rich-Prospect Browsing.</hi>
Burlington, VT: Ashgate.</bibl>
    
<bibl><hi rend="bold">Surowiecki, J.</hi> (2004). <hi rend="italic">The Wisdom of Crowds: Why the Many Are Smarter Than the Few and How Collective Wisdom Shapes Business, Economies, Societies, and Nations.</hi> New York: Doubleday.</bibl>
    
</listBibl>
</div>
</back>
</text>
</TEI>    
    
