<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ab-241">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>4Humanities: Designing Digital Advocacy</title>
<author>
<name><surname>Thomas</surname>, <forename>Lindsay</forename></name>
<affiliation>University of California, Santa Barbara, United States of America</affiliation>
<email>lindsaythomas@umail.ucsb.edu</email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Liu</surname>, <forename>Alan</forename></name>
<affiliation>University of California, Santa Barbara, United States of America</affiliation>
<email>ayliu@english.ucsb.edu </email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Rockwell</surname>, <forename>Geoffrey</forename></name>
<affiliation>University of Alberta</affiliation>
<email>geoffrey.rockwell@ualberta.ca</email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Sinclair</surname>, <forename>St&#233;fan</forename></name>
<affiliation>McGill University</affiliation>
<email>stefan.sinclair@mcgill.ca</email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Terras</surname>, <forename>Melissa</forename></name>
<affiliation>University College London</affiliation>
<email>m.terras@ucl.ac.uk</email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Bielby</surname>, <forename>Jared</forename></name>
<affiliation>University of Alberta</affiliation>
<email>bielby@ualberta.ca</email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Smith</surname>, <forename>Victoria</forename></name>
<affiliation>University of Alberta</affiliation>
<email>victoriassmith@gmail.com</email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Turcato</surname>, <forename>Mark</forename></name>
<affiliation>McGill University</affiliation>
<email>mark.turcato@mail.mcgill.ca</email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Henseler</surname>, <forename>Christine</forename></name>
<affiliation>Union College</affiliation>
<email>henselec@union.edu</email>
</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority></authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note type="abstract">The Great Recession beginning in 2008 has resulted in a series of budgetary cuts to many universities, education programs, and cultural institutions that reflect indifference about, and even hostility toward, the humanities and arts. Unlike the sciences - who have an established tradition of public advocacy and media communication - the humanities have no consistent, planned tradition of advocacy. This paper argues for planned humanities advocacy using the affordances of the digital humanities. In particular, it discusses how the 4Humanities initiative is leveraging DH for next-generation advocacy through text analysis of pubic discourse about the humanities and crowd-sourced generation of arguments for the humanities; by showing how statistics and other evidence about the contribution of the humanities to society can be analyzed and visualized; and by discussing how DH can provide special tools for humanities advocacy, while humanities advocacy can in return incentivize the creation of next-generation DH research and teaching tools.</note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
<p>
<date when="20130718"></date>
<time when="10:30:00"></time>
</p>
<p n="session">LP13</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Paper</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Long Paper</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
<term>humanities advocacy</term>
<term>digital humanities</term>
<term>4Humanities</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>digital humanities - institutional support</term>
<term>text analysis</term>
<term>crowdsourcing</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date when="2013-04-09"></date>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<desc>Initial encoding</desc>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text type="paper">
<body>
<div>

<div>
<head>Introduction: Cuts, Crisis and Criticisms of the Humanities</head>

<p>The Great Recession beginning in 2008 has resulted in a series of budgetary cuts to many universities, education programs, and cultural institutions that reflect indifference about, and even hostility toward, the humanities and arts in favor of scientific, engineering, business, and other applied fields. Even scientists are now concerned about the perceived legitimacy of their "basic research" when it lacks evident short-term application. However, the sciences have an established tradition of public advocacy and media communication that is quite effective in putting their discoveries before the public. The humanities have no such consistent, planned tradition of advocacy, and in many ways are starting from scratch. </p>

<p>This paper argues for and demonstrates planned humanities advocacy using the special affordances of the digital humanities. In particular, it discusses how the 4Humanities initiative is leveraging DH for next-generation advocacy. In this paper, we will:</p>

<list type="unordered">
<item>Show how 4Humanities uses DH to help analyze public discourse, both pro and con, about the humanities (including text analysis of such discourse as well as crowd-sourced generation of arguments for the humanities).</item>
<item>Show how statistics and other evidence about the contribution of the humanities to society can be analyzed and visualized in support of effective arguments.</item>
<item>Discuss the role of 4Humanities and, more generally, how DH can provide special tools for humanities advocacy, while humanities advocacy can in return incentivize the creation of next-generation DH research and teaching tools with a built-in public engagement dimension.</item>
</list>
</div>

<div>
<head>Analysis of Arguments Against the Humanities</head>
<p>One way to bolster advocacy for the humanities is first to look closely at the arguments made in public against them. We have compiled a small corpus of recent articles (especially from news sources accessed by a broad public) representative of criticisms of the humanities (Auslin, 2012; Bauerlein, 2011; Cohan, 2012a; Cohan, 2012b; Ellouk, 2011; Fendrich, 2009; Fish, 2007; Fish 2008; Fund, 2012; Knapp, 2011; Murdoch, 2011; Pidgeon, 2007; Riley, 2012; Sini, 2011; Stephens, 2012; Wente, 2012; Wood, 2012).</p>

<figure>
<graphic url="ab-241.001" />
<head>Fig 1:</head> <p>Voyant Collocate Cluster Visualization (Sinclair and Rockwell)</p>
</figure>

<p>We find that arguments critical of the humanities cluster around certain ideas. Principally, detractors accuse the humanities of lacking cultural and/or economic relevance. The most nuanced critiques mix or shade the charges of cultural and economic irrelevance. But other arguments refute the social usefulness of the humanities entirely, simply taking for granted their complete economic and social irrelevance. (Interestingly, however, some of these articles also defend irrelevance as a virtue, as in the case of arguments from friends of the humanities who feel that irrelevance is the basic nature of the humanities and is perfectly acceptable.)</p>

<p>A related critique of the professoriate in the humanities is that our work is no longer accessible to a larger educated public. The argument is that we are our own worst enemies because we have descended into theoretical turf battles that no one cares about. For these commentators such cultural irrelevance goes hand in hand with the supposed lack of respect that academics show for the public’s values, as epitomized in Marxism, feminism, post-colonialism, and other approaches that attack iconic ideas. The antidote sometimes proposed is a return to a nebulous concept of the traditional humanities &#8212; e.g., to the venerable search for the “beautiful.”</p>

<p>This paper will summarize our reading of the articles as well as present results from some text analysis of other rhetoric about the humanities.</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Analysis of Arguments For the Humanities</head>

<p>As important as it is to know the arguments critical of the humanities, it is also important to gather good arguments for the humanities. 4Humanities has taken two approaches to this. The first is to blog good arguments as we come across them with summaries for those who are looking for essays to help them in their advocacy. We have also summarized these in a digestible form for people to review (Bielby, 2012). Finally we ran an All Our Ideas vote on the value of the humanities (<ref type="url" target="http://allourideas.org/4humanities">http://allourideas.org/4humanities</ref>). At the time of writing this proposal there were over 1600 votes and 31 user submitted possible answers (as opposed to 12 seeds that we provided.) The top choices at the time of writing included:</p>

<figure>
<graphic url="ab-241.t01" />
<figDesc>Proposed Answer	Wins	Losses	Score	User
The humanities teach us to deal critically and logically with subjective, complex information.	22	4	82.1429	TRUE
Critical reasoning from imperfect information; empathy; understanding that the current situation is not inevitable or necessarily desirable	39	13	74.0741	TRUE
The humanities encourage us to think creatively and critically. They teach us to reason about being human and to ask questions about our world.	62	25	70.7865	FALSE
Through exploration of the humanities we learn how to think creatively and critically, to reason, and to ask questions.	11	4	70.5882	TRUE
The humanities develop informed and critical citizens. Without them democracy doesn't flourish.	53	23	69.2308	FALSE
The humanities teach us to weigh evidence skeptically, and consider more than one side of every question.	50	22	68.9189	TRUE
Humanities studies build skills in writing, critical reading. They expose us to broader cultures &amp; create well-rounded and rational people	49	22	68.4931	TRUE
The humanities are about understanding others in the world through their languages, histories, and cultures.	172	82	67.5781	FALSE
The value of the humanities is more often in the questions posed than the answers found; humanistic study is not a formulaic equation.	23	11	66.6667	TRUE
The humanities teaches detailed, analytical thinking, as well as showing the importance of contextualized thinking.	24	12	65.7895	TRUE</figDesc></figure>

<p>There is obviously overlap in the top choices, but these indicate what the digital humanities community considers important. In the paper we will provide a fuller analysis of the data along with our list of the best arguments.</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Looking Closely at the Statistics</head>
<quote>“Liberal arts graduates frequently catch or surpass graduates with career-oriented majors in both job quality and compensation.” (Koc, 2011)</quote>

<p>In addition to defining and communicating the cultural value of the humanities, the 4Humanities initiative is also committed to gathering data on the economic value of the humanities. One of the most pernicious arguments against the humanities has been the poor job prospects of graduating humanists. For this reason, we review the statistical arguments carefully, especially to highlight the fact that the data on compensation of humanists at mid-career paints a different story. A humanist may find it harder to get a first job with a degree, but she/he will probably rise faster than many with professional certification.</p>

<p>When making arguments for the humanities’ contribution to society, of course, it can be difficult to produce statistics, given that there has been no comprehensive study that gathers together available facts and figures in a usable manner. As part of the 4Humanities project we have been compiling and listing all statistics we can find in the published literature about the benefit of the humanities to society. This was done by collating the literature – including newspaper articles, reports, websites, and op-ed pieces (listed on the 4Humanities website) – and locating numeric references to the humanities. We have compiled such quantitative evidence, and at DH2013 we will present an infographic that sums up the statistical argument that the humanities are relevant to economic and intellectual development.</p>

<p>In addition, we have recently begun our “Infographics Friday” series (<ref type="url" target="http://humanistica.ualberta.ca/category/for-the-public/humanities-infographics/">http://humanistica.ualberta.ca/category/for-the-public/humanities-infographics/</ref>), highlighting a particular statistic or graphical representation on the 4Humanities website once a week, to demonstrate the range of evidence. A core remit of 4Humanities is to gather, analyse, and disseminate this disparate information to provide a knowledge base upon which others can build their opinions and bolster their understanding of the humanities.</p>
</div> 


<div>
<head>Conclusion: 4Humanities and a Digital Humanities response to the Cuts, Crisis, and Criticism</head>

<p>We argue that the mission of public engagement and advocacy in the humanities as embodied by the 4Humanities initiative provides a unique way to consolidate leading technological and methodological directions in DH with outreach to society. The humanities today have an advantage that was not available earlier: the analytical and communication methods of the digital humanities. Not only do the digital humanities provide a strong argument for the relevance of humanities learning in a digital age; they also provide unique, fresh ways of studying the contributions of the humanities to society and then getting the message out. DH research and humanities advocacy can be one, where DH helps advance advocacy, and, reciprocally, the advocacy mission helps drive research in DH. The hunt is now on to develop and extend new generations of digital humanities platforms and tools that can integrate the core research and teaching work of humanists with public visibility and engagement. Such platforms and tools (for publishing, editing, research, pedagogy, etc.) can be designed from the ground up, both to serve the needs of academics and to engage with today's networked public. This paper is a step in that direction.</p>
</div>



</div>

</body>

<back>
<div type="References">
<listBibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Auslin, M. </hi> (2012). Knowledge is Good. <hi rend="italic">National Review Online</hi>. 15 March. <ref type="url" target="http://www.aei.org/article/education/higher-education/knowledge-is-good/">http://www.aei.org/article/education/higher-education/knowledge-is-good/</ref> (accessed 13 March 2013).</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Bauerlein, M. </hi> (2011). Oh, the Humanities! <hi rend="italic">The Weekly Standard</hi>. 16 May. <ref type="url" target="http://www.weeklystandard.com/articles/oh-humanities_559340.html">http://www.weeklystandard.com/articles/oh-humanities_559340.html</ref> (accessed 13 March 2013).</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Bielby, J. </hi> (2012). Arguments for the Humanities. <hi rend="italic">CIRCA Wiki</hi>, October. <ref type="url" target="http://circa.cs.ualberta.ca/index.php/CIRCA:Arguments_FOR_the_Humanities">http://circa.cs.ualberta.ca/index.php/CIRCA:Arguments_FOR_the_Humanities</ref> (accessed 13 March 2013).</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Cohan, P.</hi> (2012a). To Boost Post-College Prospects, Cut Humanities Departments. <hi rend="italic">Forbes</hi>, 29 May. <ref type="url" target="http://www.forbes.com/sites/petercohan/2012/05/29/to-boost-post-college-prospects-cut-humanities-departments/">http://www.forbes.com/sites/petercohan/2012/05/29/to-boost-post-college-prospects-cut-humanities-departments/</ref> (accessed 13 March 2013).</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Cohan, P.</hi> (2012b). The 13 Most Useless Majors, From Philosophy to Journalism. <hi rend="italic">The Daily Beast</hi>, 23 April. <ref type="url" target="http://www.thedailybeast.com/galleries/2012/04/23/the-13-most-useless-majors-from-philosophy-to-journalism.html">http://www.thedailybeast.com/galleries/2012/04/23/the-13-most-useless-majors-from-philosophy-to-journalism.html</ref> (accessed 13 March 2013).</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Davidson, C. N.</hi> (2011). Strangers on a Train. <hi rend="italic">Academe</hi>. <hi>97 (5)</hi>. <ref type="url" target="http://www.aaup.org/AAUP/pubsres/academe/2011/SO/Feat/davi.htm">http://www.aaup.org/AAUP/pubsres/academe/2011/SO/Feat/davi.htm</ref> (accessed 13 March 2013). </bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Davidson, C. N.</hi> (2012). Humanities 2.0: Promise, Perils, Predictions. In Gold, M. (ed), <hi rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</hi>. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press. 476-489.</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Davidson, C. N., and D. T. Goldberg</hi> (2004). A Manifesto for the Humanities in a Technological Age. <hi rend="italic">The Chronicle of Higher Education: The Chronicle Review</hi>. 13 Feb.</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Delblanco, A. </hi>(2011). <hi rend="italic">College: What It Was, Is, and Should Be</hi>. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press.</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Ellouk, B.</hi> (2011). Do We Still Need the Humanities? <hi rend="italic">The Daily of the University of Washington</hi>. 26 July. <ref type="url" target="http://dailyuw.com/news/2011/jul/26/do-we-still-need-humanities/">http://dailyuw.com/news/2011/jul/26/do-we-still-need-humanities/</ref> (accessed 13 March 2013). </bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Fendrich, L.</hi> (2009). The Humanities Have No Purpose. <hi rend="italic">The Chronicle of Higher Education</hi>, 20 March. <ref type="url" target="http://chronicle.com/blogs/brainstorm/the-humanities-have-no-purpose/6738">http://chronicle.com/blogs/brainstorm/the-humanities-have-no-purpose/6738</ref> (accessed 13 March 2013).</bibl> 

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Fish, S.</hi> (2007). Bound For Academic Glory? <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, 23 December. <ref type="url" target="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2007/12/23/bound-for-academic-glory/">http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2007/12/23/bound-for-academic-glory/</ref> (accessed 13 March 2013).</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Fish, S.</hi> (2008). Will the Humanities Save Us? <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, 6 January.  <ref type="url" target="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2008/01/06/will-the-humanities-save-us/">http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2008/01/06/will-the-humanities-save-us/</ref> (accessed 13 March 2013).</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Fish, S.</hi> (2010). The Crisis of the Humanities Officially Arrives. <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, 11 October. <ref type="url" target="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/10/11/the-crisis-of-the-humanities-officially-arrives/">http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/10/11/the-crisis-of-the-humanities-officially-arrives/</ref> (accessed 13 March 2013).</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Fund, J.</hi> (2012). Censoring Naomi Riley. <hi rend="italic">The National Review Online</hi>, 12 May. <ref type="url" target="http://www.nationalreview.com/articles/299765/censoring-naomi-riley-john-fund">http://www.nationalreview.com/articles/299765/censoring-naomi-riley-john-fund</ref> (accessed 13 May 2013).</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Kirschenbaum, M.</hi> (2012). Digital Humanities As/Is a Tactical Term. In Gold, M. (ed), <hi rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</hi>. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 415-428.</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Knapp, S.</hi> (2011). The Enduring Dilemma of the Humanities. <hi rend="italic">The Phi Beta Kappa Society</hi>, 29 March. <ref type="url" target="http://www.pbk.org/home/FocusNews.aspx?id=741">http://www.pbk.org/home/FocusNews.aspx?id=741</ref> (accessed 13 March 2013).</bibl> 

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Koc, E. W.</hi> (2011). Just Wait 10 Years. <hi rend="italic">New York Times</hi>, 21 March. <ref type="url" target="http://www.nytimes.com/roomfordebate/2011/03/20/career-counselor-bill-gates-or-steve-jobs/your-college-major-matter-less-over-time">http://www.nytimes.com/roomfordebate/2011/03/20/career-counselor-bill-gates-or-steve-jobs/your-college-major-matter-less-over-time</ref>. (accessed 13 March 2013). </bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Lakoff, G.</hi> (2004). <hi rend="italic">Don’t Think of an Elephant!: Know Your Values and Frame the Debate</hi>. White River, VT: Chelsea Green Publishing Company.</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Liu, A.</hi> (2012). Where Is Cultural Criticism in the Digital Humanities? In Gold, M. (ed), <hi rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</hi>. Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota Press, 490-509.</bibl>
 
<bibl><hi rend="bold">Murdoch, R.</hi> (2011). The Steve Jobs Model for Education Reform. <hi rend="italic">The Wall Street Journal</hi>, 15 October. <ref type="url" target="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052970203914304576631100415237430.html">http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052970203914304576631100415237430.html</ref> (accessed 13 March 2013).</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Pidgeon, S.</hi> (2007). Commented on Fish, S. Bound For Academic Glory? <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi>, 23 December. <ref type="url" target="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2007/12/23/bound-for-academic-glory/#comment-100883">http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2007/12/23/bound-for-academic-glory/#comment-100883</ref> (accessed 13 March 2013).</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Riley, N. S.</hi> (2012). The Academic Mob Rules. <hi rend="italic">The Wall Street Journal</hi>, 8 May. <ref type="url" target="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052702304363104577391842133259230.html">http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052702304363104577391842133259230.html</ref> (accessed 13 May 2013).</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Sinclair, S., and G. Rockwell</hi> Collocates Cluster, from <hi rend="italic">Voyant</hi> Tools. <ref type="url" target="http://docs.voyant-tools.org/tools/links/">http://docs.voyant-tools.org/tools/links/</ref> (accessed 13 March 2013).</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Sini, M.</hi> (2011). Oh the Humanities! (OR: A Critique of Crisis). <hi rend="italic">OverLand</hi>, 22 February. <ref type="url" target="http://overland.org.au/blogs/loudspeaker/2011/02/%E2%80%98oh-the-humanities%E2%80%99-or-a-critique-of-crisis/">http://overland.org.au/blogs/loudspeaker/2011/02/%E2%80%98oh-the-humanities%E2%80%99-or-a-critique-of-crisis/</ref> (accessed 13 March 2013).</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Stephens, B.</hi> (2012). To the Class of 2012. <hi rend="italic">The Wall Street Journal</hi>, 9 May. <ref type="url" target="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052702304451104577389750993890854.html">http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052702304451104577389750993890854.html</ref> (accessed 13 March 2013).</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Wente, M.</hi> (2012). Quebec’s University Students are in for a Shock. <hi rend="italic">The Globe and Mail</hi>, 1 May. <ref type="url" target="http://www.theglobeandmail.com/commentary/quebecs-university-students-are-in-for-a-shock/article4104304/">http://www.theglobeandmail.com/commentary/quebecs-university-students-are-in-for-a-shock/article4104304/</ref> (accessed 13 March 2013). </bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Wood, P.</hi> (2012). Rick Santorum is Right. <hi rend="italic">The Chronicle of Higher Education</hi>, 29 February. <ref type="url" target="http://chronicle.com/blogs/innovations/rick-santorum-is-right/31769">http://chronicle.com/blogs/innovations/rick-santorum-is-right/31769</ref> (accessed 13 March 2013).</bibl>

</listBibl>
</div>
</back>
</text>
</TEI>

