<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ab-409">
    
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Framework for Testing Text Analysis and Mining Tools</title>
<author>
<name><surname>Simpson</surname>, <forename>John Edward</forename></name>
<affiliation>University of Alberta</affiliation>
<email>john.simpson@ualberta.ca</email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Rockwell</surname>, <forename>Geoffrey</forename></name>
<affiliation>University of Alberta</affiliation>
<email>grockwel@ualberta.ca</email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Sinclair</surname>, <forename>Stéfan</forename></name>
<affiliation>McGill University</affiliation>
<email>stefan.sinclair@mcgill.ca</email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Uszkalo</surname>, <forename>Kirsten C.</forename></name>
<affiliation>University of Alberta</affiliation>
<email>circe@ufies.org</email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Brown</surname>, <forename>Susan</forename></name>
<affiliation>University of Alberta; University of Guelph</affiliation>
<email>susanirenebrown@gmail.com</email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Dyrbye</surname>, <forename>Amy</forename></name>
<affiliation>University of Alberta</affiliation>
<email>amy.dyrbye@gmail.com</email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Chartier</surname>, <forename>Ryan</forename></name>
<affiliation>University of Alberta</affiliation>
<email>recharti@ualberta.ca</email>
</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority></authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unlnotes.unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>
            
            
    <notesStmt><note type="abstract">Text mining tool summaries regularly apply only general review criteria and do not offer any testing-based observations to help users assess actual usability. Humanists looking to try text mining tools for research need information that is relevant to their needs. This poster presents the testing framework developed for the TAPoR 2.0 portal. The poster covers:
        <list type="unordered">
            <item>The need for tool reviews</item>
            <item>The information gathered about tools</item>
            <item>The testing and reviewing process</item>
            <item>Conclusions about the state of text tools</item></list>
The poster will be accompanied by a demonstration of TAPoR 2.0 so that reviews can be seen in context.</note></notesStmt>
            
<sourceDesc>
<p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
        
<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Poster</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term></term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
<term>text mining</term>
<term>tool reviews</term>
<term>TAPoR 2.0</term>
</keywords>
    
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>software design and development</term>
<term>text analysis</term>
<term>user studies/user needs</term>
<term>content analysis</term>  
<term>data mining/text mining</term>
                    
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>
        
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date when="2013-03-29"></date>
<name>Erin Pedigo</name>
<desc>Initial encoding</desc>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
    
<text type="paper">
<body>
<div>
<div>
    
    <p>The most extensive compendium of text mining tools to date included 71 tools and summarized
each based on ten criteria (van Gemert 2007). While extensive, this listing of tools and their
properties is general in its review criteria and does not offer any testing-based observations to
help users assess actual usability. Humanists looking to try text analysis, visualization and
mining tools for research need better information that is relevant to their needs and reviews of
tools that help them make choices. This poster presents the testing framework developed for the
TAPoR 2.0 portal reviews. The poster will cover:
        
        <list type="ordered">
            <item>1. The need for tool reviews</item>
            <item>2. The information gathered about tools</item>
            <item>3. The testing and reviewing process</item>
            <item>4. Conclusions about the state of text tools</item></list>
            
The poster will be accompanied by a demonstration of TAPoR 2.0 so that users can see the
reviews in context.</p>
</div>

<div>
<head><hi rend="italic">1. The Need for Tool Reviews</hi></head>    
    
    <p>A humanities researcher new to computing methods looking for reviews of text tools on the
internet by peers is going to be disappointed. There is nothing like the <hi rend="italic">New York Review of
Books,</hi> though in the early days of humanities computing you could find short announcements
about tools in journals like <hi rend="italic">Computing in the Humanities.</hi> We, however, believe that certain text
tools are intellectual contributions to the field (Ramsay 2012) that should be reviewed not just to
help people choose what tools to use, but also as a way of engaging these tools in a dialogue
around computer-assisted interpretation. While there are individual blog entries about tools
scattered across the web, each is from the perspective of a single user with an entirely different
dataset, making comparison difficult. If we want to make computing methods accessible and
encourage colleagues to use tools we need a more systematic approach. This is especially true of
text mining tools that can’t simply be tried with a text at hand.</p>
</div>
    
<div>
<head><hi rend="italic">2. Information Gathered About Tools</hi></head>
    
    <p>TAPoR 2.0 (<ref type="url" target="http://www.tapor.ca">www.tapor.ca</ref>) is a 
portal for text analysis, visualization mining tool discovery and
review. TAPoR 2.0 is a complete redevelopment
of the original TAPoR portal (Rockwell 2009)
that has refocused the portal on discovery and
review instead of trying to provide access only
to web services. As part of the redevelopment of
TAPoR 2.0 we used a persona/scenario usability
design approach (Cooper 2004) to identify
attributes that users might want to discover
tools. Further we built TAPoR 2.0 so that editors
can add new attributes without the database
having to be reprogrammed. Some of the
attributes we currently record for tools include
the author(s), ease of use, type of analysis, type
of license and so on. We also have links to
related tools and tools people also used. Our
poster will be accompanied by a demonstration
of TAPoR 2.0 so that visitors can explore what
we have and how we represent it.</p>
    
<figure><graphic url="ab-409.001"/><head>Figure 1:</head><p>TAPoR 2.0 Home Screen</p></figure>
</div>    

<div>
<head><hi rend="italic">3. The Testing and Reviewing Process</hi></head> 
    
    <p>Recording basic information about tools alas, is not enough, especially with sophisticated text
mining tools like Mallet (<ref type="url" target="http://mallet.cs.umass.edu/">mallet.cs.umass.edu/</ref>) that take time to learn and that can be used in
different ways. With text mining tools users need longer narrative reviews. For this reason we
developed processes for testing and reviewing tools. For simpler text analysis and visualization
tools this involved developing a set of different texts with which to test tools so we could
compare their use. For text mining we had to go further and are working with the CWRC project
(Canadian Writing Research Collaboratory, <ref type="url" target="http://www.cwrc.ca">www.cwrc.ca</ref>) developing a number of literary
corpora with experts we can draw on to help assess the value of results. As of writing we have
three corpora drawn from the Orlando project (<ref type="url" target="http://www.ualberta.ca/ORLANDO">www.ualberta.ca/ORLANDO</ref>) and one of
Victorian children’s literature. We expect to have two more by the time or presentation. The
poster will discuss the criteria used to develop these open test corpora.</p>
    <p>The reviews take the form of comments that have been pinned to the top of the list of comments
available. This allows others to leave comments, though we haven’t seen much activity by
people not connected to the project (with the exception of spammers who seem to feel there is a
connection between text analysis tools and various stimulants.) We have developed guidelines
for reviews so as to make them accessible and comparable. The poster will outline our
guidelines.</p>
</div>

<div>
<head><hi rend="italic">4. Conclusions from Testing and Reviewing</hi></head>    
    
    <p>Having tested and reviewed a variety of tools and text mining systems we see some common
barriers to access. Most of these tools have been developed for use by the developers and are
poorly documented for people not involved in the development. Further, many tools, including
those we are involved in, are in continuous development so what documentation there is, is out
of date. We will therefore end this poster with lessons learned while testing and reviewing text
mining tools, with particular attention to removing usability barriers for novice users.</p>
</div>
</div>
</body>
    
<back>
<div type="References">
<listBibl>
    
<bibl><hi rend="bold">Cooper, A.</hi> (2004). <hi rend="italic">The Inmates Are Running the Asylum.</hi> Indianapolis, Indiana: SAMS.</bibl>
    
<bibl><hi rend="bold">Ramsay, S. and G. Rockwell</hi> (2012). Developing Things: Notes toward an Epistemology of Building in
the Digital Humanities. In Gold, M. K. (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</hi>.  Minneapolis,
Minnesota: University of Minnesota Press, 75-84.</bibl>
    
<bibl><hi rend="bold">Rockwell, G.</hi> (2006). TAPoR: Building a Portal for Text Analysis. <hi rend="italic">Mind Technologies:
Humanities Computing and the Canadian Academic Community.</hi> edited by Raymond
Siemens and David Moorman. Calgary: University of Calgary Press, 285-299.</bibl>
    
<bibl><hi rend="bold">van Gemert, J.</hi> (2000). <hi rend="italic">Text Mining Tools on the Internet.</hi> ISIS Technical Report Series.
<ref type="url" target="http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpls/abs_all.jsp?arnumber=4312886.">http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpls/abs_all.jsp?arnumber=4312886.</ref></bibl>
    
</listBibl>
</div>
</back>
</text>
</TEI>
    