<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-658">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Teasing Out Authorship and Style with T-tests and Zeta</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Hoover, David L.</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>New York University</orgName>, <country>USA</country></affiliation>
                    <email>david.hoover@nyu.edu </email>
                </author>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2009-04-16</date>
                <name>NG</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>

                <p>Most computational stylistics methods were developed for authorship attribution,
                    but many have also been applied to the study of style. Investigating Wilkie
                    Collin&apos;s <hi rend="italic">Blind Love</hi> (1890), left unfinished at
                    his death and completed by Walter Besant from a long synopsis and notes provided
                    by Collins, requires both authorship attribution and stylistics. External
                    evidence indicates that Besant took over after chapter 48 (Collins 2003), which
                    provides an opportunity to test whether Besant was successful in matching
                    Collins&apos;s style and to investigate the styles of Collins and Besant.
                    This divided novel also facilitates the comparison of two computational methods:
                    the T-test and Burrows&apos;s Zeta.</p>
                <p>The t-test is a well-studied method for determining the probability of a
                    difference between two groups arising by chance (a classic use in authorship and
                    stylistics is Burrows 1992.) Here I use t-tests to identify words used very
                    differently by Collins and Besant. After showing that those word frequencies
                    accurately identify the change of authorship, I examine the words themselves for
                    stylistically interesting characteristics.</p>
                <p>I created a combined word frequency list for four novels by Besant and three by
                    Collins, then deleted words occurring only once or twice, personal pronouns (too
                    closely related to the number and gender of characters), all words with more
                    than 90% of their occurrences in one text (almost exclusively proper names), and
                    words limited to one author (required for t-testing). I divided the novels into
                    167 4,000-word sections, and performed t-tests for the remaining 6,600 words
                    (using a Minitab macro). I cleaned up the results and sorted them on the p value
                    in Excel (with another macro), and retained only the 1719 words with p &lt;
                    .05, about 1,000 for Collins and 700 for Besant (see <ptr type="external"
                        target="https://files.nyu.edu/dh3/public/ClusterAnalysis-PCA-T-testingInMinitab.html"
                    /> for detailed instructions and the macros).</p>
                <p>I tested these words on six new texts for each author, a novel and five stories
                    for Besant and six novels for Collins. Beginning with the 500 most distinctive
                    words for each author, I deleted a few words that were absent from these texts
                    and used the remaining 993 words to perform a cluster analysis (Fig. 1). (To
                    keep the graph readable, I divided the novels into 10,000- word sections,
                    retaining only half the sections.) Obviously, these marker words are quite
                    characteristic of the authors.</p>
                <p>
                    <figure xml:id="fig1">
                        <head>Fig. 1. <hi rend="italic">Besant versus Collins: Cluster
                            Analysis</hi></head>
                        <graphic url="658_Fig1.tif" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                            mimeType="image/tif"/>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>When sections of <hi rend="italic">Blind Love</hi> are tested along with the
                    texts above, the authorship change after chapter forty-eight is starkly apparent
                    (Fig. 2). This graph is based on the sums of the frequencies of the 500 most
                    distinctive words for each author in each section. (The texts are divided into
                    1,000-word sections; only a few sections of the novels are shown; the
                    frequencies of Collins's marker words are multiplied by -1 for clarity.)
                    Although Besant was working from extensive notes, his style is distinctly
                    different. Had we not known which was Besant&apos;s first chapter, these
                    t-tested marker words would have easily located it.</p>
                <p>
                    <figure xml:id="fig2">
                        <head>Fig. 2. <hi rend="italic">Besant, Collins, Blind Love: T-tested Marker
                                Words</hi></head>
                        <graphic url="658_Fig2.tif" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                            mimeType="image/tif"/>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>Because the styles of Collins and Besant are so distinct, these marker words
                    should also characterize them. Consider the twenty most distinctive words for
                    each author:</p>

                <p>Besant: <hi rend="italic">upon</hi>, <hi rend="italic">all</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">but</hi>, <hi rend="italic">then</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >and</hi>,<hi rend="italic"> not</hi>, <hi rend="italic">or</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">very</hi>, <hi rend="italic">so</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >because</hi>, <hi rend="italic">great</hi>, <hi rend="italic">thing</hi>,
                        <hi rend="italic">things</hi>, <hi rend="italic">much</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">every</hi>, <hi rend="italic">there</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >man</hi>, <hi rend="italic">everything</hi>, <hi rend="italic">is</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">well</hi></p>
                <p>Collins: <hi rend="italic">answered</hi>, <hi rend="italic">to</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">had</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Mrs</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >on</hi>, <hi rend="italic">asked</hi>, <hi rend="italic">in</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">Miss</hi>, <hi rend="italic">mind</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >suggested</hi>, <hi rend="italic">person</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >resumed</hi>, <hi rend="italic">excuse</hi>, <hi rend="italic">left</hi>,
                        <hi rend="italic">at</hi>, <hi rend="italic">reminded</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">creature</hi>, <hi rend="italic">inquired</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">reply</hi>, <hi rend="italic">when</hi>
                </p>

                <p>Obviously, more of Besant&apos;s words are high frequency function words, and
                    many Collins words are related to speech presentation (<hi rend="italic"
                        >answered</hi>, <hi rend="italic">asked</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >inquired</hi>, <hi rend="italic">resumed</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >suggested</hi>, <hi rend="italic">reply</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >reminded</hi>). The presence of <hi rend="italic">added</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">begged</hi>, <hi rend="italic">declared</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">exclaimed</hi>, <hi rend="italic">explained</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">expressed</hi>, <hi rend="italic">muttered</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">rejoined</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">said</hi> as likely
                    speech markers among the other Collins marker words, but only <hi rend="italic"
                        >gasped</hi>, <hi rend="italic">groaned</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >murmured</hi>, <hi rend="italic">replied</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >stammered</hi> for Besant, suggests they have different ways of presenting
                    speech.</p>
                <p>Sorting all of each author&apos;s marker words alphabetically immediately
                    reveals word families that each author favors, as <hi rend="italic">thing</hi>,
                        <hi rend="italic">things</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">everything</hi> among
                    the twenty most distinctive Besant words already suggests (<hi rend="italic"
                        >anything</hi> and <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi> are also Besant markers).
                    His <hi rend="italic">every</hi> and <hi rend="italic">everything</hi> are
                    joined by <hi rend="italic">everybody</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                    >everywhere</hi>; <hi rend="italic">anything</hi> by <hi rend="italic">any</hi>
                    and <hi rend="italic">anywhere</hi>; <hi rend="italic">nothing</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">not</hi> by <hi rend="italic">never</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >no</hi>, <hi rend="italic">nobody</hi>, <hi rend="italic">none</hi>, and
                        <hi rend="italic">nor</hi>; and <hi rend="italic">much</hi> by <hi
                        rend="italic">more</hi>, <hi rend="italic">moreover</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >most</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">mostly</hi> among his markers.
                    Collins&apos;s <hi rend="italic">answered</hi> is joined by <hi
                        rend="italic">answer</hi>, <hi rend="italic">answering</hi>, and <hi
                        rend="italic">unanswerable</hi>; and five of his twenty words are joined by
                    two others: <hi rend="italic">ask</hi>, <hi rend="italic">asked</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">asks</hi>; <hi rend="italic">inquired</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >inquiries</hi>, <hi rend="italic">inquiry</hi>; <hi rend="italic"
                        >leave</hi>, <hi rend="italic">leaving</hi>, <hi rend="italic">left</hi>;
                        <hi rend="italic">person</hi>, <hi rend="italic">personally</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">persons</hi>; <hi rend="italic">suggest</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">suggested</hi>, <hi rend="italic">suggestion</hi>.</p>
                <p> About 600 of the 1,700 distinctive words form groups favored by one author, but
                    only about 175 form split groups, many of which fall into intriguing patterns.
                    Collins uses more contractions, so <hi rend="italic">didn&apos;t</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">doesn&apos;t</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >don&apos;t</hi> are Collins words, but <hi rend="italic">did</hi> and
                        <hi rend="italic">does</hi> are Besant words, and similarly for <hi
                        rend="italic">must</hi>, <hi rend="italic">need</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >should</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">would</hi> and their negative
                    contractions. The singular and possessive forms of <hi rend="italic"
                        >brother</hi>, <hi rend="italic">friend</hi>, <hi rend="italic">sister</hi>,
                    and <hi rend="italic">son</hi> are Collins&apos;s words and the plural forms
                    are Besant&apos;s; the singular vs. plural pattern continues almost without
                    exception in split noun groups. Verbs in <hi rend="italic">-ing </hi>are Collins
                    words and 3rd singular present forms Besant&apos;s. Finally, all nineteen
                    cardinal number marker words are Besant&apos;s, including the numbers <hi
                        rend="italic">one</hi> to <hi rend="italic">ten</hi> (note that
                    Besant&apos;s preferred plural nouns often follow numbers). This
                    extraordinary patterning may not seem particularly surprising, but, so far as I
                    know, it has never been noticed before, and cries out for investigation.</p>
                <p>Two problems with t-testing are its privileging of relatively uninteresting
                    high-frequency words and its inability to cope with words absent from one
                    author. John Burrows&apos;s Zeta addresses both of these problems (Burrows
                    2006). (The specific form used here was developed by Hugh Craig (Craig and
                    Kinney, 2009); for an automated spreadsheet and instructions for performing Zeta
                    analysis see <ptr type="external"
                        target="https://files.nyu.edu/dh3/public/ TheZeta&amp;IotaSpreadsheet.html"
                    />).</p>
                <p>Zeta&apos;s simple calculation begins with the same novels and the same word
                    frequency list used for the t-test, except that personal pronouns and words
                    present in only one author are now included. Zeta is simply the sum of the
                    proportions of Collins sections in which each word occurs and Besant sections in
                    which it does not. Here <hi rend="italic">answered</hi>, the most distinctive
                    Collins word (as in the t-tests), has a Zeta score of 1.8, and is present in 89
                    of 90 Collins sections and absent from 65 of 77 Besant sections. The most
                    distinctive Besant word is again <hi rend="italic">upon</hi>, present in all 77
                    Besant sections and absent from 25 of 90 Collins sections, with a Zeta of 0.28.
                    Below are the twenty most distinctive Zeta words (those also identified by
                    t-testing in bold):</p>

                <p>Besant: <hi rend="bolditalic">upon</hi>, <hi rend="italic">fact</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">presently</hi>, <hi rend="italic">therefore</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">however</hi>, <hi rend="bolditalic">everything</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">real</hi>, <hi rend="italic">whole</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >cannot</hi>, <hi rend="italic">though</hi>, <hi rend="italic">rich</hi>,
                        <hi rend="italic">none</hi>, <hi rend="italic">thousand</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">except</hi>, <hi rend="italic">fifty</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >ago</hi>, <hi rend="bolditalic">because</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                    >papers</hi>, <hi rend="italic">also</hi>, <hi rend="italic">twenty</hi></p>
                <p>Collins: <hi rend="bolditalic">answered</hi>, <hi rend="bolditalic">Mrs</hi>, <hi
                        rend="bolditalic">Miss</hi>, <hi rend="bolditalic">excuse</hi>, <hi
                        rend="bolditalic">suggested</hi>, <hi rend="bolditalic">resumed</hi>, <hi
                        rend="bolditalic">reminded</hi>, <hi rend="italic">doctor</hi>, <hi
                        rend="bolditalic">inquired</hi>, <hi rend="bolditalic">creature</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">notice</hi>, <hi rend="italic">circumstances</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">tone</hi>, <hi rend="italic">idea</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >temper</hi>, <hi rend="italic">object</hi>, <hi rend="italic">sense</hi>,
                        <hi rend="italic">feeling</hi>, <hi rend="italic">governess</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">impression</hi></p>
                <p>As noted above, Zeta marker words are less frequent than t-tested words. Only two
                    Zeta marker words rank in the top 100 in the novels, compared to 20 of the
                    t-tested words. About 3/4 of the 1000 t-tested marker words are also among the
                    1000 Zeta markers. Among the 2000 Zeta words are 275 words occurring in only one
                    author; 59 form new single-author families, 27 join existing single-author
                    families, and only 21 form split families.</p>
                <p>The Zeta words also effectively detect the change of authorship in <hi
                        rend="italic">Blind Love</hi>. In the scatter graph in Fig. 3, the axes show
                    the percentages of all the word types (unique words) in each section that are
                    Besant or Collins marker words (longer texts are divided into 4000-words
                    sections; the labels for even-numbered Collins sections of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Blind Love</hi> are removed; only a few sections of other novels are
                    included). Note how distinct Besant&apos;s chapters of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Blind Love</hi> are from Collins’s, though many of them are pulled toward
                    Collins. This graph also includes <hi rend="italic">The Case of Mr. Lucraft</hi>
                    (Case in bold), jointly written by Besant and James Rice; it suggests, as has
                    been argued (Boege 1956: 251-65), that Besant did most of the actual
                    writing.</p>
                <p>
                    <figure xml:id="fig3">
                        <head>Fig. 3. <hi rend="italic">Besant, Collins, Blind Love: Zeta
                                Analysis</hi></head>
                        <graphic url="658_Fig3.tif" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                            mimeType="image/tif"/>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>T-tests and Zeta analysis are both effective authorship attribution methods that
                    produce lists of characteristic vocabulary for the authors being compared. Both
                    identify morphological and semantic families of words and uncover
                    extraordinarily consistent patterns and puzzling inconsistencies that suggest
                    new directions for literary and stylistic analysis.</p>

            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Boege, F.</author>
                        <date>1956</date>
                        <title level="a">Sir Walter Besant: Novelist. Part One</title>
                        <title level="j">Nineteenth-Century Fiction</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">10</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">249-280</biblScope>

                    </bibl>

                    <bibl>
                        <author>Burrows, J. F.</author>
                        <date>1992</date>
                        <title level="a">Not Unless You Ask Nicely: The Interpretative Nexus Between
                            Analysis and Information</title>
                        <title level="j">LLC</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">91-109</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Burrows, J. F.</author>
                        <date>2006</date>
                        <title level="a">All the Way Through: Testing for Authorship in Different
                            Frequency Strata</title>
                        <title level="j">LLC</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">22</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">27-47</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Collins, W.</author>
                        <date>2003</date>
                        <title level="m">Blind Love</title>
                        <editor>Bachman, M.</editor>
                        <editor>Cox, D.</editor>
                        <publisher>Broadview Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Peterborough, Ont.</pubPlace>

                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Collins, W.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="m">Blind Love</title>
                        <publisher>Chatto &amp; Windus</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <ptr type="external"
                            target="http://ia311528.us.archive.org/0/items/blindlove00colluoft/blindlove00colluoft.pdf"/>
                        <date type="visited">18th March 2009</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <editor>Craig, H.</editor>
                        <editor>Kinney, A.,</editor>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="m">Shakespeare, Computers, and the Mystery of
                            Authorship</title>
                        <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>

                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
