<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-680">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The ecology of longevity: the relevance of evolutionary theory for digital
                    preservation</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Doorn, Peter</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Data Archiving and Networked Services</orgName>, <country>Netherlands</country></affiliation>
                    <email>peter.doorn@dans.knaw.nl</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Roorda, Dirk</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Data Archiving and Networked Services</orgName>, <country>Netherlands</country></affiliation>
                    <email>dirk.roorda@dans.knaw.nl</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-28</date>
                <name>GF</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Software and data can be considered as digital organisms that function in a
                    &quot;digital ecosystem&quot; of computers. The concept of ecology has been
                    borrowed from biology by other disciplines for explaining or describing a
                    variety of phenomena. In some cases ecology and other concepts from evolutionary
                    theory are only used as metaphors; in other cases attempts have been made to
                    apply an adapted version of the theory to the evolution of non-biological
                    phenomena. </p>
                <p>We think it makes sense to borrow the notions from evolutionary theory in
                    thinking about digital longevity. In this paper we will explore the potential of
                    Darwin&apos;s theory as an explanatory framework for digital survival. </p>
                <p>The construction of a theoretical foundation serves to answer questions of why
                    some criteria or characteristics will guarantee the &quot;survival&quot; of
                    digital objects better than other ones. Taking an evolutionary view will also
                    make clear that there is no such thing as digital permanence for eternity: some
                    objects only have better <hi rend="italic">chances</hi> to survive than other
                    ones. In computing technology, there is a struggle of survival of the fittest
                    going on. In this struggle, new technologies arise as modifications or
                    adaptations of earlier technologies and the older ones die out when newer
                    technologies are stronger or better suited for their tasks. The digital objects
                    that are already in existence have to be adapted to the new technological
                    surroundings, otherwise they become extinct. </p>
                <p>Spencer originally coined the phrase &quot;survival of the fittest&quot; in 1864,
                    drawing parallels between his ideas of economics and Darwin&apos;s theory of
                    evolution, which is driven by &quot;natural selection&quot;. With respect to
                    digital objects, it is people who are actively or passively involved in making
                    the selections, thus deciding which digital objects survive and which do not. </p>
                <p>As electronic digital data can only be understood using computers and software to
                    &quot;translate&quot; them into visible or audible form, the media and data
                    formats that are specific for hard- and software change according to the same
                    evolutionary principles. If we accept this view, we can start to ask ourselves:
                    which characteristics (comparable to the &quot;genetic properties&quot; of
                    living organisms) may influence the chances of digital survival of data? This is
                    however not unproblematic, as it is typically with hindsight that we see which
                    (traits in) a biological species have survived and how the evolutionary process
                    took place. The explanatory power of evolution theory is a posteriori, not a
                    priori. It may therefore be difficult to predict which traits are good for
                    survival. </p>
                <p>We will explore the possible use of the concept of evolvability, which is usually
                    defined as the ability of a population of organisms to generate genetic
                    diversity, hence giving a measure of an organism&apos;s ability to evolve. Maybe
                    there is a parallel here with respect to digital objects. For instance, if we
                    look at several formats for Microsoft Word (.doc, .rtf, .html, .xml (2003),
                    .ooxml) then we see an increase in usability/interchangeability, and hence
                    probably: evolvability. </p>
                <p>We can break down the survival problem to questions concerning: <xmt:uList>
                        <item>The physical attributes of the media (tape, disk, etc.)</item>
                        <item>The media format (density, size, etc.)</item>
                        <item>The data content (integrity of the bits and bytes)</item>
                        <item>The data format (the structure of the bits and bytes)</item>
                        <item>The metadata content (the substantial description of the data)</item>
                        <item>The metadata format (the format in which the metadata is
                            described)</item>
                        <item>The interlinking (the degree to which data is linked both internally
                            and externally); a web of interlinked information is an ecosystem of its
                            own.</item>
                    </xmt:uList>
                </p>
                <p>We will demonstrate how digital preservation strategies such as technology
                    preservation, software emulation, and data migration fit in an overarching
                    evolutionary framework. The ecological approach also shows that it makes no
                    sense to try to express the time horizon for the preservation of digital objects
                    as a specific or indefinite period of time, but that we can better think in
                    terms of &quot;chances of survival&quot;. </p>
                <p>The evolutionary framework can be used to argue why certain attributes and
                    formats are more likely to survive than others. Also, analogous to natural
                    selection, we will make clear that there is no single &quot;best&quot; strategy
                    for survival of digital data. Some factors simply increase the chances of
                    digital longevity, whereas other factors reduce these chances. Good factors for
                    longevity may be bad for other desired characteristics. For example: stripping
                    executable information from data improves its longevity, but hinders its
                    functionality. It may also be so that some factors are intensely ambiguous for
                    longevity. We may now think that &quot;wrapping&quot; text in WordPerfect in the
                    1990s was (with hindsight) not so good for survival, and that packaging it in
                    Microsoft Word seems acceptable. This is probably related to the status (or
                    market dominance) of the software packages. Similarly, packaging data in SGML in
                    1990 might have been not so good, while packaging it in XML in 2009 seems
                    excellent. In the end, the environment determines what was good and what was bad
                    for longevity. </p>
                <p>So, when the whole &quot;technological ecosystem&quot; changes, what was well
                    adapted before the change may appear to be ill suited in the next technological
                    phase. Digital preservation strategies can use the principle of digital
                    selection in order to maximize the adaptation of digital objects to their
                    environment, thus increasing their chances of digital longevity. </p>
                <p>Whether it makes sense to apply evolution theory to digital curation can be
                    studied by looking at a number of parallels in other scientific domains. We will
                    deal briefly with attempts to use Darwin&apos;s ideas in the social sciences and
                    in technology. In the social sciences the idea of a &quot;social ecology&quot;
                    was already applied and empirically tested in the 1920s by, among others, Robert
                    Park and Ernest Burgess of the &quot;Chicago School&quot; of urban ecology. With
                    respect to man-created systems it is probably better to use the ideas on
                    evolution by Lamarck. Lamarckism is the idea that an organism can pass on
                    characteristics that it acquired during its lifetime to its offspring (also
                    known as heritability of acquired characteristics or soft inheritance). </p>
                <p>Several researchers have proposed that Lamarckian evolution may be accurately
                    applied to cultural evolution. Human culture can be looked upon as an ecological
                    niche-like phenomenon, where the effects of cultural niche construction are
                    transmissible from one generation to the next. Ecological notions on the
                    evolution of software, in which ideas and characteristics of programming
                    languages compete with each other, have been formulated in information science.
                    Inheritance is an important concept with an evolutionary basis. </p>
                <p>The development of open source software has also been described as evolving in a
                    Lamarckian fashion. Ensuring free access and enabling modification at each stage
                    in the process means that the evolution of software occurs in the fast
                    Lamarckian mode: each favourable acquired characteristic of others&apos; work
                    can be directly inherited. </p>
                <p>Kauffman and Dennett point out the parallels between biological evolution and
                    technological evolution. They distinguish two stages: (i) explosion of the
                    number of greatly different designs when there are still many unoccupied niches;
                    (ii) microevolution where the existing designs are optimised for competition in
                    existing niches. </p>
                <p>It is also useful to compare the selection and survival of digital information
                    with that of analogue information. In both cases there is &quot;information
                    selection&quot; and evolution. What makes the digital world so different from
                    the analogue world? </p>
                <p>Next we will treat a few examples of the evolution of computing technologies,
                    software, file formats and data sets, which will illustrate how well
                    evolutionary theory is suited for explaining what has happened empirically. It
                    makes sense to look backwards and use evidence from the – still very short –
                    historical evolution of computing technology since the 1940s and &apos;50s. Can
                    we still read the first image, the first word processor file, the first
                    database, the first web page, email or pdf-file? If yes, how come this is still
                    possible? If not, why? And how did the formats of those data types (probably
                    equivalent to the taxonomical rank of the <hi rend="italic">genus</hi> in
                    biology) evolve, and which abandoned file formats (&quot;<hi rend="italic"
                        >species</hi>&quot;) can still be read today? </p>
                <p>Maybe there is a manifestation of genotype/phenotype here, where the application
                    can be considered as the phenotype. Applications struggle with each other in the
                    &quot;econosphere&quot; of consumers. The surviving application dictates the
                    data format. If there are two strong surviving applications in a domain, you get
                    peer-to-peer data convertors. If there are many, weaker survivors, you get
                    interchange formats, which are better for preservation. A familiar lesson is not
                    to rely on monopolists. </p>
                <p>Finally, there is a marked tendency among data curators to set criteria for
                    &quot;trusted digital repositories&quot;, the nature reserves of the digital
                    world. On the basis of the evolutionary ideas expressed in this paper, it makes
                    sense not to make such criteria too narrow. They should be chosen in such a way
                    that they make use of the &quot;natural&quot; evolutionary processes of
                    technology and digital objects, making sure that what is threatened by
                    extinction can be rescued in an effective way. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
