<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-657">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Visualization and Analysis of Visiting Styles in 3D Virtual Museums</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sookhanaphibarn, Kingkarn</name>
                    <affiliation>Intelligent Computer Entertainment Laboratory Global COE Program in
                        Digital Humanities for Japanese Arts and Cultures <orgName>Ritsumeikan
                        University</orgName> <reg><country>Japan</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>kingkarn@ice.ci.ritsumei.ac.jp</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Thawonmas, Ruck</name>
                    <affiliation>Intelligent Computer Entertainment Laboratory Global COE Program in
                        Digital Humanities for Japanese Arts and Cultures <orgName>Ritsumeikan
                        University</orgName> <reg><country>Japan</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>ruck@ci.ritsumei.ac.jp</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-05-01</date>
                <name>NG</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>A virtual museum is a cyberspace in persistent virtual worlds, such as Second Life,
                for displaying digitalized heritage documents. Urban et. al. (2007) reported that
                over 150 sites in Second Life (SL) were developed for education and museum
                activities. Virtual museums in SL offer visitors opportunities to engage in opening
                art exhibitions, discuss with specialists, and enjoy exploring collections of the
                wide range of artifacts. Those artifacts displayed in the virtual museums vary from
                3D documents of the world heritages to fictional creations (Rothfarb, R. and
                Doherty, P., 2007). </p>
            <p>This paper aims at visualization and analysis of visitor behaviors in 3D virtual
                museums. Without loss of generality, we focused on a museum in Second Life, named
                Ritsumeikan Digital Archive Pavilion (RDAP) as shown in Figures 1-2. The museum was
                used in this paper for developing a prototype of our visualization and analysis
                tool. Efficient visualization of the user movement is very useful for analyzing
                his/her behaviors, in an implicit manner, in order to extract the disclosed
                information of individuals in the cyberspace.</p>
            <p>Applications of the proposed visualization method include the following: <xmt:oList
                    rend="arabic">
                    <item>The curators can design the exhibit space based on the majority of
                        visitors as illustrated in Section 3. </item>
                    <item>The storytelling of an individual visitor can be expressed as a sequence
                        of screenshots capturing the most favored exhibits (as described in Fujita,
                        H. et al., 2008). </item>
                    <item>A guide system can be applied so as to achieve a satisfactory museum tour
                        as introduced by Sookhanaphibarn and Thawonmas.</item>
                </xmt:oList>
            </p>
            <p>
                <figure xml:id="fig1">
                    <graphic url="657_Fig1.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                        mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    <head>Figure 1. Kimono exhibition in Ritsumeikan Digital Archive Pavilion
                        (RDAP)</head>
                </figure>
            </p>
            <p>
                <figure xml:id="fig2">
                    <graphic url="657_Fig2.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                        mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    <head>Figure 2. Floor plan of RDAP with the locations of 19 Kimono objects
                        denoted by a small solid square</head>
                </figure>
            </p>
            <div>
                <head>Visualization and analysis of visiting patterns</head>
                <p>To validate our visualization approach, 36 avatars’ movements in RDAP were
                    synthesized for obtaining four visiting styles. These styles, based on the
                    metaphor of animal behavior, are ant, fish, grasshopper, and butterfly styles as
                    follows (Veron, E. &amp; Levasseur, M., 1983; Chittaro, L., 2004): <xmt:oList
                        rend="arabic">
                        <item>The ant visitors spend quite a long time to observe all exhibits and
                            walk close to exhibits, but avoid empty spaces. </item>
                        <item>The fish visitors prefer to move to and stop over at empty spaces, but
                            avoid areas near exhibits. </item>
                        <item>The grasshopper visitors spend a long time to see selected exhibits,
                            but ignore the rest of exhibits. </item>
                        <item>The butterfly visitors observe almost exhibits, but spend varied times
                            to observe each exhibit. </item>
                    </xmt:oList>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Local Visualization</head>
                <p>Tracing the user movement in Second Life was achieved by using the provided
                    Linden Second Life script, named sensor function. The sensor function detects
                    and reports the user position (<hi rend="italic">x,y</hi>) within the particular
                    range. It repeats every particular time interval. In this paper, the considered
                    data consist of the three dimensional positions of an individual visitor and
                    their corresponding time spent.</p>
                <p>Figure 3 shows four visiting paths in RDAP. The visualization consists of line
                    segments and white dots. A colored line segment is a part of the avatar
                    movement. A white dot represents the location of a Kimono object.</p>
                <p>The avatar’s path is displayed with the spectrum colors containing red, orange,
                    yellow, green, cyan, blue, and violet. A path is in the form of connecting
                    segments from red to violet. The session is equally divided in time into 7
                    periods in the ascending order from red to violet. The color of a particular
                    segment indicates the passage of time.</p>
                <p>The length of a segment inversely represents the time spent. For example, the
                    avatar as shown in Figure 3 (a) spent the longest time in the first period
                    recognizable from the shortest red segment. The avatar started moving faster
                    during the last two periods as denoted by longer blue and violet. In our
                    visualization, the shorter a segment is, the longer an avatar spends time in
                    that particular area. </p>
                <p>Absent colors show that a longer time was spent than one period. For example, no
                    red and orange segments are shown in Figure 3 (b) because the avatar spent time
                    from the first period to the third near the entrance denoted by the yellow area.
                    If an avatar spends too much time at a particular position exceeding the period
                    length, then the color corresponding to that period will be skipped.</p>
                <p>
                    <figure xml:id="fig3-a">
                        <graphic url="657_Fig3-a.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="center" width="40mm"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>(a) Ant visiting style</head>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="fig3-b">
                        <graphic url="657_Fig3-b.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="center"  width="40mm"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>(b) Fish visiting style</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <figure xml:id="fig3-c">
                        <graphic url="657_Fig3-c.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="center"  width="40mm"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>(c) Grasshopper visiting style</head>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="fig3-d">
                        <graphic url="657_Fig3-d.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="center"  width="40mm"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>(d) Butterfly visiting style</head>
                        <head>Figure 3: Visualization of four visiting styles in RDAP. These color
                            figures will be provided in URL below.
                            http://www.ice.ci.ritsumei.ac.jp/~kingkarn/</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Analysis</head>
                <p>Our visualization approach can describe the aforementioned visiting styles. Ant,
                    Fish, Grasshopper, and Butterfly visiting styles are displayed on totally
                    different vivid graphic graphs. Hence, our tool is useful for distinguishing the
                    visiting types. </p>
                <p>The Ant visiting style is shown in Figure 3 (a). The avatar’s path was along the
                    white dots. It means that the visitor walked close to Kimono objects in order to
                    look at them in detail. The path contained its segments of nearly equal length,
                    indicating that the visitor spent his/her time with the exhibits almost
                    equally.</p>
                <p>The Fish visiting style is shown in Figure 3 (b). The avatar’s path was limited
                    to the empty space between two exhibit rows. It means that this visitor
                    preferred to stroll to take the atmosphere of the gallery. Most segments far
                    from the white dots depict that the avatar did not pay attention to the Japanese
                    art imposed on Kimonos. The Grasshopper visiting style is shown in Figure 3 (c).
                    The avatar’s path was drawn as a triangle polygon having the smaller area than
                    that of the Ant style. Its segments represent a kind of diagonally walking
                    across the gallery to the interesting exhibits.</p>
                <p>The Butterfly visiting style is shown in Figure 3 (d). The avatar’s path was the
                    longest path of the four styles. Its segments show plenty of diagonally walking
                    across the gallery to most exhibits. The diagonal segment does not imply his/her
                    preference, but this unorganized visit does not follow a well structured
                    sequence like the Ant.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Global Visualization</head>
                <p>The global visualization of all visitors in each category is displayed in Figure
                    4. The methodology of this global visualization consists of <xmt:oList
                        rend="arabic">
                        <item>visiting style identification,</item>
                        <item>trace accumulation of all users belonging to the same visiting style,
                            and</item>
                        <item>contrast enhancement in order to highlight the most popular
                            route.</item>
                    </xmt:oList>
                </p>
                <p>Using the synthesized data of 36 visitors, the global visualization of each
                    visiting style can guide curators to rotate the museum items and arrange the
                    sequence of items. Table 1 summarizes the interesting or skipped items
                    associated with the visiting styles. An interesting item (I) can be determined
                    if its observation area is darkened; otherwise, the item (S) is considerably
                    ignored. The item numbers are those assigned in Figure 2.</p>
                <p>Curators can design an efficient exhibition based on the majority of visitors. It
                    is assumed that our museums consist of four rooms each of which the majority of
                    visitors are ant, fish, grasshopper and butterfly, respectively. <xmt:oList
                        rend="arabic">
                        <item>The ant room: the 13th item is possibly not related to others;
                            therefore, a new one should be substituted.</item>
                        <item>The fish room: the visitors prefer to pass slowly through the room.
                            Therefore, all exhibits should be placed along both sides of the main
                            path. The exit should be on either side of the entrance to prevent
                            congestion. </item>
                        <item>The grasshopper room: half of the items are possibly not visitor
                            attraction for busy people; on the other hand, they are perhaps varying
                            and unrelated. Therefore, the curators should be re-design the
                            exhibition room; in addition, the skipped items should be replaced with
                            others more related to those visited.</item>
                        <item>The butterfly room: the visit routes should be unorganized; therefore,
                            the sequence of exhibits should be rearranged and some skipped items
                            should be replaced/removed, accordingly.</item>
                    </xmt:oList>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <figure xml:id="fig4-a">
                        <graphic url="657_Fig4-a.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="center"  width="40mm"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>(a) Common paths of ant visitors</head>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="fig4-b">
                        <graphic url="657_Fig4-b.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="center"  width="40mm"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>(b) Common paths of fish visitors</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <figure xml:id="fig4-c">
                        <graphic url="657_Fig4-c.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="center"  width="40mm"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>(c) Common paths of grasshopper visitors</head>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="fig4-d">
                        <graphic url="657_Fig4-d.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="center"  width="40mm"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>(d) Common paths of butterfly visitors</head>
                        <head>Figure 4. Visualization of common paths based on four visiting styles,
                            each of a group of seven visitors. Kimono exhibits and the user’s paths
                            are denoted by red dots and blue lines. The color intensity indicates
                            the frequency of visits. The darker blue the visualization shows, the
                            more visitors spend time at that particular area.</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <table>
                        <head>Table 1. Example of visual analytics from Figure 4 showing the
                            interesting and skipped items in RDAP are as denoted by “I” and “S”,
                            respectively</head>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="label">Items</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Ant</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Grasshopper</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Butterfly</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>S</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>S</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>4</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>5</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>6</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>S</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>7</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>8</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>S</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>9</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>S</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>10</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>S</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>11</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>S</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>12</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>13</cell>
                            <cell>S</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>S</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>14</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>S</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>15</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>S</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>16</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>17</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>18</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>S</cell>
                            <cell>S</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>19</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                            <cell>I</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Urban, R., Twidale, M.B. and Marty, P.F. </author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">Second Life for Museums and Archeological Modeling</title>
                        <title level="m"> Digital Humanities 2007, Conference Abstracts Book</title>
                        <date type="visited">15 Nov 2009</date>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dh2007/abstracts/xhtml.xq?id=254"
                        />
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Rothfarb, R. and Doherty, P. </author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">Creating Museum Content and Community in Second
                            Life</title>
                        <title level="m">Museums and the Web 2007: Proceedings</title>
                        <editor>J. Trant and D. Bearman</editor>
                        <publisher>Archives &amp; Museum Informatics</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Toronto</pubPlace>
                        <date type="visited">3 August 2009</date>
                        <ptr target="http://www.archimuse.com/mw2007/papers/rothfarb/rothfarb.html"
                        />
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Fujita, H. and Arikawa, M. </author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">Animation of Mapped Photo Collections for
                            Storytelling</title>
                        <title level="j">IEICE Trans. INF &amp; SYST</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">Vol. E91-D, No. 6</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">1681-1692</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Sookhanaphibarn, K. and Thawonmas, R. </author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">A Movement Data Analysis and Synthesis Tool for Museum
                            Visitors’ Behaviors</title>
                        <title level="j">Lecture Notes in Computer Science. Subseries of Information
                            Systems and Applications, incl. Internet/Web, and HCI</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">Vol. 5879</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">144-154</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Veron, E. &amp; Levasseur, M</author>
                        <date>1983</date>
                        <title level="m">Ethnographie de l'exposition. L'espace, le corps et le
                            sens</title>
                        <publisher>Bibliothque publique d'Information. Centre Georges
                            Pompidou</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Chittaro, L. and Leronutti, L.</author>
                        <date>2004</date>
                        <title level="a">A Visual Tool for Tracing Users’ Behavior in Virtual
                            Environments</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Proceedings of the Working Conference on
                            Advanced Visual Interfaces, AVI’04 ACM</title>
                        <biblScope type="pp">40-47</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
