<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-755">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Authorship Discontinuities of El Ingenioso Hidalgo don Quijote de la Mancha
                    as detected by Mixture-of-Experts</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Coufal, Christopher</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Duquesne University</orgName> <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>coufalc@duq.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Juola, Patrick</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Duquesne University</orgName> <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>juola@mathcs.duq.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-29</date>
                <name>GF</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>In the literary world, authorship of great novels is like writing a great piece
                    of music; while there may never be a perfect way to determine if someone wrote a
                    particular work or not, equations and algorithms have been developed in
                    information theory and statistics to help those trying to discover the true
                    authorship of contested written works. Because no method is perfect, using a set
                    of methods on the same works can be used to give high probabilities of
                    authorship. The JGAAP system houses a collection of methods such as Histogram
                    Distance and Manhattan Distance and event sets such as word bigrams and
                    character trigrams to allow users to perform multiple tests on contested works
                    to see if the supposed author is actually the author by comparing samples from
                    both the contested author and other possible authors. </p>
                <p>We apply this framework and show a notable discontinuity in the authorial style
                    of the novel <hi rend="italic">El Ingenioso Hidalgo don Quijote de la
                        Mancha</hi>, better known as <hi rend="italic">Don Quijote</hi> (or <hi
                        rend="italic">Don Quixote</hi>).</p>
            <div>
                <head>Background</head>
                <p>While there have been skeptics and scholars alike that have doubted Miguel de
                    Cervantes Saavadre&apos;s true authorship of the entirety of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Don Quijote</hi>, no one had tested whether or not Cervantes was in fact
                    the true author of the whole of <hi rend="italic">Don Quijote</hi>. The purpose
                    of using the JGAAP system was to either give merit to or disprove this theory.
                    By comparing to other authors who wrote works at about the same time <hi
                        rend="italic">Don Quijote</hi> was written, the JGAAP system would test to
                    see if the text that Cervantes supposedly wrote was closer to the first volume
                    of <hi rend="italic">Don Quijote</hi> or closer to other authors of the same
                    time period. If a definitive break could be established between where the
                    program attributed Cervantes as the author and where it did not, that would
                    suggest either a major style shift or the presence of another author different
                    from Cervantes, while no break at all would suggest that Cervantes was in fact
                    the true author of the second volume of <hi rend="italic">Don Quijote</hi>,
                    assuming that he was also the author of the first volume. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Methods and Materials</head>
                <p>For this authorship attribution, the program JGAAP 4.0 was downloaded from <ref
                        target="http://www.jgaap.com" rend="newWindow" type="external"
                        >http://www.jgaap.com</ref>, developed by Patrick Juola at Duquesne
                    University. The <hi rend="italic">Don Quijote</hi> text used was acquired from
                    Project Gutenburg at <ref target="http://www.projectgutenburg.org"
                        rend="newWindow" type="external">http://www.projectgutenburg.org</ref>. The
                    full text of Don Quijote was then stripped of the introductions and separated
                    into chapters by volume. The first volume was then set as the basis for Miguel
                    de Cervantes&apos; original authorship. Every third chapter, starting with
                    chapter three, was used as the base case for Cervantes&apos; work. Two other
                    authors used for comparison, Fransisco de Quevedo and Mateo Alemán, were also
                    used. Quevedo&apos;s, <hi rend="italic">Historia de la vida del Buscón, llamado
                        Don Pablos, ejemplo de vagamundos y espejo de tacaños and Alemán&apos;s
                        Guzmán del Alfarache</hi> were also taken from Project Gutenburg and broken
                    into roughly the same number of chapter-type sections as the number of chapters
                    used for Cervantes&apos; <hi rend="italic">Don Quijote</hi>. In order to make
                    sure that Cervantes&apos; was actually the author of volume one of <hi
                        rend="italic">Don Quijote</hi>, every chapter not used in the base case was
                    compared to the base chapters, Quevedo&apos;s work, and Alemán&apos;s work. Each
                    test used JGAAP&apos;s Normalize Whitespace, Strip Punctuation, and Unify Case
                    canonicizers on all of the documents. Five event sets - Word, WordBiGram,
                    WordTriGram, WordTetraGram, and Word Length - were all paired with nine analysis
                    methods - Camberra Distance, Cosine Distance, RN Cross Entropy, Histogram
                    Distance, Kullback Leibler Divergence, Levenshtein Distance, Manhattan Distance,
                    KS Distance, and Naive Bayes Classifier, for a total of 45 unique event
                    set-analysis methods. Once the first volume of Cervantes&apos; work was
                    confirmed to be uniformly Cervantes&apos;, volume two of <hi rend="italic">Don
                        Quijote</hi> was tested in the same manner as the first volume in order to
                    provide an accurate analysis. </p>
                <p>We apply a mixture-of-experts approach to the evaluation of authorship. Each
                    different method is treated as a single &quot;expert&quot; in different aspects
                    of authorial style, and permitted to vote on who (among the candidates) is the
                    author of any specific fragment. If all 45 test &quot;experts&quot; vote on
                    Cervantes, we consider this to be strong evidence supporting his authorship,
                    while if only 5 or so of the 45 consider Cervantes to be the most likely author,
                    we consider this to be evidence <hi rend="italic">against</hi>. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Results</head>
                <p>As a result of the analysis on the second volume of <hi rend="italic">Don
                        Quijote</hi>, the JGAAP program indicated that starting at chapter 6
                    Cervantes was not the author. Out of the 45 tests run on each chapter, the
                    chapters in the first volume had a mean of 37.54 occurrences of Cervantes as the
                    author with a standard deviation of .852. The first five chapters of the second
                    volume had a mean of 36.50 occurrences of Cervantes as the author with a
                    standard deviation of 1.517. Chapters 6-74 of the second volume, however, had a
                    mean of 4.90 occurrences of Cervantes as the author with a standard deviation of
                    1.436. This radical shift in authorship means either Cervantes completely
                    shifted his writing technique or he did not write the latter 69 chapters of the
                    second volume of <hi rend="italic">Don Quijote</hi>. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Discussion</head>
                <p>While there are people who are skeptic about the authorship of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Don Quijote</hi>, nothing up until now has given those claims any grounds
                    other than speculations based on inconsistencies in the text. Although this
                    analysis does not guarantee that Cervantes did not write the last 69 chapters of
                    the second volume, it does make the probability of that claim much greater.
                    This, in part, is due to the fact that none of the tests in JGAAP has been
                    tested enough to show that it will work for all documents. As further analysis
                    of the methods continues, the results of the tests used in this authorship
                    attribution will most likely validate these results. As tests and methods prove
                    to not work, the analysis will be redone with these tests omitted from the
                    analysis giving a more accurate result. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <!--<back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        REFERENCE
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>-->
    </text>
</TEI>
