<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-846">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>A New Digital Method for a New Literary Problem: A Proposed Methodology for
                    Bridging the "Generalist" - "Specialist" Divide in the Study of World
                    Literature</title>
                <author><name>Howell, Sonia</name>
                    <affiliation>School of English and Media Studies, <orgName>National University
                            of Ireland, Maynooth</orgName>, Maynooth Co. Kildare,
                            <country>Ireland</country></affiliation>
                    <email>sonia.howell@nuim.ie</email>
                </author>
                <author><name>Keating, John G.</name>
                    <affiliation>An Foras Feasa:The Institute for Research in Irish Historical and
                        Cultural Traditions, <orgName>National University of Ireland,
                            Maynooth</orgName>, Maynooth Co. Kildare,
                        <country>Ireland</country></affiliation>
                    <email>john.keating@nuim.ie</email>
                </author>
                <author><name>Kelleher, Margaret</name>
                    <affiliation>An Foras Feasa:The Institute for Research in Irish Historical and
                        Cultural Traditions, <orgName>National University of Ireland,
                            Maynooth</orgName>, Maynooth Co. Kildare,
                        <country>Ireland</country></affiliation>
                    <email>margaret.kelleher@nuim.ie</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-40-16</date>
                <name>CD</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>This paper is situated within the debate between “specialist” and “generalist”
                methods of analysis in the study of world literature. It is argued that a systemic
                linguistic discourse analysis of appropriately encoded text passages can provide a
                methodology which can be utilised to interrogate the national and international
                demarcations of comparative literary analysis. A case study consisting of a textual
                analysis of the dialogical relationship between patient and therapist in a
                “factional”, i.e. works of fiction, which draw upon historical fact. Irish and
                English novel is provided. The benefits of the results yielded to current
                understandings of national literature and definitions of world literature are
                discussed.</p>
            <p> In 1827, the German poet, Johann Wolfgang von Goethe, declared to his young disciple
                Johann Peter Eckermann that “National literature is now a rather unmeaning term; the
                epoch of world literature is at hand, and everyone must strive to hasten its
                approach” (Eckermann, cited in [<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl3">Damrosch, 2003b,
                    p. 1</ref>]). History informs us however that Goethe was premature in his
                heralding of a new age of “postnational” literature, as up until recently all
                literatures tended to have been studied along national lines [<ref type="internal"
                    cRef="bibl4">Dimock, 2006, pp. 2-5</ref>]. Yet in more recent decades, nations
                and, by extension, “national” literatures have become increasingly under threat in
                their sovereignty over all elements of human life due to the homogenising and
                heterogenising effects of globalisation. Globalisation is defined by Malcolm Waters
                as being “a social process in which the constraints of geography on social and
                cultural arrangements recede and in which people become increasingly aware that they
                are receding” [<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl12">Waters, 1995, p. 3</ref>]. It is
                not surprising therefore, that in an age where national boundaries, both physical
                and mental, are become increasingly insignificant and blurred, we find a renewed
                interest in Goethe’s concept of <hi rend="italic">Weltliteratur</hi>.</p>
            <p>As with all things new, the emerging discipline of world literature has evoked fear
                and reservations among literary scholars. According to David Damrosch, the
                possibility of recognizing the ongoing, vital presence of the national within the
                life of world literature poses enormous problems for the study of world literature
                    [<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl2">Damrosch, 2003a, p. 514</ref>]. Thus the
                field tends to be divided into “specialists”, those who are concerned with national
                literatures, and “generalists”, those who are interested in studying global
                patterns. But instead of this either/or method, Damrosch maintains that what is need
                is a method that can mediate between broad and often reductive overviews and
                intensive, but often atomistic close readings [p. 519]. As Franco Moretti argues,
                “we must find a way to combine the individual who reads a single work with great
                collective efforts and vision” [<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl9">Sutherland, 2006,
                    Monday 9 January, 2006</ref>]. This paper argues that a combination of Systemic
                Functional Linguistics and Digital Humanities offers one way whereby this may be
                achieved.</p>
            <p>The complexities involved in the interpreting of “literary language” for electronic
                media have perhaps posited the greatest deterrent for literary scholars in embracing
                digital humanities to date. The pioneering work of scholars such as Willard McCarty
                and Jerome McGann (among others) unfortunately remain the exception among their
                peers in the field of literary studies. The majority within the discipline retain
                the fear that computer based analysis of texts can only reveal “broad sweeping
                patterns” within literary works. Interestingly, this fear echoes the reservations
                that are held about the theoretical methods deployed by “generalists” in the study
                of world literature. Contrary to both these fears, this paper will argue that
                computer-based literary research can be utilized to provide both a means of analysis
                for the specificities of national literatures, while also serving as a tool for
                carrying out comparative textual analysis at an international scale. We wish to
                present to the following methodology to the community.</p>
            <div>
                <head>Case Study: The Patient-Therapist Relationship in Literature</head>
                <p>This project will consist of an analysis of a passage of dialogue between patient
                    and therapist in Sebastian Barry’s <hi rend="italic">The Secret Scripture</hi>
                    (2008) and Pat Barker’s <hi rend="italic">Regeneration</hi> (1995). For the
                    purpose of this study, we have chosen a novel by an Irish writer and an English
                    writer respectively. Given that this methodology is in its infancy, it is
                    presumed best to begin with two texts written in the same language and which
                    originate from countries of similar cultural systems. <hi rend="italic">The
                        Secret Scripture</hi> is set in present day Ireland but the narrative is
                    made up of a double narrative; the personal recollections of Roseanne Clear, who
                    was incarcerated in a mental institution during the mid twentieth century, and
                    the account by the psychiatrist, Dr. Greene, of his own investigation into
                    Roseanne’s admittance into the hospital. <hi rend="italic">Regeneration</hi> is
                    based on the real-life experiences of British army officers being treated for
                    shell shock during World War I at Craiglockhart War Hospital in Edinburgh. Its
                    narrative relays the treatment of soldiers suffering mental break down. It is
                    shaped predominately around the discussions which the psychiatrist, Dr. Rivers,
                    has with a number of patients within the asylum in which he works. Both novels
                    are centered around events which have caused psychological distress to the
                    individual characters, but which have also caused what is known as ‘cultural
                        trauma’<note>Neil J. Smelser defines cultural trauma as being a memory
                        accepted and publicly given credence by a relevant membership group and
                        evoking an event or situation which is a) laden with negative effect, b)
                        represented as indelible, and c) regarded as threatening a society's
                        existence or violating one or more of its fundamental cultural
                        presuppositions (Smelser cited in [Alexander et al., 2004, p. 44])</note> to
                    the nations in which they are set.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Methodology</head>
                <p>Our method of analysis is based on Systemic functional linguistics (SFL) which is
                    a model of grammar that was developed by Michael Halliday in the 1960s [<ref
                        type="internal" cRef="bibl5">Halliday, 1976</ref>, <ref type="internal"
                        cRef="bibl6">Halliday, 2004</ref>]. It is part of a broad social semiotic
                    approach to language called systemic linguistics. The term <hi rend="italic"
                        >systemic</hi> refers to the view of language as “a network of systems, or
                    interrelated sets of options for making meaning”. The term <hi rend="italic"
                        >functional</hi> indicates that the approach is concerned with meaning, as
                    opposed to formal grammar, which focuses on word classes such as nouns and
                    verbs, typically without reference beyond the individual clause.
                    Systemic-Functional Linguistics (SFL) is a theory of language centred around the
                    notion of language function. SFL places the function of language as central
                    (what language does, and how it does it), in preference to more structural
                    approaches, which place the elements of language and their combinations as
                    central. Specifically, it begins with a social context, and looks at how
                    language both acts upon, and is constrained by, this social context. In the
                    model, and methodology, particular aspects of a given social context (such as
                    the topics discussed, the language users and the medium of communication) define
                    the meanings likely to be expressed and the language likely to be used to
                    express those meanings. Since language is viewed as semiotic potential, the
                    description of language is a description of choice. Systemic linguists examine
                    the choices language users can make in a given setting to realise a particular
                    linguistic product (the available choices depend on aspects of the context in
                    which the language is being used). By examining the different choices for the
                    discourse between characters in similar social contexts in different texts, we
                    believe that it may be possible to identify, or describe, the features
                    associated with national literatures that address the problem described
                    here.</p>
                <p>Our approach is essentially a discourse analysis rather than textual analysis,
                    although it relies on encoded text for comparative analysis. Specifically, we
                    draw on existing SFL models of sociolinguistic and cognitive approaches to
                    doctor-patient discourse [<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl10">Todd and Fisher,
                        1993</ref>, <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl11">Togher, 2001</ref>]. These
                    models (i) analyse the patterns of talk that are produced by the situational
                    demands of the particular setting, (ii) provide a detailed examination of the
                    interplay of language use in this organisational context of health care
                    delivery, and (iii) examine the production of doctor-patient communication, and
                    (iv) examine the relationship between social structure and social interaction,
                    and explore the relationship between power and resistance. The discourse
                    analyses will utilise custom developed software that analyses encoded passages
                    of text from the novels. A number of encoding schemes exist and provide
                    mechanisms for encoding linguistic data, for example, the Text Encoding
                    Initiative (TEI) [<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl8">Sperberg-McQueen and
                        Burnard, 1994</ref>] or the more recent XCES, based on the Corpus Encoding
                    Standard (CES) which is a part of the EAGLES Guidelines developed by the Expert
                    Advisory Group on Language Engineering Standards (EAGLES). EAGLES provides a set
                    of encoding standards for corpus-based work in natural language processing
                    applications [Ide et al., 2000].</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Discussion</head>
                <p>Through the investigation into past experiences in an attempt to divulge facts
                    about the present condition, the patient-therapist relationship has enormous
                    significance in “factional” novels, given their link to cultural memory and cul-
                    tural trauma. For example, the revelation of the occurrence of nominalisation in
                    the dialogue between patient and therapist provides textual evidence as to
                    whether the patient successfully ‘moves on’ from the traumatic past experience.
                    Nominalisation is an example of <hi rend="italic">grammatical metaphor</hi>; the
                    term given when one grammatical class is substituted for another, for example,
                    replacing <hi rend="italic">he departed</hi> with <hi rend="italic">his
                        departure</hi>. The lexical items are the same, but their place in the
                    grammar has changed. In this example, the meaning expressed by an individual
                    differs in that one form identifies a transient event while the other is more
                    permanent. Attention is also paid to the gender of the characters. The
                    case-study will provide (i) an example of a recurring literary structure of
                    focused dialogue, (ii) one which has a general referent in therapeutic terms:
                    literature of trauma etc., and (iii) but also a dialogue which gathers
                    particular meaning from its specific national and cultural context of conflict
                    (in the case of our chosen novels, an emerging independent Ireland and immediate
                    post World War I Britain).</p>
                <p>We demonstrate how the findings of our study can be utilized to provide a
                    specialist analysis of the texts within their respective national literatures of
                    Ireland and Britain by applying them to answer a specific literary question
                    about the texts in their national contexts. Having done so, we then illustrate
                    that our findings also elucidate what can be achieved by generalist studies in
                    the context of world literature by comparing the results to provide a commentary
                    on variations in the artistic treatment of cultural trauma.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>Our case study tests a methodology, which is concerned with analyzing a ‘common-
                    denominator’ (the patient-therapist relationship) between texts. This opens up
                    the two novels under examination to a useful comparative reading as works of
                    world literature, while also yielding useful results to study of the texts
                    within their respective national literatures. In so doing it (i) introduces a
                    new methodology to the academic community and (ii) demonstrates the application
                    of the results produced by said methodology to the answering of a specific
                    literary question. The ultimate aim of the model is to provide a digital
                    linguistic tool that supports individual and collaborative projects in the study
                    of world literature, thus assuaging the needs of both ‘specialists’ and
                    ‘generalists’. In so doing, it offers a solution to one of the problems present
                    in the study of world literature while simultaneously advancing the use of
                    digital humanities in literary studies.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl1"><seg type="label">Alexander et al., 2004</seg>
                        <author>Alexander, J. C.</author><author>Eyerman, R.</author>
                        <author>Giesen, B.</author>
                        <author>Smelse, N. J.</author>
                        <author>Sztompka, P.</author>
                        <date>2004</date>
                        <title level="m">Cultural Trauma and Collective Identity</title>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>California University Press</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl2"><seg type="label">Damrosch, 2003a</seg>
                        <author>Damrosch, D.</author>
                        <date>2003a</date>
                        <title level="m">What is World Literature?</title>
                        <pubPlace>Princeton and Oxford</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl3"><seg type="label">Damrosch, 2003b</seg>
                        <author>Damrosch, D.</author>
                        <date>2003b</date>
                        <title level="a">World literature, national contexts</title>
                        <title level="j">Modern Philiology</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">100</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">512–531</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl4"><seg type="label">Dimock, 2006</seg>
                        <author>Dimock, W. C.</author>
                        <date>2006</date>
                        <title level="m">Through Other Continents: American Literature Across
                            Deep-Time</title>
                        <pubPlace>Princeton, NJ</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl5"><seg type="label">Halliday, 1976</seg>
                        <author>Halliday, M. A. K.</author>
                        <date>1976</date>
                        <title level="m">Cohesion in English</title>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Longman</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl6"><seg type="label">Halliday, 2004</seg>
                        <author>Halliday, M. A. K.</author>
                        <date>2004</date>
                        <title level="m">An introduction to functional grammar</title>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Arnold</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl7"><seg type="label">Ide et al., 2000</seg>
                        <author>Ide, N.</author>
                        <author>Bonhomme, P.</author>
                        <author>Romary, L.</author>
                        <date>2000</date>
                        <title level="a">Xces: An xml-based encoding standard for linguistic
                            corpora</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceeding">LREC-2000</title>
                        <name type="venue">Athens, Greece</name>
                        <biblScope type="pp">825–830</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl8"><seg type="label">Sperberg-McQueen and Burnard, 1994</seg>
                        <author>Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.</author>
                        <author>Burnard, L.</author>
                        <date>1994</date>
                        <title level="m">Guidelines for the encoding and interchange of
                            machine-readable texts</title>
                        <pubPlace>Chicago and Oxford</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Text Encoding Initiative</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl9"><seg type="label">Sutherland, 2006</seg>
                        <author>Sutherland, J.</author>
                        <date>Monday, 9 January, 2006</date>
                        <title level="a">The ideas interview: Franco moretti</title>
                        <title level="j">The Guardian</title></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl10"><seg type="label">Todd and Fisher, 1993</seg>
                        <author>Todd, A. D.</author>
                        <author>Fisher, S.</author>
                        <date>1993</date>
                        <title level="m">The Social Organization of Doctor-Patient
                            Communication</title>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Ablex Publishing</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl11">
                        <seg type="label">Togher, 2001</seg>
                        <author>Togher, L.</author>
                        <date>2001</date>
                        <title level="a">Discourse sampling in the 21st century</title>
                        <title level="j">Journal of Communication Disorders</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">34</biblScope><biblScope type="pp"
                            >131–150</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl12"><seg type="label">Waters, 1995</seg>
                        <author>Waters, M.</author>
                        <date>1995</date>
                        <title level="m">Globalization</title>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Routledge</publisher></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
