<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-865">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>WW1 and WW2 on a Specialist E-forum. Applying Corpus Tools to the Study of
                    Evaluative Language</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sokół, Małgorzata</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Szczecin University</orgName>, <country>Poland</country></affiliation>
                    <email>msokol@autograph.pl</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-21</date>
                <name>CD</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The 70th anniversary of WW2 generated a new discussions about Poles’ attitudes to
                    the country’s important historical events. The general aim of my present study
                    is to investigate how contemporary Poles’ attitudes to the two world wars are
                    expressed in electronic discourse, using the example of a specialist Internet
                    forum. The research data comes from an active Polish forum devoted to the
                    history of the two world wars: <hi rend="italic">Your Forum About the World
                        Wars</hi> retrieved from <ref type="external" target="http://www.dws.org.pl"
                        >www.dws.org.pl</ref>. The quantitative-qualitative analysis of the compiled
                    corpus is conducted by means of the UAM Corpus Tool, a multiple-level
                    environment for annotation and analysis of text corpora (<ref type="external"
                        target="http://www.wagsoft.com/CorpusTool/"
                        >http://www.wagsoft.com/CorpusTool/</ref>).</p>
                <p>The forum under study provides a challenging research context for the study of
                    evaluative language in the electronic medium by means of corpus tools. The forum
                    gathers both professionals and amateurs interested in an academic debate on the
                    issues related to their interests in the history of the two world wars.
                    Interaction on the forum follows the rules of scholarly exchange, where careful
                    use of language and factual expression are encouraged, whereas emotionality is
                    rather disfavoured. This makes textual realizations of evaluation less overt:
                    thus, how attitudinal language is transmitted through the text can be studied
                    effectively by means of corpus tools.</p>
                <p>The theoretical basis of my study is a functional approach to the analysis of
                    evaluative language, where evaluation encompasses both attitudinal and affective
                    aspects of language use (e.g. <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl3">Hunston and
                        Thompson, 1999</ref>). For the corpus-based study of evaluative language, I
                    adopt Martin and White’s Appraisal Framework (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl4"
                        >Martin and White, 2005</ref>), selecting their systems of Attitude and
                    Engagement. More specifically, I analyse linguistic realisations of affect
                    (within the system of Attitude) and modality and evidentiality (within the
                    system of Engagement) as elements of interactional aspects of language use. In
                    this way I aim to investigate evaluation as 1) expression of both individual and
                    communal value systems of language users, and 2) expression of the
                    speaker-audience relations (especially with the focus on the rhetorical effects
                    of evaluation and its role in the social construction of knowledge). With the
                    present study I also hope to contribute to the previous research that shows how
                    text analyses within the framework of systemic-functional linguistics can profit
                    from the use of corpus-linguistic methods (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl2"
                        >Bednarek, 2008</ref>; <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl3">Thompson and
                        Hunston, 2006</ref>), at the same time attempting to investigate how the
                    combination of SFL and CL works for the Polish language. </p>
                <p>The preliminary results of the study in progress prove the presence of evaluative
                    language across the corpus, with the prevalence of engagement over attitude.
                    This demonstrates that the members of the forum under study are primarily
                    involved in objective and to-the-point discussions on the issues related to
                    their interests. Evaluative language is mainly used as a persuasive tool to
                    enhance the power of knowledge claims, and to manage interpersonal relations. As
                    regards the general attitudes of the forum members, the study proves that they
                    are actively engaged in constructing and preserving the collective memory of the
                    two world wars. The wars are discussed with professional commitment and without
                    overly sentimental pathos, which makes the forum and history of the two world
                    wars attractive also for young people.</p>
                <p>The application of the UAM Corpus Tool in the analyses of evaluative language
                    proves advantageous first of all thanks to the tool’s possibility of multi-level
                    annotation and cross-classification of features. These features allow me to
                    study the distribution of evaluative language relative to the sub-generic status
                    of postings (i.e. whether a posting is identified as a voice in a discussion,
                    initiation of a discussion, request, query, etc.). In addition, the tool allows
                    to manage the problem of evaluation “hidden” behind stretches of discourse, as
                    well as to analyse the distribution patterns of evaluative lexis. Finally, as
                    the UAM Corpus Tool allows annotation of both text and images, it can be used
                    for the analysis of multimodal genres, an example of which is an e-forum. The
                    UAM Corpus Tool can be useful and flexible in corpus-based analyses of
                    evaluative language, however its application invariably demonstrates the
                    importance of human choice in working with corpora in discourse analysis (cf.
                    also <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl1">Baker, 2006</ref>).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl1">
                        <author>Baker, P.</author>
                        <date>2006</date>
                        <title level="m">Using Corpora in Discourse Analysis</title>
                        <pubPlace>London - New York</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Continuum</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl2"><author>Bednarek, M.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="m">Emotion Talk Across Corpora</title>
                        <pubPlace>Houndmills - New York</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl3"><editor>Hunston, S.</editor>
                        <editor>Thompson, G.</editor>
                        <date>1999</date>
                        <title level="m">Evaluation in Text. Authorial Stance and the Construction
                            of Discourse</title>
                        <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl4"><author>Martin, J. R.</author>
                        <author>White, P. R. R.</author>
                        <date>2005</date>
                        <title level="m">The Language of Evaluation. Appraisal in English</title>
                        <pubPlace>Houndmills - New York</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl5"><editor>Thompson, G.</editor>
                        <editor>Hunston, S.</editor>
                        <date>2006</date>
                        <title level="m">System and Corpus. Exploring Connections</title>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Equinox</publisher></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
