<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-003">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Present, Not Voting: Digital Humanities in the Panopticon</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Terras, Melissa</name>
                    <affiliation>Senior Lecturer in Electronic Communication, Deputy Director of UCL
                        Centre for Digital Humanities, Department of Information Studies</affiliation>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-06-01</date>
                <name>CD</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="keynotes">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The field of Digital Humanities continues to change and evolve rapidly, as we
                    utilise, appropriate, and develop internet, communication, and computational
                    technologies. In this plenary, a specific focus will be placed on one individual
                    project – The Transcribe Bentham project at UCL (<ref type="external"
                        target="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/transcribe-bentham/"
                        >http://www.ucl.ac.uk/transcribe-bentham/</ref>) – as a viewpoint through
                    which to witness the changing demands and needs placed on those working within
                    the Digital Humanities.</p>
                <p>Transcribe Bentham is a one year, Arts and Humanities Research Council funded
                    project, housed under the auspices of the Bentham Project at UCL (<ref
                        type="external" target="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/Bentham-Project/"
                        >http://www.ucl.ac.uk/Bentham-Project/</ref>). The Bentham Project aims to
                    produce new editions of the scholarship of Jeremy Bentham (1748-1832). Bentham
                    was a political radical. An English jurist, philosopher, and legal and social
                    reformer, he became a leading theorist in Anglo-American philosophy of law, and
                    influenced the development of welfarism. He is well known for his advocacy of
                    utilitarianism and animal rights, but is perhaps most famous for his work on the
                    “panopticon”: a type of prison in which wardens can observe (-<hi rend="italic"
                        >opticon</hi>) all (<hi rend="italic">pan</hi>-) prisoners without the
                    incarcerated being able to tell whether or not they are being watched. This
                    concept has influenced prison reform, philosophy, literature, and social media
                    since.</p>
                <p>Bentham and UCL have a close relationship. Whilst it is untrue that he founded
                    UCL, he did influence those who did, and as the first English University to open
                    its doors to all, regardless of race, creed or political belief (provided they
                    could afford the fees) UCL went a long way to fulfilling Bentham&apos;s
                    vision of how Universities should operate. He took a great interest in the new
                    institution, and UCL now hosts Bentham&apos;s 60,000 pages of handwritten
                    manuscripts arranged in 174 boxes. His “auto-icon” famously sits in the main
                    cloisters: Bentham&apos;s preserved skeleton, dressed in his own clothes,
                    surmounted by a wax head, as per his will and testament. An apocryphal story has
                    it that Bentham&apos;s “auto-icon” is wheeled yearly into UCL Senate
                    meetings, where he is noted in the minutes as being “present, not voting”.</p>
                <p>Twelve volumes of Bentham&apos;s correspondence have so far been published by
                    the Bentham Project, plus various collections of his work on jurisprudence and
                    legal matters (<ref
                        target="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/Bentham-Project/Publications/index.htm"
                        type="external"
                        >http://www.ucl.ac.uk/Bentham-Project/Publications/index.htm</ref>).
                    However, there is much more work to be done to make his writings more
                    accessible, and to provide transcripts of the materials therein. Although a
                    previous grant from the AHRC in 2003-6 has allowed for the completion of a
                    catalogue of the manuscripts held within UCL (<ref type="external"
                        target="http://www.benthampapers.ucl.ac.uk/"
                        >http://www.benthampapers.ucl.ac.uk/</ref>), and transcriptions have been
                    completed of some 10,000 folios, there are many hours of work that need to be
                    invested in reading, transcribing, labelling, and making accessible the works of
                    this interdisciplinary historical figure if they are to be analysed, consulted,
                    and utilised by scholars across the various disciplines interested in
                    Bentham&apos;s writings.</p>
                <p>Crowdsourcing – the harnessing of online activity to aid in large scale projects
                    that require human cognition – is becoming of interest to those in the library,
                    museum and cultural heritage industry, as institutions seek ways to publically
                    engage their online communities, as well as aid in creating useful and usable
                    digital resources. As one of the first cultural and heritage projects to apply
                    crowdsourcing to a non-trivial task, UCL&apos;s Bentham Project has recently
                    set up the &quot;Transcribe Bentham&quot; initiative; an ambitious, open
                    source, participatory online environment which is being developed to aid in
                    transcribing 10,000 folios of Bentham’s handwritten documents. To be launched in
                    July 2010, this experimental project will aim to engage with individuals such as
                    school children, amateur historians, and other interested parties, who can
                    provide time to help us read Bentham’s manuscripts. The integration of user
                    communities will be key to the success of the project, and an additional project
                    remit is to monitor the success of trying to engage the wider community with
                    such documentary material: will we get high quality, trustworthy transcriptions
                    as a result of this work? Will people be interested in volunteering their time
                    and effort to read the (poor) handwriting of a great philosopher? What technical
                    and pragmatic difficulties will we run into? How can we monitor success in a
                    crowdsourced environment?</p>
                <p>In addition to introducing the project, this plenary will use the Bentham
                    Project, and the Transcribe Bentham open participatory initiative, as a
                    panopticon through which to view the changing nature of Digital Humanities
                    scholarship, and the role of the Digital Humanities scholar, alluding to other
                    related work in the field, and concerns which have emerged in the development
                    and discussion of the project aims. How do issues such as digital identity,
                    scholarly and community engagement, professionalization and employment issues,
                    funding, short scale projects, and large scale digitisation affect the role of
                    the digital humanist? How can we successfully embrace ever changing internet
                    technologies, and trends such as crowdsourcing, to further our research in
                    cultural heritage and computational methods? How can we measure the impact of
                    our endeavours in the online environment, and how can we persuade others of the
                    value of our work? What can we do better – as a discipline – to make sure our
                    voice is heard in the academy, so that the role, remit, and focus of Digital
                    Humanities can be treated as a bona fide academic endeavour? What can we do
                    better – as individuals – to further the cause of Digital Humanities as a
                    discipline, as well as fostering our own scholarly development?</p>
                <p>By looking at specific issues that have arisen in the Transcribe Bentham project,
                    this plenary aims to provide an honest and open overview of pressing concerns
                    and opportunities for both the project, and Digital Humanities as a discipline,
                    in the current information and academic environments.</p>
                <p>Melissa Terras and Transcribe Bentham can be followed on twitter at
                    #TranscriBentham and #melissaterras respectively. The complete transcript of
                    this plenary will be made available shortly after delivery on Melissa Terras’
                    blog: <ref type="external" target="http://melissaterras.blogspot.com/"
                        >http://melissaterras.blogspot.com/</ref>, and viewable thereafter in the
                    blog archive for July 2010.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
