<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-008">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Embroidered Digital Commons: Rescension</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Carpenter, Ele</name>
                    <affiliation>Goldsmiths College, University of London</affiliation>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-06-14</date>
                <name>CD</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="art">
        <body>
            <p>The &apos;Embroidered Digital Commons’ is an artwork facilitated by Ele Carpenter as
                part of the Open Source Embroidery project, utilising social and digital
                connectivity. The artwork is a practice-based research project exploring the
                language of the digital commons through close reading and stitching, in which
                conference delegates are invited to participate.</p>
            <p>In 2003 the Raqs Media Collective wrote <hi rend="italic">A Concise Lexicon of/for
                    the Digital Commons</hi>. The full lexicon is an A-Z of the interrelationship
                between social, digital and material space. It weaves together an evolving language
                of the commons that is both poetic and informative. The terms of the lexicon are:
                Access, Bandwidth, Code, Data, Ensemble, Fractal, Gift, Heterogeneous, Iteration,
                Kernel, Liminal, Meme, Nodes, Orbit, Portability, Quotidian, Rescension, Site,
                Tools, Ubiquity, Vector, Web, Xenophilly, Yarn, and Zone.</p>
            <p>The ‘Embroidered Digital Commons’ is an ambitious project to hand-embroider the whole
                lexicon, term by term, through workshops and events as a practical way of
                close-reading and discussing the text and its current meaning. Each term is chosen
                in relation to the specific context of its production through group workshops,
                conferences and events. The term ‘Yarn’ was embroidered at the HUMlab Digital
                Humanities Media Lab at Umeå University in Sweden, 2009. Here at the DH2010
                conference we will aim to stitch the complex term ‘Rescension’.</p>
            <p>The concept of the digital commons is based on the potential for everything that is
                digital to be common to all. Like common grazing land, this can mean commonly owned,
                commonly accessed or commonly available. But all of these blurred positions of
                status and ownership have complex repercussions in the field of intellectual
                property and copyright. The commons has become synonymous with digital media through
                the discourse surrounding free and open source software and creative commons
                licensing. The digital commons is a response to the inherent &apos;copy n
                paste&apos; reproducibility of digital data, and the cultural forms that they
                support. Instead of trying to restrict access, the digital commons invite open
                participation in the production of ideas and culture - where culture is not
                something you buy, but something you do.</p>
            <p>The use of metaphor to explain technological concepts was expertly developed by Lady
                Ada Byron Lovelace in her letters and notes accompanying the Analytical Engine. Her
                love of poetical science combined the influences of her father, Lord Byron, and her
                mathematical mother, Lady Lovelace. Ada gave us the textile - metaphors for code and
                programming in the 1830s, informed by the binary punch card programming of the
                Jacquard Loom and Charles Babbage&apos;s Analytical Engine (Plant, 1997).</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Rescension</hi><lb/>The project for the DH2010 conference is to
                consider and embroider the following text: “Rescension<lb/> A re-telling, a word
                taken to signify the simultaneous existence of different versions of a narrative
                within oral, and from now onwards, digital cultures. Thus one can speak of a
                &apos;southern&apos; or a &apos;northern&apos; rescension of a myth, or of a
                &apos;female&apos; or &apos;male&apos; rescension of a story, or the possibility (to
                begin with) of Delhi/Berlin/Tehran &apos;rescensions&apos; of a digital work. The
                concept of rescension is contraindicative of the notion of hierarchy. A rescension
                cannot be an improvement, nor can it connote a diminishing of value. A rescension is
                that version which does not act as a replacement for any other configuration of its
                constitutive materials. The existence of multiple rescensions is a guarantor of an
                idea or a work&apos;s ubiquity. This ensures that the constellation of narrative,
                signs and images that a work embodies is present, and waiting for iteration at more
                than one site at any given time. Rescensions are portable and are carried within
                orbiting kernels within a space. Rescensions taken together constitute ensembles
                that may form an interconnected web of ideas, images and signs.” (Raqs Media
                Collective, 2003) </p>
            <p>The embroidery is a rescension of the lexicon. As we sew we retell the story of the
                digital commons (itself creative commons licensed to be retold). And as we emphasise
                the line of our stitches and falter over knotted words, we make our own subtle
                interpretations of the text, adding nuances of colour, and personalized
                references.</p>
            <p>The Digital Humanities is a large net woven by many scholars from many fields, each
                with their own perspectives on the concept of how the digital is common to all
                people, and how it is restricted. Curiously we watch people sewing in the dim light
                – what does it say? What does it mean? Where are you from? How do you retell the
                story of your knowledge? What is your lexicon?</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">A Concise Lexicon of/for the Digital Commons</hi> uses its own
                terms to describe new terms. So the word ‘rescension’ is described in relation to
                ‘fractal’, ‘kernel’, ‘node’, and ‘ubiquity’.</p>
            <p>In the ‘Embroidered Digital Commons’, the text forms a kernel which is “the central
                rescension, of a narrative, a code, a set of signs … that invites modification,
                extrapolation and interpretation, by its very presence.” (Raqs Media Collective,
                2003). It is the core of an idea at the centre of discourse.</p>
            <p>The text is open for any group to embroider, as a fractal or fragment of “free
                cultural code” as described in the lexicon: a fractal “is a rescension of every
                other fractal that has grown from within it. In the same way a fragment of free
                code, or free cultural code, carries within it myriad possibilities of its own
                reproduction and dispersal within a shared symbolic or information space.” (Raqs
                Media Collective, 2003)</p>
            <p>We are nodes in the network of communication, and each thread and word is reinforced
                through repetition, where every utterance is both the same and different each time.
                The lexicon describes “echoes and resonances” as “rescensions” which travel through
                nodes, “and each node is ultimately a direct rescension of at least one other node
                in the system and an indirect rescension of each junction within a whole cluster of
                other nodes.” (Raqs Media Collective, 2003). The embroidered patches become a
                central node, where ideas and arguments can cluster.</p>
            <p>According to the Lexicon ‘Ubiquity’ is: “A rescension, when in orbit, crosses the
                paths of its variants. The zone where two orbits intersect is usually the site of an
                active transaction and transfer of meanings. Each rescension carries into its own
                trajectory memes from its companion. In this way, through the encounters between
                rescensions, ideas spread, travel and tend towards ubiquity.” (Raqs Media
                Collective, 2003)</p>
            <p>By the end of the conference the term ‘Rescension’ will become ubiquitous: in our
                minds, in our presentations, in our conversations, in our pricked fingers and in our
                notes scribbled incomprehensibly in the dark. And possibly in a patchwork which
                defines or redefines the term, and enables it to continue traveling.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl><author>Plant, Sadie</author>
                        <date>1997</date>
                        <title level="m">Zeros and Ones: Digital Women and the New
                            Technoculture</title>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Fourth Estate</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Raqs Media Collective</author>
                        <date>2003</date>
                        <title level="a">A Concise Lexicon of/for the Digital Commons</title>
                        <title level="m">Sarai Reader 03: Shaping Technologies</title>
                        <editor>Monica Narula</editor>
                        <editor>Shuddhabrata Sengupta</editor>
                        <editor>Jeebesh Bagchi</editor>
                        <editor>Ravi Vasudevan</editor>
                        <editor>Ravi Sundaram</editor>
                        <editor>Geert Lovink</editor>
                        <publisher>Sarai-CSDS/WAAG</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Delhi/Amsterdam</pubPlace><biblScope type="pp">365</biblScope><ptr
                            target="http://www.raqsmediacollective.net/texts4.html"/>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>Ele Carpenter is a curator, artist and writer based in the UK and Sweden. She is
                    a lecturer in MFA Curating at Goldsmiths College University of London, and is a
                    Postdoctoral Research Fellow at HUMlab in affiliation with Bildmuseet at the
                    University of Umeå, Sweden.</p>
                <p>Since 2005 Ele has facilitated the Open Source Embroidery project using
                    embroidery and code as a tool to investigate participatory production and
                    distribution methods. Ele is currently working on the &apos;Open Source
                    Crafter&apos; publication, and facilitating the ‘Embroidered Digital Commons’
                    distributed embroidery.</p>
                <p>Ele received her PhD on the relationship between politicised socially engaged art
                    and new media art, with CRUMB at the University of Sunderland in 2008; and was
                    previously Curator, NGCA Sunderland (1997-2002); Associate Curator, CCA Glasgow
                    (2003-5).</p>
                <p><ptr type="external" target="http://www.elecarpenter.org.uk"/> &#xa0;&#xa0;&#xa0;&#xa0;&#xa0;&#xa0;&#xa0;&#xa0;&#xa0;&#xa0;&#xa0;&#xa0;&#xa0;&#xa0;&#xa0;&#xa0;&#xa0;&#xa0;&#xa0;&#xa0;&#xa0;&#xa0; 
                    <ptr type="external" target="http://www.open-source-embroidery.org.uk"/>
                 
                   <ptr type="external" target="http://www.eleweekend.blogspot.com"/>.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
