<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-599">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Creative Engagement with Creative Works: a New Paradigm for
                    Collaboration</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Jones, Steven E. </name>
                    <affiliation>Loyola University <reg><orgName>Loyola University Chicago</orgName></reg> Center for Textual Studies and Digital
                        Humanities <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>sjones1@luc.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Shillingsburg, Peter </name>
                    <affiliation>Loyola University <reg><orgName>Loyola University Chicago</orgName></reg> Center for Textual Studies and Digital
                        Humanities <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Thiruvathukal, George K. </name>
                    <affiliation>Loyola University <reg><orgName>Loyola University Chicago</orgName></reg> Center for Textual Studies and Digital
                        Humanities <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-21-04</date>
                <name>AC</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="poster">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Funded in part by a Digital Start-up Grant from the National Endowment for the
                    Humanities, <hi rend="bold">Creative Engagement with Creative Works</hi> is a
                    project to build a new online environment (e-Carrel) and integrated tools with
                    the aim of improving understanding of creative processes across various
                    humanities disciplines and genres. Studies of the production and reception of
                    literary, historical, musical, and philosophical works are all built on primary
                    materials that are textual in the broad sense--documentary, material objects:
                    manuscripts, newspapers, periodicals, pamphlets, books, and images. But current
                    solutions to digitizing and providing access to these materials are structurally
                    flawed and lead away from the often-stated goal of extensive collaboration.
                    Digital transcriptions relying on XML or other inline markup can often prevent
                    or limit collaboration on the files themselves, can (paradoxically) threaten a
                    project’s integrity, and can lead to early maintenance problems and the ultimate
                    abandonment of projects beyond the lifetimes of their initial creators.</p>
                <p>We propose using standoff markup instead, indexing these files to inviolate core
                    files, thus affecting the way humanities disciplines interact with primary
                    materials--moving away from proprietary, look-but-don't-touch window-case
                    projects toward secure and enduring projects that are open to ongoing annotation
                    and re-markup, and which thus encourage widely collaborative knowledge
                    sites.</p>
                <p>Electronic projects that restrict their construction and enhancement to a select
                    few persons as a way to protect the intellectual integrity of their resources
                    inadvertently introduce a significant threat to the durability of text files,
                    whose hard-won accuracy is the result of expert attention. The creators’ anxiety
                    to protect the results of their time-consuming and labor-intensive
                    in-line-tagging leads to a proprietary attitude that’s detrimental to scholarly
                    collaboration, because everyone knows that the text files are vulnerable to
                    inadvertent change every time they are reopened for further tagging. Protective
                    restriction also restricts truly collaborative work, the life of digital
                    humanities projects in the world.</p>
                <p>These restrictions can be loosened or eliminated by a fundamentally different
                    approach to collaboration, durability, and maintenance, pioneered in scientific
                    fields following principles of: <xmt:uList>
                        <item>modular component structure,</item>
                        <item>connectivity,</item>
                        <item>extensibility,</item>
                        <item>distribution and aggregation systems,</item>
                        <item>stand-off enhancement mechanisms, and</item>
                        <item>methods for identifying and crediting researchers with their
                            individual contributions to composite research projects.</item>
                    </xmt:uList>
                </p>
                <p>These trends in software development allow for decentralized alterations. But
                    even free/open source (FOSS) software projects are not without problems. The
                    past was dominated largely by projects where the code was kept under tight
                    wraps, using version control systems such as CVS (Concurrent Versions System)
                    and Subversion. Only a handful of FOSS projects succeed with this model, notably
                    the Firefox project, but many FOSS projects are already migrating to more
                    distributed approaches (the Python language, the Linux kernel, etc.). Much like
                    archives, software development projects in the FOSS community tend to
                    self-organize and establish their own governance. While they make their code
                    available (as required by the FOSS licensing schemes) they also tend to fall
                    into disuse, making it hard for new developers to come along and take the
                    project to new levels.</p>
                <p>Distributed version control systems record a project's entire history and state,
                    which can be copied freely, allowing derived works to take place. When a copy is
                    made, however, the entire history is kept intact, allowing new contributors to
                    either make their own changes or to push their changes back to the original
                    maintainer. The push/pull model is so sophisticated that anyone who makes
                    changes can get recognition for their work, because their specific changes to
                    the code are encoded in the derived history.</p>
                <p>Our Creative Engagement with Creative Works and e-Carrel environment incorporates
                    these principles and adds the functions of stand-off files for markup and
                    annotation, along with a dynamic authentication mechanism. Experimentation has
                    shown the considerable promise of such functionality. (See the Just InTime
                    Markup system rototyped at the University of New South Wales at ADFA by our
                    Senior Consultant, Paul Eggert and his team working on Australian literature;
                    and see Desmond Schmidt’s MVD or Multi Version Document system, the architecture
                    and some code of which we are incorporating). These are the building blocks of
                    our project’s coherent vision for archiving creative works for creative
                    collaboration, preservation, and dynamic interactive access, realized in the
                    form of tools and programming frameworks.</p>
                <p>We establish an image file and a base text for each significant version of a
                    work. Text data for all versions are compressed in a composite, inviolable
                    CorTex file, which anchors all stand-off contributions. Each participant's
                    contribution is credited and protected from work by other contributors. Endusers
                    choose a historical text (or other object) plus desired types of enhancements
                    from a menu dynamically aggregated from distributed sources. The e-Carrel
                    processes and presents perspectives of texts and enhancements for viewing,
                    printing, or export in commonly used formats. Individual projects using the
                    system can vet and certify parts of a project. And--most important--this system
                    allows for the storage, retrieval, and coordination of different, even
                    conflicting editorial or critical approaches to the same literary work. In this
                    way, it opens the horizon of any given project’s ongoing reception.</p>
                <p>By giving scholars and students a vested interest in a growing integrated
                    collaborative project, CECW ensures preservation and access to textual research
                    projects and their superstructure of critical analysis at the same time that it
                    promotes collaboration beyond the project initiators' participation and goals.
                    Project viability follows community ownership and becomes a widely distributed
                    responsibility. The system ensures long-term maintenance and growth through
                    collective ownership, distributed storage, and the principle of LOCKSS (Lots of
                    copies keep stuff safe). Our strong definition of LOCKSS, which distributes
                    multiple accurate copies, and in an ongoing process verifies them by way of the
                    persistent CorText data and checksum system, is significantly different from the
                    "soft" version of LOCKSS that just sends "copies" into the world in whatever
                    state and trusts to the hive mind for endurance and integrity.</p>
                <p>CECW makes use of RDF capabilities and is XML aware but is by design markup
                    agnostic. It allows for the importation of materials from other systems and
                    prepares perspectives of the E-Carrel materials for export in various forms
                    compatible with other systems (such as PDF and in-line coded XML).</p>
                <p>This poster session will provide demos of portions of the software in
                    development, in particular, the standoff markup tool used within the E-Carrel
                    environment. A case-study CoreText will be loaded for the purposes of
                    demonstration.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Eggert, Paul</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">The Book, the e-Text, and the Worksite</title>
                        <title level="m">Text Editing, Print and the Digital World</title>
                        <publisher>Ashgate</publisher>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title level="m">Loyola University Center for Textual Studies and Digital
                            Humanities</title>
                        <ptr target="http://www.ctsdh.luc.edu/" type="external"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Schmidt, Desmond</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">A Data Structure for Representing Multi-Version Texts
                            Online</title>
                        <title level="j">Int. J. Human-Computer Studies</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">67</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">497-514</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Shillingsburg, Peter</author>
                        <date>2006</date>
                        <title level="m">From Gutenberg to Google</title>
                        <publisher>Cambridge UP</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
