<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-691">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Knowledge and Conservation - Creating the Digital Library of New Hispanic
                    Thought</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Priani, Ernesto</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México - UNAM</orgName>,
                            <country>Mexico</country></affiliation>
                    <email>epriani@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Galina, Isabel</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México - UNAM</orgName>,
                            <country>Mexico</country></affiliation>
                    <email>igalina@unam.mx</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Martínez, Alí</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México - UNAM</orgName>,
                            <country>Mexico</country></affiliation>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Chávez, Guillermo</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México - UNAM</orgName>,
                            <country>Mexico</country></affiliation>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-09</date>
                <name>CD</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="poster">
        <body>
            <p>This paper presents the Digital Library of New Hispanic Thought (Biblioteca Digital
                del Pensamiento Novohispano). In Mexico, during the seventeenth century, two comets
                were observed, leading to the publication of various texts on the meaning of this
                astrological phenomenon (Trabulse 1994a). During this period relatively few books
                were published due to high costs, the required approval of the Inquisition for
                publication and the lack of potential buyers. This proliferation of publications on
                the subject can be viewed as an indication of the importance of these events for the
                Catholic Church, the colonial government and the intellectuals of the period
                (Trabulse 1994b). The Heavens were, in Spanish colonial Mexico, a scientific,
                religious, social, political and ideological battleground (Moreno 1998). </p>
            <p> To this date most digitization projects for New Hispanic publications, namely Google
                Books and Biblioteca Virtual Cervantes, have focused primarily on access and
                preservation and although useful, do not constitute digital scholarly editions. The
                original aim of this project was to provide the basis for a critical digital edition
                through collaborative commentary of digital diplomatic transcriptions. The process
                however, in particular during the migration of our tailor made DTD to using TEI,
                also served as a research tool which enabled us to develop a conceptual framework to
                formulate further research on these texts. </p>
            <p>This is the first project from our university to use XML and TEI. </p>
            <div>
                <head>From single publication to digital library</head>
                <p>The original aim of the project was to make available in digital format the first
                    book by Fray Diego Rodríguez, published in 1652. However, this idea was quickly
                    superseded as we realized that, taking into consideration the relatively large
                    number of books on comets and astrology published in this period, it was more
                    desirable to present all texts as a corpus. We therefore decided to focus on the
                    common theme of astrology/astronomy with the main objective of not only
                    gathering and creating a corpora and providing access but also developing and
                    publishing a digital critical edition with tools to aid scholars in their
                    research. The outcome is the publication of all known texts of the period, eight
                    in total.<note>See References.</note> With the exception of one, none of these
                    texts has ever been reedited. </p>
                <p>Up to now, due to the fact that the ideas contained within these texts were no
                    longer of any scientific value, the text itself has not been considered
                    particularly important. Moreover, of the few studies that exist on these
                    publications, the tendency is to view them as general testimonies rather than
                    concentrating on the texts themselves (Cf. Navarro, 1959 and Cullen, 1984). This
                    new edition of the texts in digital format gave us the opportunity to examine
                    the text in detail and reconsider previous interpretations.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Textual processing</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Digitization of texts</head>
                    <p>The eight texts were transcribed into plain text digital format and
                        diplomatic transcriptions were produced. The only text that had been
                        reedited previously had been updated for spelling and grammar as well as
                        correcting original errors, in order to make it more readable for a modern,
                        non-academic audience (Cf. Navarro 1959 and Cullen 1984). Other editions had
                        been facsimiles (Trabulse 2001). As the BDPN is aimed mainly at specialists
                        and we wished to both preserve the texts as faithfully as possible and to
                        provide analytical tools, diplomatic transcriptions were considered the most
                        adequate. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Creating digital texts - DTD</head>
                    <p>The texts were then marked up in XML. We wished to approach the text with no
                        preexisting theory or structure –and as a part of pedagogical approach to
                        the use of XML as a research tool-, allowing the text to speak for itself.
                        In order to do this we set about producing categories as the text was
                        analysed. These categories were then converted into tags which eventually
                        formed the DTD for the XML mark up. The objective of this was that the
                        analysis of the text for creating the DTD was in itself a critical analysis.
                        Once our own DTD had been developed, we then began the process to migrate to
                        TEI. In order to do so we sorted through our categories and found
                        equivalents. This process helped us define a new conceptual framework for
                        studying the texts. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Digital Library Tools</head>
                <p>The main objectives of the BDPN web interface<note>Biblioteca Digital del
                        Pensamiento Novohispano (<ref type="external"
                            target="http://www.dbpn.unam.mx">www.dbpn.unam.mx</ref>)</note> were two
                    fold: to present the marked up XML texts as a new digital edition and to offer
                    tools to continue to carry out analytical work. Currently the system allows the
                    user to view the published texts and consult them through indexes which are
                    automatically generated from the XML tags (<ref type="internal" cRef="fig1">see
                        Fig.1</ref>). An advanced search function allows the user to search
                    specifically in over one hundred tags (<ref type="internal" cRef="fig2">see
                        Fig.2</ref>) <figure xml:id="fig1">
                        <head>Fig. 1 Index search interface</head>
                        <graphic url="691_Fig1.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="fig2">
                        <head>Fig. 2 Specific tag search interface</head>
                        <graphic url="691_Fig2.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>Additionally the system includes expert commentary on the text (<ref
                        type="internal" cRef="fig3">see Fig.3</ref>). Specialists in the subject may
                    obtain a username and password that allows them to comment on the texts and
                    these appear as part of the critical edition. This provides the framework for
                    future national and international collaboration on these particular texts. The
                    project is not conceived as a closed edition and it will hopefully continue to
                    be expanded to permit new enquiries of research to be developed. <figure
                        xml:id="fig3">
                        <head>Fig. 3 Screenshot of expert commentary</head>
                        <graphic url="691_Fig3.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Discussion and Conclusions</head>
                <div>
                    <head>DTD categories to TEI</head>
                    <p>The original DTD was used to identify all possible elements that could be of
                        interest to the study; from classical mythology and Christian metaphysics to
                        geographic and geospatial indicators. Almost one hundred categories were
                        identified. Once the text was marked up using our DTD we then migrated to
                        TEI Lite. In order to do so we needed to find equivalents for our elements.
                        This migration process obliged us to refine our categories and interestingly
                        to simplify our analytic framework. As we started using common TEI tags such
                        as date, place, name, with the type attribute, we realized that we could
                        eliminate many of our tailor made categories as they were redundant or too
                        specific. </p>
                    <p>This process helped us to identify the truly relevant categories for these
                        texts. For example, source (citation, commentary, authors), geographical and
                        geospatial terms, diseases associated with comets and old Spanish terms.
                        Significantly, the migration to TEI allowed us to identify all the comets
                        mentioned in the corpus using the element attribution date. Now that we have
                        identified the thematic structure of theses texts using these categories, we
                        now know that we wish to focus our research on astrological themes used,
                        diseases commonly associated with comets, geographical areas affected by
                        astrological predictions and the type of Spanish used in the period. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Documentation and technical development</head>
                    <p>A key issue in the development of this project was to produce enough
                        documentation so that this can survive as an open ended project, allowing
                        new texts to be incorporated when and if they are discovered. It is known
                        many Humanities projects do not develop adequate documentation that allows
                        text files to be reused (Warwick, et al. 2009). </p>
                    <p>Our experience shows that creating adequate documentation is extremely
                        difficult. One of the main problems was the frequent changes in the tags. As
                        the text was analysed and marked up, this tended to produce new
                        requirements. It proved difficult to maintain the documentation up to date
                        in order to describe and explain all the considerations and changes. This is
                        a very time consuming process. It is difficult to anticipate these changes
                        and to contemplate them adequately in the project timeline. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion and future work</head>
                <p>The work done thus far has initially helped us to view all these texts as a
                    network. This had not been done previously. Additionally in order to develop the
                    tags we approached the texts with no preconceived structure and this has allowed
                    completely new concepts to emerge from the texts. The move to TEI helped us to
                    identify with precision the framework with which to approach further research
                    into the text and produce a new reading of this corpus. </p>
                <p> In the future we hope to incorporate the facsimiles as images and mark them up
                    so that specific parts of the image can be associated with the textual
                    transcription. </p>
                <p>We also hope to generate international interest in these documents that up to now
                    have been hidden in specialized libraries, mainly in Mexico. There is currently
                    little critical digital content in Spanish in general and of this period in
                    particular. We aim ultimately to generate new research on the subject and we
                    believe that this tool can contribute to the study of New Hispanic thought.
                    Additionally we aim to generate research and publications that also reflect on
                    the experience of producing pre-modern electronic textual editions. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Annex 1- Digitized works</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl><author>Escobar Salemerón y Castro, José de</author>
                        <date>1681</date>
                        <title level="m">Discurso Cometológico y relación del nuevo cometa</title>
                        <pubPlace>México</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Viuda de Bernardo Calderón</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Evelino, Gaspar Juan</author>
                        <date>1682</date>
                        <title level="m">Especulación astrologica y physica de la naturaleza de los
                            cometas, y juizio del que este año de 1682 se ve por todo el
                            mundo</title>
                        <pubPlace>México</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Viuda de Bernardo Calderón</publisher>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kino, Eusebio Francisco</author><date>1681</date>
                        <title level="m">Exposicion astronomica de el cometa</title>
                        <pubPlace>México</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Francisco Rodríguez Luprecio</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>López Bonilla, Gabriel</author><date>1675</date>
                        <title level="m">Discurso y relación Cometographica</title>
                        <pubPlace>México</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Viuda de Bernardo Calderón</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Rodríguez, Diego</author>
                        <date>1652</date>
                        <title level="m">Discurso etheorologico del nuevo cometa visto en aqueste
                            hemisferio mexicano y generalmente en todo el mundo</title>
                        <pubPlace>México</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Viuda de Bernardo Calderón</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Rodríguez, Diego</author>
                        <title level="u">Modo de calcular qualquier eclipse de Sol y Luna según las
                            tablas arriba puestas del mobimiento de Sol y Luna segun
                            Tychon</title><edition>Manuscrito inédito</edition></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Rodríguez, Diego</author><title level="u">Tratado General de
                            Reloxes de Sol</title><edition>Manuscrito inédito</edition></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Ruiz, Juan</author><date>1653</date>
                        <title level="m">Discurso hecho sobre la significación de impresiones
                            meteorológicas que se vieron el año pasado de 1652</title>
                        <pubPlace>México</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>imprenta de Juan Ruiz</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Sigüenza y Góngora, Carlos de</author>
                        <date>1690</date>
                        <title level="m">Libra astronómica y philosophica</title>
                        <pubPlace>México</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Viuda de Bernardo Calderón</publisher>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl><author>Carlos de Sigüenza y Góngora</author>
                        <date>1984</date>
                        <title level="m">Seis obras</title>
                        <editor>Cullen Bryant, William</editor>
                        <pubPlace>Caracas</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Biblioteca Ayacucho</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Moreno Corral, Arturo</author>
                        <date>1998</date>
                        <title level="m">Historia de la astronomía en México</title>
                        <pubPlace>Mexico</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>FCE</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Trabulse, Elías</author>
                        <date>1994a</date>
                        <title level="m">Historia de la ciencia en México</title>
                        <pubPlace>México</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>FCE</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Trabulse, Elías</author>
                        <date>1994b</date>
                        <title level="m">Los orígenes de la ciencia moderna en México.
                            1630-1680</title>
                        <pubPlace>México</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>FCE</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Carlos de Sigüenza y Góngora</author>
                        <date>2001</date>
                        <title level="m">Libra astronómica y philosophica</title><editor>Trabulse,
                            Elías</editor>
                        <pubPlace>México</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Sociedad Mexicana de Bibliófilos</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Carlos de Sigüenza y Góngora</author><date>1959</date>
                        <title level="m">Libra astronómica y philosophica</title><editor>Navarro,
                            Bernave</editor>
                        <pubPlace>México</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Warwick, C.</author>
                        <author>Galina, I.</author>
                        <author>Rimmer, J.</author>
                        <author>Terras, M.</author>
                        <author>Blandford, A.</author>
                        <author>Gow, J.</author>
                        <author>Buchanan, G.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Documentation and the users of digital resources in the
                            humanities</title>
                        <title level="j">Journal of Documentation</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">65(1)</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">33-57</biblScope></bibl>
                    <!--<bibl><author>Escobar Salemerón y Castro, José de</author>
                        <date>1681</date>
                        <title level="m">Discurso Cometológico y relación del nuevo cometa</title>
                        <pubPlace>México</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Viuda de Bernardo Calderón</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Evelino, Gaspar Juan</author>
                        <date>1682</date>
                        <title level="m">Especulación astrologica y physica de la naturaleza de los
                            cometas, y juizio del que este año de 1682 se ve por todo el
                            mundo</title>
                        <pubPlace>México</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Viuda de Bernardo Calderón</publisher>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kino, Eusebio Francisco</author><date>1681</date>
                        <title level="m">Exposicion astronomica de el cometa</title>
                        <pubPlace>México</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Francisco Rodríguez Luprecio</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>López Bonilla, Gabriel</author><date>1675</date>
                        <title level="m">Discurso y relación Cometographica</title>
                        <pubPlace>México</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Viuda de Bernardo Calderón</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Rodríguez, Diego</author>
                        <date>1652</date>
                        <title level="m">Discurso etheorologico del nuevo cometa visto en aqueste
                            hemisferio mexicano y generalmente en todo el mundo</title>
                        <pubPlace>México</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Viuda de Bernardo Calderón</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Rodríguez, Diego</author>
                        <title level="u">Modo de calcular qualquier eclipse de Sol y Luna según las
                            tablas arriba puestas del mobimiento de Sol y Luna segun
                            Tychon</title><edition>Manuscrito inédito</edition></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Rodríguez, Diego</author><title level="u">Tratado General de
                            Reloxes de Sol</title><edition>Manuscrito inédito</edition></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Ruiz, Juan</author><date>1653</date>
                        <title level="m">Discurso hecho sobre la significación de impresiones
                            meteorológicas que se vieron el año pasado de 1652</title>
                        <pubPlace>México</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>imprenta de Juan Ruiz</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Sigüenza y Góngora, Carlos de</author>
                        <date>1690</date>
                        <title level="m">Libra astronómica y philosophica</title>
                        <pubPlace>México</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Viuda de Bernardo Calderón</publisher>
                    </bibl>-->
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
