<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-684">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Objective Detection of Plautus' Rules by Computer Support</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Deufert, Marcus</name>
                    <affiliation>Department of Classics, <orgName>University of Leipzig</orgName>,
                        <country>Germany</country></affiliation>
                    <email>mdeufert@eaqua.net</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Blumenstein, Judith</name>
                    <affiliation>Department of Classics, <orgName>University of Leipzig</orgName>,
                        <country>Germany</country></affiliation>
                    <email>jblumenstein@eaqua.net</email>
                </author>

                <author>
                    <name>Trebesius, Andreas</name>
                    <affiliation>Department of Classics, <orgName>University of Leipzig</orgName>,
                        <country>Germany</country></affiliation>
                    <email>atrebesius@eaqua.net</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Beyer, Stefan</name>
                    <affiliation>Natural Language Processing Group, Institute of Mathematics and
                        Computer Science, University of Leipzig, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>sbeyer@eaqua.net</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Büchler, Marco</name>
                    <affiliation>Natural Language Processing Group, Institute of Mathematics and
                        Computer Science, University of Leipzig, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>mbuechler@eaqua.net</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-15</date>
                <name>JL</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>The metre of the Roman comic poet Plautus (flourished ca. 200 B.C.) still leaves one
                mystified. Although the scientific work of the 19th and early 20th century has
                established a number of important rules and licences, the exact range of these laws
                and licences remains a matter of debate. Taking into account these many open
                questions it is not surprising that metrical studies (as well as the important
                editions) of Plautus still display a huge amount of discrepancy in their handling of
                Plautine metre. The specific problem consists of the large number of transmitted
                verses in the Plautine corpus and the great complexity and diversity of competing
                explanations of remarkable metrical phenomena.</p>

            <p>Therefore, until now the results of scholarship often fail to convince, since they
                are based either on a limited textual basis or deal with a specific metrical
                phenomenon from the perspective of a single law or licence without taking into
                account competing explanations.</p>

            <p>This paper will cover a wide range of previous research from both Classics (Lotman
                2000) and literature (Garzonio, 2006) to several techniques in the field of Computer
                Science (Heyer et al., 2008 and Volk, 2007). Metric analyses can be already be
                computed on German poems with only a small set of rules (Bobenhausen, 2009). Results
                imply, however, that foreign words are especially difficult to handle. In contrast
                to this, ancient texts pose a different problem as lots of variations of an original
                often exist. For this reason metric analysis can be divided into three different
                tasks: <xmt:uList>
                    <item><label>Task 1</label>: Dealing with different <hi rend="bold"
                            >variations</hi> and variations of variations (Andreev, 2009 and
                        Rehbein, 2009). Within this paper, a primary version of a verse is defined
                        by researchers from Classics. Differences of variants in relation to the
                        primary version are highlighted as described in (Büchler et al.,
                            2009<note>In this paper the same visualisation is used to highlight
                            differences of "literal" citations in a historic context.</note> and
                        Rehbein, 2009). The variance caused by transmissions of several authors is
                        also important to consider, however, when working with fuzziness.
                        Consequently a set of possible metric analysis annotations are suggested
                        rather than just one result.</item>
                    <item><label>Task 2</label>: <hi rend="bold">Applying a metric rule-set</hi> to
                        a text corpus (Bobenhausen, 2009 and Fusi 2008). Within this research -
                        similar to part of speech tagging (Heyer et al., 2003) – a set of rules is
                        applied to text. However, only the most probable metric candidate is
                        selected. In contrast to that research (Bobenhausen, 2009 and Fusi, 2008),
                        the approach in this paper scores several possible metric analyses.</item>
                    <item><label>Task 3</label>: <hi rend="bold">Training of a metric ruleset</hi>
                        based on manually annotated data from researchers. Typically, a fixed set of
                        rules is taken as presumed, however, new rules need to be added manually.
                        This paper thus also focuses on the computation of new rules. The importance
                        of this step is motivated by the Theory of Selective Perception. Based on
                        this, new and uncommon rules are determined by a computer model that is both
                        objective and independent rather than selective like a human being.</item>
                </xmt:uList>
            </p>
            <p>In the field of natural language processing the task of tagging text is quite similar
                to part of speech tagging (POS). Typically, for such a tagger a Hidden Markov Model
                (Heyer et al., 2008) is trained and is traversed by dedicated algorithms like the
                Viterbi algorithm (Heyer et al., 2008). However, the already mentioned fuzziness of
                text variants makes both the training and traversing steps difficult. Furthermore,
                in the training step it is necessary to observe data on a larger window than the
                typical memory of 2 or 3. This would increase the complexity drastically during the
                trainings phase. Within the applying phase the Viterbi algorithm is typically used
                (Heyer et al., 2003). This algorithm reduces all paths locally except the most
                probable one. In metric analysis however this assumption is quite critical since due
                to syllable fusion an senarius is not required to have 12 but can also consist of 17
                or 18 syllables.</p>

            <p>Motivated by the aforementioned problems of existing approaches this paper describes
                a three step approach. In a first step possible syllables are computed. This is
                simply done by using training data. In contrast to German poems (Bobenhausen, 2009)
                the approach is aware of possible fusions of syllables. In the second step all
                possible combinations are computed instantly removing candidates that do not fulfil
                the metric requirements. The training itself is done by distance-based
                co-occurrences (Büchler, 2008) on metric tags. In the last step metric candidates
                are scored based on both the training data as well as the variance of the
                alternatively transmitted variances. All relevant candidates are selected by
                researchers of Classics. The remaining metric analysis is represented in a dedicated
                visualisation highlighting the differences of several variants to the primary
                version (Büchler, 2009 and Rehbein, 2009).</p>

            <p>As an outcome of this paper several results will be shown. Besides the difference
                visualisation both results and experiences in training and application of a metric
                model will be provided.</p>

            <p>Both the expected results and the developed software, which can be easily adapted to
                other ancient poets, will give an original input to the research community and
                motivate and enable further investigations in the same spirit.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>

                    <bibl><author>Andreev, V. S.</author>
                        <date>2009</date><title level="a">Patterns in Style Evolution of
                            Poets</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Digital Humanities
                            2009</title><biblScope type="pp">52-53</biblScope></bibl>

                    <bibl><author>Bobenhausen, K.</author><date>2009</date>)<title level="a"
                            >Automatisches Metrisches Markup</title><title level="m"
                            type="proceedings">Digital Humanities 2009</title><biblScope type="pp"
                            >69-72</biblScope></bibl>

                    <bibl><author>Büchler, M.</author><date>2008</date><title level="m">Elemente
                        einer Forensischen Linguistik</title> Working report</bibl>

                    <bibl>
                        <author>Büchler, M.</author><author>Geßner, A.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Unsupervised Detection and Visualisation of Textual Reuse
                            on Ancient Greek Texts</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">2009 Chicago Colloquium on Digital
                            Humanities and Computer Science</title><name type="venue"
                            >Chicago</name><date type="conference">Nov. 2009</date></bibl>

                    <bibl><author>Fortson, B. W.</author><date>2008</date><title level="a">IV,
                            Language and Rhythm in Plautus</title>
                        <title level="m">Synchronic and Diachronic Studies</title><pubPlace>Berlin /
                        New York</pubPlace></bibl>
                    
                    <bibl><author>Fusi, D.</author><date>2009</date>
                        <title level="m">An Expert System for the Classical Languages: Metrical
                            Analysis Components</title><ptr
                            target="http://www.fusisoft.it/Doc/ActaVenezia.pdf"/><ptr
                            target="http://www.fusisoft.it/Chiron/Metrics/Default.aspx"/>
                        <date type="visited">Nov. 10th 2009</date></bibl>
                    
                    <bibl><author>Garzonio, S.</author><date>2006</date>
                        <title level="a">Italian and Russian Verse: Two Cultures and Two
                            Mentalities</title><title level="j">Studi Slavistici</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">III</biblScope><biblScope type="pp"
                            >187-198</biblScope>
                        
                    </bibl><bibl><author>Heyer, G.</author><author>Quasthoff, U.</author>
                        <author>Wittig, T.</author>
                        <date>2008</date><title level="m">Text Mining: Wissensrohstoff Text –
                            Konzepte, Algorithmen, Ergebnisse. 2nd edition</title>
                        <publisher>W3L-Verlag</publisher></bibl>

                    <bibl><author>Lotman, M.-K.</author><date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Word-ends and Metrical Boundaries in Ancient Iambic
                            Trimeter of Comedy</title><title level="j">Studia Humaniora
                            Tartuensa</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope><biblScope type="pp">1-16</biblScope>
                        <ptr target="http://www.ut.ee/klassik/sht/2000/lotman1.pdf"/><date
                            type="visited">Nov., 10th 2009</date></bibl>

                    <bibl><author>Questa, C.</author><date>2007</date><title level="m">La metrica di
                    Plauto e di Terenzio</title><pubPlace>Urbino</pubPlace></bibl>
                    
                    <bibl><author>Rehbein, M.</author><date>2009</date><title level="a">Multi-Level
                            Variation</title><title level="m" type="proceedings">Digital Humanities
                            Conference Abstracts</title>
                        <date type="conference">2009</date><biblScope type="pp"
                            >11-12</biblScope><date type="conference">2009</date></bibl>

                    <bibl><author>Volk, A.</author><date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">Rhythmic Similarity based on Inner Metric
                            Analysis</title><title level="m" type="proceedings">Utrecht Summer
                            School Multimedia Retrieval</title>
                        <name type="venue">Utrecht</name><date type="conference">Aug.
                        2007</date></bibl>

                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
