<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-628">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>LogiLogi: The Quest for Critical Mass</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Wiersma, Wybo</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>King's College London</orgName> <reg><country>UK</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>mail@wybowiersma.net</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-03-22</date>
                <name>GF</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="poster">
        <body>
            <p>In this abstract, and more so in the poster-presentation, we will report on the
                process of, and the problems involved in, gaining a critical mass of users for an
                interactive hypertext application for the Digital Humanities. The aim of any DH
                application ultimately is to be used, but for collaborative ones, the contributions
                and interactions of existing users are often what make it worthwhile for new
                visitors. Gaining an initial critical mass of users for such applications is
                notoriously hard, but especially important if they are ever to be used at all.</p>
            <p>First we briefly introduce LogiLogi, the system on which we are going to try to get a
                community started. Next our strategy for gaining users, some possible improvements,
                and attempts so far, are explained. Here we will also discuss the kinds of users we
                target, and the possible size of the application&apos;s critical mass. We finish
                with an overview of the usage-data that our poster will report on. </p>
            <div>
                <head>System</head>
                <p>LogiLogi is a Web 2.0 application that tries to find an informal middle-road
                    between good conversations and journal-papers by providing a form of quick,
                    informal publication, peer-review, and annotation of short philosophical texts.
                    It is intended for all those ideas that one cannot turn into a full-sized paper,
                    but that one deems too interesting to leave to the winds.</p>
                <p>It does not make use of forum-threads (avoiding their many problems), but of tags
                    and links that can also be attached to phrases by people other than the text's
                    original author. It also features a rating-system modelled after journal-based
                    review. Well-rated texts earn authors more voting-power, and thus a measure of
                    standing, within their peer group (of which there are multiple).</p>
                <p>LogiLogi is Free Software, and has been under development for 3 years, during
                    which about 30 volunteers have done 8 man-years of work (worth $500.000). A
                    public beta is already online and fully functional at <ref
                        target="http://www.LogiLogi.org" type="external">www.LogiLogi.org.</ref>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Strategy</head>
                <p>Things that have been done so far to gain users are, first of all, making sure
                    that LogiLogi works properly. LogiLogi has been extensively tested and improved
                    at the LIRMM lab of the University of Montpellier this September. And it was
                    used there by about 30 active users for internal discussions until the end of
                    October. Secondly, some seed-content has been added (about 100 philosophical
                    texts, some of which are part of larger essays). And finally, since October, it
                    has been made easy for users to track new replies, annotations, and votes for
                    their documents, both through a personalized RSS feed, and e-mail alerts. These
                    things have made LogiLogi practically usable for the first time. </p>
                <div>
                    <head>Target Audience</head>
                    <p>LogiLogi has not yet been advertised widely, and changing this is one of the
                        first things we will do next. LogiLogi aims for a wide audience of scholars,
                        students, and people interested in philosophy, but to set the right tone, we
                        first aim for people with academic credentials (students and scholars).
                        Among them, most success is expected with students, both because of their
                        limited access to other publishing channels, and their greater average
                        computer-literacy. Possible places to reach them are forums, newsgroups, and
                        (limited) advertising via Google Adwords. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Process</head>
                    <p>Then, as part of user-driven, agile development, feedback will be collected
                        from users on possible improvements: both ongoing, from users on the web,
                        and from a small group of philosophers/students in a usability test. Some of
                        these improvements will then be implemented, after which we plan to repeat
                        the process, with another round of usability testing and improvements. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Improvements</head>
                    <p>A possible improvement so far identified is simplifying the application, for
                        example by (temporarily) limiting the number of voting-communities
                        (peergroups) to one. This would have the additional advantage of reducing
                        the number of users that are needed to reach critical mass, because votes
                        are no longer limited to, and divided between groups. While it is hard to
                        determine what the critical mass of LogiLogi would be, from what we saw in
                        the LIRMM case, it most likely lies between 30 to 60 active users per
                        peergroup (or for the whole site, if there is only one peergroup). To
                        examine this further, a small literature study of the notion of critical
                        mass, and of the factors influencing its size (especially for hypertext
                        based applications, close to the humanities) will also be undertaken.</p>
                    <p>Another place for improvement is the editing and annotation process: its
                        responsiveness, especially, could be improved. LogiLogi currently requires
                        people to open a new page when they want to insert annotations or links,
                        while it would be a lot easier if this could be done while reading the text,
                        at least for simple annotations. And finally, a demo-video will be created,
                        which quickly explains what LogiLogi is, and how it can be used. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Report</head>
                    <p>In our poster we will present LogiLogi, explain the notion of critical mass,
                        and report on developments in the number of users. In addition, the
                        strategies and improvements we applied, and their practical, and causal
                        relationships will be explained, where possible. Also, we will not just be
                        reporting the number of registered users, or unique visitors, but also on
                        the number of documents, annotations, replies, and votes given over the
                        time-period from December 2009 until June 2010. Thus a detailed view will be
                        given of the process of gaining critical mass. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>Whether we succeed or not in gaining a critical mass for LogiLogi, there will be
                    meaningful results from this experiment, as it not only involves presenting, or
                    further improving an already quite usable interactive Digital Humanities
                    application, but foremostly trying to give it a critical mass of users, and
                    exploring this process, producing insights and a valuable case-study (of success
                    or failure) for future Digital Humanities projects to learn from: projects which
                    will, most likely, be more interactive than their predecessors, and thus will
                    sooner or later face the same challenge of gaining a critical mass of users.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Acknowledgements</hi><lb/>We are grateful to Lars Buitinck,
                    Maarten Geraedts, Allan van Hulst, Auke Klazema, Bart Leusink, Miguel Lezama,
                    Charl Linssen, Jan Mikac, Steffen Michels, Roel 3 van Rijswijk, Bruno Sarlo,
                    Thierry Stamper, Artyom Syazantsev, Rens van Summeren, Pieter van der Vlis,
                    Jordy Voesten, Ilona Wilmont, Andrew Wolters and Feng Zhu for their
                    contributions to the development of LogiLogi over the years. Among them we want
                    to especially thank Bruno, Charl, Miguel, and Steffen, without whom LogiLogi
                    would not have been what it is today.</p>
                <p>We would also like to thank the Philosophy Department of the University of
                    Groningen for the initial small grant that got LogiLogi started, and the
                    University of Nijmegen which twice provided a group of Computer and Information
                    Science students to work on LogiLogi for credits as part of their GIPHouse
                    program. In addition we are grateful to the OFSET (Organization for Free
                    Software in Education and Teaching) foundation for supporting us with a small
                    grant.</p>
                <p>We would also like to thank the audiences of our presentations at the FOSDEM
                    (Free and Open source Software Developers&apos; European Meeting) of 2007 and
                    2009 in Brussels, the TDOSE (Technical Dutch Open Source Event) of 2007 in
                    Eindhoven, the Netherlands, the ECAP (European conference on Computing and
                    Philosophy) conferences of 2008 and 2009 in Montpellier and Barcelona, the
                    Digital Humanities 2008 conference in Oulu, Finland, the RMLL (Rencontres
                    Mondiales du Logiciel Libre) of 2008 in Mont-de-Marssan, France, the FKFT (Free
                    Knowledge, Free Technology Conference) of 2008 in Barcelona, and the
                    Philosophers Rally of 2009 in Enschede, the Netherlands, for their questions and
                    insightful comments.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Abrahamsson, P. et al.</author>
                        <date>2002</date>
                        <title level="a">Agile Software Development Methods: Review and
                            Analysis</title>
                        <title level="j">VTT Publications</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">478</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Baez, M. and Casati, F.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Liquid Journals: Knowledge Dissemination in the Web
                            Era</title>
                        <title level="m">LiquidPub Site</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Ball, Philip</author>
                        <date>2005</date>
                        <title level="m">Critical Mass: How One Thing Leads to Another</title>
                        <publisher>Arrow Books Ltd</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Economides, Nicholas and Himmelberg, Charles</author>
                        <date>1995</date>
                        <title level="m">Critical Mass and Network Size with Application to the US
                            Fax Market. Tech. rep</title>
                        <publisher>New York University, Leonard N. Stern School of Business,
                            Department of Economics</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <ptr target="http://ideas.repec.org/p/ste/nystbu/95-11.html"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Evans, Mark</author>
                        <date>2010</date>
                        <title level="a">What Makes a New Service Sticky?</title>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://www.markevanstech.com/2007/08/03/what-makes-a-new-servicesticky/"
                        />
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Gladwell, Malcolm</author>
                        <date>2002</date>
                        <title level="m">The Tipping Point: How Little Things Can Make a Big
                            Difference</title>
                        <publisher>Abacus</publisher><edition>New Edition</edition>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Grafton, Anthony</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="m">Worlds Made by Words: Scholarship and Community in the
                            Modern West</title>
                        <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Harvard</pubPlace><edition>1st ed</edition>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Katz, Michael L. and Shapiro, Carl</author>
                        <date>1985</date>
                        <title level="a">Network Externalities, Competition, and
                            Compatibility</title>
                        <title level="j">American Economic Review</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">75.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">424-40</biblScope>
                        <ptr target="http://ideas.repec.org/a/aea/aecrev/v75y1985i3p424-40.html"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kemper, Andreas</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="m">Valuation of Network Effects in Software Markets: A Complex
                            Networks Approach</title>
                        <publisher>Physica-Verlag Heidelberg</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Heidelberg</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kolb, David</author>
                        <date>2005</date>
                        <title level="a">Association and Argument: Hypertext in and around the
                            Writing Process</title>
                        <title level="j">The New Review of Hypermedia and Multimedia: Applications
                            and Research</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">7-26</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kumar, V.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">Critical Mass in E-Education</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Eighth IEEE International Conference on
                            Advanced Learning Technologies, 2008</title>
                        <name type="venue">Santander, Cantabria, Spain</name>
                        <date type="conference">2008</date>
                        <biblScope type="pp">1009–1010</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Levinson, Paul</author>
                        <date>2001</date>
                        <title level="m">Digital McLuhan: A Guide to the Information
                            Millennium</title>
                        <publisher>Routledge</publisher><edition>New Edition</edition>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Liebowitz, S. J.</author>
                        <date>2010</date>
                        <title level="m">Network Externalities</title>
                        <ptr target="http://www.utdallas.edu/~liebowit/palgrave/network.html"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>LogiLogi.org</author>
                        <title level="m">Philosophy Beyond the Book</title>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <ptr target="http://en.logilogi.org"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Marwell, Gerald and Oliver, Pamela</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="m">The Critical Mass in Collective Action</title>
                        <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher><edition>1st ed</edition>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Nadeau, Richard, Cloutier, Edouard and Guay, J. H.</author>
                        <date>1993</date>
                        <title level="a">New Evidence About the Existence of a Bandwagon Effect in
                            the Opinion Formation Process</title>
                        <title level="j">International Political Science Review/ Revue
                            internationale de science pol</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">14.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">203-213</biblScope>
                        <ptr target="http://ips.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/14/2/203"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>O&apos;Hear, Stephen</author>
                        <date>2004</date>
                        <title level="a">Critical mass</title>
                        <title level="j">Times Educational Supplement</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">4564</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">74</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Papadimoulis, Alex</author>
                        <date>2010</date>
                        <title level="m">The Great Pyramid of Agile - The Daily WTF</title>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://thedailywtf.com/Articles/The-Great-Pyramid-of-Agile.aspx"
                        />
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Prasarnphanich, P. and Wagner, C.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">Creating Critical Mass in Collaboration Systems: Insights
                            from Wikipedia</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">2nd IEEE International Conference on
                            Digital Ecosystems and Technologies, 2008</title>
                        <name type="venue">Phitsanulok, Thailand</name>
                        <date type="conference">2008</date>
                        <biblScope type="pp">126–130</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Prasarnphanich, P. and Wagner, C.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">Explaining the Sustainability of Digital Ecosystems based
                            on the Wiki Model through Critical Mass Theory</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Schachter, Joshua</author>
                        <date>2010</date>
                        <title level="m">Del.icio.us: How tags exploit the self-interest of
                            individuals to organize the Web for everyone</title>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://www.technologyreview.com/tr35/Profile.aspx?Cand=T&amp;TRID=432"
                        />
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Sundararajan, Arun</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="m">Network Effects</title>
                        <ptr target="http://oz.stern.nyu.edu/io/network.html"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>The LogiLogi Foundation</author>
                        <title level="m">Software Libre for Your Web of Free Deliberation</title>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <ptr target="http://foundation.logilogi.org/"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Wagner, C. et al.</author>
                        <date>20XX</date>
                        <title level="a">Creating a Successful Professional Virtual Community: A
                            Sustainable Digital Ecosystem for Idea Sharing</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Wiersma, W. and David, S.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Two Scholarly Web-Agoras: The LogiLogi and Talia/Philospace
                            Approaches</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">ECAP 2009 Abstract</title>
                        <name type="venue">Barcelona, Spain</name>
                        <date type="conference">2009</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Wiersma, W. and Lezama, M.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">LogiLogi: Combining Openness and Quality of Content</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">FKFT 2008 Proceedings</title>
                        <date type="conference">2008</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Wiersma, W. and Sarlo, B.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">LogiLogi: A Webplatform for Philosophers</title>
                        <title level="m">Digital Humanities 2008 Book of Abstracts</title>
                        <publisher>University of Oulu</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Oulu, Finland</pubPlace>
                        <biblScope type="pp">221–222</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Wiersma, Wybo</author>
                        <date>2010</date>
                        <title level="m">LogiLogi: Philosophy Beyond the Book</title>
                        <ptr target="http://www.logilogi.org/pub/beyond/paper.pdf"/>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
