<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="ab-709">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Coalition of Humanities and Arts Infrastructures and Networks - CHAIN</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Wynne, Martin</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of Oxford</orgName>, <country>UK</country></affiliation>
                    <email>martin.wynne@oucs.ox.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Anderson, Sheila</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>King's College London</orgName> (DARIAH) <reg><country>UK</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>sheila.anderson@kcl.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Fraistat, Neil</name>
                    <affiliation>Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities, <orgName>University of Maryland</orgName> (centerNet) <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>fraistat@mac.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Kainz, Chad</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of Chicago</orgName> (Project Bamboo) <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>cjkainz@uchicago.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Krauwer, Steven</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Utrecht University</orgName> (CLARIN) <reg><country>Netherlands</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>s.krauwer@uu.nl</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Robey, David</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of Oxford</orgName> (Network of Expert Centres) <reg><country>UK</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>d.j.b.robey@reading.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Short, Harold</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>King's College London</orgName> (ADHO) <reg><country>UK</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>harold.short@kcl.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-29</date>
                <name>GF</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
        <text type="session">
            <body>
                <p>A panel will discuss areas of cooperation and practical work between the
                various initiatives engaged in building e-infrastructure to support the next
                generation digital research in the Humanities.
                </p>
                <p>Following from a panel session at DH2009, in October 2009 representatives of
                    numerous important associations, networks and projects met and resolved to
                    form <hi rend="italic">CHAIN</hi> – the Coalition of Humanities and Arts Infrastructures and
                    Networks. The initial &apos;CHAIN Gang&apos; comprised:
                    <xmt:uList>
                        <item>arts-humanities.net</item>
                        <item>ADHO - Association of Digital Humanities Organisations</item>
                        <item>CLARIN</item>
                        <item>centerNet</item>
                        <item>DARIAH</item>
                        <item>NoC - Network of Expert Centres in Great Britain and Ireland</item>
                        <item>Project Bamboo</item>
                        <item>TextGrid</item>
                    </xmt:uList>
                </p>
                <p>The representatives of these various initiatives identified the current
                    fragmented environment where researchers operate in separate areas with
                    often mutually incompatible technologies as a barrier to fully exploiting the
                    transformative role that these technologies can potentially play. <hi rend="italic">CHAIN</hi>
                    recognised that their current and planned activities were interdependent and
                    complementary and resolved that they should be oriented towards working
                    together to overcome barriers, and to create a shared environment where
                    technology services can interoperate and be sustained, thus enabling new
                    forms of research in the Humanities.
                </p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">CHAIN</hi> will act as a forum for areas of shared interest to its participants,
                    including:
                    <xmt:uList>
                        <item>advocacy for an improved digital research infrastructure for the
                            Humanities;</item>
                        <item>development of sustainable business models;</item>
                        <item>promotion of technical interoperability of resources, tools and services;</item>
                        <item>promotion of good practice and relevant technical standards;</item>
                        <item>development of a shared service infrastructure;</item>
                        <item>coordinating approaches to legal and ethical issues;</item>
                        <item>interactions with other relevant computing infrastructure initiatives;</item>
                        <item>widening the geographical scope of our coalition.</item>
                    </xmt:uList>
                </p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">CHAIN</hi> will promote an open culture where experiences, including successes
                    and failures, can be shared and discussed, in order to support and promote the
                    use of digital technologies in research in the Humanities.
                </p>
                <p>This session will feature panellists from the <hi rend="italic">CHAIN</hi> gang, who will introduce
                    the practical measures that they are engaged in to build a coherent,
                    interoperable and maximally effective services to support research in the
                    Humanities, and will address the following questions:
                    <xmt:uList>
                        <item>What are the main barriers to progress?</item>
                        <item>What are the most exciting opportunities?</item>
                           
                    </xmt:uList>
                </p>
            </body>
        </text>
    </TEI>
    


