<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-766">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Towards a Computational Narration of Inner World</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Zhu, Jichen</name>
                    <affiliation>Department of Digital Media, <orgName>University of Central
                        Florida</orgName> <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>jzh@mail.ucf.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-30</date>
                <name>NG</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>Narrative, as it evolves with technological developments, constantly reinvents
                    itself in order to better capture new social orders and individual experiences.
                    As an emerging cultural expression, however, most computer-generated narrative
                    works are still restricted to an action-based, goal-driven aesthetics, leaving
                    little space for characters’ inner world. This paper proposes to expand the
                    range of computer-generated narrative by addressing this imbalance between the
                    “physical” and the “internal.” It presents our approach for algorithmically
                    narrating characters’ inner world by leveraging the synergy between modernist
                    stream of consciousness literature and contemporary research in artificial
                    intelligence and cognitive science. The <hi rend="italic">Riu</hi> system, a
                    text-based computational narrative system inspired by Woolf’s novel <hi
                        rend="italic">Mrs. Dalloway</hi>, is provided as a case study towards this
                    new direction.</p>
            <div>
                <head>Computer-Generated Narrative</head>
                <p>Contemporary forms of narrative have evolved rapidly as digital technologies
                    continue to be integrated in modern society. New conventions at the levels of
                    both content and discourse have been established to reflect the constantly
                    changing relationship between human and technology. For instance, popular
                    science fictions of the 1980s (e.g., <hi rend="italic">The Terminator</hi>)
                    embodied the prevailing cyborg discourse and confusions of human identity within
                    the Cold War context (Edwards, 1996). Similarly, hypertext fictions in the 1990s
                    instantiated the postmodernist mentality of its time by turning everything –
                    writer, reader, and society – into fragments (Johnson-Eilola, 1997). In this
                    regard, the emerging form of <hi rend="italic">computer-generated
                        narrative</hi>,<note>Although this paper focuses on text-based narratives
                        generated by computer algorithms, the core of the discussion can be extended
                        to other computational narrative forms, such as video games.</note> that
                    is, stories produced by computer algorithms, may offer an important cultural
                    expression to portray our increasingly technology-dependent modern life.</p>
                <p>Compared to other forms of electronic literature (e.g., hypertext fictions), the
                    strict technological requirements for computer-generated narrative have confined
                    its development largely to the computer science community, particularly
                    artificial intelligence (AI). Over the past decades, serious attempts have been
                    made to integrate narratology theory into existing AI framework for story
                    generation (Bringsjord &amp; Ferrucci, 2000; Cavazza &amp; Pizzi, 2006; Mateas,
                    2002; Meehan, 1976). Despite the considerable progress the community has made,
                    the expressive power of computer-generated narrative is still limited compared
                    to its non-digital antecedents. In particular, this paper is concerned with the
                    prominent goal-driven, problem-solving aesthetics that dominate many story
                    generation systems. A salient example is the <hi rend="italic">Tale-Spin</hi>
                    system (Meehan, 1976), which generates stories in the spirit of: Joe Bear was
                    hungry; Joe couldn’t reach his food because of certain obstacles; Joe resolved
                    the issues; Joe got his food. </p>
                <p>It is true that recent narrative systems have evolved in numerous aspects since
                    then. Nevertheless, this ultra-rational, &quot;behaviorist&quot; narrative
                    style, afforded by Meehan’s now-widely-adopted planning-based framework, has
                    remained and been taken for granted by many practitioners. As we become more
                    aware of digital media’s capability of constructing subjective mental imagery
                    and evoking users’ imagination and awareness (Harrell, 2009), it is crucial to
                    revisit some of these early assumptions of computer-generated narrative and
                    critically understand the expressive affordances as well as restrictions of the
                    computational techniques that we use. </p>
                <p>This paper proposes to expand the spectrum of computer-generated narratives by
                    focusing on the richness of characters’ inner world, hidden behind the external
                    world of actions. This approach aligns with modernist writers’ concerns of
                    depicting &quot;hidden life at its source&quot; (Woolf, 1957 [1925]). Notice
                    this is not a strong AI attempt to model human (semi-)consciousness. Instead,
                    the goal is to explore new ways of conveying human subjectivity and life stories
                    by algorithmically generating <hi rend="italic">narratives</hi> that are
                    reminiscent of similar phenomena. Informed by modernist literary techniques
                    (particularly Virginia Woolf’s work), cognitive science discoveries and AI, this
                    paper proposes a new approach for generating inner narratives and presents
                    initial results from our on-going narrative project <hi rend="italic"
                    >Riu</hi>.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Synergy of the Old and New</head>
                <p>As argued elsewhere (Zhu &amp; Harrell, 2010 (forthcoming)), the overlooked
                    synergy between stream of consciousness literature, artificial intelligence
                    (AI), and cognitive science provides valuable insights to generating stories
                    about characters’ inner world. In their respective historical contexts, both
                    stream of consciousness literature and AI challenged the domination of
                    behaviorism by turning <hi rend="italic">internally</hi> to the human psyche.
                    Rejecting the literary representation of characters as the &quot;external
                    man&quot;, modernist writers such as Virginia Woolf and James Joyce invented
                    techniques to depict the moment-by-moment psychic existence and functioning of
                    the &quot;internal man&quot; (Humphrey, 1954). Similarly, AI broke away from the
                    behaviorism-dominated scientific community in the 1950s and legitimated human
                    mental constructs, such as knowledge and reasoning, as crucial subjects of
                    scientific inquiries.</p>
                <p>The differences between AI and modernist literature further dissolve when we take
                    account of recent cognitive science theory, a sister field of AI. Stream of
                    consciousness literature’s key concern with pre-speech level of consciousness,
                    minimally mediated by rationality and language, is echoed by new discoveries in
                    cognitive linguistics. Recent research (Fauconnier &amp; Turner, 2002) has
                    confirmed that the vast cognitive resources of &quot;backstage cognition&quot;
                    are called up unconsciously when we engage in any language activity.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Generating Inner Narratives</head>
                <p>Generating narratives about characters’ inner world requires innovation at the
                    story content, discourse and algorithmic levels. The techniques in stream of
                    consciousness literature offer invaluable insights into literary representations
                    of inner life, such as Woolf’s loosely structured plot, the &quot;caves&quot; of
                    characters’ past (Woolf, 1957 [1925]), and various modes of interior monologues
                    (Cohn, 1978). </p>
                <p>The insights from planning-generated stories illustrate the impact of underlying
                    computational techniques. Substantial changes at the algorithmic level therefore
                    are needed to incorporate the new content and aesthetic requirements. As we have
                    argued (Zhu &amp; Ontañón, 2010), computational analogy, influenced by related
                    cognitive science studies, is one of the promising directions towards our goal.
                    Its emphasis on similarities and associations between different constructs is
                    particularly useful to establish connections between external events and inner
                    thoughts (e.g., the action of &quot;buying flowers&quot; and flower-related
                    memories). Computational analogy may also be used to depict &quot;the train of
                    thoughts&quot; by connecting a sequence of related events, one after another.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Case Study: <hi rend="italic">Riu</hi></head>
                <p>Our generative narrative project Riu is an on-going attempt to computationally
                    generated stories about characters’ inner world. Inspired by Woolf’s novel <hi
                        rend="italic">Mrs. Dalloway</hi> (Woolf, 2002 (1925)), this project
                    harnesses computational analogy at different levels of story generation for
                    various narrative effects (Zhu &amp; Ontañón, 2010). Similar to our earlier
                    conceptual-blending-based (Fauconnier &amp; Turner, 2002) project <hi
                        rend="italic">Memory, Reverie Machine</hi> (Zhu &amp; Harrell, 2010
                    (forthcoming)), <hi rend="italic">Riu</hi> is explicitly geared towards
                    algorithmically narrating characters’ inner world, through the depiction of
                    characters’ unrolling thoughts and subjective variations of such thoughts based
                    on user interaction. An excerpt of system output at the current stage of
                    development can be found in Fig 1. </p>
                <p><figure xml:id="fig1">
                    <head>Figure 1. Sample output of <hi rend="italic">Riu</hi> (including user input)</head>
                        <graphic url="766_Fig1.tif" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                            mimeType="image/tif"/>
                    </figure></p>
                <p>Rather than ordering events in ways that lead to a desired goal, as in many
                    planning-based systems, <hi rend="italic">Riu</hi> adopts the computational
                    analogy algorithm of structural mapping (Falkenhainer, Forbus &amp; Gentner,
                    1989; Gentner, 1983) to connect external events with inner thoughts. The overall
                    plot is loosely structured with potential inner thoughts between various
                    external events. The overall story intends to invoke what Woolf described as
                    &quot;no plot, no comedy, no tragedy, no love interest or catastrophe&quot;
                    (Woolf, 1957 [1925]) and thus focuses primarily on characters’ psyche. </p>
                <p>In Fig 1, the protagonist’s memory of a pet bird (italicized) is triggered
                    because of its similarity to his encounter of another animal in the external
                    story world. Importantly, inner events such as memories in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Riu</hi> also have a significant impact on the protagonist’s external
                    actions. In the case of Fig 1, when the user chooses to play with the cat on the
                    street, the system infers that this action may, again, lead to the death of the
                    cat and hence the protagonist’s sadness. In order to prevent that from
                    happening, the system ignores this user command and removes &quot;play&quot;
                    from the next user input options. </p>
                <p>In conclusion, computer-generated narrative is an important frontier in digital
                    humanities as a potential cultural expression innate to our contemporary
                    society. Drawn on the synergy between stream of consciousness literature,
                    artificial intelligence, and cognitive science, this paper proposed a new
                    approach for expanding its narrative spectrum and focusing on characters’ inner
                    world with its connection to external behaviors and environments. The <hi
                        rend="italic">Riu</hi> system was used to illustrate the initial results of
                    our work, which suggests new expressive possibilities afforded by our
                    approach.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bringsjord, S. &amp; Ferrucci, D. A. </author>
                        <date>2000</date>
                        <title level="m">Artificial Intelligence and Literary Creativity: Inside the
                            Mind of Brutus, a Storytelling Machine</title>
                        <publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Hillsdale, NJ</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Cavazza, M. &amp; Pizzi, D.</author>
                        <date>2006</date>
                        <title level="a">Narratology for Interactive Storytelling: A Critical
                            Introduction</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Proceedings of TIDSE</title>
                        <date type="conference">2006</date>
                        <biblScope type="pp">72-83</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Edwards, P. N.</author>
                        <date>1996</date>
                        <title level="m">The Closed World: Computers and the Politics of Discourse
                            in Cold War America</title>
                        <publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Cambridge, Mass.</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Falkenhainer, B., Forbus, K. D. &amp; Gentner, D. </author>
                        <date>1989</date>
                        <title level="a">The Structure-Mapping Engine: Algorithm and
                            Examples</title>
                        <title level="j">Artificial Intelligence</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">41</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">1-63</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Fauconnier, G. &amp; Turner, M. </author>
                        <date>2002</date>
                        <title level="m">The Way We Think: Conceptual Blending and the Mind's Hidden
                            Complexities</title>
                        <publisher>Basic Books</publisher>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Gentner, D.</author>
                        <date>1983</date>
                        <title level="a">Structure-Mapping: A Theoretical Framework for
                            Analogy</title>
                        <title level="j">Cognitive Science</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">155-70</biblScope>
                    </bibl>

                    <bibl>
                        <author>Harrell, D. F.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Toward a Theory of Phantasmal Media: An Imaginative
                            Cognition and Computation-Based Approach to Digital Media</title>
                        <title level="j">CTheory</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Humphrey, R.</author>
                        <date>1954</date>
                        <title level="m">Stream of Consciousness in the Modern Novel</title>
                        <publisher>University of California Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley and Los Angeles</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>

                    <bibl>
                        <author>Johnson-Eilola, J.</author>
                        <date>1997</date>
                        <title level="m">Nostalgic Angels: Rearticulating Hypertext Writing</title>
                        <publisher>Ablex Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Norwood, NJ</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Mateas, M.</author>
                        <date>2002</date>
                        <title level="m">Interactive Drama, Art, and Artificial Intelligence</title>
                        <publisher>Carnegie Mellon University</publisher>
                        <edition>Ph.D.
                            dissertation</edition>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Meehan, J.</author>
                        <date>1976</date>
                        <title level="m">The Metanovel: Writing Stories by Computer</title> 
                        <publisher>Yale University</publisher><edition>Ph.D.
                            dissertation</edition>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Woolf, V.</author>
                        <date>1957 [1925]</date>
                        <title level="a">Modern Fiction</title>
                        <title level="m">The Common Reader: First Series</title>
                        <editor>V Woolf </editor>
                        <publisher>Hogarth Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Woolf, V.</author>
                        <date>2002 [1925]</date>
                        <title level="m">Mrs. Dalloway</title>
                        <publisher>Harcourt </publisher>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Zhu, J. &amp; Harrell, D. F.</author>
                        <date>2010: forthcoming</date>
                        <title level="a">Computational Narration of Inner Thought: Memory, Reverie
                            Machine</title>
                        <title level="m">Hyperrhiz: New Media Cultures</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Zhu, J. &amp; Ontañón, S.</author>
                        <date>2010</date>
                        <title level="a">Towards Analogy-Based Story Generation</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Proceedings of the First International
                            Conference on Computational Creativity (ICCC X)</title>
                        <name type="venue">Lisbon, Portugal</name>
                        <date type="conference">2010</date>
                    </bibl>


                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
