<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-789">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>A New Spatial Analysis of the Early Chesapeake Architecture</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Graham, Wayne</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of Virginia</orgName> <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>wayne.graham@virginia.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-29</date>
                <name>AC</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="poster">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Practitioners of the "new social history," which came to prominence beginning in
                    the 1960s and 70s, utilized digital tools and data-driven methodologies to glean
                    an understanding of people who left little documentary record of their daily
                    lives. Perhaps most enduring of these techniques has been the utilization of
                    quantitative methods to describe communities and to build better arguments about
                    the daily lives of historical subjects. The focus for these historians is not
                    only the high points thought worthy of record in diaries, newspapers, or court
                    papers, but also how quotidian interaction and daily chores – such as cooking,
                    cleaning, or plowing – were accomplished and how their patterns differed across
                    regions. While quantitative techniques have yielded a rich analysis of the past,
                    temporal, social, and geographic dimensions of historical data often diverge and
                    can be muddled in the choices scholars make about how best to tell their story
                    given time and resource considerations, as well as how to argue the larger
                    points of a particular person's, event's, or object's societal influence.</p>
                <p>In our recent work at the Scholars' Lab at the University of Virginia Library
                    (where we support geospatial technology in the humanities and social sciences
                    and have recently played host to an NEH-funded Institute for Enabling Geospatial
                    Scholarship and a Mellon Scholarly Communication Institute on spatial tools and
                    methods), we have been advocating the idea that incorporating geographic
                    information systems into projects can yield interesting new interpretative
                    apparatus for scholarship. This is neither a new concept, or an especially easy
                    path to take. Martyn Jessop has detailed the obstacles to incorporation of
                    geospatial information in humanities research in the pages of Literary and
                    Linguistic Computing.<note>Martyn Jessop, “The Inhibition of Geographical
                        Information in Digital Humanities Scholarship,” Lit Linguist Computing
                        (November 20, 2007): fqm041.</note>However, to test the approaches we
                    advocate to others, I decided to revisit a project that I undertook a few years
                    ago with several prominent historians and archaeologists of the architectural
                    development of the Colonial Chesapeake.<note> Willie Graham, Carter L. Hudgins,
                        Carl R. Lounsbury, Fraser D. Neiman and James P. Whittenburg, “Adaptation
                        and Innovation: Archaeological and Architectural Perspectives on the
                        Seventeenth-Century Chesapeake,” The William and Mary Quarterly 64, no. 3
                        (July 2007),<ref
                            target="http://www.historycooperative.org/journals/wm/64.3/graham.html"
                            rend="newWindow" type="external">
                            http://www.historycooperative.org/journals/wm/64.3/graham.html.</ref></note>
                    While the data resulting from their work is the basis of two important essays on
                    Chesapeake architecture, and additionally served as the framework for an NEH
                    grant investigating the development of slave quarters in Virginia, it has
                    languished and few outside the project team actually know of the data’s
                        existence.<note>See Doug Sanford (University of Mary Washington) and Dennis
                        Pogue (Mount Vernon), "Measuring the Social, Spatial, and Temporal
                        Dimensions of Virginia Slave Housing," National Endowment for the
                        Humanities, 2009 and Cary Carson et al., “New World, Real World: Improvising
                        English Culture in Seventeenth-Century Virginia,” Journal of Souther History
                        LXXIV (February 2008).</note> I considered this a perfect example of an
                    important project to rethink by adding a more defined geographic dimension to
                    its analytical approach. Could the application of GIS technologies further test
                    our long-held beliefs about the development of the Chesapeake?</p>
                <p>In their seminal essay on "impermanent" Chesapeake architecture, Cary Carson,
                    Norman Barka, William Kelso, Gary Wheeler Stone, and Dell Upton first attempted
                    systematically to synthesize and analyze data extracted from several
                    investigations into early Chesapeake architecture.<note>Cary Carson et al.,
                        “Impermanent Architecture in Southern American Colonies,” in <hi
                            rend="italic">Material Life in America</hi>, 1600-1860 (Boston: Northern
                        University Press, 1988), 113-158.</note> This article was squarely focused
                    on the structures settlers built between first shelters and more durable
                    buildings. Despite the genius of their work, the Carson team was limited in that
                    archaeological work in the Chesapeake region was then still young, and the data
                    from a scant two dozen sites supported their analysis.</p>
                <p>In the nearly three decades since this piece was published, more than ten times
                    that number of sites has been identified and excavated. However, this boom in
                    investigation of the Colonial Chesapeake resulted not in masses of usable data
                    for broad-scale analysis, but in the explosion of a so-called "gray
                    literature"—reports produced for project clients and funding organizations, but
                    circulated only in limited numbers. Often, after their initial compilation,
                    these reports have languished in state or institutional archives and little
                    systematic work has been done to organize, or even make available, this often
                    tangled mass of data. As a result, the accumulation of archaeological data has
                    far outpaced its published analysis. Further complicating matters are embargoes
                    placed upon research reports (usually meant to help protect against artifact
                    theft) that even further distance access to raw facts on these early sites from
                    the hands of researchers. </p>
                <p>In conjunction with celebrations marking the 400<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                    anniversary of the founding of the Jamestown settlement, a new team (consisting
                    of Willie Graham, Carter Hudgins, Carl Lounsbury, Fraser Neiman, James
                    Whittenburg, and myself) looked to the more recent archaeology.<note>The data
                        that the "Adaptation and Innovation: Archaeological and Architectural
                        Perspectives on the Seventeenth-Century Chesapeake" and “New World, Real
                        World: Improvising English Culture in Seventeenth-Century Virginia,”
                        articles were based on is available for browsing at <ref
                            target="http://deca.swem.wm.edu" rend="newWindow" type="external"
                            >http://deca.swem.wm.edu.</ref></note> Having collected references to
                    archaeological sites mentioned in articles, research reports, conference
                    proceedings, and in personal interviews, Willie Graham of the Colonial
                    Williamsburg Foundation amassed an index of known sites dated before ca. 1720 in
                    the Colonial Chesapeake. From this index, our research team designed a data
                    model that provided a crucial new dimension into this particular facet of
                    history by combining solid statistics pertaining to material culture with an
                    appreciation for the historical discourse in this area of study. Dubbed the
                    Database of Early Chesapeake Architecture (DECA), we took a quantitative
                    approach to this expanded set of archaeological and architectural data making it
                    possible for the first time to accurately date significant shifts in the
                    cultural repertoires of Chesapeake colonists and link them in convincing – and
                    testable – ways to the unique ecological, economic, and social conditions to
                    which they were a response. Through the use of solid data modeling techniques,
                    information from hundreds of new archaeological and architectural investigations
                    provided a fresh opportunity to analyze the emergence of regional building
                    practices and chart the dynamics of social interaction in the tobacco colonies
                    through the arrangement of planters’ houses and outhouses, as well as in the
                    types of goods the colonists possessed and food they consumed.</p>
                <p>When the database was initially designed, it was composed of a handful of simple
                    tables detailing building and phase dates, dimensions, floor plan types, chimney
                    types, and foundation characteristics and documented using the unified modeling
                    language (UML). As the project progressed, the database structure evolved to
                    include owner information and documentary references, resulting in a complex
                    implementation of relational tables. However, the only documentation of place
                    was in the recording of a town or county in which the site was located.</p>
                <p>My current work reimagines the original DECA project to include not only its core
                    statistical information, but also well-defined geographic locations allowing
                    scholars to ask new questions of the data and visualize them in new and
                    compelling ways. Through the addition of well-constructed geospatial
                    information, and the application of tools and methods, we are refining a more
                    striking analysis of the Chesapeake data for the use of our faculty
                    collaborators in the Scholars' Lab. A new presentation, not only of traditional
                    statistical outputs (distribution curves, ANOVA tables, etc.), but of
                    distribution patterns in architectural and archaeological details manifested
                    across time and across the landscape of the Chesapeake, affords researchers even
                    more insight into regional differentiation in building patterns, and more
                    striking opportunities to display and engage their data. This presentation will
                    describe the spatial tools and methods we advocate in the Scholars' Lab
                    including the use of the PostGIS data store, Ruby on Rails (with the GeoKit
                    gem), and OpenLayers, outline their application to the Chesapeake dataset, and
                    offer some observations on lessons (both methodological and substantive) learned
                    in my revisiting of this digital humanities project through the lens of
                    geospatial analysis.</p>
            </div>
            <!-- <div>
                <head>SECOND SECTION</head>
                <p>PARAGRAPH</p>
                <div>
                    <head>SUBSECTION</head>
                    <p>PARAGRAPH</p>
                </div>
            </div>-->
        </body>
        <!-- <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl> REFERENCE </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>-->
    </text>
</TEI>
