<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-780">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>An Open Source Toolkit for Flexible Browsing of Historical Maps on the
                    Web</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Ohno, Shin</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Ritsumeikan University</orgName> <reg><country>Japan</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>ohnoshin@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Saito, Shinya</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Ritsumeikan University</orgName> <reg><country>Japan</country></reg></affiliation>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Inaba, Mitsuyuki</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Ritsumeikan University</orgName> <reg><country>Japan</country></reg></affiliation>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-27</date>
                <name>CD</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
            <change><date>2010-05-13</date><name>CD</name><desc>Modification of the bibliographical
                    references within the text</desc></change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="poster">
        <body>
            <p>Map browsing on the web is now commonly used, and most people have used map services
                such as <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl1">Goole Maps</ref>, <ref type="internal"
                    cRef="bibl2">Google Earth</ref>, and Yahoo! Maps. These services also provide
                developer API, which makes it easy to integrate map services into the website. Map
                browsing in practical use is covered with those services, but displaying historical
                maps as exhibits is not, which requires different approaches.</p>
            <p>We, three members of Web Technology Research Group of the Digital Humanities Center
                of Japanese Arts and Cultures, Ritsumeikan University have developed an image
                viewer, which can handle zooming, panning, and rotating. Although there exist many
                similar toolkits, none has all three features with JavaScript written. Furthermore,
                we would like to share it as open source library.</p>
            <p>This paper starts with elucidating Japanese historical maps, their unique features
                and needs. After that, it discusses our image viewer, its design and implementation
                to meet their needs. </p>
            <div>
                <head>Purpose</head>
                <p>Since Japanese historical maps do not have concepts of geo-coding usually and are
                    distorted, it is difficult to integrate them with map services such as Google
                    Maps.</p>
                <p>Using Keyhole Markup Language (KML) makes it possible to integrate these maps
                    with Google Earth. There is some research on historical maps on Google Earth
                        (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl3">Zeile et al. 2007</ref><ref
                        type="internal" cRef="bibl4">Nishimura et al. 2007</ref>). Although those
                    tools are highly functional for defining 3D geographical information on the web,
                    the user interface is not easy to use for traditional humanities scholars who
                    are normally not familiar with KML language. Moreover, setting the image in
                    Google Earth is not always their priority. Therefore, when it is necessary to
                    exhibit original, hand-drawn maps on the web, one has to take different
                    approaches to integrating these images into the web.</p>
                <p>Because of these issues, image viewers are usually used to implement historical
                    maps for exhibition. These viewers enable users to zoom images, and to see their
                    details if they are provided in high quality. Moreover, today’s high technology
                    for user interface allows us to use such viewers with regular web browsers.</p>
                <p>Since most of these viewers are not open source based applications, however, no
                    room exists for us to extend and add more features. Even though they are
                    provided as open source, most of them depend on a Flash plug-in, and there is no
                    implementation with JavaScript. Because JavaScript is lightweight and easy to be
                    integrated into websites, we have decided to implement this map viewer with
                    JavaScript, and open it to the public as an open source product, and we believe
                    there should be alternative options for us as open source based toolkits for
                    these needs. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Design</head>
                <figure xml:id="fig1">
                    <head>Figure 1: Sample of Japanese historical map</head>
                    <graphic url="780_Fig1.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                </figure>
                <p>In this section, we discuss what kinds of features are required for historical
                    map viewers, and compare them with related software.</p>
                <p>When displaying Japanese historical maps as image exhibits on the Web, we
                    encounter difficulties in handling angles. With no clear concept of top or
                    bottom in these maps, names of places are labeled from many directions. This is
                    related to the fact that people in those days put rather a large map on the
                    table or the floor to read it. Because of this particular feature of the
                    historical maps, as opposed to maps today, browsing tools for these historical
                    maps should provide a way of viewing them from multiple angles. Therefore, we
                    decided to design our tool to support flexible browsing rather than geographical
                    accuracy.</p>
                <p>What we found out about other image viewers is that many can support zooming and
                    panning, but not rotating. Most of them also depend on a Flash plug-in, and
                    there are no implementations with JavaScript. There are comparisons of similar
                    software for viewer of maps or images. <xmt:uList>
                        <item>
                            <label>Google Maps/Google Earth</label> Since their beginning, these
                            services with web browsers have become more commonly used, and more
                            people have become used to them, which in turn has changed the way we
                            access geographical resources. However, historical maps do not have
                            accurate longitude and latitude, and even using KML to integrate them
                            into Google Earth, the images are distorted and we need to change the
                            purpose to display them. Plus, KML is rather complicated to maneuver it
                            very well. <table rend="narrow">
                                <row>
                                    <cell/>
                                    <cell rend="0.8cm"><hi rend="bold">API</hi></cell>
                                    <cell rend="1cm"><hi rend="bold">Free</hi></cell>
                                    <cell><hi rend="bold">Rotat<c>-</c>able</hi></cell>
                                    <cell><hi rend="bold">Zoom<c>-</c>able</hi></cell>
                                    <cell><hi rend="bold">Image Cutting</hi></cell>
                                    <cell><hi rend="bold">Open source</hi></cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell role="label">Google Maps</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>No</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>No</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell role="label">Google Image Cutter</cell>
                                    <cell>No</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>No</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell role="label">Google Earth</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>No</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell role="label">Open Zoom</cell>
                                    <cell>No</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>No</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell role="label">Open Layers</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>No</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell role="label">Ojikit Image Viewer</cell>
                                    <cell>No</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                    <cell>No</cell>
                                    <cell>Yes</cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                        </item>
                        <item><label>GMap Image Cutter by LCU<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl5">GMap
                                    Image Cutter</ref> by LCU</label>: To use Google Maps image
                            viewer, LCU developed GMap Image Cutter tool to cut a large image into
                            many small pieces. With this Cutter provided, users can integrate images
                            to their own website with the same Google Maps user interface. </item>
                        <item><label><ref type="internal" cRef="bibl6">OpenZoom</ref></label>:
                            OpenZoom is a free and open source toolkit for delivering
                            high-resolution images and zoomable user interfaces. Like GMap Image
                            Cutter, it can cut a large image into many small file-size images. With
                            this software, users can download an appropriate file size to their
                            local computer, which works to prevent network traffic from congesting
                            in cases in which the image is too large to download. This is SWF based,
                            and requires a Flash Plugin.</item>
                        <item><label><ref type="bibl7">OpenLayers</ref></label>: OpenLayers is a
                            free and open source library for handling geographical information
                            written in JavaScript. Since OpenLayers implements both WMS(Web Map
                            Service) and Web Feature Service, users can integrate many different
                            maps service to their own website. It has zooming and panning features
                            for browsing maps on the web. </item>
                        <item><label>Ojikit ImageViewer</label> Ojikit Image Viewer is the toolkit
                            we have developed. It has zooming, panning, rotating features, as well
                            as an open source license. While it does not have the function to cut a
                            large image into smaller files, improvement of broadband allows us to
                            transfer files without so much reduction. Moreover, one file is easier
                            to store and manage than many files. </item>
                    </xmt:uList>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Implementation</head>
                <p>Giving consideration to what historical maps viewers need to be, we have
                    developed an open source toolkit. This toolkit is written in JavaScript, and it
                    has lightweight features and an open source license. Written in JavaScript,
                    Mozilla and Safari based browser uses SVG, and the Internet Explorer uses VML to
                    handle vector images. To develop this library seamlessly in different browsers,
                    this library depends on jQuery and Raphael.js.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Application</head>
                <p>We have applied this tool to Japanese historical maps as our Center has a large
                    number of historical map images, open to the public. Unlike other image viewers,
                    which do not support rotating function, this toolkit enables us to rotate all
                    images. Figure 2 shows one example of these map images as they look on the
                    screen. With this toolkit, users can read labels written from many directions,
                    as they are on the map.</p>
                <figure xml:id="fig2">
                    <head>Figure 2: The left map is rotated 130 degrees, and the right map is
                        rotated 210 degrees.</head>
                    <graphic url="780_Fig2a.jpg" rend="left" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    <graphic url="780_Fig2b.jpg" rend="left" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>Addressing a culture-specific problem of Japanese historical maps, this paper
                    discusses current map viewer systems to deal with this problem. This toolkit was
                    developed as a viewer for Japanese historical maps per se. However, its
                    extensive and easy integration feature leads us to consider some other
                    possibility to apply it for other fields that have similar demands such as
                    rotation and zooming features with easy integration. While this toolkit’s
                    development is our on-going project, its source code is meanwhile open to any
                    users.</p>
                <p>There are three future areas of research related to our toolkit. First, we have
                    applied our toolkit to Japanese old maps browsing as a test this time, and we
                    are trying to produce more tests with the toolkit. Secondly, related to the
                    first point, we think that this toolkit is useful not only for maps, but also
                    for other images that need to be browsed from many different directions, such as
                    handwriting manuscripts, and apply different resources. Finally, this toolkit
                    does not consider geo-reference. In our center, there is a group for GIS
                    research, and for future provision, we are discussing how to co-reference its
                    geographical information with each other, so that this tool can represent
                    geo-reference.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl4">
                        <author>Nishimura, Y. et al.</author>
                        <title level="a">Analysis of Silk Road Old Maps Using Google Earth</title>
                        <publisher>Information Processing Society of Japan</publisher>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">SIG Computers and the Humanities
                            Symposium 2007</title><date>2007</date>
                        <biblScope type="pp">155- 162</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl3">
                        <author>Zeile, P.</author>
                        <author>Farnoudi F.</author>
                        <author>Streich, B.</author><date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">Fascination google earth - use in urban and landscape
                            design</title>
                        <title level="m">Embodying Virtual Architecture: The Third International
                            Conference of the Arab Society for Computer Aided Architectural Design
                            (ASCAAD 2007)</title>
                        <biblScope type="pp">141-148</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl1">
                        <title level="m">Google Maps</title>
                        <ptr target="http://code.google.com/intl/en/apis/maps/"/>
                        <date type="visited">10 October, 2009</date></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl2"><title level="m">Google Earth</title>
                        <ptr target="http://earth.google.com/intl/en/"/>
                        <date type="visited">10 October, 2009</date></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl5"><title level="m">GMap Image Cutter</title>
                        <ptr target="http://www.casa.ucl.ac.uk/software/googlemapimagecutter.asp"/>
                        <date type="visited">10 October, 2009</date></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl6"><title level="m">OpenZoom</title>
                        <ptr target="http://openzoom.org/"/>
                        <date type="visited">10 October, 2009</date></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl7"><title level="m">OpenLayers</title>
                        <ptr target="http://openlayers.org/"/>
                        <date type="visited">4 March, 2010</date>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
