<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-752">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Digital Humanities Internships: Creating a Model iSchool-Digital Humanities
                    Center Partnership </title>
                <author>
                    <name>Conway, Paul</name>
                    <affiliation>School of Information, <orgName>University of Michigan</orgName>, <country>USA</country></affiliation>
                    <email>pconway@umich.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Fraistat, Neil</name>
                    <affiliation>Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities, <orgName>University of
                        Maryland</orgName>, <country>USA</country></affiliation>
                    <email>nfraistat@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Galloway, Patricia</name>
                    <affiliation>School of Information, University of Texas, Austin <reg><orgName>University of Texas at Austin</orgName></reg>, <country>USA</country></affiliation>
                    <email>galloway@ischool.utexas.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Kraus, Kari</name>
                    <affiliation>College of Information Studies, <orgName>University of
                        Maryland</orgName>, <country>USA</country></affiliation>
                    <email>karimkraus@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Rehberger, Dean</name>
                    <affiliation>MATRIX, <orgName>Michigan State University</orgName>, <country>USA</country></affiliation>
                    <email>Dean.Rehberger@matrix.msu.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Walter, Katherine</name>
                    <affiliation>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities, <orgName>University of
                        Nebraska-Lincoln</orgName>, <country>USA</country></affiliation>
                    <email>kwalter@unlnotes.unl.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-20</date>
                <name>GF</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>Creative partnership between computer science and the humanities – what we now
                call &quot;digital humanities&quot; – is the cornerstone of the digital
                    revolution. Cathy Davidson writes (2008) that &quot;perhaps we need to see
                    technology and the humanities not as a binary but as two sides of a necessarily
                    interdependent, conjoined, and mutually constitutive set of intellectual,
                    educational, social, political, and economic practices.&quot; Significant
                    educational challenges exist, however, in creating a cadre of professionals who
                    understand the intellectual context of digital humanities research and who are
                    also capable of building the supporting infrastructure of digital collections,
                    tools, and services (de Smedt 2002). The American Council of Learned
                    Societies&apos; groundbreaking report – <hi rend="italic">Our Cultural
                        Commonwealth: Report of the Commission on Cyberinfrastructure for the
                        Humanities and Social Sciences</hi> – focuses attention on the need to
                    &quot;cultivate leadership in support of cyberinfrastructure from within the
                    humanities and social sciences, encourage digital scholarship, develop and
                    maintain open standards and robust tools, and create extensive and reusable
                    digital collections&quot; (ACLS 2006, p. 4). </p>
                <p>An international network of digital humanities centers creates and develops
                    access to the digital documents, images, languages, sound, and film that
                    constitute the human record and facilitate its understanding. In a quite
                    separate but potentially symbiotic movement, graduate schools of information in
                    the United States and elsewhere are producing technologically sophisticated
                    professionals with deep backgrounds in and commitments to the humanities.
                    Schools of Information, or &quot;iSchools&quot; have emerged from a
                    two-decade long era of consolidation and reform, during which traditional
                    schools of library science struggled with irrelevancy, diminished scale, and a
                    fundamental societal transformation in the use of new and emerging technologies
                    (Sawyer 2008). In North America, twenty-four iSchools have formed a caucus 
                        (<ref target="http://www.ischools.org/" rend="newWindow"
                                type="external">http://www.ischools.org/</ref>)
                     to advance a common agenda regarding the future of information
                    studies. John Unsworth (2007) notes that digital humanities centers can
                    establish new working relationships between humanities faculty and iSchool
                    programs. iSchool faculty &quot;are about half from other disciplines, and
                    humanities computing is very much about information organization, ontologies,
                    taxonomies, schema, preservation, interface design, and other issues that are
                    studied and taught in [iSchool] programs. The [iSchool] connection also would
                    help to activate the NEH/IMLS connection, as well as the NSF cyberinfrastructure
                    connection.&quot; </p>
                <p>While the move to develop digital humanities centers has demonstrated great
                    successes, it has also meant the development of a number of unique but remote
                    archives that are in danger of being lost. Universities in this digital age need
                    to produce research and graduates that transcend traditional barriers and ways
                    of working. The most influential origins of change wrought by information
                    technology might well emerge from the humanities and information sciences, which
                    consider most deeply the heritage and future of the human experience. The
                    progress of this interdisciplinary field, however, requires new models of
                    collaboration among the information sciences and the humanities disciplines. In
                    this context it is worth noting that all of the iSchools involved in the digital
                    humanities internship program (described below) have well established archives
                    programs, from which they recruit graduate students to send to the participating
                    DH Centers. </p>
                <p>This paper for DH2010 presents a new model partnership initiative to help build
                    curricular and scholarly institutional infrastructures that leverage the
                    existing and emerging capabilities of iSchools and digital humanities centers.
                    With generous three-year support from the U.S. Institute of Museum and Library
                    Services (IMLS), three iSchools and three digital humanities centers are placing
                    graduate student interns for extended summer work experiences in digital
                    humanities centers. The collaborators include the iSchools at the University of
                    Maryland, the University of Texas and the University of Michigan; and the DH
                    Centers at the University of Maryland (Maryland Institute for Technology in the
                    Humanities), the University of Nebraska (Center for Digital Research in the
                    Humanities), and Michigan State University (MATRIX). The partners are also
                    developing a collaborative research program that draws on complementary areas of
                    expertise and interest in the digital humanities and information studies. The
                    project is in its second year, preparing to place a second set of interns in
                    summer 2010, with a total of 18 internships offered over the duration of the
                    project. </p>
                <p>The DH2010 paper contextualizes the model internship program within the broader
                    academic framework of the mission and activities of iSchools, including the
                    humanities-oriented profiles of students, a curriculum that meaningfully
                    combines--in holistic fashion--computational, legal, informational, cultural,
                    social, and managerial content; and faculty research that crosses the two
                    cultures of the humanities and sciences. </p>
            <div>
                <head>Student Profiles</head>
                <p>The DH2010 paper presents a demographic analysis of the students enrolled at the
                    three collaborating iSchools, demonstrating the affinity (and enriching the
                    alliance) between iSchools and DH Centers. A majority of students enter into
                    iSchool programs with undergraduate and/or graduate degrees in the arts and
                    humanities, frequently outnumbering their more science-oriented peers by
                    statistically significant margins. At Maryland&apos;s iSchool, for example,
                    approximately 62 percent of current masters students (or 212 out of 343)
                    obtained undergraduate degrees in English, History, Art History, Religion,
                    Classics, and Philosophy. At Texas, well over half of the students have solid
                    humanities backgrounds in literature, the arts, and especially in history; and
                    show an impressive understanding of the values, styles, and methods of
                    humanities researchers. At Michigan the humanities subject expertise of fully
                    one-third of entering graduate students is integrated into a broader framework
                    that incorporates techniques for systematically creating, managing, preserving
                    and otherwise enhancing the value of cultural heritage information. </p>

            </div>
            <div>
                <head>iSchool Curriculum</head>
                <p>The DH2010 paper exposes how iSchools have implemented curricula of relevance to
                    digital humanities centers, particularly in the area of cyberinfrastructure. At
                    Michigan, for example, a suite of technology/systems-oriented courses teach
                    students how to build and evaluate dynamic complex websites and databases;
                    undertake preservation reformatting of books, graphical, and audiovisual
                    resources; produce EAD finding aids and other access tools; and create and
                    maintain online communities. At Maryland, students are exposed to the legal
                    issues in managing information and the corpus of documents – such as donor
                    agreements – that codify them. Copyright, privacy, freedom of information, and
                    other topics pertinent to archives and digital libraries are also covered. At
                    Texas, a series of courses in digitization for preservation and access is paired
                    with courses in digital libraries and a sequence developing digital archiving
                    practices to provide students with a range of skills and knowledge pertinent to
                    preserving and providing access to humanities content.</p>

            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Faculty Research</head>
                <p>The DH2010 paper shows that iSchool faculty – an increasing number of whom have
                    PhDs in arts and humanities disciplines – often conduct research with the
                    potential to leverage and support the work of DH Centers. At Michigan, for
                    example, Paul Resnick is pioneering work on recommender systems and the
                    incentives that motivate eCommunities; Paul Conway is discovering how image
                    quality issues in the large-scale digitization of cultural heritage resources
                    impact innovative scholarship and use. At Texas, Gary Geisler is delving into
                    improved interfaces for digital library presentations of materials from
                    collections of the Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center; Patricia Galloway is
                    investigating the use of tools from information retrieval and computational
                    linguistics to frame digital corpora for the purposes of management and
                    presentation. At Maryland, Derek Hansen and Kari Kraus recently received an NSF
                    grant to understand and tailor alternate reality games for purposes of education
                    and scholarly collaboration. </p>
                <p>The DH2010 paper demonstrates how the first round of internships from the model
                    program is establishing rich connections between iSchools and DH Centers. The
                    model is sufficiently well articulated that it could further close working
                    relationships between arts and humanities departments and DH Centers that wish
                    to develop their own signature majors, minors, or concentrations in digital
                    humanities. The paper concludes with a summary of successes, progress, and
                    road-blocks in implementing the new internship model.</p>

            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Funding</head>
                <p>This work was supported by The Institute of Museum and Library Services [grant
                    number RE-05-08-0063-08]. </p>

            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>ACLS</author>
                        <date>2006</date>
                        <title level="m">Our Cultural Commonwealth: The Report of the American
                            Council of Learned Societies Commission on Cyberinfrastructure for the
                            Humanities and Social Sciences</title>
                        <publisher>American Council of Learned Societies</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Washington, DC</pubPlace>
                        <date type="visited">5 March 2010</date>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://www.acls.org/cyberinfrastructure/OurCulturalCommonwealth.pdf"
                        />
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Davidson, C.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">Humanities 2.0: Promise, Perils, Predictions</title>
                        <title level="j">PMLA</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">123(3)</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">707-717</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>de Smedt, K.</author>
                        <date>2002</date>
                        <title level="a">Some Reflections on Studies in Humanities Computing</title>
                        <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">17(1)</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">89-101</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Sawyer, S. and Rosenbaum, H.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">I-Schools: Mice roaring or the future is now
                            arriving?</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">2008 I-Conference</title>
                        <name type="venue">Los Angeles, CA</name>
                        <date type="conference">28 February – 2 March 2008</date>
                        <ptr target="http://www.ischools.org/oc/conference08/ic08_PC_Papers.html"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Unsworth, J.</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">Digital Humanities Centers as Cyberinfrastructure</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Digital Humanities Centers
                            Summit</title>
                        <name type="venue">Washington, DC</name>
                        <date type="conference">12 April</date>
                        <ptr target="http://www3.isrl.illinois.edu/~unsworth/dhcs.html"/>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
