<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-807">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Unfolding History with the Help of the GIS Technology: a Scholar-Librarian
                    Quest for Creating Digital Collections</title>
                <author><name>Smith, Natasha</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName> <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>nsmith@email.unc.edu</email></author>
                <author><name>Allen, Robert</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName> <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>rallen@email.unc.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author><name>Whisnant, Anne</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName> <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>anne_whisnant@unc.edu</email></author>
                <author><name>Eckhardt, Kevin</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName> <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>kevineck@email.unc.edu</email></author>
                <author>
                    <name>Moore, Elise</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</orgName> <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>elimoore@email.unc.edu</email></author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-27</date>
                <name>CD</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Carolina Digital Library and Archives (CDLA) and Documenting the American South
                    (DocSouth) are a digital library laboratory that creates, develops, and
                    maintains online collections regarding the history of the American South with
                    materials drawn primarily from the outstanding archival holdings of the UNC
                    library. In this presentation, we plan to demonstrate how the close partnership
                    between UNC librarians and faculty forges its path in the frontier of digital
                    humanities. Our experience clearly demonstrates that digital historical
                    scholarship cannot be done on the old model of the scholar laboring alone, “the
                    solitary scholar who churns out articles and books behind the closed door of his
                    office” (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl4">see Kenneth Price, 2008</ref>). By bringing together faculty and librarians’
                    expertise, collaborators endeavor to use digital technologies in a variety of
                    innovative ways to collect, organize, and display data and materials that
                    illuminate the temporal and spatial unfolding of historic events. Recent
                    experimental work with GIS helps us to better understand how the use of digital
                    technologies changes the way we do research in humanities and how it facilitates
                    learning in the classroom. Indeed, “GIS, in combination with other branches of
                    scholarship, has the potential to provide a more integrated understanding of
                    history” (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl3">see Ian N. Gregory, 2003</ref>).</p>

                <p>At the same time, the wide array of issues (digitizing and geo-referencing of
                    Sanborn and other historic maps, use of JavaScript mapping APIs, such as Google
                    Maps and the open-source Open Layers, for zooming and hotspot addition, layering
                    and geo-tagging scholarly content) will be presented based on several completed
                    and in progress digital history collections built in close collaboration of UNC
                    librarians working with UNC scholars. </p></div>

                <div><p>1. “Going to the Show” (<ref type="external" target="http://www.docsouth.unc.edu/gtts/"
                        >www.docsouth.unc.edu/gtts/</ref>) is the first digital archive devoted to
                    the early experience of cinema across an entire state. In a research project,
                    Prof. Allen collaborated with digital publishing experts and special collections
                    librarians at UNC to create an online, interactive digital collection of maps,
                    photos, postcards, newspaper clippings, architectural drawings, city directories
                    and historical commentary that illuminate and reconstruct cultural and social
                    life during the first three decades of the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century in North Carolina.
                    Supported by a grant from the N.C. State Library and a National Endowment for
                    the Humanities Digital Humanities Fellowship, “Going to the Show” (GttS)
                    developed the innovative system for layering content on electronically stitched
                    and geo-referenced Sanborn Fire Insurance Maps. Especially in its highly
                    detailed case study of early moviegoing in Wilmington, N.C., GttS demonstrates
                    the extraordinary potential for illuminating community history through the
                    interaction of documentary material and Sanborn maps (<ref type="internal" cRef="fig1">see Figure 1</ref>).  </p><figure
                        xml:id="fig1">
                        <head>Figure 1. Google Maps AP1 used to present 1915 SAnborn map with
                            layered historic materials to document the moviegoing in North
                            Carolina.</head>
                        <graphic url="807_Fig1.jpg" xmt:type="full"
                            rend="left-img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
               </div>
                <div><p>2. Building on the digital history project “Going to the Show”, the project team
                    decided to expand the reach of their expertise by creating a web-based toolkit
                    that will allow libraries, schools, museums, local history societies, and other
                    community organizations to preserve, document, interpret, display, and share the
                    history of their downtowns. Called “<hi rend="italic">Main Street, Carolina:
                        Recovering the History of Downtown Across North Carolina</hi>,” the toolkit
                    will provide users with a flexible, user-friendly digital platform on which they
                    can add a wide variety of “local” data: historical and contemporary photographs,
                    postcards, newspaper ads and articles, architectural drawings, historical
                    commentary, family papers, and excerpts from oral history interviews—all keyed
                    to and layered on top of digitized Sanborn Fire Insurance Maps. The toolkit will
                    consist of a PHP-based web application and a JavaScript API. The web application
                    will be compact in size, resource-light, and easy to install on the local
                    organization’s own web server or that of a third-party web-hosting service. It
                    will provide administrative tools for configuring the site, creating place
                    markers, creating simple web pages for content, and customizing the look and
                    feel (<ref type="internal" cRef="fig2">see Figure 2</ref>). These place markers can then be associated with images,
                    stories, or other content, providing a visual link between the content and
                    related physical locations. The map interface is the focal point of the software
                    and will allow users to explore content associated with specific geographic
                    locations by interacting with place markers, or "push-pins," overlaid on top of
                    historic maps. Clicking on a place marker's icon will display an information
                    bubble which can contain text, images, and links to additional content. The user
                    will be able to view and effortlessly pan across entire downtowns as a seamless
                    integration of multiple high-resolution map pages; zoom from a bird-eye view to
                    the smallest cartographic feature; compare successive map iterations showing the
                    same building, block, or neighborhood; and overlay any of these views with
                    contemporary satellite and map images at the same scale. The JavaScript API will
                    allow users to include digitized maps created for other CDLA projects as layers
                    in their own websites or mash-ups which use the Google Maps or Open Layers
                    mapping APIs. For example, a user could embed an historic map in a blog post or
                    add a Sanborn Map as a layer to their existing website which uses Google Maps to
                    show the location of homes that are listed on the <hi rend="italic">National
                        Register of Historical Places</hi>. MSC is funded by a private funding and
                    an NEH Start-up Grant. Development for this project began in October 2009. We
                    plan to release the toolkit and pilot projects developed in collaboration with
                    external partners in summer 2010, prior to the start of the conference. </p><figure
                        xml:id="fig2">
                        <head>Figure 2. “<hi rend="italic">Main Street, Carolina: Recovering the
                                History of Downtown Across North Carolina</hi>” tool kit.
                            Administrative form for entering historical documents.</head>
                        <graphic url="807_Fig2.jpg" xmt:type="full"
                            rend="left-img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div><p>3. “Driving through Time: The Digital Blue Ridge Parkway in North Carolina” will
                    present an innovative visually and spatially based model for illustrating North
                    Carolina’s key role in creating the Parkway, representing the twentieth-century
                    history of a seventeen-county section of the North Carolina mountains, and for
                    understanding crucial elements of the development of the American National Park
                    system. The project will feature historic maps, photographs, postcards,
                    government documents, oral history interviews, and newspaper clippings. Each
                    historic document will be assigned geographic coordinates so that it can be
                    viewed on a map, enabling users to visualize and analyze the impact of the Blue
                    Ridge Parkway on the people and landscape in western North Carolina over both
                    space and time (<ref type="internal" cRef="fig3">See Figure 3</ref>). Primary sources will be drawn from the
                    collections of the UNC-Chapel Hill University Library, the Blue Ridge Parkway
                    Headquarters, and the North Carolina State Archives. These materials are
                    especially significant in that they document one of North Carolina’s most
                    popular tourist attractions, but also in the way that they help illuminate the
                    way that the Blue Ridge Parkway transformed the communities through which it
                    passed. In addition to the digitized primary sources, the project will include
                    scholarly analyses of aspects of the development of the Blue Ridge Parkway. </p>

                <p>A geospatial format is uniquely appropriate for considering the history of the
                    Parkway and its region. As a narrow park corridor pushed through a
                    long-populated southern Appalachian landscape, the Parkway rearranged spaces,
                    repurposed lands, reorganized travel routes, and opened and closed economic
                    opportunities through control of road routing, access, and use. The social
                    conflicts it engendered, therefore, frequently entailed spatial components –
                    should the road go here, or there; should it take more or less land; should this
                    or that property be favored with direct Parkway access (or not)? Understanding
                    these aspects of Parkway history without reference to spatial relationships on
                    the land is challenging, as the project’s scholarly adviser, Dr. Anne Mitchell
                    Whisnant, recognized when publishing her 2006 book, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Super-Scenic Motorway: A Blue Ridge Parkway History</hi> (UNC Press). Her
                    experience, both in writing the book and in delivering numerous public
                    presentations since its appearance, is that narrative alone cannot provide the
                    public with the tools to comprehend past controversies or present land
                    protection challenges. Using digital and geospatial technologies to open a new
                    window on the history of the Parkway and its region is especially timely
                    considering the approach of the Parkway’s 75th anniversary in 2010 and the
                    National Park Service’s 100th anniversary in 2016. </p>
                <p>The collaboration between the library and Dr. Whisnant has been enhanced by
                    Whisnant’s engagement in related field of “public history,” which is history
                    practiced outside the walls of academia, with and for public audiences. Based in
                    academia but designed for public benefit, “Driving through Time” has offered an
                    exceptional opportunity for involving undergraduate and graduate students in Dr.
                    Whisnant’s Introduction to Public History class in its creation. As a scholarly
                    project being built through the expertise of a large team (as nearly all public
                    history undertakings are), “Driving through Time” has been an ideal space for
                    students to gain hands-on experience in doing public history collaboratively, in
                    real-time, with their instructor. Students are doing original primary source
                    research in the university’s special collections, identifying materials for
                    inclusion in the online exhibit, developing their own historical narratives,
                    working with new tools such as wikis and databases, and contributing to the
                    creation of metadata. Because the instructor has not predetermined the final
                    outcome, furthermore, students are being given ownership over both their process
                    and their final products and practicing navigating the unexpected twists, turns,
                    delights, and disappointments that historical research always entails. <figure
                        xml:id="fig3">
                        <head>Figure 3. "Driving throug Time: The Digital Blue Ridge Parkway in
                            North Carolina"</head>
                        <graphic url="807_Fig3.jpg" xmt:type="full"
                            rend="left-img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl1">
                        <author>Knowles, Anne Kelly</author>
                        <title level="m">Placing History: How Maps, Spatial Data, and GIS Are
                            Changing Historical Scholarship</title>
                        <pubPlace>Redlands, Calif.</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>ESRI Press</publisher>
                        <date>2008</date></bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="bibl2"><author>Whisnant, Anne Mitchell</author>
                        <title level="m">Super-Scenic Motorway: A Blue Ridge Parkway History</title>
                        <publisher>UNC Press</publisher>
                        <date>2006</date></bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="bibl3">
                        <author>Gregory, Ian N.</author>
                        <title level="m">A place in History: A Guide to Using GIS in Historical
                            Research</title>
                        <date>2003</date>
                        <edition>2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Edition. </edition>
                        <ptr target="http://www.ccsr.ac.uk/methods/publications/ig-gis.pdf"/>
                    </bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="bibl4"><author>Price, Kenneth</author>
                        <title level="a">Electronic Scholarly Editions</title> <title level="m">A
                            Companion to Digital Literary Studies</title>
                        <editor>Schreibman, Susan</editor>
                        <editor>Siemens, Ray</editor>
                        <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Blackwell</publisher>
                        <date>2008</date></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
