<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-816">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Works, Documents, Texts and Related Resources for Everyone</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Robinson, Peter</name>
                    <affiliation>Institute for Textual Scholarship, <orgName>University of
                        Birmingham</orgName> <reg><country>UK</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>p.m.robinson@bham.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Meschini, Federico</name>
                    <affiliation>Centre for Textual Studies, <orgName>De Montfort University</orgName> <reg><country>UK</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>fmeschini@dmu.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-05-04</date>
                <name>AC</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>A common trope in discussions of scholarly editions in digital form is to praise,
                    on the one hand, the extraordinary potential of electronic editions while, on
                    the other hand, regretting that so few actual electronic editions come anywhere
                    near realizing this potential (Robinson 2005). The potential is well-known: an
                    explicit hyper-textual structure, publication in a distributed network
                    environment, escape from the storage limit of the printed medium and possession
                    of multiple layout possibilities (such as normalized and diplomatic
                    transcriptions juxtaposed to facsimile images).</p>
                <p>The difficulties are also well-known: among them, the need for a formal,
                    comprehensive and efficient encoding scheme to underpin scholarly editions in
                    electronic form. The Text Encoding Initiative Guidelines provided a crucial
                    element, by supplying namings, specifications and structure for key components
                    of electronic editions: thus the specialized lower-level elements for manuscript
                    description and critical apparatus, along with higher-level elements such as
                    msDescription and facsimile. However, the TEI does not address two areas,
                    crucial for the full encoding of scholarly editions in electronic form:
                        <xmt:oList rend="arabic">
                        <item>The naming of components of the editions: thus, of the works edited
                            and their parts; the source manuscripts or print documents and their
                            parts which carry the texts of the work edited;</item>
                        <item>The relationships between the components: thus, between the documents,
                            the texts they carry, and the works which those texts instance.</item>
                    </xmt:oList>
                </p>
                <p>This paper reports on a scheme prepared by the authors, designed to provide a
                    solution to the problems proposed in both areas. The provision of a shared
                    epistemological framework for handling works, texts and text sources (cf.
                    Buzetti 2009) will also facilitate the shift from stand alone publishing
                    frameworks to shared distributed on-line environments, enabled by powerful and
                    flexible underlying infrastructures,<note>Such as the European initiative DARIAH
                            &lt;<ref target="http://www.dariah.eu" rend="newWindow" type="external"
                            >http://www.dariah.eu/</ref>&gt;</note> generally named Virtual
                    Research Environments (Fraser 2005, Dunn et al. 2008).</p>
                <p>This framework will advance interoperability, long a problem area in electronic
                    texts. Interoperability has been defined by IEEE as “The ability of two or more
                    systems or components to exchange information and to use the information that
                    has been exchanged”.<note>&lt;<ref
                            target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interoperability" rend="newWindow"
                            type="external"
                        >http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interoperability</ref>&gt;</note> A recent
                    briefing paper by Gradmann identifies four different levels of interoperability,
                    one built on the top of the other. From the bottom these levels are
                    technical/basic, syntactic, functional and semantic. While technologies such as
                    TCP/IP, HTTP and XML already provide sound basis for interoperability at the
                    lower levels, much work is still to be done at the top levels. The semantic
                    frame for interoperability offered by this scheme speaks to this need.</p>
                <p>Semantic issues in networked publication systems are advanced by the work done in
                    the last years on the ‘Semantic Web’ (Berners-Lee et al. 2001), which has
                    recently evolved into the Linked Data initiative (Berners-Lee 2006). The
                    Semantic Web seems to have survived its own hype, having finally entered the
                    plateau of productivity phase, as happened for XML some years ago. The
                    ontological level of the Semantic Web stack, represented by the OWL language,
                    has presented a steep learning curve, due partly to its roots in Description
                    Logic and First-Order Logic (Gruber 1993), but also presents at the same time
                    the greatest potential.</p>
                <p>The relationship between textual scholarship in its electronic dimension and
                    ontologies has not hitherto been much apparent, as textual scholars using
                    digital methods have focussed rather on the related, but separated field of
                    Library and Information Science (Vickery 1997). However, ontologies have much to
                    offer the textual editing enterprise. Both ‘recensio’ and the construction of a
                    stemmatic graph are implicit formalizations that would benefit from the adoption
                    of an explicit modelling. Moreover, both Sperberg-McQueen and Peter
                    Shillingsburg implicitly hints at the potentialities of an ontological approach
                    in scholarly editions, the former when writing about the “infinite set of facts
                    related to the work being edited” (Sperberg-McQueen 2002) and the latter about
                    “electronic knowledge sites” (Shillingsburg 2006).</p>
                <p>In the world of digital humanities and electronic editions proficient uses of
                    ontologies have already appeared, such as the Discovery<note>&lt;<ref
                            target="http://www.discovery-project.eu" rend="newWindow"
                            type="external">http://www.discovery-project.eu/</ref>&gt;</note> and
                    the Nines<note><ref target="http://www.nines.org" rend="newWindow"
                            type="external">&lt;http://www.nines.org/&gt;</ref></note> projects,
                    also leveraging existing standards from related sectors such as IFLA’s
                            FRBR<note><ref
                            target="http://www.ifla.org/en/publications/functional-requirements-for-bibliographic-records"
                            rend="newWindow" type="external"
                            >&lt;http://www.ifla.org/en/publications/functional-requirements-for-bibliographic-records&gt;</ref></note>
                    (Mimno 2005) or the cultural heritage oriented CIDOC-CRM<note><ref
                            target="http://cidoc.ics.forth.gr" rend="newWindow" type="external"
                            >&lt;http://cidoc.ics.forth.gr/&gt;</ref></note> (Ore et al. 2009).</p>
                <p>Substantial work is now being done on implementing an actual interchange and
                    interoperability framework for electronic editions, and arbitrary portions of
                    them, of the kind, in (for example) the COST Action Interedition.<note><ref
                            target="http://www.interedition.eu" rend="newWindow" type="external"
                            >&lt;http://www.interedition.eu/&gt;</ref></note> A first proposal by
                    Peter Robinson (Robinson 2009) was based on the Kahn/Wilensky Architecture (Kahn
                    et al. 1995),<note>Which constitutes also the basis for the Handle system <ref
                            target="http://www.handle.net" rend="newWindow" type="external"
                            >&lt;http://www.handle.net/&gt;</ref></note> having therefore a naming
                    authority together with a series of key/value pairs identifying portions of an
                    electronic text, which therefore could be exchanged over the net thanks to a
                    protocol such as the one established by the OAI-PMH standard.<note><ref
                            target="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/openarchivesprotocol.html"
                            rend="newWindow" type="external"
                            >&lt;http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/openarchivesprotocol.html&gt;</ref></note>
                    This addressed the first need stated above, for agreed conventions on naming.
                    The second need, for formal expression of relationships, is addressed by the
                    adoption of the Linked Data paradigm. While keeping the use of the Kahn/Wilensky
                    Architecture for the labelling system, and using a URN-like syntax compatible
                    with the Semantic Web requirements, an ontology representing the entities
                    involved together with their relationships has been developed.</p>
                <p>The main entities of this ontology are: <xmt:uList>
                        <item>‘Work’: Canterbury Tales, and ‘WorkPart’, the first line of the
                            Canterbury Tales;</item>
                        <item>‘Document’, the Hengwrt or the Ellesmere manuscripts, and
                            ‘DocumentPart’, a page, folio or quire, which might carry an instance of
                            the ‘Work’</item>
                        <item>‘Text’: a single instance of a work, or work part, in a document or
                            document part. Thus: the <hi rend="italic">text</hi> of the <hi
                                rend="italic">work</hi> 'The Canterbury Tales' as it appears in the
                                <hi rend="italic">document</hi>, the Hengwrt manuscript;</item>
                    </xmt:uList>
                </p>
                <p>The three-fold distinction between ‘Work’, ‘Document and ‘Text’ reflects the
                    fundamental scholarly distinction between the ‘Work’, independent of its
                    realization in any object; the ‘Document’ which might carry an instance of the
                    ‘Work’; and the ‘Text’: the instance of the work in the document. Digital
                    resources such as ‘Image’ or ‘Transcript’ are related to ‘Text’ and ‘Document’
                    and their parts, using relationship such a ‘hasImage’, ‘isTranscriptOf’, or
                    ‘transcribedFrom’. Basic properties such as “isPartOf” or other properties from
                    existing vocabularies, such as Dublin Core,<note><ref
                            target="http://dublincore.org" rend="newWindow" type="external"
                            >&lt;http://dublincore.org/&gt;</ref></note> have also been used, so to
                    guarantee compatibility with other schemes in the best possible way. The
                    resulting RDF can be stored in a triplestore and made available on the web, so
                    to allow further uses from third parties without the need to establish exclusive
                    protocol verbs.</p>
                <p>This paper will present the methodological thinking behind the development of
                    this ontology for the interchange of electronic editions of literary texts,
                    starting from the first proposal until the more recent developments. The
                    ontology will be contextualized with the existing related standards,
                    particularly FRBR, CIDOC-CRM and the recent OAI-ORE<note><ref
                            target="http://www.openarchives.org/ore" rend="newWindow"
                            type="external">&lt;http://www.openarchives.org/ore/&gt;</ref></note> (a
                    gross-grained vocabulary for the reuse and exchange of digital objects developed
                    by the Open Access Initiative) and with the similar initiative of the Canonical
                    Text Service Protocol (CTS),<note><ref
                            target="http://chs75.chs.harvard.edu/projects/diginc/techpub/cts"
                            rend="newWindow" type="external"
                            >&lt;http://chs75.chs.harvard.edu/projects/diginc/techpub/cts&gt;</ref></note>
                    which recently also added an ontological dimension to its basic syntax
                    (Romanello et al. 2009).</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Berners-Lee, T.</author>
                        <author>Hendler, J.</author>
                        <author>Lassila, O.</author>
                        <date>2001</date>
                        <title level="a">The Semantic Web</title>
                        <title level="j">The Scientific American</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">May 2001</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">34–43</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Berners-Lee, T.</author>
                        <date>July 2006</date>
                        <title level="m">Linked Data</title>
                        <ptr target="http://www.w3.org/DesignIssues/LinkedData.html"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Buzzetti, D.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Digital Editions and Text Processing</title>
                        <title level="m">Text Editing, Print and the Digital World</title>
                        <editor>Deegan, M.</editor>
                        <editor>Sutherland, K.</editor>
                        <publisher>Ashgate</publisher>
                        <biblScope type="pp">45-61</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Dunn, S.</author>
                        <author>Blanke, T.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">Next Steps for E-Science, the Textual Humanities and
                            Vres</title>
                        <title level="j">D-Lib Magazine</title>
                        <biblScope type="vol">14</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue">1/2</biblScope>
                        <ptr target="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/january08/dunn/01dunn.html"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Fraser, M.</author>
                        <date>2005</date>
                        <title level="a">Virtual Research Environments: Overview and
                            Activity</title>
                        <title level="j">Ariadne</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">44</biblScope>
                        <ptr target="http://www.ariadne.ac.uk/issue44/fraser/"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Gradmann, S.</author>
                        <title level="m">INTEROPERABILITY. A key concept for large scale, persistent
                            digital libraries</title>
                        <ptr
                            target="www.digitalpreservationeurope.eu/publications/briefs/interoperability.pdf"
                        />
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Gruber, T.R.</author>
                        <date>1993</date>
                        <title level="a">A translation approach to portable ontology
                            specifications</title>
                        <title level="j">Knowledge Acquisition</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">5</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">199–220</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kahn, R.</author>
                        <author>Wilensky R.</author>
                        <date>May 1995</date>
                        <title level="m">A Framework for Distributed Digital Object Services</title>
                        <ptr target="http://WWW.CNRI.Reston.VA.US/home/cstr/arch/k-w.html"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Mimno, D.</author>
                        <author>Crane G.</author>
                        <author>Jones, A.</author>
                        <date>2005</date>
                        <title level="a">Hierarchical Catalog Records: Implementing a Frbr
                            Catalog</title>
                        <title level="j">D-Lib Magazine</title>
                        <biblScope type="vol">11</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue">10</biblScope>
                        <ptr target="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/october05/crane/10crane.html"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Ore, C.</author>
                        <author>Eide, Ø.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">TEI and cultural heritage ontologies: Exchange of
                            information?</title>
                        <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                        <biblScope type="vol">24</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">161-172</biblScope>
                        <ptr target="http://llc.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/24/2/161"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Robinson, P.</author>
                        <date>2005</date>
                        <title level="a">Current Issues in Making Digital Editions of Medieval
                            Texts—or, Do Electronic Scholarly Editions Have a Future?</title>
                        <title level="j">Digital Medievalist</title>
                        <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                        <ptr target="http://www.digitalmedievalist.org/journal/1.1/robinson/"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Robinson, P.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Electronic Editions for Everyone</title>
                        <title level="m">Text and Genre in Reconstruction</title>
                        <editor>McCarty. W.</editor>
                        <publisher>Open Book Publishing</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                        <biblScope type="pp">183-201</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Romanello, M.</author>
                        <author>Berti, M.</author>
                        <author>Boschetti, F.</author>
                        <author>Babeu A.</author>
                        <author>Crane G.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="m">Rethinking Critical Editions of Fragmentary Texts by
                            Ontologies</title>
                        <publisher>Elpub</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Milano, Italy</pubPlace>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://conferences.aepic.it/index.php/elpub/elpub2009/paper/view/158"
                        />
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.</author>
                        <date>2002</date>
                        <title level="m">How to Teach Your Edition How to Swim</title>
                        <ptr target="http://www.w3.org/People/cmsmcq/2002/cep97/swimming.xml"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Shillingsburg, P.</author>
                        <date>2006</date>
                        <title level="m">From Gutenberg to Google: Electronic Representations of
                            Literary Texts</title>
                        <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Vickery, B. C.</author>
                        <date>1997</date>
                        <title level="a">Ontologies</title>
                        <title level="j">Journal of Information Science</title>
                        <biblScope type="vol">23</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">277-286</biblScope>
                        <ptr target="http://jis.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/23/4/277"/>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
