<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-824">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Social Lives of Books: Mapping the Ideational Networks of Toni
                    Morrison</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Finn, Edward</name>
                    <affiliation>Department of English, <orgName>Stanford University</orgName>, <country>USA</country></affiliation>
                    <email>edfinn@stanford.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-20</date>
                <name>CD</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Overview</head>
                <p>This paper is a case study that is part of a larger Ph.D. dissertation project:
                    an exploration of the networks of references and ideas that make up the social
                    lives of books online. In a time of rapidly evolving ecologies of reading and
                    writing, I argue that the Internet affords us massive amounts of new data on
                    previously invisible cultural transactions. New architectures for reviewing,
                    discussing and sharing books blur the lines separating readers, authors and
                    critics, and these cultural structures capture thousands of conversations,
                    mental connections and personal recommendations that previously went unrecorded.
                    I call these webs of references, allusions and recommendations ideational
                    networks. Using Toni Morrison’s career as a model, I will closely examine the
                    ideational networks surrounding her work using the methodologies of social
                    network analysis in order to define a new, statistically informed conception of
                    cultural capital in the digital era.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Background</head>
                <p>My project is founded on the argument that as literary production evolves, new
                    kinds of reading communities and collaborative cultural entities are emerging.
                    Many of these communities are ephemeral and quite often they are fostered by
                    commercial interests seeking to capitalize on their cultural production.
                    Nevertheless, a handful of websites like Amazon continue to dominate the
                    marketplace for books and attract millions of customer reviews, ratings and
                    purchase decisions, and the literary ecologies of these book reviews have become
                    valuable research resources. The ideational networks I explore are made up of
                    first books, authors, characters and other literary entities (these are the
                    nodes), and second the references linking them together as collocations in book
                    reviews, suggestions from recommendation engines, and other architectures of
                    connection. Advancing from my first case study, Thomas Pynchon, to Morrison’s
                    ideational networks, I have discovered the utility of social network analysis
                    methodologies to better analyze graphs of these literary references. With new
                    data and new tools, I hope to trace the networks of influence and exchange that
                    have contributed to making Toni Morrison arguably the most critically acclaimed
                    and popularly successful author in the United States.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Proposal</head>
                <p>This paper will present my research on the ideational networks surrounding the
                    works of Toni Morrison. Morrison makes an excellent subject for this kind of
                    study for a number of reasons. As a Nobel laureate and widely read popular
                    author, she has attracted millions of devotees. In her writing she often draws
                    on the African American literary tradition of the talking book, and throughout
                    her career she has explored the ontological power of narrative to create and
                    destroy worlds. It is not surprising, then, that as an author she is deeply
                    committed to expanding the act of reading not only to include millions of
                    people, especially women, who never considered themselves readers before, but
                    also to changing its definition to include conversation, community, and a kind
                    of collaborative reflection. This element of Morrison’s authorial appeal is best
                    exemplified by her long-running association with Oprah’s Book Club, an
                    enterprise that has had a huge impact on the U.S. publishing industry and on
                    conceptions of reading as a social act.</p>
                <p>My presentation will explore the communities of readership that have emerged
                    around Morrison’s work and consider the literary company in which her readers
                    and reviewers perceive her. Focusing on a limited set of professional book
                    reviews, reader reviews and recommendations from a dataset of print media,
                    Amazon and LibraryThing, I will map out connections that reviewers and consumers
                    have made between Morrison’s works and other literary figures and texts (<ref
                        type="internal" cRef="fig1">see Figure 1</ref>). I believe these connections
                    will delineate Morrison’s position as an extremely popular author who
                    nevertheless challenges her readers to grapple with unflinching, emotionally raw
                    narratives. Her books have introduced millions to deeply troubled corners of
                    American history, combining a modernist style with diverse literary traditions
                    in a way that is both acutely culturally specific and universally compelling. I
                    hypothesize that these factors have driven her remarkable ability to create
                    togetherness and communities of readership even as she traces out the wounds and
                    scars of division, inequality and bias latent in American culture. I also hope
                    to contrast her ideational networks with those of Thomas Pynchon, who has
                    pursued a radically different literary approach through his aversion to
                    publicity and his recondite fiction.</p>
                <figure xml:id="fig1">
                    <head>Figure 1: Sample image from work in progress of a Morisson ideational network based
                        on Amazon's recommendation engine. Here the nodes are books connected together by Amazon's "Customers who bought
                        this also bought" feature, centered on Morisson's novels in the middle.
                        Arrows indicate direction (i.e. Twain's <hi rend="italic">Huckleberry
                            Finn</hi> is recommended from O'Brien's <hi rend="italic">The Things
                            They Carried</hi>, but not vice versa). Note both the range of texts and
                        the cultural vectors present, with syllabus classics like Salinger,
                        Steinbeck, Miller and Howthorne moving down from the center, canonical
                        Native American writers at the top left, etc. Visualization based on Prefuse
                        Java Toolkit.</head>
                    <graphic url="824_Fig1.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                        mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Methodology</head>
                <p>This argument will draw on results from several specific datasets of ideational
                    networks. </p>

                <p>I have collected professional book reviews from a set of major U.S. newspapers
                    and magazines that consistently reviewed Morrison’s publications. These will be
                    analyzed along with customer reviews from Amazon’s product pages for Morrison’s
                    works, which have been accumulating reviews since 1996. Employing the
                    MorphAdorner project’s Named Entity Recognition tool, I am assembling a
                    dictionary of proper nouns that reviewers use as literary references in
                    discussing Morrison’s work. Tagging those references in the reviews, I will then
                    explore collocations of references to construct network graphs of the books,
                    authors and other literary entities that reviewers link together.</p>
                <p>I have also assembled a database of book recommendations using Amazon’s
                    “Customers who bought this also bought” engine and LibraryThing’s recommendation
                    engine. These links provide a valuable counterpoint to those works that
                    reviewers choose to mention, since these recommendations are generated by
                    indirect user actions (i.e. when a user buys, reviews or catalogs multiple texts
                    and thereby creates a statistical association among them). Recommendation
                    engines attempt to mimic or track the sale and ownership of cultural products,
                    creating a feedback loop of cultural consumer desire, while review analysis
                    explores a more abstract realm of ideational exchange.</p>
                <p>Using methodologies of social network analysis, I will identify those works and
                    authors with the most prestige (i.e. the books most frequently recommended) and
                    centrality (i.e. the author who is best-connected to other authors) in these
                    networks and consider the role of Morrison’s texts as centers of ideational
                    networks and, potentially, as bridges between different genre or category
                    groupings. I also hope to explore the role of clustering effects in these
                    networks to see if they are based on predictable factors like genre.</p>
                <p>Depending on the speed of my progress with the objectives above and the
                    cooperation of Oprah’s Book Club, I also hope to explore the networks of
                    discussion and dialog that have emerged around Morrison’s long collaboration
                    with Oprah Winfrey, which has inspired millions of people to take up or return
                    to reading as a leisure activity in adult life. I hope to apply similar
                    methodologies of literary reference to see how Book Club participants
                    contextualized Morrison.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>As I continue to refine my understanding of ideational networks and improve the
                    methodologies necessary to study them, I am beginning to develop techniques that
                    can effectively be applied to very different authors and provide comparable
                    data. This second case study will provide fertile ground for exploring Toni
                    Morrison’s unique authorial fame and to map out the kinds of cultural production
                    that large groups of committed readers can engage in online. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bourdieu, P.</author>
                        <date>1993</date>
                        <title level="m">The Field of Cultural Production: Essays on Art and
                            Literature</title>
                        <editor>Johnson, Randal</editor>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Columbia University Press</publisher>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>English, J.</author>
                        <date>2005</date>
                        <title level="m">The Economy of Prestige</title><pubPlace>Cambridge,
                            MA</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher></bibl>

                    <bibl><author>Farr, C. K.</author>
                        <date>2005</date>
                        <title level="m">Reading Oprah: How Oprah’s Book Club Changed the Way
                            America Reads</title>
                        <pubPlace>Albany</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>State University of New York Press</publisher></bibl>

                    <bibl><author>Heer, J.</author>
                        <date>2007</date><title level="m">Prefuse Java
                            Toolkit</title><publisher>Berkeley Institute of
                        Design</publisher></bibl>

                    <bibl><author>Guillory, J.</author>
                        <date>1993</date>
                        <title level="m">Cultural Capital: The Problem of Literary Canon
                            Formation</title>
                        <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher></bibl>

                    <bibl><author>Moretti, F.</author>
                        <date>2005</date>
                        <title level="m">Graphs, Maps, Trees: Abstracted Models for a Literary
                            History</title>
                        <pubPlace>London and New York</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Verso</publisher>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="m">MorphAdorner</title>
                        <publisher>Northwestern University</publisher>
                        <date>2009</date><ptr target="http://morphadorner.northwestern.edu/"
                        /></bibl>

                    <bibl><author>Radway, J.</author>
                        <date>1997</date>
                        <title level="m">A Feeling for Books: The Book-of-the-Month Club, Literary
                            Taste, and Middle-Class Desire</title>
                        <pubPlace>Chapel Hill</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>University of North Carolina Press</publisher>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
