<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-890">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Understanding the 'Capacity' of the Digital Humanities: The Canadian
                    Experience, Generalised </title>
                <author>
                    <name>Siemens, Ray</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of Victoria</orgName>, <country>Canada</country></affiliation>
                    <email>siemens@uvic.ca</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Eberle-Sinatra, Michael</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Université de Montréal</orgName>, <country>Canada</country></affiliation>
                    <email>michael.eberle.sinatra@umontreal.ca</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Siemens, Lynne</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of Victoria</orgName>, <country>Canada</country></affiliation>
                    <email>siemensl@uvic.ca</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Sinclair, Stéfan</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>McMaster University</orgName>, <country>Canada</country></affiliation>
                    <email>sgsinclair@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Brown, Susan</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of Guelph</orgName>, <country>Canada</country></affiliation>
                    <email>sbrown@uoguelph.ca</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Timney, Meagan</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of Victoria</orgName>, <country>Canada</country></affiliation>
                    <email>mbtimney.etcl@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Rockwell, Geoffrey</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of Alberta</orgName>, <country>Canada</country></affiliation>
                    <email>geoffrey.rockwell@ualberta.ca</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-25</date>
                <name>AC</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="session">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Chair</hi>: Ray Siemens</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Presenters</hi> (4-5 minute presentations): <xmt:uList>
                        <item>Michael Eberle-Sinatra, “Understanding Academic Capacity: A Charge
                            from our Funding Agency”</item>
                        <item>Lynne Siemens, “Developing Academic Capacity in Digital Humanities:
                            Thoughts from the Canadian Community and Beyond”</item>
                        <item>Ray Siemens, “DH Training Capacity: Established Curriculum,
                            Institutes, Camps, and Beyond”</item>
                        <item>Stéfan Sinclair, “Building from the Ground up: Training Digital
                            Humanities Scholars as Developers”</item>
                        <item>Susan Brown, “Hidden Capacity (in DH-impacted disciplines)”</item>
                        <item>Meagan Timney, “Transitions: Emerging in the Field”</item>
                        <item>Geoffrey Rockwell, “Cyberinfrastructure for Research in the
                            Humanities: Expectations and Capacity”</item>
                    </xmt:uList>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>Panel Description: In a recent report from Council of Canadian Academies, <hi
                        rend="italic">The State of Science &amp; Technology in Canada</hi> (2006, p.
                    24; <ref target="http://www.scienceadvice.ca/documents/Complete%20Report.pdf"
                        type="external">http://www.scienceadvice.ca/documents/Complete%20Report.pdf</ref>)
                    humanities computing was identified as an “emerging field” with “significant
                    strength,” alongside several other science-oriented “transdisciplinary fields …
                    for which future prospects are seen to be more significant than currently
                    established strength.” Concomitant discussions with our chief research funding
                    agency, the Social Science and Humanities Research Council of Canada (SSHRC),
                    yielded a need to understand, better, the ‘capacity’ of this community in Canada
                    and beyond, in part to gauge the potential future impact of our interdiscipline
                    which, itself, has been generously supported for a decade with dedicated
                    programs such as SSHRC’s Image, Text, Sound Technology program and research
                    infrastructural programs such as the Canadian Foundation for Innovation (CFI).
                    Manifest in a report commissioned by SSHRC, our panel discusses the results of
                    and reactions to the activity of attempting to understand our field’s capacity,
                    both within the national context that spawned the study and the borderless
                    environment occupied by the field.</p>
                <p>The panel consists of several very short presentations, followed by discussion.
                    <hi rend="bold">Michael Eberle-Sinatra</hi>’s presentation will discuss specific aspects of the
                    report itself, among them the field’s history of interrelationship with
                    supporting programs, societies, and initiatives; how the field presents itself
                    to, and intersects with, the larger humanities community; the field’s notable
                    successes, notable contributions, and chief projects; and what is anticipated to
                    be needed next to enable excellent and timely research across the humanities,
                    from the perspective of the field – all through the lens of the fields enabling
                    possibilities via methods, tools and cyberinfrastructure. <hi rend="bold">Lynne Siemens</hi> will
                    juxtapose the growing acceptance of digital humanities research and teaching
                    methods, technologies and resources with a series of challenges that still face
                    scholars, especially new scholars, in developing their work in the field, via
                    the results of a recent survey of digitally-impacted faculty, staff and students
                    in the Humanities and Social Sciences (which yield a focus on funding,
                    infrastructure and leadership). <hi rend="bold">Ray Siemens</hi> discusses the crucial role of
                    training, broadly construed, a point which will be picked up on and carried much
                    further by <hi rend="bold">Stéfan Sinclair</hi>, who acknowledges that the training of humanists with
                    advanced programming skills is essential to the digital humanities’ recognition
                    of tool conception and development as first class scholarly activities, to the
                    process of building as a way of exploring and understanding, touching also on
                    important issues of peer-review and professional recognition for innovative work
                    in tool-building. <hi rend="bold">Meagan Timney</hi>, a postdoctoral fellow in digital humanities,
                    discusses several issues specifically confronting emerging scholars in the field
                    of digital humanities and <hi rend="bold">Susan Brown</hi> will posit, from the position of someone
                    at a university that has no formal digital humanities programs or even dedicated
                    courses in the calendar, that there is considerable untapped capacity for
                    digital humanities training in the Canadian, and other, higher education systems
                    – highlighting the fact that there are many people with significant training or
                    research experience in the digital humanities area teaching across the
                    humanities where their work has as a matter of course included the impact of
                    digital textuality but they would not identify with our field by its name, the
                    result of underfunding of the traditional disciplines and lack of institutional
                    resources to create new programs or organise existing offerings in new,
                    pertinent configurations. <hi rend="bold">Geoffrey Rockwell</hi> will close by asking "what is
                    infrastructure in the humanities?" – presenting a model for the research
                    computing infrastructure we should expect from our universities and suggesting
                    the capacity at Canadian universities to meet this need as well as the politics
                    of positioning computing as infrastructure.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
