<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-837">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Software Demonstration, “Emergent Time” timeline tool</title>
                <author>
                    <name>York, Christopher</name>
                    <affiliation>HyperStudio, <orgName>Massachusetts Institute of
                            Technology</orgName>
                        <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>cyork@mit.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Trettien, Whitney</name>
                    <affiliation>HyperStudio, Massachusetts Institute of Technology</affiliation>
                </author>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-27</date>
                <name>AC</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="poster">
        <body>
            <p>Emergent Time is a prototype collaboration tool for humanists and social scientists
                working with timelines—narrative arrangements of events. In Emergent Time, timelines
                are owned by particular users, and represent the user's interpretive reading of a
                series of events. While an individual timeline “belongs” to a user, many of the
                events it interprets may be shared by other users and interpreted differently in
                their timelines. Users construct timelines individually, using a single form to
                build on events others created before them, or to create new events from scratch.
                The application thus balances personal expression and argument (in the form of
                individual timelines) with collaboration and shared work (in the form of raw
                events).</p>
            <p>Throughout the prototype, clicking on an event in a timeline will show how other
                users have interpreted that particular incident. Thus, one can read horizontally to
                follow the argument of a given timeline, or depth-wise to jump between different
                timelines that interpret the same event from different perspectives.</p>
            <div>
                <head>Overview timelines</head>
                <p>The prototype's salient feature is a set of overview timelines, built by
                    analyzing the network of links between timelines and events within the
                    community. These links indicate the most important events for a given topic. For
                    example, a search for “John F Kennedy” might show the most highly-cited events
                    in his life: birth, election, and assassination. To accomplish this, the
                    prototype uses a proprietary implementation of Page &amp; Brin's PageRank
                    algorithm. Events that are linked to in many timelines are likely to be
                    important to the community, and receive a high rank; conversely, timelines that
                    interpret many important events receive a boost in rank. Emergent Time uses
                    these ranks to indicate which event entries are regarded as most authoritative
                    by the general populace of users, and displays them when given a matching
                    topic.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Collaboration strategy</head>
                <p>In Emergent Time only the author of a given event can revise it, but the
                    community at large can add source critique comments and propose alternate
                    versions of the event. The design intention was to spark general discussion
                    about whether a given event's description is well-supported by the primary
                    sources cited. Because many versions of a given event may exist, this encourages
                    users to link to the version that is factually best-supported in their own
                    timelines, while passing over those with poor evidentiary support or
                    badly-formulated descriptions. Hence, using an event in one's own timeline
                    constitutes both a signal of interest in the historical incident and a vote of
                    confidence in the event author's scholarship. The collaboration workﬂow thus
                    serves as a macrocosm of the scholarly publication process, allowing authors and
                    readers to evaluate the evidence in support of a given interpretation, and to
                    “vote with their feet” by citing it rather than another in their own work.</p>
                <p>As a result the overview timelines will come to reﬂect not only which events are
                    most important for the interpretive community, but also which versions of a
                    particular event are most authoritative. This allows overview timelines to
                    present the most inﬂuential event entries for a given topic, and to accommodate
                    shifts in communal knowledge as new evidence is found and new interpretations of
                    a given incident become normative.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>In contrast to other tools</head>
                <p>This collaborative strategy is intended to capture established conventions for
                    historical analysis and source critique, and use the resulting citation networks
                    to construct overview timelines that accurately reﬂect the community's current
                    normative views. By distributing small bits of knowledge among many event
                    entries, promoting general discussion of the veracity of each, and then allowing
                    users to “vote” for a given version of the facts by including the event in their
                    timeline, it addresses shortcomings in other collaborative digital humanities
                    approaches: <xmt:uList>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">Open-revision wiki</hi>. An open wiki implements
                            what might be called “last man standing” collaboration. The last person
                            to edit an article has license to revise and amend all the others' work,
                            potentially reshaping it to his own ends. Of course, wiki history allows
                            others to revise it back, but this encourages “squatting,” or
                            continually monitoring an article in order to control its
                            contents.</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">Moderated wiki</hi>. Some wikis establish an
                            editorial bureaucracy to address these issues. However, this in effect
                            defers interpretation to an appointed “expert,” much after the fashion
                            of a traditional encyclopedia (with the proviso that the general public
                            can submit material for editorial consideration).</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">Voting systems</hi>. Finally, simple voting systems
                            that ask users to “rate this article” suffer from known problems with
                            blind polling. Anonymity encourages arbitrary voting; users might vote
                            multiple times or use incomparable rankings; and the population of
                            elective voters is self-selecting. By contrast, Emergent Time's
                            collaboration model is designed to circumvent such problems, since users
                            “vote with their feet” by citing one formulation of an event rather than
                            another in their timelines, and no one user can dominate interpretation
                            by being the last to revise. While this model is relatively new to
                            digital collaboration tools, it is quite similar to traditional
                            humanities footnote and endnote citations. It clearly marks authorship
                            and source material for a given interpretation, encourages communal
                            discussion of the adequacy of an author's evidence, and holds authors
                            accountable for their votes by embedding the citations within their
                            work.</item>
                    </xmt:uList>
                </p>
                <p>Even with a sparse demo data set, it is clear that the Emergent Time prototype
                    achieves a successful balance between individual work (seen when viewing a
                    particular timeline) and community connections (via the interpretation
                    comparison popup, and the related timelines and related users links). It
                    encourages users to focus on developing their own ideas, while still suggesting
                    points of contact with the wide community — for example, in the event editor,
                    which shows possible base events as the user enters information. The opening
                    page's list of recent community activity is well-suited to draw users into other
                    work and give a sense of liveliness. Most importantly, even for small data sets,
                    it's clear that the overview timelines do actually reﬂect the community's
                    current notion of the “most important” events.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
