<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-819">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Critical Editing of Music in the Digital Medium: an Experiment in MEI</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Viglianti, Raffaele</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>King's College London</orgName> <country>UK</country></affiliation>
                    <email>raffaele.viglianti@kcl.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-40-21</date>
                <name>CD</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="poster">
        <body>
            <p>Critical editions of music have not received the level of attention that research in
                Digital Humanities has given to textual criticism, which already has an established
                scholarly production of written contributions and digital publications. Digital
                representations in literary criticism are used for analytical purposes as well as
                for accommodating critical editions in the digital medium, which offers a high
                degree of interactivity and opens toward experimentation with new formats of
                publication. Nonetheless, there has been little debate about music editing in the
                new medium and only a few digital publications have been developed.</p>
            <p>Several aspects of digital textual criticism can find an application on music
                documents because similar issues exist in the representation of primary sources and
                editorial intervention. In fact, since the early stages of music scholarship,
                musicologists looked at the editorial practices of classical philologists while
                working towards a definition of their own scientific finalities (<ref
                    type="internal" cRef="bibl6">Grier, 1996</ref>). The study of documentary
                sources transmitting a written work (manuscript or printed) is the main correlation
                between music and textual criticism. For instance, the discrepancy identified by
                    <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl11">Tanselle (1989)</ref> between text and the
                artefacts that transmit it, is a condition that applies to music notation as well as
                literature; however, literature is ‘a one-stage and music a two-stage art’ (<ref
                    type="internal" cRef="bibl8">Goodman, 1976:114</ref>; also discussed by <ref
                    type="internal" cRef="bibl5">Feder, 1987</ref>). A musical work, in fact, does
                not exist only as written notation but also requires performance to reach its final
                receiver. For this reason, understanding the complexity of the music work-concept
                and its associated cultural practices is central to the digital representation of
                music critical editions. Even though the recent research in digital textual
                scholarship provides a rich paradigm for the emergent field of digital editing of
                music, there is the need for more research on digital representation and publication
                of detailed notation data. </p>
            <p>The work conducted for a postgraduate dissertation (MA) at King’s College London
                attempted to discuss some of these issues. This poster presents the results of the
                dissertation’s case study: a digital edition of Claude Debussy’s Syrinx (La Flûte de
                Pan) for flute solo. The XML-based model represents notation, variant readings and
                editorial intervention; additionally, several different views are extracted and
                rendered for presentation with vector images.</p>
            <div>
                <head>An experiment with MEI: <hi rend="italic">Syrinx (La Flûte de Pan)</hi> by
                    Claude Debussy</head>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Syrinx (La Flûte de Pan)</hi> by Claude Debussy (1862 – 1918)
                    is a short piece for flute solo originally composed as theatrical interlude for
                    the play <hi rend="italic">Psyché</hi> (1913) by Gabriel Mourey under the title
                        <hi rend="italic">La Flûte de Pan</hi>. Despite Debussy showing little
                    interest in the publication of the piece, the first performer, Louis Fleury,
                    contributed to the reception of the piece as independent from Mourey’s play. The
                    piece maintains a relevant role in the solo flute repertoire. Two principal
                    sources have been used for the digital edition: the first edition published
                    posthumously by Jobert in 1927 under the new title <hi rend="italic">Syrinx</hi>
                    and a recently discovered manuscript in a private collection in Brussels dated
                    1913 (MSB), which constituted the base text. </p>
                <p>For the creation of a digital model for the new edition, the use of a combination
                    of TEI and MusicXML was initially considered;<note>MusicXML (distributed with a
                        royalty-free license) is an interchange format developed by Recordare LLC
                            (<ref target="http://www.recordare.com" type="external"
                            >http://www.recordare.com</ref>). It is employed by free and commercial
                        music editors (i.e. Finale and Sibelius) as intermediate representation to
                        exchange data (often with loss).</note> however, MusicXML does not match
                    TEI’s flexibility when encoding primary sources and variant readings. MusicXML,
                    in fact, is primarily designed ‘to be sufficient, not optimal’ (<ref
                        type="internal" cRef="bibl7">Good, 2001</ref>); therefore, it represents
                    normalised common western music notation to facilitate interchange and does not
                    allow the flexibility in the granularity that is required when representing the
                    editor’s interpretation and understanding.</p>
                <p>The Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) provided an alternative choice.<note><ref
                            type="external" target="http://www2.lib.virginia.edu/innovation/mei/"
                            >http://www2.lib.virginia.edu/innovation/mei/</ref></note> This XML
                    format is modelled on TEI and attempts to follow the same principles. In
                    particular it specifically focuses on formalising interpretation through
                    declarative knowledge and claims to be independent from rendering software while
                    also addressing processing matters (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl9">Roland,
                        2002</ref>).<note>This approach recalls the claim of <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl10"
                            >Sperberg-McQueen (1997)</ref> that ‘declarative’ information
                        about the editorial process can be represented and modelled through markup:
                        ‘there is an infinite set of facts related to the work being edited’ and
                        ‘any edition records a <hi rend="italic">selection</hi> from the observable
                        and the recoverable portions of this infinite set of facts’. This <hi
                            rend="italic">selection</hi> represents what the edition ‘<hi
                            rend="italic">knows</hi> […] about the work edited, its genesis and/or
                        transmission, etc.’. This body of information is ‘declarative’.</note>
                    Moreover, it includes a module for the representation of variant readings and
                    transcription of primary sources; therefore a combination with TEI did not seem
                    to be necessary. The MEI format is still in development; however, the University
                    of Paderborn (Germany) and the University of Virginia (USA) recently received a
                    grant to take MEI out of its beta phase and produce public guidelines, which
                    should be completed by the end of July 2010.<note><ref type="external"
                            target="http://www2.lib.virginia.edu/press/music/index.html"
                            >http://www2.lib.virginia.edu/press/music/index.html</ref></note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The encoding model</head>
                <p>The poster will show how the MEI model represents some editorial aspects common
                    with textual editing (i.e. bibliographical metadata, correction and
                    regularisation) and editorial issues related to the nature of the music notation
                    (i.e. apparatus, rhythmic constraints, performative instructions). In particular
                    it will show: <xmt:oList rend="arabic">
                        <item><hi rend="italic">The header</hi>: similarly to TEI, MEI provides a
                            “header” (&lt;meihead&gt;) that allows documenting information about the
                            digital file and its sources. Notably, the elements in the description
                            of the manuscript source MSB attempt to emulate the much more detailed
                            encoding model offered by the TEI manuscript description module. The
                            header also documents the encoding criteria for notation. <figure>
                                <code xml:space="preserve">
&lt;measure&gt;
    &lt;staff&gt;
        &lt;layer&gt;
            //- Notes
            &lt;note&gt;, &lt;beam&gt;, &lt;tuplet&gt;, etc.
                 ...
        &lt;/layer&gt;
        //- Phrase marks
        &lt;slur&gt;
                 ...
        //- Dynamics, tempo markings and 
        directions positioned above the staff
        &lt;dir&gt;, &lt;dynam&gt;, &lt;breath&gt;, etc.
                 ...
        //- Dynamics, tempo markings and 
        directions positioned below the 
        staff
        &lt;dir&gt;, &lt;dynam&gt;, &lt;breath&gt;, 
        etc.
                 ... 
    &lt;/staff&gt;
&lt;/measure&gt;  
</code>
                                <head>Example 1: Encoding criteria for notation</head>
                            </figure>
                        </item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">Variant readings</hi>: The MEI file represents this
                            edition’s base text (MSB) and adds additional information every time a
                            difference in the other sources occurs. If the sources agree, it is
                            expressed silently. This criterion is identified by the TEI guidelines
                            as ‘internal parallel segmentation’.<note><ref type="external"
                                    target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html#TCAPPS"
                                    >http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TC.html#TCAPPS</ref></note>
                            Example 2 shows alternative notations encoded with &lt;app&gt; and
                            &lt;rdg&gt;; the attribute type specifies which reading has been
                            selected for the edition. It is worth explaining the basic mechanisms
                            behind the element &lt;slur&gt;, since they are also common to other
                            elements. The attribute staff defines to which staff the phrase mark
                            belongs to; place defines whether the slur has to be rendered above or
                            below the staff; tstamp identifies the beat in which the slur starts and
                            dur the beat in which the slur ends. <figure>
                                <code xml:space="preserve">
&lt;measure id=&quot;m28&quot; n=&quot;28&quot;&gt;
  ...
  &lt;app&gt;
     &lt;rdg source=&quot;MSB&quot;&gt;
        &lt;slur staff=&quot;1&quot; tstamp=&quot;2&quot; dur=&quot;4&quot; 
         place=&quot;above&quot;/&gt;
     &lt;/rdg&gt;
     &lt;rdg source=&quot;FEJ&quot; type=&quot;ed&quot;&gt;
        &lt;slur staff=&quot;1&quot; tstamp=&quot;2&quot; 
         dur=&quot;2.875&quot; place=&quot;above&quot;/&gt;
        &lt;slur staff=&quot;1&quot; tstamp=&quot;3&quot; 
        dur=&quot;3.75&quot; place=&quot;above&quot;/&gt;
     &lt;/rdg&gt;
  &lt;/app&gt;
  ...
&lt;/measure&gt;
                            </code>
                                <head>Example 2: Alternative phrase marks in bar 28 from source MSB
                                    and FEJ.</head>
                            </figure></item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">Editorial conjecture and intervention</hi>: change
                            of hand, additions, corrections and supplied notation have been encoded
                            with elements equivalent to the ones employed by the TEI. </item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">Problematic cases</hi>: bar 22 in MSB presents an
                            incongruent rhythm and a missing barline to separate it from bar 23. The
                            encoding used an empty-element version of &lt;beam&gt; to encode the
                            differences in beaming resulting from the different rhythms and a
                            &lt;gap&gt; element for the missing barlines. </item>
                    </xmt:oList></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Presentation</head>
                <p>For this edition, a number of different perspectives from the MEI document are
                    produces using XSLT 2.0 to serialize into a text format for Mup, a program that
                    converts its own notation format into Post Script vector graphics (PS). To
                    extract musical information from the encoded edition, a heavily customised
                    version of a MEI to Mup XSLT provided on the MEI website under the Educational
                    Community Licence. The poster will show the following views: <xmt:oList
                        rend="italic">
                        <item><hi rend="italic">The edited piece</hi>. The XSLT script extracts all
                            the variant readings chosen for the edition, includes the editorial
                            interventions marked with &lt;supplied&gt; and creates a new MEI
                            document tree containing only the notation for the edition. This tree is
                            then serialised into Mup language and rendered in PS.</item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">Synoptic apparatus</hi>. Instead of printing a
                            traditional apparatus, this edition proposes a synoptic apparatus of the
                            two main sources (MSB and FEJ). This is automatically built to display
                            measures that contain variant readings. Moreover, it has been programmed
                            to display the notation of the two sources in a semi-diplomatic manner
                            and excluding editorial intervention. <figure xml:id="fig1">
                                <head>Figure 1: synoptic display of variants in bar 32: Accent in
                                    FEJ but <hi rend="italic">decrescendo</hi> in MSB</head>
                                <graphic url="819_Fig1.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                                    mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                            </figure>
                        </item>
                        <item><hi rend="italic">Breath marks</hi>. MSB has fewer breath marks than
                            the first edition FEJ and it is possible that Debussy did not provide
                            all the breath marks necessary for performance. Trevor Wye (1994), in
                            his edition of Syrinx, introduces a number of recommended breath marks
                            to support the performance. Since Wye employs MSB as a base text, his
                            breath marks are suitable for this edition’s notation as well. The
                            encoding for this case study edition includes Wye’s additions with the
                            element &lt;add resp=&quot;Wye&quot;&gt;. The XSLT programmed to
                            transform the edited music notation can, if requested, include these
                            marks in the Mup output.</item>
                    </xmt:oList>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Future work</head>
                <p>The views created for this prototype are static; however it would be highly
                    desirable to combine them in an interactive environment. For example, the
                    apparatus could be enhanced allowing moving measures on the screen to be
                    compared. Performers might be interested in knowing different tempi and breath
                    marks from other editions, like Wye’s breath marks, and include them in the
                    edition to be printed out with a printing device at home. Paper editions with a
                    similar approach are not uncommon, but often include comparative tables of tempi
                    and resolution of ornaments that cannot be directly included in the edited text
                        (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl1">see Palmer, 1991</ref>).</p>
                <p>Even though the Web is currently the preferred digital publishing environment,
                    there still is not a straightforward method to output notation as HTML and
                    possibly there will never be. The only possibility to publish music on the Web
                    is through graphic information; however, systems for delivering complex
                    interactivity based on image formats are becoming increasingly common.
                    OpenLayers, for example, shows how images can be made highly interactive through
                    the superimposition of layers.<note><ref type="external"
                            target="http://openlayers.org/">http://openlayers.org/</ref></note>
                    Future work will focus on implementing interactivity on the PS views in
                    OpenLayers.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <p>N.B. All websites mentioned in footnotes have been accessed 6 March 2010.</p>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl1">
                        <author>Bach, Johann S. </author><date>1991</date>
                        <title level="m">Inventions and Sinfonias (Two- and Three-Part
                            Inventions)</title>
                        <editor>Palmer, W. A. </editor>
                        <pubPlace>Van Nuys (CA, USA)</pubPlace><publisher>Alfred
                            Publishing</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl2"><author>Debussy, Claude</author>
                        <date>1927</date>
                        <title level="m">Syrinx</title>
                        <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Jobert</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl3"><author>Debussy, Claude</author>
                        <date>1991</date>
                        <title level="m">La Flûte de Pan</title>
                        <editor>Ljungar-Chapelon, A.</editor>
                        <pubPlace>Malmö</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Autographus Musicus</publisher><edition>Facsimile</edition>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl4"><author>Debussy, Claude</author>
                        <date>1996</date>
                        <title level="m">Syrinx (La Flûte de Pan)</title><editor>Stegemann,
                            M.</editor>
                        <editor>Ljungar-Chapelon, A.</editor><pubPlace>Wien</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Wiener Urtext Edition</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl5"><author>Feder, Georg</author>
                        <date>1987</date>
                        <title level="m">Musikphilologie: eine Einführung in die musikalische
                            Textkritik, Hermeneutik und Editionstechnik</title>
                        <pubPlace>Darmstadt</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Wissenschaftliche Buchgesellschaft</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl6"><author>Grier, James</author>
                        <date>1996</date>
                        <title level="m">The Critical Editing of Music: History, Method, and
                            Practice</title>
                        <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace><publisher>Cambridge University
                            Press</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl7"><author>Good, M.</author>
                        <date>2001</date>
                        <title level="a">MusicXML for Notaiton and Analysis</title>
                        <title level="j">Computing in Musicology</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">12</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">113-124</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl8"><author>Goodman, Nelson</author>
                        <date>1976</date>
                        <title level="m">Languages of art: an approach to a theory of
                            symbols</title>
                        <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl9"><author>Roland, P.</author>
                        <date>2002</date>
                        <title level="m">The Music Encoding Initiative (MEI)</title>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://www2.lib.virginia.edu/innovation/mei/Papers/maxpaper.pdf"/>
                        <date type="visited">6 March 2010</date></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl10">
                        <author>Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <date type="written">1997</date><title level="a">How to teach your edition
                            how to swim</title>
                        <title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">24.1</biblScope><biblScope type="vol"
                            >27-39</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl11"><author>Tanselle, G. Thomas</author><date>1989</date>
                        <title level="m">A rationale of textual criticism</title>
                        <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>University of Pennsylvania Press</publisher></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
