<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-880">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Towards Digital Built Environment Studies: An Interface Design for the Study
                    of Medieval Delhi</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Keshani, Hussein</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of British Columbia</orgName> Okanagan, <country>Canada</country></affiliation>
                    <email>hussein.keshani@ubc.ca</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-23</date>
                <name>AC</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="poster">
        <body>
         <p>Computing technologies such as CADD, GIS or databases, are generally developed
                    with the aims of the producers of the built environment (architects, engineers,
                    urban planners etc.) in mind. These existing technologies tend to be adapted
                    uncomfortably for pedagogical and research purposes. The field of built
                    environment studies, which here refers to scholarly fields like architectural
                    history and urban history and not practical fields like architecture, is just
                    beginning to consider how computing technologies can be designed and employed
                    for analytical and scholarly ends. What would software designed by practitioners
                    of built environment studies with their aims in mind look like? Engaging with
                    this problem is not only an opportunity to imagine a new practical tool but also
                    to critically inquire into the aims of built environment studies and the
                    assumptions embedded into existing built environment computing technologies.
                    This paper presents the <hi rend="bold">Medieval Delhi Humanities Computing
                        Research Collective</hi>’s proposal for an interface design concept that is
                    the culmination of their attempts to analyse both their own research questions,
                    processes and the suitability of existing technological strategies from the
                    perspective of architectural and urban historians. </p>
           <div>
                <head>The Medieval Delhi Humanities Computing Research Collective</head>
                <p>The Collective is a Canadian-led international team of historians and art and
                    architectural historians from leading research institutions in Canada, the
                    United Kingdom, India, and Japan with expertise in Medieval Delhi and humanities
                    computing initiatives. Formed in 2008, the Collective is a result of the
                    Medieval Delhi Humanities Computing Initiative funded by UBC Martha Piper
                    Research Grant (Jan. 2008 to Sept. 2009). The Collective first met as a group in
                    a workshop and planning session on April 2-3, 2009 in Victoria, established
                    institutional linkages, data sharing agreements, and a common data repository,
                    and is working together to attract additional funding. The Collective is
                    currently completing its work on conceptualizing researcher oriented
                    technologies and strategies for architectural and urban historical research of
                    Medieval Delhi.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Imagining Data Collages</head>
                <p>Researchers interested in studying the built environment in a systematic way
                    typically need to reconcile diverse forms of data – spatial, textual, and visual
                    – and increasingly computing technologies are vital not only for storing and
                    retrieving this information but for analyzing it as well. To be able to research
                    built environments effectively then, a researcher-oriented digital interface and
                    infrastructure becomes increasingly necessary. Not only does one need to need to
                    build an array of databases of historical texts in multiple languages,
                    chronologically organized photographs, maps and satellite data and other forms
                    of information, but one needs to figure out simple productive ways to connect
                    and interface with these various databases, integrate them with large-scale
                    databases and design overlaying analytical tools that truly facilitate
                    historical inquiry and collective scholarship. If planning officials,
                    architects, tourism industries and others increasingly develop and use computing
                    technologies with their goals in mind why should not the built environment
                    scholarly community?</p>
                <p>The Collective’s approach treats architectural sites and urban form as a
                    collection of visual and textual representations of varying precision across
                    time and space each with their own interpretable contexts. For example, a site
                    is not viewed as entirely knowable in its moment of creation but as something
                    that evolves in form and memory and can be known only through its various
                    representations whether they be the textual account of a 12th C court historian,
                    the textual and pictorial accounts of a 19th C British traveller, the textual
                    and photographic records of a 20th C Japanese archaeological team, the oral and
                    videographic account of an Indian tourist from Mumbai, or a 21st century
                    satellite image. These representations amount to a collage of data hence the
                    term Data Collage. While this approach is familiar to researchers of
                    architectural and urban history it is generally not incorporated into existing
                    technology strategies which tend to favour virtual reconstructions or presume
                    the stability of knowledge and a uniform level of precision for spatial and
                    chronological information. This representational approach has important
                    implications for how data should be structured and engaged with.</p>
                <p>Instead of attempting to recreate a historic architectural site or region as
                    virtual reality, Data Collages treat an architectural site or region as a
                    collection of intersecting and conflicting representations. Ideally, a Data
                    Collage will allow researchers of an historic site to access all relevant
                    three-dimensional digital models, photographs, paintings and historical textual
                    descriptions in original and translated texts and be able to see how these
                    various representations are interrelated chronologically and spatially and where
                    they conflict.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>AlSayyad, Nezar</author>
                        <date>1999</date>
                        <title level="a">Virtual Cairo: An Urban Historian’s View of Computer
                            Simulation</title>
                        <title level="j">Leonardo</title>
                        <biblScope type="vol">32</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">93-100</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Andres, Frederic</author>
                        <author>Fukami, Naoko</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">Advanced Semantic Management of Digital Resources</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Ubicomm - International Conference on
                            Mobile Ubiquitous Computing, Systems, Services and Technologies
                            (UBICOMM'07)</title>
                        <name type="venue">Papeete, French Polynesia (Tahiti)</name>
                        <date type="conference">4-9 November 2007</date><biblScope type="pp">249-254</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Ara, Matsuo</author>
                        <date>1977</date>
                        <title level="m">Indo shi ni okeru Isuramu seibyō (Dargāhs in Medieval India
                            – A Historical Study of the Shrines of Sufi Saints in Delhi with
                            Reference to the Relationship between Religious Authority and Ruling
                            Power)</title>
                        <publisher>Tōkyō Daigaku Shuppankai; University of Tokyo Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Tokyo</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl><title level="m">ARCHNET</title>
                        <ptr target="http://archnet.org"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Asami, Y.</author>
                        <author>Kimura, T.</author>
                        <author>Haneda , M.</author>
                        <author>Fukami, N.</author>
                        <date>2002</date>
                        <title level="a">Estimation of Route and Building Sites Described in
                            Pre-modern Travel Accounts Through Spatial Reasoning</title>
                        <title level="j">Papers and Proceedings of the Geographic Information
                            Systems Association</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">11</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">369-372</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Thuraisingham, Bhavani M.</author>
                        <date>2001</date>
                        <title level="m">Managing and mining multimedia databases</title>
                        <publisher>CRC Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Boca Raton, Florida</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Cohen, Daniel J.</author>
                        <author>et al.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">Interchange: The Promise of Digital History</title>
                        <title level="j">JAH</title>
                        <biblScope type="vol">95</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://www.journalofamericanhistory.org/issues/952/interchange/index.html"
                        />
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Financial Express, The</author>
                        <date>2006</date>
                        <title level="a">Rescuing our Monuments</title>
                        <title level="j">The Financial Express</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">2006-02-19</biblScope>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://www.financialexpress.com/news/rescuing-our-monuments/147737/0"
                        />
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Fukami, Naoko</author>
                        <date>1994</date>
                        <title level="a">Studies on Muqarnas-vaulting in the Islamic Architecture:
                            1) the Area of central Asia: Khorasan, Khoarzum and Turan</title>
                        <title level="j">Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians of
                            Japan</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">22</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">2-36</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Fukami, Naoko</author>
                        <date>1996</date>
                        <title level="a">Studies on Muqarnas-vaulting in the Islamic Architecture:
                            2) the Area of Iran: Mazandaran, Azerbaijan, Tehran, Isfahan and
                            Yazd-Fars-kerman</title>
                        <title level="j">Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians of
                            Japan</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">25</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">23-61</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Fukami, Naoko</author>
                        <date>1996</date>
                        <title level="a">Studies on Muqarnas-vaulting in the Islamic Architecture:
                            3) the Areas of Anatolia, Syria and Iraq</title>
                        <title level="j">Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians of
                            Japan</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">27</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">2-46</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Fukami, Naoko</author>
                        <date>1999</date>
                        <title level="a">Madrasas at Isfahan: From Architectural Features and their
                            Distributions</title>
                        <title level="j">The Memoirs of the Institute for Oriental Culture</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">137</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">257-294</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Garrido, González</author>
                        <date>2004</date>
                        <title level="a">Madinat al-zahraí: Investigación y representación, SIGraDi
                            2004</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Proceedings of the 8th Iberoamerican
                            Congress of Digital Graphics</title>
                        <name type="venue">Porte Alegre, Brasil</name>
                        <date type="conference">10-12 November 2004</date>
                        <ptr target="http://cumincades.scix.net/cgi-bin/works/Show?sigradi2004_047"
                        />
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Grabar, Oleg</author>
                        <date>1996</date>
                        <title level="m">The Shape of the Holy: Early Islamic Jerusalem</title>
                        <publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Princeton</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hindu, The</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">IIT to prepare a 3-D database of historical sites</title>
                        <title level="j">The Hindu</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">Thursday, May 31, 2007</biblScope>
                        <ptr target="http://www.hindu.com/thehindu/holnus/002200705311730.htm"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Husain, M.A.</author>
                        <date>1936</date>
                        <title level="m">A Record of All the Qur’anic and Non-Historical Epigraphs
                            on the Protected Monuments of the Delhi</title>
                        <publisher>ASI</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>New Delhi</pubPlace>
                        <edition>reprint 1999</edition>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>INTACH</author>
                        <date>2000</date>
                        <title level="m">Delhi: The Built Heritage—A Listing</title>
                        <publisher>Intach Delhi Chapter</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Delhi</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title level="m">IRCICA</title>
                        <ptr target="http://www.islamicarchitecturedatabase.org"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Keshani, Hussein</author>
                        <date>1999</date>
                        <title level="m">Building Nizamuddin: A Delhi Sultanate Dargah and its
                            Surrounding Buildings</title> M.A. Thesis <pubPlace>University of
                            Victoria</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kumar, Sunil</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">Balancing Autonomy with Service: Frontier Military
                            Commanders and their Relations with the Delhi Sultans in the 13th and
                            14th centuries, Presidential Address, Medieval History Section</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Proceedings of the Punjab History
                            Congress</title>
                        <name type="venue">Patiala</name>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kumar, Sunil</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">The Ignored Elites: Turks, Mongols and a Persian
                            Secretarial Class in the early Delhi Sultanate</title>
                        <title level="j">Modern Asian Studies</title>
                        <biblScope type="vol">43</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">45-77</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kumar, Sunil</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="m">The Emergence of the Delhi Sultanate, 1192-1286</title>
                        <publisher>Permanent Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Delhi</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kumar, Sunil</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="m">The Present in Delhi’s Pasts</title>
                        <publisher>Three Essays Collective</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Delhi</pubPlace>
                        <edition>Second Edition</edition>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kumar, Sunil</author>
                        <date>2000</date>
                        <title level="a">Assertions of Authority: a Study of the Discursive
                            Statements of Two Sultans of Delhi—‘Ala al-Din Khalaji and Nizam al-Din
                            Auliya</title>
                        <title level="m">The Making of Indo-Persian Culture: Indian and French
                            Studies</title>
                        <editor>Alam, Muzaffar</editor>
                        <editor>Delvoye, Francoise</editor>
                        <editor>Gaborieau, Marc</editor>
                        <publisher>Manohar</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Delhi</pubPlace>
                        <biblScope type="pp">37-65</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kumar, Sunil</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">Juzjani, Minhaj-i Siraj</title>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia Iranica</title>
                        <publisher>E.J. Brill</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Leiden</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kumar, Sunil</author>
                        <date>2001</date>
                        <title level="a">Qutb and Modern Memory</title>
                        <title level="m">Partitions of Memory</title>
                        <editor>Kaul, Suvir</editor>
                        <publisher>Permanent Black</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Delhi</pubPlace>
                        <biblScope type="pp">140-182</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kumar, Sunil</author>
                        <date>2006</date>
                        <title level="a">Service, Status and Military Slavery in the Delhi Sultanate
                            of the thirteenth and early fourteenth centuries</title>
                        <title level="m">Slavery and South Asian History</title>
                        <editor>Eaton, Richard</editor>
                        <editor>Chatterjee, Indrani</editor>
                        <publisher>Indiana University Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Bloomington</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kumar, Sunil</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">Trans-regional Contacts and Relationships in Islam’s
                            Eastern frontier: the Delhi Sultanate in the thirteenth and fourteenth
                            Centuries</title>
                        <title level="j">Annales Islamalogiques</title>
                        </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kumar, Sunil</author>
                        <date>1999</date>
                        <title level="a">Perceiving ‘your’ Landscape: Neighbourhood Settlements and
                            the Hauz-i Rānī</title>
                        <title level="m">Perceiving Landscape</title>
                        <editor>Layton, R.</editor>
                        <editor>Ucko, P.</editor>
                        <publisher>Routledge and Kegan Paul</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <biblScope type="pp">159-174</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kumar, Sunil</author>
                        <date>1994</date>
                        <title level="a">When Slaves were nobles: The Shamsi bandagan in the early
                            Delhi Sultanate</title>
                        <title level="j">Studies in History</title>
                        <biblScope type="vol">10</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">23-52</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Matsubara, Kosuke</author>
                        <author>Fukami, Naoko</author>
                        <author>Arai, Yuji</author>
                        <author>Imamura, Fumiaki</author>
                        <author>Iitsuka Mayumi</author>
                        <author>Yamada Eri</author>
                        <date>2005</date>
                        <title level="a">A study on preservation for the old city of Fez,
                            Morocco-From the Viewpoint of the Separation of Public and
                            Private</title>
                        <title level="j">Journal of Housing Research Foundation</title>
                        <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue">31</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">113-124</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title level="m">Invitation of Proposal for Procurement of High-Resolution
                            Imagery for Delhi</title>
                        <ptr target="www.mcdonline.gov.in/"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Mohan, Madan</author>
                        <date>2004</date>
                        <title level="a">Spatial Data Modeling in GIS for Historical Restoration and
                            Conservation of Cultural Heritage of Seven Cities Of Delhi</title>
                        <title level="j">International Archives of Photogrammetry Remote Sensing and
                            Spatial Information Sciences</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">vol. 35, part 5</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">896-902</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Mohan, Madan</author>
                        <date>2004</date>
                        <title level="a">Historical Information System for Surveying Monuments and
                            Spatial Data Modeling for Conservation of Cultural Heritage in
                            Delhi</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Technical Papers, FIG Working Week,
                            Intercontinental Athenaeum Athens</title>
                        <name type="venue">Athens, Greece</name>
                        <date type="conference">22–27 May 2004</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Okabe, Atsuyuki</author>
                        <date>2006</date>
                        <title level="m">GIS-Based Studies in the Humanities and Social
                            Sciences</title>
                        <publisher>Taylor Francis</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Boca Raton</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Okabe, Atsuyuki</author>
                        <date>2004</date>
                        <title level="m">Islamic Area Studies With Geographical Information
                            Systems</title>
                        <publisher>Routledge</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Page, J.A.</author>
                        <author>Hasan. Zafar</author>
                        <date>1916</date>
                        <title level="m">Monuments of Delhi</title>
                        <publisher>ASI</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Delhi</pubPlace>
                        <edition>reprint 2004</edition>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Soja, Edward</author>
                        <date>1989</date>
                        <title level="m">Postmodern Geographies</title>
                        <publisher>Verso</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Soja, Edward</author>
                        <date>2003</date>
                        <title level="a">Writing the City Spatially</title>
                        <title level="j">City: analysis of urban trends, culture, theory, policy,
                            action</title>
                        <biblScope type="vol">7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">269-281</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Sokhi, B. S.</author>
                        <date>1992</date>
                        <title level="a">Spotting historical monuments and sites: Mapping of
                            historical monuments and sites of Delhi using SPOT satellite
                            image</title>
                        <title level="j">Journal of the Indian Society of Remote Sensing</title>
                        <biblScope type="vol">20</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="issue">2-3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">65-71</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title level="m">Properties inscribed on the World Heritage List</title>
                        <ptr target="http://whc.unesco.org/en/statesparties/in"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Verma, Richi</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">City's unprotected monuments dying a slow death</title>
                        <title level="j">The Times of India</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">9 Jun 2008</biblScope>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/Cities/Delhi/Citys_unprotected_monuments_dying_a_slow_death/rssarticleshow/3112362.cms"
                        />
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Welch, Anthony</author>
                        <date>1996</date>
                        <title level="a">Gardens that Babur Did Not Like: Landscape, Water, and
                            Architecture for the Sultans of Delhi</title>
                        <title level="m">Mughal Gardens: Sources, Places, Representations, and
                            Prospects</title>
                        <editor>Wescoat, J. L.</editor>
                        <editor>Wolschke-Bulmahn, J.</editor>
                        <publisher>Dumbarton Oaks Research Library, Harvard University</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Washington DC</pubPlace>
                        <biblScope type="pp">59-93</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Welch, Anthony</author>
                        <date>1984</date>
                        <title level="a">Qur'an and Tomb, the religious epigraphs of two early
                            Sultanate tombs in Delhi</title>
                        <title level="m">Indian Epigraphy, its Bearing on Art History</title>
                        <editor>Asher, F.</editor>
                        <editor>Gai, S.</editor>
                        <publisher>Smithsonian Institution</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                        <biblScope type="pp">247-257</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Welch, Anthony</author>
                        <author>Keshani, Hussein</author>
                        <author>Bain, Alexandra</author>
                        <date>2002</date>
                        <title level="a">Epigraphs, Scripture, and Architecture</title>
                        <title level="j">Muqarnas, an Annual on the Visual Culture of the Islamic
                            World, The Aga Khan Program at Harvard and M.I.T</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">XIX</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">12-43</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Welch, Anthony</author>
                        <date>1997</date>
                        <title level="a">The Shrine of the Holy Footprint in Delhi</title>
                        <title level="j">Muqarnas, an Annual on the Visual Culture of the Islamic
                            World, The Aga Khan Program at Harvard and M.I.T</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">XIV</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">166-178</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Welch, Anthony</author>
                        <date>1996</date>
                        <title level="a">A Medieval Muslim Center of Learning in India: the Hauz
                            Khas Madrasa in Delhi</title>
                        <title level="j">Muqarnas, an Annual on the Visual Culture of the Islamic
                            World, The Aga Khan Program at Harvard and M.I.T</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">XIII</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">165-190</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Welch, Anthony</author>
                        <date>1993</date>
                        <title level="a">Architectural Patronage and the Past: The Tughluq Sultans
                            of Delhi</title>
                        <title level="j">Muqarnas, an Annual on the Visual Culture of the Islamic
                            World, The Aga Khan Program at Harvard and M.I.T</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">X</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">311-322</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Welch, Anthony</author>
                        <date>1985</date>
                        <title level="a">Hydraulic Architecture in Medieval India: The
                            Tughluqs</title>
                        <title level="j">Environmental Design, Journal of the Islamic Environmental
                            Design Research Centre</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">74-81</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Welch, Anthony</author>
                        <author>Crane, Howard</author>
                        <date>1984</date>
                        <title level="a">The Tughluqs: Master Builders of the Delhi
                            Sultanate</title>
                        <title level="j">Muqarnas, an Annual on the Visual Culture of the Islamic
                            World, The Aga Khan Program at Harvard and M.I.T</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">I</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">123-166</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Welch, Anthony</author>
                        <date>2005</date>
                        <title level="a">The Qutb Minar</title>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopedia of Medieval Islamic Civilization</title>
                        <publisher>Routledge</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Welch, Anthony</author>
                        <date>1997</date>
                        <title level="a">Tughlukids: Architecture</title>
                        <title level="m">Encyclopaedia of Islam</title>
                        <publisher>E.J. Brill</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Leiden</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Yamamoto, T., Ara, M. and Tsukinowa, T.</author>
                        <date>1968-70</date>
                        <title level="m">Delhi: Architectural Remains of the Sultanate Period (in
                            Japanese)</title>
                        <title level="m">Indo Shiseki Chōsa Dan hen</title>
                        <edition>3 vols</edition></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
