<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Word Order in Latin Prose Applied to a Case of
                    Authorship Attribution: Book IV of the <title level="m">Stratagemata</title> by
                    Sextus Iulius Frontinus (1st century AD). The Contribution of Quantitative
                    Methods via Computerized Text Analysis.</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Empar</forename>
                        <surname>Espinilla Buisan</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Barcelona</name>, Spain <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Montserrat</forename>
                        <surname>Nofre Maiz</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Barcelona</name>, Spain <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Stylistics</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Background</head>
                    <p>For some time, the Servei de Lexicometria at the University of Barcelona has
                        been working in conjunction with the Latin Linguistics Group (Catalan
                        acronym GLLUB) of the same university on the promotion and application of
                        quantitative methods and computerized analysis of texts in the field of
                        corpus languages, in this case Latin. Most of the work carried out to date
                        has focused on questions of authorship attribution. Our main object of study
                        is Sextus Iulius Frontinus, a writer of technical prose who was active
                        during the first century AD. Parts of his work present problems of
                        attribution; to add to the difficulty, there are few other candidates for
                        the authorship of the doubtful text.</p>
                    <p>Three texts by Frontinus have survived: <title level="m">De
                            agrimensura</title> ("Agrimensura", fragments on land survey and its
                        legislation), <title level="m">Stratagemata</title> ("Stratagems", a set of
                        instructional anecdotes for Roman army officers, which illustrated the
                        principles of the art of warfare via examples of strategems selected from
                        Greek and Roman history) and <title level="m">De aquaeductu urbis
                            Romae</title> ("On the aqueducts of the city of Rome", a treatise on
                        water supply for Rome). The problem of attribution arises with the fourth
                        and last book of the <title level="m">Stratagemata</title>. The hypotheses
                        proposed by philologists for the date of book IV do not coincide: due to the
                        lack of qualitatively distinctive linguistic features, the pseudo-Frontinus
                        has been placed in the first century (thus a contemporary of the author
                        himself), at the beginning of the second, and between the fourth and fifth.
                        For this reason we decided to work on this text of doubtful authorship by
                        applying quantitative statistical analysis methods with computerized support
                        (Espinilla-Nofre: 1998). In that study, we used some of the quantitative
                        methods that are generally accepted for questions of authorship attribution
                        (Holmes: 1994): the ratio of simple forms/occurrences, the ratio of
                        forms/occurrences with a fixed number of occurrences (fixed N), the ratio of
                        simple occurrences/forms, the ratio of hapax legomena/forms, the R-HonorE
                        function, the ratio of hapax dislegomena/forms and the study of the length
                        of forms. These data allowed a comparison between the doubtful text and the
                        rest of the works of Frontinus. The results in that first study highlighted
                        two points:<list>
                            <item>i. Between the doubtful text and the texts reliably attributed to
                                Frontinus there is no inconsistency (this finding underlines the
                                difficulties facing traditional hypotheses).</item>
                            <item>ii. Another point of reference is required, i.e. another author,
                                with whom to compare the data obtained.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>So as the second stage of the project we have decided to approach the problem
                        from another perspective. Following on from previous studies
                        (Tweedie-Frischer: 1999; Frischer-Holmes-Tweedie, et al: 1999) and others,
                        we are keen to analyze the order of the forms in the text in question and to
                        compare them (1) with the texts recognized as Frontinian, and (2) with
                        another text of a later date (control author, Tweedie: 1998). This analysis
                        assumes that there was a change in word order in the Latin sentence between
                        the classical era and the later period (Linde: 1923, Marouzeau: 1953). In
                        spite of the fact that the use of the computer is a considerable aid in
                        performing quantitative analysis of the texts, our study has faced two
                        particular problems from the very beginning: <list>
                            <item>I. The first derives from the premise of an established word order
                                in Latin. The generalized opinion is that word order is basically
                                S(ubject)-O(bject)-V(erb). However, there are a number of
                                deviations, and certain scholars have questioned the assumption of
                                this standard word order in Latin prose (Pinkster: 1991): <list>
                                    <item>A. Deviations according to sentence type: unlike assertive
                                        sentences, in imperatives the verb is usually placed at the
                                        beginning.</item>
                                    <item>B. Deviations according to type of clause (main or
                                        subordinate) and the use of different types of subordinate
                                        clauses.</item>
                                    <item>C. Deviations deriving from the internal structure of the
                                        constituents of the sentence: the general tendency in Latin
                                        is to place the syntactically relevant constituents (the
                                        heavy material) on the right, and the constituents of less
                                        syntactic importance (the light elements) as near the
                                        beginning as possible, even though this tendency may be
                                        altered for pragmatic and semantic reasons; questions of
                                        theme and rheme, or topic and focus. Nonetheless, in our
                                        study, we subscribe in principle to the premise that in the
                                        classical era the most common order followed by authors in
                                        Latin prose was SOV, and, in the later period, SVO.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item>II. The second intrinsic difficulty when working with corpus
                                languages can be summarized as follows (Ramos: 1996): <list>
                                    <item>A. Productivity: the corpus does not show which of the
                                        linguistic rules that can be extracted are the most
                                        productive.</item>
                                    <item>B. Grammaticality: to clarify the grammatical differences
                                        observed between authors it is obviously impossible to
                                        consult a native speaker.</item>
                                    <item>C. Representativity of the corpus: the corpus at our
                                        disposal is a set of materials that has been preserved due
                                        to a particular sequence of events. It is not specifically
                                        selected for study by linguists.</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The Corpus Studied</head>
                    <p>For our study, we compared book IV of the Stratagema of Frontinus with books
                        I, II and III, and also with the work of a control author: <title level="m"
                            >De diversis fabricae architectonicae</title>, by Caetius Faventinus,
                        another writer of technical prose who lived in the later period. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Methodology</head>
                    <p>
                        <list>
                            <item>I. Technical data<list>
                                    <item>A. Computerization of the texts in the corpus (ASCII
                                        format)</item>
                                    <item>B. The computer program used to analyze the corpus was
                                        TACT (Textual Analysis Computing Tools), version 2.1.
                                        gamma.</item>
                                    <item>C. The corpus was coded with COCOA labels, following the
                                        marking guidelines of the MAKEBASE module in TACT.</item>
                                    <item>D. The data were obtained using the USEBASE module in
                                        TACT.</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item>II. Methods of analysis<list>
                                    <item>A. We examine whether the verb is in final position in the
                                        various texts in our corpus.</item>
                                    <item>B. We study the position of the direct object in relation
                                        to the verb that governs it.</item>
                                    <item>C. We establish the type of clause (main or subordinate)
                                        in which the verb is found.</item>
                                    <item>D. We establish differences between the position of the
                                        verb according to the type of subordinate clause.</item>
                                    <item>E. We do not restrict ourselves to cases of direct objects
                                        represented by nouns or pronouns in the accusative, but also
                                        study cases of governed complement (in genitive, dative or
                                        ablative) and those in which the direct object is
                                        represented by a subordinate clause.</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Working Hypothesis And Results Obtained</head>
                    <p>The aim of our study is to provide arguments to corroborate or reject our
                        working hypothesis: following the traditional assumption of Latin word
                        order, the text of the <title level="m">Stratagemata</title> recognized as
                        authentically Frontinian (books I, II and III) must follow word order SOV,
                        while the work of the control author will predominantly follow word order
                        SVO. According to the word order we find in the doubtful book IV we will be
                        able to place it in one or other era. We will thus have a set of data which,
                        though unable to date the writing exactly, will lend support to one of the
                        traditional philological hypotheses.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Agud</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Fernandez Delgado</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Ramos Guerreira</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Las lenguas de corpus y sus problemas
                                linguisticos</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Madrid</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Ediciones Clasicas</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Espinilla Buisan</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Nofre Maiz</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Metodos estadisticos y problemas de autoria. El libro
                                IV de las Estratagemas de S. Julio Frontino</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Mellet</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">JADT 1998. 4emes Journees Internationales d'Analyse
                                statistique des Donnees Textuelles</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Nice</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Universite de Nice-Sophia Antipolis-Centre National de la
                                    Recherche Scientifique-INaLF</publisher>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">B.</forename>
                                    <surname>Frischer</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <surname>Holmes</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author><name>
                                    <forename type="first">F.</forename>
                                    <surname>Tweedie</surname>
                                </name> et al</author>
                            <title level="a">Word-order transference between Latin and Greek: The
                                relative position of the accusative direct object and the governing
                                verb in Cassius Dio and other Greek and Roman prose authors</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Harvard Studies in Classical Philosophy</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol"/>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp"/>
                                <date>(forthcoming)</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">I.</forename>
                                    <surname>Holmes</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Authorship attribution</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">28</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">87-106</biblScope>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Linde</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Die Stellung des Verbs in der lateinischen
                                Prosa</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Glotta</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">12</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">153-178</biblScope>
                                <date when="1923">1923</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Marouzeau</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">L'ordre des mots en latin</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Les Belles Lettres</publisher>
                                <date when="1953">1953</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Pinkster</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Evidence for SVO in Latin?</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Wright</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Latin and the romance languages in the Early Middle
                                Ages</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Routledge</publisher>
                                <date when="1991">1991</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">69-92</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A></forename>
                                    <surname>Ramos Guerreira</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">El estatuto linguistico del corpus latino: algunas
                                precisiones</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Agud</surname>
                                </name> et al </editor>
                            <title level="m">Las lenguas de corpus y sus problemas
                                linguisticos</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Madrid</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Ediciones Clasicas</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">35-54</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Siewirska</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Constituent order in the languages of Europe</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
                                <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Mouton de Gruyter</publisher>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">F.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Tweedie</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">The provenance of De Doctrina Christiana attributed to
                                John Milton: a statistical investigation</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">13</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">77-97</biblScope>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">F.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Tweedie</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">B.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">D.</forename>
                                    <surname>Frischer</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Analysis of classical Greek and Latin compositional
                                word-order data</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Journal of Quantitative Linguistics</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">6</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">85-97</biblScope>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
