<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">A Toolbox for the Electronic Classroom</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Peter</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
                        <surname>Havholm</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">The College of Wooster</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Larry</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
                        <surname>Stewart</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">The College of Wooster</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>The Electronic Classroom</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Writing about the new economy, Jeff Madrick remarks that the kinds of good jobs
                    increasing most rapidly "require communication skills, social ease, and basic
                    reasoning abilities ..." Acquiring such skills, he believes, "may only be
                    possible through higher education, where students are exposed to a sophisticated
                    culture, a variety of experiences, and varying disciplines that require analysis
                    of facts and concepts" (33). In our view, the conventional classroom on a
                    college or university campus remains the best facility for such an education,
                    and we think the new technologies can be used to make it even more powerful.</p>
                <p>By contrast, much excitement about technology in governing bodies is lavished on
                    various money-saving adaptations of distance education using the web. Perhaps as
                    a result, some advocates of increased use of technology in higher education seem
                    to believe the traditional classroom anachronistic (see Daniel, 1996 and 1997).
                    In our opinion, such thinking bodes ill for the kind of learning we see as
                    vital. Rather than using technology to replace teachers and conversation, we
                    think it should take its place with more conventional tools as another way to
                    enhance teaching and learning conceived in traditional ways.</p>
                <p>In what follows, we describe (and illustrate in presentation) a technologically
                    enhanced classroom and accompanying tools that operationalize a philosophy of
                    pedagogy that puts technology at the service of active learning. While we have
                    previously presented some of the tools we use in this classroom (Havholm and
                    Stewart 1996, 1998), this presentation aims at showing a style of teaching we
                    believe to be particularly promising. While it is too soon to claim more than
                    anecdotal success, we know it promotes active learning because it demonstrably
                    extends students' powers of inquiry.</p>
                <p>We and colleagues increasingly favor this kind of use of technology - in a range
                    of disciplines - at The College of Wooster. It saves no money in the short term,
                    however. Rather than doing away with buildings or teachers, it adds technology
                    to a conventional classroom housing a small number of people, one of whom is
                    salaried. But over the long term, if we are right, our graduates have the
                    intellectual and cultural capital that allows them to think and learn
                    independently. They will not need expensive re-training every time their
                    environment changes a little.</p>
                <p>Our electronic classroom looks like a seminar room, with a table in the middle,
                    surrounded by comfortable chairs. It differs in that along its walls twenty to
                    thirty networked computers stand ready, each linked to one another, to a
                    screen/video projector overhead, and to the internet. Such a classroom clearly
                    values physically proximate talk, but it also brings the huge resources of the
                    internet to any conversation that wishes them. Moreover, it makes possible the
                    easy use of a range of new tools that encourage active learning.</p>
                <p>For example, Peter Havholm and our colleague Jenna Hayward use a freeware beta
                    version of PennMUSH in a course on dramatic structure to allow the class (of 29)
                    to improvise a seven-episode serial drama. Students play characters and invent
                    actions on-line, edit the logs of their online sessions into scripts, and then
                    publish a final version on the web for friends (on- and off- campus) to
                    read.</p>
                <p>Because of the technology, they can write and publish a play that belongs to all
                    of them. Most important, however, is that this exercise is not done in a
                    playwriting class but in a study of drama. Rather than honing writing skills,
                    writing and publishing a play in this class tests the principles of structure
                    students are learning from their reading of a dozen plays and Aristotle's <title
                        level="m">Poetics</title>. And because the technology makes publication so
                    easy, the whole project takes only about 15% of class time.</p>
                <p>Having students write and publish a drama to test theoretical ideas was a natural
                    development from another kind of project several of us in the English department
                    use in our writing courses. In the Journalism course, in Introduction to
                    Non-fictional Writing, and in English 101 as well as in the course Writing for
                    Magazines, students spend two to five weeks writing, editing, designing, and
                    producing a magazine, using page layout software, which they then either give
                    away or sell on campus.</p>
                <p>The publishing projects have pleased several of us because students so much enjoy
                    writing to intrigue and amuse their peers - and because the projects make
                    self-evidently necessary the tasks of re-writing, careful consideration of
                    audience and voice, and editing. No need for exhortation about these activities;
                    one cannot make a magazine to impress one's friends without them. We also
                    believe that preparing writing for publication - with headlines, pullquotes,
                    illustrations, captions, and the rest - provides valuable experience in
                    imagining oneself as one's reader and in visual thinking.</p>
                <p>Among the tools that have been particularly useful in courses in narrative or
                    narrative theory is the Linear Modeling Kit (or LMK), a program the two of us
                    designed and have worked with for several years (see Havholm and Stewart, 1996).
                    The LMK is essentially an authoring system, and it allows users to create
                    applications that generate any kind of text according to principles proposed by
                    the user. For example, a student can use the LMK to create a "folktale
                    generator" by entering what the student perceives to be the parts or elements of
                    a folktale, any principles of order among those parts, and characteristic text
                    for each part. Depending on the complexity of the input, the generator will
                    produce hundreds, thousands, or millions of different texts. In our classes,
                    students have created not only folktale generators but bildungsroman generators,
                    romance generators, tragedy generators, and argument generators.</p>
                <p>As do all the activities we discuss here, working with the LMK acts as an
                    heuristic, forcing students to move back and forth between theory and practice.
                    To produce an LMK generator, students must first abstract principles from
                    narratives they have read and then turn them into instructions for their
                    generators. The generator then operationalizes the student's theory; it produces
                    narratives created according to the principles the student has derived.</p>
                <p>Another of the tools we use in the electronic classroom is the Stylistic Analysis
                    Kit (or SAK), a combination concordance and counting program with a nearly flat
                    learning curve. Although the SAK is a fairly conventional program, its ease of
                    use separates it from many of the tools used by professional researchers and
                    makes it ideal for the student in the classroom.</p>
                <p>When analyzing their own papers, students are almost always driven back to their
                    texts by, for example, discovering their average sentence length to be half that
                    of the person sitting at the next computer or by learning that "the" comprises
                    14.7% of their total words. Here, students move between the abstraction of
                    statistics and their own practice as writers. Even those who seem generally to
                    lack curiosity are fascinated by the statistical record of their writing and
                    eager to determine what practices account for those statistics.</p>
                <p>There has recently been much publicity about the ease with which new hardware and
                    software can be used to create complex video projects. Our students have begun
                    to find that - like desktop publishing software - the new video tools can be
                    used to explore and test ideas. Ben Speildenner chose to make a video as his
                    final project in our colleague Jenna Hayward's course in Post-Colonial
                    Literature. In <title level="m">Urban Legends</title>, he wanted to to evoke
                    reflection congruent with one of the principal issues of the course. The class
                    had talked about how easy it is to essentialize one's own culture while seeing
                    other cultures as "different." Ben chose several urban legends - that Disney
                    makes heavy use of phallic imagery in <title level="m">The Little
                        Mermaid</title>, that there's a boy with a shotgun in the background of a
                    scene in <title level="m">Three Men and a Baby</title>, that there's a hanged
                    Munchkin in <title level="m">The Wizard of Oz</title> if you look closely enough
                    at the right moment, and that spiders can lay eggs on your face - to shake our
                    presuppositions. He wanted his presentations of these legends to push his
                    audience into problematizing their own culture. He thinks that our urban legends
                    show us to be more "different" than we think we are. But he wanted to stimulate
                    thought, not to impose his ideas on the class.</p>
                <p>In <title level="m">Understanding and Cognition</title>, Terry Winograd and
                    Fernando Flores make a convincing case against the use of computers as
                    "restricted to representing knowledge as the acquisition and manipulation of
                    facts, and communication as the transferring of information" (78). Rather, they
                    argue that we need to design computers as "equipment for language" so that they
                    can "create new possibilities for the speaking and listening that we do"
                    (79).</p>
                <p>Our version of the electronic classroom and our use in it of the tools we have
                    described reflect this understanding of technology. In every case, students use
                    the tools to interrogate ideas in ways novel in humanistic study. In an
                    important sense, each tool allows students to test their understanding: the
                    effectiveness of a serial drama tests ideas about dramatic structure; reader
                    response to a published magazine tests convictions about rhetoric; the variety
                    of lawful stories an LMK generator produces tests the powers of the theory of
                    narrative it has been "taught"; the SAK's quantitative analysis leads to testing
                    qualitative ideas about writing style; and his classmates' response to
                    Spieldenner's <title level="m">Urban Legends</title> tested his hypothesis that
                    presenting urban legends can help us think in new ways about "difference."</p>
                <p>In every case, we believe, the technology adds power to students' ability to
                    question and therefore to understand - in the context of a kind of discussion as
                    old as learning.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Ernest</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Boyer</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Foreword</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Campus Life: In Search of Community</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Lawrenceville, NJ</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Princeton, UP</publisher>
                                <date when="1990">1990</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Daniel</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">The Mega-Universities and Knowledge Media</title>
                            <title level="s">Open &amp; Distance Learning</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Kogan</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Daniel</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Why Universities Need Technology Strategies</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Change</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol"/>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">10-17</biblScope>
                                <date when="1997"> July/August 1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Peter</forename>
                                    <surname>Havholm</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Larry</forename>
                                    <surname>Stewart</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Modeling the Operation of Critical Theory on the
                                Computer</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">30</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">107-115</biblScope>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Peter</forename>
                                    <surname>Havholm</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Larry</forename>
                                    <surname>Stewart</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Using a Narrative Generator to Teach Literary
                                Theory</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">ALLC-ACH '96 Conference Abstracts</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Bergen</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">135-37</biblScope>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Peter</forename>
                                    <surname>Havholm</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Larry</forename>
                                    <surname>Stewart</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Computers and Active Learning: Using the Stylistic
                                Analysis and Linear Modeling Kits</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">ALLC-ACH '98 Conference Abstracts</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Debrecen</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">135-37</biblScope>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Madrick</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Computers: Waiting for the Revolution</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The New York Review of Books</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">45</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">5</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">29-33</biblScope>
                                <date when="1998">March 26, 1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Terry</forename>
                                    <surname>Winograd</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Fernando</forename>
                                    <surname>Flores</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Understanding Computers and Cognition: A New Foundation
                                for Design</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Addison-Welsey</publisher>
                                <date when="1987">1987</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
