<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Multi Dimensions Concept-Based Information Retrieval
                    System</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Zainal</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Hasibaun</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Indonesia</name>, Indonesia <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Computational / Corpus Linguistics</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>Most of the problems in information retrieval systems occur from three
                        sources: impreciseness of query and document representations, the changing
                        state of mind in document relevant judgement, and the discrepancy of
                        retrieval technique to match query and information need. The traditional
                        approach to information retrieval systems, such as Boolean based retrieval
                        technique, cannot solve these problems (Belkin and Croft, 1987). According
                        to McCain (1989) and Pao and Worthen (1989), retrieval by keywords and cited
                        documents will end up with different sets of documents retrieved. There were
                        relevant documents retrieved by keywords but not retrieved by references,
                        and vice versa. Hence, a new approach to retrieval technique is needed.</p>
                    <p>This study is intended to build a new approach to information retrieval
                        systems by employing the inherent structure of a document collection in an
                        effort to learn more about document components that might improve
                        information retrieval performance. The document components examined are the
                        pattern of keywords, citing documents, and cited documents. Three
                        independent variables were studied: co-keyword, co-citing document, and
                        co-cited document (Hasibuan, 1995). These three variables constitute the
                        multi-dimensions concept-based information retrieval system. By providing
                        such variables as entry points to search relevant documents, it is widening
                        the naturalness of the system in order to accommodate users' information
                        needs.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Methodology</head>
                    <p>A test collection was constructed from a collection of research articles
                        published by National Atomic Research Agency (BATAN), covering the period
                        1985 through 1998. An automatic program was written to build indexes of
                        keywords, citing documents, and cited documents for each document. The
                        relationship that may occur between two documents can be depicted as in
                        Figure 1. Pair-wise document similarity is calculated on those three
                        variables. As in Figure 1, the similarities between documents A and B can be
                        viewed in terms of documents Q and S, which cite documents A and B
                        (co-cited), and documents Y and Z, which are cited by A and B (co-citing).
                        In addition to that, the similarity of documents A and B can be counted on
                        the number of shared terms (co-keyword).</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Figure 1. Relationship of Two Documents (A and B)</head>
                    </figure>
                    <p>Document similarity is measured by using the simple matching coefficient
                        proposed by Van Rijsbergen (1979) and Salton (1989). The similarity of
                        document A and B is calculated as follows:<lb/><formula rend="block"
                            >Similarity (A, B) = | X Ç Y | </formula></p>
                    <p>The variables X and Y represent the sets of index terms occurring in two
                        documents. Hence, the similarity of document A and B is measured in terms of
                        the number of shared index terms. These sets of index terms can be expanded
                        to include values for citing documents and cited documents. The retrieval
                        technique used is based on this document similarity.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Results</head>
                    <p>The preliminary results of the research showed that relevant documents
                        retrieved by one component did not always agree with other components (see
                        Figure 1). Figure 1 shows document 0376 and document 0419 have 11 shared
                        index terms, two shared cited documents and three shared citing documents.
                        As we expected, most of the document pairs have zero frequency of shared
                        cited document and shared citing document. This finding is in line with our
                        previous research finding in Hasibuan (1995). According to these results, it
                        is suggested to build a multi-dimension concept-based retrieval system. The
                        system built is able to provide users with a facility to search several
                        interrelated options of search strategy. Given that kind of facility, a user
                        can be more flexible to start his/her search by using one of the dimensions,
                        says keyword, then navigates the system using other dimensions of document
                        similarity. At any moment, the documents retrieved can be viewed, evaluated
                        and judged for their relevance.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Figure 1. A Portion of Search Results of the Multi-dimension
                            Concept-based Information Retrieval System</head>

                    </figure>
                    <p>The search results shown in Figure 1 are posted in a hypertext based, so that
                        a user can continue browsing uninterruptedly, in order to further his/her
                        search to retrieve more on the other possible relevant documents. For each
                        pair of documents retrieved, the system will provide the frequency of its
                        co-keyword, co-cited documents and co-citing documents. Furthermore, the
                        non-zero frequency of each entry in the columns of co-citing and co-cited
                        documents becomes an active icon. If we click 2 in column co-cited, then we
                        can see the documents that are co-cited by document 0376 and 0419 (see
                        Figure 2). There are documents 0523 and 0531. The abstract of each document
                        retrieved can be viewed by clicking the number of the document (see Figure
                        3).</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Figure 2. An Example of Co-cited Documents </head>
                    </figure>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Figure 3. An Example of Abstract Document Retrieved</head>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Conclusion</head>
                    <p>Multi-dimensions concept-based retrieval system provides relaxed facility in
                        order to search information by utilizing the components of documents -
                        co-keyword, co-cited documents, and co-citing documents. With this facility,
                        the system can widely accommodate the range of user's search strategy in
                        information seeking. The drawback of the system compared to the traditional
                        system is that this new approach needs more space of computer storage in
                        order to accommodate all its index files. Furthermore, it can slow down the
                        search process. However, this trade-off is compensated for by the
                        flexibility of the system to provide more search strategies, more
                        comprehensive retrieval of relevant documents, and easy to browse from one
                        document to another document. Ultimately, by utilizing these three
                        components of a document, the system can reduce the possibility of low
                        retrieval system performance due to the impreciseness of query and document
                        representations, lack of relevant judgement, and lack of matching function
                        between query and document.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Nicholas</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >J.</forename><surname>Belkin</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">W.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >Bruce</forename><surname>Croft</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Retrieval Techniques</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Annual Review of Information Science And
                                Technology</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">22</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">109-145</biblScope>
                                <date when="1987">1987</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Zainal</forename><forename
                                        type="middle"
                                    >A.</forename><surname>Hasibuan</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Document Similarity and Structure: Using Bibliometric
                                Methods and Index Terms As Approaches to Improving Information
                                Retrieval Performance</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <edition>Doctoral Dissertation</edition>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>School of Library, Archive and Information Science,
                                    Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana</publisher>
                                <date when="1995">1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Katherine</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >W.</forename><surname>McCain</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Descriptor and Citation Retrieval in the Medical
                                Behavioral Sciences Literature: Retrieval Overlaps and
                                Novelty</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Journal of the American Society for Information
                                Science</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">40</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">110-114</biblScope>
                                <date when="1989">1989</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Miranda</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >L.</forename><surname>Pao</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Dennis</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >B.</forename><surname>Worthen</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Retrieval Effectiveness by Semantic and Citation
                                Searching</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Journal of the American Society for Information
                                Science</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">40</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">4</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">226-235</biblScope>
                                <date when="1989">1989</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Gerard</forename>
                                    <surname>Salton</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Automatic Text Processing: The Transformation, Analysis
                                and Retrieval of Information by Computer</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Addison-Wesley Publishing Company</publisher>
                                <date when="1989">1989</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Van Rijsbergen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Information Retrieval</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Butterworth</publisher>
                                <date when="1979">1979</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
