<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">WebCAPE - Language Placement Testing over the
                    Web</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Charles</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">D.</forename>
                        <surname>Bush</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Brigham Young University</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>The Electronic Classroom</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <p>WebCAPE is a web-based implementation of the BYU Computer-Adaptive Placement
                        Exam (CAPE) series. These exams use adaptive procedures to assess language
                        ability, drawing from a large bank of calibrated test items. Tests are
                        administered from a web server computer through the internet to a browser
                        application on students' computers. Test security in WebCAPE is maintained
                        through a combination of application design and standard web methods.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Background</head>
                    <p>Students entering a university language program come with a wide range of
                        previous language training and experience. Thus, determining which class
                        students should enroll in becomes an enormous task for language departments.
                        A placement exam can be used, but paper-based standardized placement exams
                        bring their own headaches: students have to be brought in at a fixed time
                        and place, the test takes a long time to take and everyone has to wade
                        through all the questions, and then you have to wait while the tests are
                        sent in for scoring and for the results to come back.</p>
                    <p>The Humanities Research Center at Brigham Young University has developed a
                        set of language placement exams that overcome these problems. The exams are
                        delivered by computer and thus do not require a lock-step controlled
                        environment. The exams are adaptive, effectively eliminating questions far
                        above or below the students' ability. And since questions are drawn from a
                        large bank of test items, each student gets what amounts to a unique test,
                        thus avoiding problems with test security. The computer-adaptive approach
                        also means the test need only take long enough to determine a particular
                        student's ability level and produces a placement score on the spot.</p>
                    <p>Underlying the BYU CAPE (Computer-Adaptive Placement Exam) application is a
                        large bank of calibrated test items. Initially, several hundred questions
                        were written, testing a variety of language skills: vocabulary, grammar,
                        reading comprehension, etc. These were then statistically calibrated for
                        difficulty and discrimination among ability levels. Test item banks have
                        been developed for Spanish, German, French, Russian, and most recently,
                        English as a Second Language.</p>
                    <p>Originally CAPE tests were implemented as individual application programs.
                        But more recently, a new implementation has been developed for an
                        internet/web environment. This version, called WebCAPE, uses a web server
                        for the core functionality and test item banks, but administers the actual
                        tests over the internet through a standard browser application. Thus WebCAPE
                        tests can be given on any computer with an internet connection and Netscape
                        4.0 or equivalent.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>How It Works</head>
                    <p>Students enter WebCAPE through their school's menu page. This page is
                        customized for the school, incorporating their seal or logo, a background
                        campus scene, and school colors into the page design. Page content includes
                        a brief explanation of the tests and how the school utilizes their results,
                        along with basic instructions for taking the test.</p>
                    <p>When students select their language from the menu page, they go to a
                        registration page. This page is also specific to the school. Students enter
                        their identification information in the top section of the page. They may
                        also enter their e-mail address for an e-mail copy of their test
                        results.</p>
                    <p>Clicking the Begin Exam button takes students into the actual exam. After
                        some initialization, a new browser window opens to the exam environment.
                        This is served completely from the WebCAPE server and is the same for all
                        tests. The top frame contains title information. The middle section displays
                        the current test item. The bottom frame contains the exam control panel
                        where the students indicate their answer, then click Confirm Response to
                        register their response.</p>
                    <p>First, the exam presents six <emph rend="italics">level check</emph>
                        questions selected from the full difficulty range. Based on these answers,
                        the algorithm computes a preliminary ability estimate. It then begins to
                            <emph rend="italics">probe</emph> with questions to fine-tune that
                        estimate. In essence, it presents harder and easier questions until it can
                        focus to a statistically reliable value. On average, the entire testing
                        process takes 20-25 minutes.</p>
                    <p>When the exam finishes, students are returned to the registration page and
                        their results are posted in the bottom section of the page. Here their final
                        ability estimate is mapped to a recommended course by reference to a table
                        of cut-off points established by the school. Beginning and ending
                        time-stamps are also posted, for validation and timing purposes. In
                        addition, the exam returns details of the students' session. These are not
                        normally displayed for the student to see, but are sent to the school for
                        analysis.</p>
                    <p>As a final step, students click Submit Results. This generates an e-mail
                        message with all of the information to the school/department and a summary
                        message to the student's e-mail address. A confirmation page is also
                        generated by this process, which in turn takes them back to the menu page,
                        ready for the next student.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Security</head>
                    <p>WebCAPE is designed to be reasonably secure for its intended use. Access
                        control is maintained through the menu page, registration pages only accept
                        entrance from a corresponding menu page, and the exam environment can only
                        be entered from a properly configured registration page. Both are maintained
                        on the WebCAPE server and isolated from outside access. The host school
                        controls access to their menu page, typically by either setting up links or
                        bookmarks in the lab where they administer the exam, or by only giving the
                        URL to their properly registered students. When needed, the WebCAPE server
                        can also be configured to restrict access to a particular IP address or
                        range (a designated lab, for example), or to require a userID and
                        password.</p>
                    <p>Test security is maintained mostly by the design of the page set. Test items
                        are individual html files that do not contain answer information or other
                        clues. The answer <emph rend="italics">key</emph> is read into the
                        programming of the control frame when it loads. And should a student manage
                        to hack into the answer table, there is no way to identify which answer goes
                        with which question. At the server level, hackers are thwarted by the
                        built-in resistance of the server and operating system configuration.</p>
                    <p>Foolproofing security is more problematic. Because it uses a standard
                        internet browser, WebCAPE cannot keep students from doing things the browser
                        allows: like closing the window or using the back button or even quitting
                        the browser program entirely. All that can be done is to write clear
                        instructions and incorporate warning alerts. This suggests administering
                        WebCAPE tests in a controlled environment (like a student lab) with a
                        standardized browser configuration and a proctor to monitor things.</p>
                    <p>The biggest vulnerability to cheating in WebCAPE comes at the student
                        workstations. The exam cannot prevent students from using a dictionary,
                        getting help from friends or even having someone else take the test. This
                        clearly demands a proctored environment.</p>
                    <p>WebCAPE test security measures mentioned thus far try to prevent cheating to
                        get a higher score. But students taking a placement test may also try to get
                        a lower score. The current version of WebCAPE does not directly address this
                        problem. However the results message it sends to the department does include
                        details of the test session, which can be analyzed when needed - an alert
                        human would immediately suspect a test with all-wrong answers. Other
                        suspicious patterns like all-one-letter answers or only a few seconds
                        between answers can also be easily recognized by a human. The next version
                        of WebCAPE will probably include processing to at least flag patterns such
                        as these.</p>
                    <p>Ultimately there may still be a few students that get misplaced, either by
                        faking out the test or by slipping through the statistical margin of error.
                        These will still have to be dealt with by human administrative procedures.
                        But WebCAPE should keep the number small enough to manage.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Implementations</head>
                    <p>WebCAPE is implemented as a service rather than as a program package. Schools
                        pay for access for their students to take the tests rather than buy the
                        program itself. For most schools, the best alternative is a flat fee for
                        unlimited tests, but a lower-cost option for a fixed number of tests is also
                        available. In each case there is also a one-time setup fee for creating the
                        customized menu and registration pages. Planning is underway to also
                        implement a pay-per-test entrance to WebCAPE. This would allow someone to
                        take the test on their own initiative to see how they might place into
                        college-level courses. A third configuration as a high school exit exam has
                        been proposed. This would be for high school language programs, allowing
                        students to find out where they would place into college courses.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Future</head>
                    <p>WebCAPE is currently available for French, German and Spanish, with Russian
                        to be added shortly. For all four languages, the test items are strictly
                        text-based questions. While different test items assess different aspects of
                        language ability, they are still confined to written text. But the latest
                        CAPE exam under development, English-as-a-Second-Language, goes beyond that
                        text-only limit. ESL-CAPE incorporates sound clips into many test items and
                        thus adds listening comprehension to the language skills it assesses.
                        ESL-CAPE also has an option to calculate separate ability estimate scores
                        for grammar, reading comprehension, and listening comprehension - the other
                        exams only give a composite estimate. A stand-alone implementation of
                        ESL-CAPE is now being piloted. Web implementation will be ready for
                        production testing next year.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Selected Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Harold</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Madsen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Jerry</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Larson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Computerized Adaptive Language Testing: Moving Beyond
                                Computer Assisted Testing</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">CALICO Journal</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">2</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">32-36</biblScope>
                                <date when="1985">March 1985</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Jerry</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Larson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">S-CAPE: A Spanish Computerized Adaptive Placement
                                Exam</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">William</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">Flint</forename>
                                    <surname>Smith</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Modern Technology in Foreign Language Education:
                                Applications and Projects</title>
                            <title level="s">ACTFL Foreign Language Education series</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Skokie, IL</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>National Textbook Co.</publisher>
                                <date when="1989">1989</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">277-289</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Jerry</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Larson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Computerized Adaptive Placement Exams in French,
                                German, Russian, and Spanish. Foreign Language Notes</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Newsletter of Foreign Language Educators of New
                                Jersey</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">XXXVIII</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">13-15</biblScope>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Jerry</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Larsen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">An Argument for Computer Adaptive Language
                                Testing</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Methods and Applications of CALL for Foreign Language
                                Education in Korean Universities. Proceedings of the Conference on
                                Applications of Computer-Assisted Language Learning (CALL), Dongduck
                                Women's University. Seoul, Korea, November 29, 1996</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">51-80</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
