<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Primroses and Power: a Study on Linguistic Excellence
                    in Political Discourse</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Anna</forename>
                        <surname>Loiacono</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Università degli Studi di Bari</name>, Italy <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Angela</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">Maria</forename>
                        <surname>D'Uggento</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Università degli Studi di Bari</name>, Italy <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Barbara</forename>
                        <surname>Cafarelli</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Università degli Studi di Bari</name>, Italy <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Rosaria</forename>
                        <surname>Romita</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Università degli Studi di Bari</name>, Italy <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Stylistcs</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The aim of this paper is to focus on a linguistic corpus in order to detect, by
                    statistical methods and computational tools, either correspondences or contrasts
                    between the hypotheses made by the linguist and the applied procedures made by
                    the software experts.</p>
                <p>The corpus is selected from nineteenth century Victorian speeches; in particular,
                    Parliamentary and political speeches delivered by Benjamin Disraeli, both as a
                    member of Parliament and as Prime Minister.</p>
                <p>Analogous types of research have been recently carried out [see <emph
                        rend="italics">Labbè, Bolasco, Lebart, Salem,</emph> 1995] with reference to
                    contemporary politicians such as de Gaulle, Mitterand and the Italian
                    Berlusconi. In fact, computational research in political discourse is a highly
                    significant new brand of criticism, which contributes to the modern notion of
                    political contest by some more hidden truths that can be revealed. Nonetheless,
                    we should say that, in most cases, where contemporary politicians are concerned,
                    the use of "ghost writers" for writing public speeches definitely undermines
                    that language structure/personality relationship which justifies work in textual
                    analysis.</p>
                <p>Dealing with 19th century England, we have considered Victorian politics as being
                    the first true "arena" for party politics and as constituting fundamental
                    principles for political dialectics.</p>
                <p>The main source of reference was the collection of <title level="m">Selected
                        Speeches by T. E. Kebbel</title> in two volumes, borrowed from the
                    Parliament Library in Rome. Disraeli's personal letters written to Lady Bradford
                    and Lady Chesterfield also constitute a valuable source of reference, in that
                    they unveil psychological traits and personal idiosyncrasies of the statesman.
                    Moreover, in classical biographies we have found revealing hints of modernity
                    and wisdom that we think useful to compare to our times. In a further
                    perspective, we would aim at setting up a series of parameters which might
                    characterise English political discourse, defining also its specific contexts by
                    comparing corpora (for example Tory vs Whig discourse or Conservative vs
                    Radical, etc.).</p>
                <p>Some intriguing questions have led us to pursue this goal, bearing in mind the
                    old lessons of rhetoricians concerning oratory and trying to see them in the
                    light of modern standard rules: how great is the analogy existing between
                    oratorical qualities, original style and words, phrases and discourse markers
                    more or less unconsciously uttered by an individual? By which standards can this
                    analogy be assessed? And which is the "benchmark" for moral evaluative
                    judgement, when we use a meta-linguistic code to filter the quintessence of
                    discourse? Should, for instance, the most frequent items adhere in meaning and
                    collocation to their speaker's actual socio-political presuppositions? And in
                    which degree should their collocation be found in accordance with given
                    parameters? Moreover, what can computational analysis discover beyond or in
                    contrast to all previous evaluative criticism on the same subject to which so
                    many scholars have contributed in the course of centuries?</p>
                <p>We have tried to answer these questions by examining, through data processing,
                    which linguistic marks might define or confirm the features for linguistic
                    excellence.</p>
                <p>Our stylometric study is concerned with the Victorian century, an age rich in
                    syntactical perfection and lexical complexities.</p>
                <p>We have selected thirty-four speeches given by Disraeli between 1830 and 1870,
                    and have processed them through the software programme "Lexico 2" and SPSS. The
                    corpus has 205,800 occurrences<note n="1">According to an empirical criterion, a
                        corpus can be considered wide enough if it is greater than 200,000 words;
                        moreover the ratio V/N (vocabulary or number of different words divided by
                        total occurrences) is 9.8% (when this ratio is over 20%, the corpus is not
                        to be considered wide enough. See Bolasco, <title level="m">Analisi
                            Multidimensionale dei dati</title>. Carocci Editore. Roma. 1999. p.203)
                    </note>, with a type/token ratio of 9.83% (known also as a measure of vocabulary
                    richness) and a Guiraud's coefficient G=44.61.</p>
                <p>In table 1, for all the sub corpora in the decades, we show the the number of
                    occurrences (N), forms (V) and hapax (V1), the word with maximum frequency for
                    each decade.</p>
                <p>Hapax forms (words used only once) constitute nearly the 50% of the total amount
                    of different words, which is a representative ratio marking a highly varied
                    though integrated vocabulary.</p>
                <p>In table 2, we show a list of the fifty most important words considered as truly
                    connotative of Disraeli's mind and world, displayed according to total
                    decreasing frequency, making a distinction between the decades, the absolute
                    frequency (F) and the normalized occurrences (x 1000 words).</p>
                <p>Moreover, we have disambiguated words (textual forms) in order to obtain the
                    correct rank and we have made a distinction, for some forms, between pronouns,
                    nouns, verbs, adjectives, adverbs and conjunctions. The choice was made to build
                    up the so-called lexical universe of Disraeli's discourse: the chosen words
                    (i.e. power, principle, democracy, oligarchy, empire, etc.) have first been seen
                    as collocates and, for them, we have built their lexical universe, in order to
                    define specific contexts and co-texts through the relationship of proximity and
                    distance.</p>
                <p>We have patterned some meaningful words from a diachronic point of view, marking
                    the evolution of his political thought, throughout his long parliamentary
                    activity, detecting their characteristic trends and we have also carried out a
                    factor analysis for some groups of words, clustered according to some semantic
                    categories (i.e. self, key words, generic words, geography, negative words,
                    etc.)</p>
                <p>What clearly appears by means of statistical exploitation is as follows:<list>
                        <item>1. High occurrence of a limited number of forms (mainly unspecific in
                            meaning);</item>
                        <item>2. High occurrence of hapax forms and of various different forms, used
                            with a very low frequency;</item>
                        <item>3. percentage of polysyllabic adjectives of Latin origin, used
                            according to alliterative and symmetric structures, creating an
                            appealing effect of harmony and balance. The same effect is obtained by
                            collocating meaningful words used in pairs and the same occurs with
                            words plus adjectives often used in pairs;</item>
                        <item>4. High percentage of adjectives in relation to the corpus as a whole
                            and most of them belonging to the semantic category of "greatness" and
                            of "positive feeling".</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>We think that Disraeli's discourse is powerful, confident, determined, endowed
                    with energy and a brand of sincere English imperialism. He certainly cared for
                    England and for himself and a true interest was also Ireland.</p>
                <p>What might appear strange is the zero occurrence of the word "Judaism", even
                    considering the very low presence of all vocabulary concerned with race and
                    religion. He supposedly divided with care his choice of language genres (novel,
                    essays and speeches) according to some well defined goals to pursue.</p>
                <p>The high occurrence of generic words, i.e. with a neutral connotative value,
                    seems to confirm some critical judgements expressed by his opponents for which
                    Disraeli's political commitment was in most cases supported only by generic
                    principles of well re-constructed political heritage and, only in a lesser
                    degree he offered detailed policies on various occasions.</p>
                <p>A possible consequence that originates from this analysis and supports the
                    original hypothesis made is that Disraeli's political success and his prolonged
                    prominence as a first-rate politician (even when in opposition) was mainly due
                    to his gifts of linguistic excellence and flamboyant oratory. From a different
                    perspective, his Italian-Jewish ancestry adds an odd and mysterious flavour to
                    his success, in the pure aristocratic context of Victorian England.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Blake</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Disraeli</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Methuen &amp; Co. Ltd</publisher>
                                <date when="1978">1978</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Bolasco</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Analisi Multidimensionale dei dati</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Roma</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Carocci Editore</publisher>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Bolasco</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">L'individuazione di forme testuali per lo studio
                                statistico dei testi con tecniche di analisi
                                multidimensionale</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">SIS Atti della XXXVII Riunione Scientifica 1994</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">Vol. 2</biblScope>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">95-103</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Bolasco</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Criteri di lemmatizzazione per l'individuazione di
                                coordinate semantiche</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor><name><forename type="first"
                                        >S.</forename><surname>Bolasco</surname></name></editor>
                            <editor><name><forename type="first"
                                        >R.</forename><surname>Cipriani</surname></name></editor>
                            <title level="m">Ricerca qualitativa e computer: teorie metodi e
                                applicazioni</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Milano</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Franco Angeli</publisher>
                                <date when="1995">1995</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">87-111</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Bolasco</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">L'analisi informatica dei testi</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Ricolfi</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">La ricerca qualitativa</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>NIS</publisher>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">165-202</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Kebbel</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Selected speeches of the Late Earl of
                                Beaconsfield</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">2 vols.</biblScope>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1882">1882</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >I.</forename><surname>Holmes</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">The analysis of Literary Style-A review</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Journal of the Royal Statistical Society, Series
                                A</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">148</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">4</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">328-41</biblScope>
                                <date when="1985">1985</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <surname>Labbé</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Le vocabulaire de François Mitterand</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Presses de la FNSP</publisher>
                                <date when="1990">1990</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <surname>Labbé</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first"
                                        >P.</forename><surname>Hubert</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">La structure du vocabulaire de Général De
                                Gaulle</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">JADT 1995</title>
                            <title level="m">Atti Analisi Statistica dei Dati Testuali</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">Vol. II</biblScope>
                                <pubPlace>Roma</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>CISU</publisher>
                                <date when="1995">1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Lebart</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <surname>Memmi</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a"/>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">SIS Atti della XXXII Riunione Scientifica 1984</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">Vol. I</biblScope>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1984">1984</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">27-41</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Lebart</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Salem</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Statistique Textuelle</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Dunod</publisher>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Lebart</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Salem</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Berry</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Exploring textual data</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Levinson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Pragmatics</title>
                            <title level="s">Cambridge Textbooks in Linguistic</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1995">1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">W.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">F.</forename>
                                    <surname>Moneypenny</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Buckle</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">The life of Benjamin Disraeli Earl of
                                Beaconsfield</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">6 vols.</biblScope>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1910">1910-1920</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Oakes</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Statistics for Corpus Linguistics</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>Edinburgh University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Sinclair</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Corpus, Concordance, Collocation</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1991">1991</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Smith</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Disraeli. A brief life</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">F.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Tweedie</surname></name></author>
                            <editor><name><forename type="first">R.</forename><forename
                                        type="middle"
                                >H.</forename><surname>Baayen</surname></name></editor>
                            <title level="a">How variable may a constant be? Measures of Lexical
                                Richness in Perspective</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Computer and Humanities</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">32</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">5</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">323-352</biblScope>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first"/>
                                    <surname>Zetland</surname> Marques of </name></editor>
                            <title level="m">The Letters of Disraeli to Lady Bradford and Lady
                                Chesterfield</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">2 vols.</biblScope>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1929">1929</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
