<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Computer-Aided Acquisition of Language Teaching
                    Materials from Corpora</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Svetlana</forename>
                        <surname>Sheremetyeva</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">New Mexico State University</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>The Electronic Classroom</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <p>Awareness of domain-tuned linguistic peculiarities present in expository
                        texts is a relevant concept in helping students' reading and writing
                        competency in terms of genre literacies.</p>
                    <p>Support for this point of view comes from the analysis of academic written
                        genres, competing demands for limited resources, the tyranny of scheduling
                        and from graduate students' verbal protocols about their reading process
                        (Sengupta 1997).</p>
                    <p>Genre literacy or sublanguage approach in instructed SLA advocated in this
                        paper tries to exploit lexical, morphological, syntactic and semantic
                        restrictions on the specialized languages used by experts in certain fields
                        of knowledge for communication or in particular types of texts (technical
                        and scientific articles, instructions, installation manuals, etc.).</p>
                    <p>Notions of sublanguage distinctiveness rely on linguistic knowledge
                        concerning different kinds of sublanguage regularities and restrictions.
                        (Kittredge and Lehrberger 1982). Sublanguages are special subsystems of a
                        natural language with restricted vocabulary and grammar which, on the one
                        hand, share some properties with a language as a whole and, on the other
                        hand, are characterized by some deviations from "general" language.</p>
                    <p>As far as language instruction is concerned, both defining the content of
                        this knowledge and ways of sublanguage knowledge elicitation are problems
                        which do not have a single answer. Despite a long-standing interest in the
                        analysis of written genres (sublanguages), little research has focused on
                        how to really use genre specificity in language instruction.</p>
                    <p>This presentation explores critical issues in the selection of an appropriate
                        methodological framework for the analysis of profession-related texts. It
                        aims to provide suggestions as to the kind of sublanguage analysis method
                        that is supposed to form the basis for developing a system of typological
                        parameters useful in acquisition of teaching materials and thus tuning
                        language instruction to the needs of professional communication.</p>
                    <p>To describe a particular sublanguage it is necessary to study laws underlying
                        natural language phenomena and laws which make a sublanguage differ from a
                        language. Sublanguages can be described in many ways. Language instruction
                        is influenced by such practical parameters as scope and nature of
                        vocabulary, grammar specificity, potential for ambiguity, lexical and
                        grammar correlation, if any, which can and should be discovered on the basis
                        of corpus analysis (Biber et al. 1998; Wichmann et al. 1997).</p>
                    <p>This study focuses on verbs, as they are central to the structure of a
                        sentence and consequently to text structure (Levin 1993; Aarts and Meyer
                        1995). The reason is that in professional reading most problems usually
                        derive not from technical nouns and noun expressions which are relatively
                        easy to find in specialized dictionaries but from grammar which is often
                        characterized by extended sentences with frequently long and telescopic
                        embedded structures.</p>
                    <p>The current study also proposes and tests a sublanguage-specific hypothesis
                        of correlation between lexical meaning, morphological representation (tense,
                        voice, finiteness) and syntactic realization (subject, object, predicate,
                        attribute, etc.) of a particular verb in a sublanguage.</p>
                    <p>Material for the research includes five corpora of 50,000 words each from
                        different technical sublanguages: aerospace engineering, automobile
                        engineering, mechanical engineering, technology engineering and patents. The
                        sample corpora are taken from four technical journals (<title level="j"
                            >Space Flight</title>, <title level="j">Automobile and Tractor</title>,
                            <title level="j">Materials Engineering</title>, and <title level="j"
                            >Machine Design</title>) and a corpus of US patent claims.</p>
                    <p>The main method of analysis is a computer-aided corpus-based combination of
                        qualitative and quantitative (statistical) techniques applied to a
                        pre-tagged corpus, which proved to be useful for linguistic knowledge
                        elicitation (Sheremetyeva 1998). Tagging, done manually by trained
                        linguists, codes morphosyntactic realizations of sublanguage verbs. For
                        example, in the sentence "Making_TIA this apparatus they used_2IA a new
                        technology", the tag TIA means that the verb "make" is used as an adverbial
                        modifier in the form of Present Participle, the tag 2IA shows that the verb
                        "use" is realized as a predicate in the form of Past Simple Active.</p>
                    <p>This methodology allows for a standard automatic frequency count procedure to
                        be applied to provide:<list>
                            <item>a) a verb inventory and its size in terms of verb
                                occurrences;</item>
                            <item>b) a verb morphology and grammar inventory and their sizes in
                                terms of occurrences of specific values of tense, aspect, voice,
                                finiteness/nonfiniteness and syntactic functions as well as in terms
                                of co-occurrence of grammatical features (for example, in the
                                sublanguage of automobile engineering the most frequently used
                                nonfinite realization of verbs is the Past Participle in the
                                function of attribute, while no realization of verbs as Gerunds or
                                Infinitives in the function of subject was found);</item>
                            <item>c) an inventory of lexical and morphosyntactic correlations (for
                                example, in the sublanguage of automobile engineering the verb "use"
                                is most often realized as the Past Participle in the function of
                                attribute while the most frequent realization of the same verb in
                                the aerospace engineering sublanguage is the Present Participle in
                                the function of adverbial modifier).</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Qualitative analysis of each of the above inventories included sense
                        analysis. The number of senses for each lexeme in a sublanguage is, on
                        average, much smaller than in the language as a whole. Thus, of the seven
                        senses of the word <emph rend="italics">engage</emph> in the Cobuild English
                        Language Dictionary, the patent sublanguage uses only one, which includes
                        this word in the following synonym set: <emph rend="italics">engage, hold,
                            attach, lock, join, clamp, fasten</emph>. Clearly,paradigmatic and
                        syntagmatic relations are different in a sublanguage.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Conclusions</head>
                    <p>The paper presents a computer-aided methodology and the results of selecting
                        teaching materials for optimizing students' reading and writing competencies
                        in terms of genre literacies on the material of four technical sublanguages. </p>
                    <p>The results of the study show "deviations" of every sublanguage from the
                        general language and from each other. They also confirm that there exists a
                        correlation between lexical meanings of many sublanguage verbs and their
                        morphosyntactic realizations. These deviations can be used for selecting
                        professionally oriented language teaching materials to most effectively
                        foster language proficiency development.</p>
                    <p>The approach was tested and proved to be very useful at the Department of
                        Foreign Languages of South Ural State University (Russia). It is expected to
                        be portable to other sublanguages and can be used both for developing
                        theoretical and practical issues in applied linguistics.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">B.</forename>
                                    <surname>Aarts</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Ch.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">F.</forename>
                                    <surname>Meyer</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">The Verb in Contemporary English: Theory and
                                Description</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1995">1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <surname>Biber</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Conrad</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <surname>Reppen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Corpus Linguistics. Investigating Language Structure
                                and Use</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Kittredge</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Lehrberger</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Sublanguage: studies of language in restricted
                                domains</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1982">1982</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">B.</forename>
                                    <surname>Levin</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">English Verb Classes and Alternations</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Sengupta</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Academic reading skills for L2 learners: Does teaching
                                selective reading help?</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Proceedings of the Annual Conference of American
                                Association for Applied Linguistics. Seattle, March 13-17,
                                1997</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name><forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname/>Sheremetyeva</name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Acquisition of Language Resources for Special
                                Applications</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Proceedings of the workshop Adapting Lexical and Corpus
                                resources to Sublanguages and Applications in conjunction with The
                                First International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation,
                                Granada, Spain, May 1998</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Wichmann</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Fligelstone</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <surname>McEnery</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Knowles</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Teaching and large Corpora</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Eddison Wesley Longman Inc.</publisher>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
