<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The Miguel Cervantes Digital Library: The Hispanic
                    Voice on the WEB</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Andrés</forename>
                        <surname>Pedreño</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Universidad de Alicante</name>, Spain <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Digital Resources</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>This paper describes the philosophy behind what represents one of the most
                    ambitious projects of its kind ever to have been undertaken in the
                    Spanish-speaking world: The Miguel Cervantes Digital Library (<ptr
                        target="http://cervantesvirtual.com/"/>). It explains the reasons behind its
                    creation, the private-public sector alliance which has made it possible, and the
                    new ground being explored by its creators in terms of innovative application of
                    digital methods and of new services it offers to its audience world-wide.</p>
                <p>The Miguel Cervantes Digital Library is the result of a unique collaboration
                    between Alicante University and Spain's biggest bank, the Banco Santander
                    Central Hispano who have joined forces to create the world's biggest digital
                    library containing Spanish-speaking works. It represents an example of
                    successful partnership between university and business, with the Santandar
                    Central Hispano Bank providing complete sponsorship for the full development of
                    the project. The University, on the other hand, provides the academic expertise,
                    technological know-how and qualified workforce necessary to fulfil objectives
                    and ensures international use of the Library's resources by way of collaboration
                    agreements with universities and institutions all over the world. The paper will
                    address the issue of this partnering of academia and private enterprise as a
                    case study of how two vastly different institutions have successfully worked
                    together in the overall management and vision of a large, global project.</p>
                <p>The Miguel Cervantes Digital Library hopes to act as inspiration to other
                    non-English speaking cultures to create their own novel digital tools which can
                    be used by a multiracial and multilingual student and academic community of
                    Internet users world-wide. Far from being a static collection of digitised
                    books, the Library is envisaged as a vehicle for the Hispanic academy to promote
                    their works, as a window to Hispanic literature and culture for scholars of
                    Hispanic languages and cultures, and as a voice for the Hispanic university
                    community world-wide. The actual content of the Library reflects this ambition
                    as it includes sections such as:<list type="bulleted">
                        <item>the digital publication of theses, which acts as a window to Hispanic
                            research and a forum of academic debates</item>
                        <item>a voice library with quality recordings of top Hispanic voices who
                            have volunteered to recite one of the Library's most visited works. Well
                            known Hispanic poets and authors also take part in this section,
                            reciting parts of their own work</item>
                        <item>a directory with over 3000 links to digital Hispanic resources and to
                            outstanding digital collections, libraries and technology-related
                            resources. All the links have a full explanation in Spanish for Hispanic
                            users unfamiliar with the potential of the Web for study and
                            research</item>
                        <item>personalised pages on Hispanic authors, debate forums, its own
                            electronic news bulletin, and a facility enabling readers, collectors
                            and editors to interact and locate rare books</item>
                        <item>initiatives aimed at bringing together "the Old" (printed material)
                            and "the New" (electronically produced works). As well as a section
                            called "Trueque" which brings together publishers, booksellers,
                            collectors and readers in an attempt to locate rare and out-of-print
                            editions, the project envisages traditional publication of text-books
                            and critical studies accompanied by interactive electronic versions
                            available in the Miguel Cervantes Digital Library "Research"
                            section</item>
                        <item>a section where the Library encourages and publishes in its pages the
                            results of research projects and collaborations related to educational
                            software development undertaken in or considered to be of interest to
                            the Hispanic world. With the help of Latin-American governments and
                            universities, we aim to equip villages, schools and communities with
                            educational, literary and cultural material which, without modern
                            technology, would be beyond their reach.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Another feature of this project is the use of technology to preserve and promote
                    minority Hispanic languages, and to affirm different Hispanic cultures by way of
                    specialised gateways and portals. The design of these sections does not only
                    entail the use of new techniques, but also involves collaboration agreements
                    whereby staff from the Miguel Cervantes Digital Library travel to other centres,
                    universities and institutions all around different areas of Spain and Latin
                    America in order to digitise "in situ" documents, objects and works of art.
                    Existing language portals include Catalan, Basque and Galician, and gateways on
                    Hispanic cultures are being developed on Cuba, Argentina and Mexico in
                    collaboration with key institutions in these countries. Visits and contacts
                    between academic institutions in these countries and the Library have
                    illustrated the ground we need to make up in order to reach standards already
                    achieved in other parts of the world as far as the use of digitised content for
                    the study of the humanities is concerned. By opening up different channels of
                    communication and collaboration within the different Hispanic communities
                    (Spain, Latin America and the United States), we aim to provide academics all
                    over the World, and especially in Spanish-speaking communities, with a major new
                    research tool and to create a new concept of a digital library.</p>
                <p>During the past two years we have learned much from other worthy initiatives that
                    are being undertaken in Spain, Latin America and further afield to digitise
                    material reflecting Hispanic languages, literature and cultures. The author will
                    provide a brief overview of the most notable projects in this area, and will
                    offer a picture of the state of the art as to what techniques are being used to
                    produce electronic resources in the Hispanic community at present and what the
                    future holds.</p>
                <p>The final section of the paper will deal with the technical underpinnings of this
                    project at present and in the future. Techniques used for digitisation of texts,
                    manuscripts, images and voices will be discussed, and advances in this area made
                    possible by certain strategic partnerships with universities, libraries and
                    other institutions in Spain and abroad will be acknowledged.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
