<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ab-321">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>User ethnographies: informing requirements specifications for Ireland’s, national, trusted digital repository.</title>
<author>
<name><surname>Webb</surname>, <forename>Sharon</forename></name>
<affiliation>An Foras Feasa, Ireland</affiliation>
<email>sharon.webb@nuim.ie</email>
</author>
<author>
  <name><surname>Keating</surname>, <forename>John</forename></name>
  <affiliation>An Foras Feasa, Ireland</affiliation>
  <email>John.Keating@nuim.ie</email>
</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority></authority>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace> 
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
<p></p>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt><note type="abstract">This paper discuss the development and use of user ethnographies to inform requirements specification for Ireland&#039;s, national, trusted digital repository - the Digital Repository of Ireland (DRI). It discusses requirements specifications in light of our requirements interviews and our national report, which forms a crucial part of the information gathering phase of requirements engineering, and consider and critique how user ethnographies can enhance our understanding of the user and their software needs. It will also consider the specification of requirements both as natural language statements and executable requirements which support user testing and the development of live documentation.</note></notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
<p>
<date when="20130717"></date>
<time when="13:30:00"></time>
</p>
<p n="session">LP09</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Paper</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
<term>Long Paper</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
<term>User ethnography</term>
<term>use cases</term>
<term>requirements engineering</term>
<term>trusted digital repository</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>archives</term>
<term>repositories</term>
<term>sustainability and preservation</term>
<term>user studies / user needs</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date when="2013-04-23"></date>
<name>Laura Weakly</name>
<desc>Initial encoding</desc>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text type="paper">
<body>
<div>

<div>
<head>1 Introduction</head>
<p>The Digital Repository of Ireland (DRI) is an interactive national trusted
digital repository for contemporary and historical, social and cultural data
held by Irish institutions; providing a central internet access point and
interactive multimedia tools, for use by the public, students and scholars.
DRI is a four-year exchequer funded project, comprising six Irish academic
partners, and is supported by the National Library of Ireland, the National
Archives of Ireland (NAI) and the Irish national broadcaster, RT&#201;.<ref type="note" target="n01">1</ref></p>


<p>DRI is in its second year and has completed a number of project
deliverables, including initial requirements statements, a lean prototype with
core functionality and a national practice report, <hi rend="italic">Digital archiving in Ireland:
National survey of the humanities and social sciences</hi> (O'Carroll et al. 2012). This report is
based on the findings from our requirements interviews which represent the
first phase of engagement between DRI and its stakeholders and can be
described as a ‘descriptive ethnographic contribution’ (Wynne et al. 2012). The principle aim
of the interviews was to inform the system’s business, functional and nonfunctional
requirements as well as to drive policy decisions and inform
guidelines on issues such as metadata, file formats and access rights. Since
DRI’s remit extends to the humanities as well as the social sciences the
interviews revealed a diverse problem domain (Hull et al. 2011). However, even within this
diverse space the interviews uncovered many similarities, shared problems
and challenges among the community of users.</p>

<p>The diversity of DRI’s community, that is national cultural institutions,
university libraries and other higher education institutions, as well as their
respective research institutes, national broadcasters and various independent
and state bodies, requires reconciliation between their various perspectives.
This paper will discuss requirements specifications in light of these
stakeholder interviews and the national report, which form a crucial part of
the information gathering phase of requirements engineering, and consider
how user ethnographies can enhance our understanding of the user and their
software needs.</p>
</div>

<div><head>2 Methodology - requirements gathering and qualitative
interviews.</head>
<p>The generation of use cases and use case scenarios are paramount to the
successful development, and completion, of digital humanities projects,
resources and artifacts and is crucial in the first phase of requirements
engineering, that is requirements elicitation and information gathering. Use
cases inform the system that will be and advance the development teams’
knowledge of their end user, focusing attention on authentic users and their
needs. These use cases, and the actors involved, must be linked to some, but
perhaps augmented, reality. Analysis of the various actors is required to
develop use case scenarios that consider the context in which the future
system, that is the Digital Repository of Ireland (DRI), will be used.</p>

<p>To achieve this we used a qualitative approach to requirements elicitation
and carried out extensive stakeholder interviews (we completed 40 separate
interviews between Nov. 2011 - Aug. 2012). While alternative approaches to
requirements elicitation exist, and include quantitative methods such as
online voting and user questionnaires, as well as traditional JAD (Joint
Application Development) methods, (Maciaszek et. al. 2001) we elected the use of semi-formal
and topic driven requirements interviews because they enhanced our user
engagement and helped to develop important ties and relationships with our
community (O'Carroll et al. 2012). This approach allowed us to incorporate our requirements
interviews with policy management and ensured that we addressed the key
concerns of the community and developed strategies for digital rights
management, digital preservation, access control, digital standards, among
others. The interviews were ‘an inquiry’ rather than ‘an inquisition’, (Weigers et al. 2006) and
as such required close analysis to extract requirements, as they were not
explicitly stated or expressed. The result of this analysis is requirements
statement as well as descriptive user ethnographies linked to specific
activities, namely preservation, interaction and access.</p>

<p>Ethnographic research, as a core feature of anthropology and sociology,
encourages us to observe social and cultural norms and can help us interpret
individual, as well as group, behaviour, activities and practices. As a research
methodology it is concerned with ‘why’ we perform and engage in certain
cultural and social norms and as such can help us understand technological
practices and workflows associated with particular software systems.
R&#246;nkk&#246; et al. (2002), describe ethnographic research as a means to
emphasise ‘the members’ point of view’ and as a method which can help us
‘understand the organisation of social, cultural and technical setting[s]’.
From a software engineering view point user ethnographies can provide an
‘inside perspective’ (R&#246;nkk&#246; et al. 2002) and help reveal the different methods, practices, and
indeed agendas, of the community. Some of these ‘inside perspectives’ are
captured in our national report which considers key topics such as digital
preservation, user tools, file formats and metadata standards (O'Carroll et al. 2012).</p>

<p>A user ethnography, in this context, is essentially a composite analysis of the
methods and practices identified as the salient features of the system to be,
which we considered as part of the social, cultural and institutional norms of
particular methods, behaviors and user activity linked to digital archiving. It
is a term borrowed from the anthropological practice which may involve
participant observation or immersion in a particular group or society.
However, this was not possible given resource limitations and the scope of
this project. Instead, we chose requirements interviews, focus groups with a
subset of users, feature development through executable requirements
specification and online surveys to develop the user ethnography, the
extended use case scenario, to provide a holistic view of the problem domain
in order to inform the solution.</p></div>

<div><head>3 Reconciling ‘the members’ point of view’ -
requirements engineering and user ethnographies</head>

<p>Requirements engineering is a key aspect of the software development cycle
and is a necessary activity for any small or large scale project. The methods
developed within DRI to capture the requirements were informed by the
need to capture a ‘panoramic view’ of DRI’s community (Passos et al. 2012). A high level
consideration of requirements was necessitated given the broad range of
users and their needs. The ethnographic approach, that is considering the
setting, the field or indeed the culture of our designated community, allowed
us to ‘focus on the participants and their interactions in [the] system rather
than the data, its structure and its processing’ (Sommerville et al. 1993).</p>

<p>From this analysis we developed our requirements statements which were
expressed as structured, natural language statements as well as executable
specifications, developed as Cucumber tests or features which support user
testing and the development of live documentation (Wynne et al. 2012). Cucumber features
are also key to the ethnographic approach as they are specified
collaboratively with the software development team and key stakeholders in
DRI. This allows us to observe and analyse particular activities related to
core functionality and provides essential feedback, validation and
verification of the requirements specification.</p>

<p>Feature development is key to the reconciliation process as it allows us to
test particular high level requirements in terms of specific user goals. For
example, feature development with an audio archive highlighted a missing
requirement in terms of time coding audio content in comparison to
“tagging” associated with images based content. Through this process we try
to reiterate the importance of the informants point of view (the problem
rather than just the solution) and in this sense we view feature development
as part of “participant observation” techniques.</p></div>

<div>
<head>4 Conclusion</head>
<p>To develop our requirements specifications, we used a qualitative
methodology to drive requirements gathering and have similarly applied a
qualitative method, that is user ethnographies, to reconcile the various
perspectives of the community. Our national practice report represents the
first analysis of DRI’s requirements but reconciling the various perspectives
requires further, more thorough analysis of each domain, that is humanities
and social sciences, within the context of three separate activities,
preservation, access and interaction. This paper will consider the
development of these user ethnographies, a method which is an important
aspect of software engineering and requirements engineering and how they
inform the final stages of requirements specification.</p></div>

                
</div>

</body>

<back>
<div type="References">
<listBibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">O’Carroll, A., and S. Webb</hi> (2012).  Digital archiving in Ireland.
National survey of the humanities and social sciences. National University
of Ireland Maynooth available at <ref type="url" target="http://www.dri.ie/publications">www.dri.ie/publications</ref></bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Wynne, M., and A. Helles&#248;y</hi> (2012). The Cucumber book, behaviour-driven
development for testers and developers. <hi rend="italic">Pragmatic Programmers.</hi></bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Hull, E., K. Jackson, and D. Jeremy.</hi> (2011). Requirements
engineering. <hi rend="italic">Springer.</hi></bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Maciaszek, L. A.</hi> (2001). Requirements analysis and system design,
developing information systems with UML. Addison-Wesley.</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Weigers, K. E.</hi> (2006). More about software requirements, thorny issues and
practical advice. Microsoft Press.</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">R&#246;nkk&#246;, K., O. Lindeberg, and Y. Dittrich.</hi> (2002). ‘Bad practice’ or
‘bad methods’. Are software engineering and ethnographic discourses
incompatible? <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the International Symposium on Empirical
Software Engineering</hi>, Nara, Japan 204-10.</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Passos, C., D. S. Cruzes, and T. Dyb&#229;</hi> (2012). Challenges of applying
ethnography to study software practices. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the ACM-IEEE
international symposium on Empirical software engineering and
measurement</hi> 9-18.</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Sommerville, I., T. Rodden, P. Sawyer, R. Bentley, and
M. Twidale</hi> (1993). Integrating ethnography into the requirements
engineering process. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the IEEE International Symposium
onRequirements Engineering</hi> 165-73.</bibl>

<bibl><hi rend="bold">Sharp, H.</hi> (2012). Keynote: Using ethnography in empirical software
engineering. 16th International Conference on Evaluation &amp; Assessment
in Software Engineering.</bibl>

</listBibl>
</div>

<div type="Notes">
<note xml:id="n01" n="1">See <ref type="url" target="http://www.dri.ie">www.dri.ie</ref></note>

</div>

</back>
</text>
</TEI>

