<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The Academic vs. Subject Corpus: Development of
                    Criteria for the Teaching of ESP According to Lexical Needs in Spanish
                    Polytechnic Courses</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Alejandro</forename>
                        <surname>Curado Fuentes</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Universidad de Extremadura</name>, Spain <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <p>The aim of this paper is to offer the details gathered from the lexical
                        analysis of English texts read in Information Science related majors in
                        Spanish universities. In such a textual collection, lexical items are
                        arranged according to the notions of word frequency and range across text
                        types and genres, or within given subject fields and topics in the
                        Information science and technology disciplines. How strong these lexical
                        combinations are, based on their statistical M.I. (Mutual Information)
                        measurement, is also quite pertinent to our study. The degree of collocation
                        is thus assessed in the light of common coreness. That these patterns are
                        more or less consistent in our corpus is, indeed, a key characteristic to
                        value so that a reference with the total number of texts and running words
                        can be established. Finally, as the findings show that there exist
                        representative lexical items for a limited or reduced number of texts,
                        keywords must be explored. For the observation of results drawn according to
                        the three approaches mentioned - word frequency / range, collocations and
                        keywords - the focus is placed on both the text and the subject-matter. This
                        is essentially done to follow the priority of working with language and
                        content from the ESP (English for Specific Purposes) perspective. As a
                        consequence, a categorization is made regarding a specified kind of context
                        - e.g. text types.</p>
                    <p>As in the case of genre, the environments of text and discourse are of prime
                        importance for the situation of lexical items in the scope of academic
                        linguistic competence. Text types are approached in relation to how text is
                        organized and reflects coherence and cohesion, while the second setting -
                        genre - registers the writer's inclination and intentionality to produce
                        discourse for a community (e.g. academic). There are two other parameters -
                        subject and topic - on which the distribution of the lexical items of our
                        corpus is based. In their case, a framework based on content is provided,
                        and the findings yield the core lexis according to thematic / conceptual
                        fields.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>a. Word frequency and range.</head>
                    <p>In this first division, the most frequent text type words are provided
                        according to how recurrent they are across six sets of ten texts. These are
                        grouped as follows:<list>
                            <item>1. Definitions.</item>
                            <item>2. Descriptions.</item>
                            <item>3. Classifications.</item>
                            <item>4. Exemplifications.</item>
                            <item>5. Discussions.</item>
                            <item>6. Conclusions.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>The samples are taken randomly to represent the rhetorical functions and
                        sub-sections of genres with which the learner must cope and come to
                            grips.<note n="1">1. Only these six types are chosen due to the fact
                            that others, such as the discourse function signalling contrast, are
                            contained by Discussions on five occasions, whereas illustrations are
                            coped with in Exemplifications. In turn, the two sections of research
                            articles included - Discussions and Conclusions - are given priority
                            over Abstract, Introduction, Method and Results since these are already
                            selected for the compilation of Descriptions, Classifications,
                            Definitions and Exemplifications to a greater or lesser degree (see
                            distribution of the text type sub-corpus).</note> The relevant
                        vocabulary analyzed from this perspective is classified as argumentative,
                        procedural and discourse/grammar items, examined in demarcated domains such
                        as distinctive subject fields and genres. <note n="2">2. How certain genres
                            and types can be characterized by core or subject-core lexis is
                            described, among others, by Carter (1997, 1988).</note></p>
                    <p>Our immediate concern thus lies in having all the interrelationships among
                        the subject fields represented visually in order to make the selection of
                        text samples accordingly.</p>
                    <p>We offer figures which refer to the number of sources belonging to four
                        specified disciplines in Informatics-related majors - pointed out by
                        abbreviations (e.g. 'C.S.' stands for Computer Science and so forth).</p>
                    <p>In addition, in our corpus, capital letters refer to the codes used for the
                        subjects/topics within disciplines as shown in the Appendices (Appendix 1).
                        As will be observed, in addition to all the labels A - F, each single
                        subject field is also represented individually by some texts (not shared
                        with other studies).</p>
                    <p>There are more texts in the 'F' category, which the four scientific areas
                        share - Computer Science, Information Science, Audio-visual Communication
                        and Optical/Wave communication. In contrast, the subject 'Communication
                        Theory', included in the Audio-visual Communication, Information Science and
                        Telecommunication programs of studies, is formed by only four sources. In
                        turn, Audio-visual Communication is the discipline with the smallest amount
                        of readings involved - only one text for each genre. <note n="3">3. The
                            correspondence of number of texts and disciplines obeys the aim of
                            assembling core language and subject matter: the lower the measure of
                            samples, the more subject-specific the texts tend to be.</note></p>
                    <p>The selection of the texts is made by having as yardsticks the overall
                        distribution and length of these in the corpus. As a result, if there are up
                        to five descriptions (out of 10 possible ones) included in the 'F' or 'All
                        disciplines' category, this is due to the fact that these passages are quite
                        common in these readings. In addition, these five samples are not as long as
                        other types, such as definitions in this division. Finally, that the balance
                        in relation to the entire corpus be kept is, as has been pointed out, a
                        chief consideration.</p>
                    <p>So that the text type findings based on frequency and range are also framed
                        with the detailed knowledge of the subjects and topics comprised, the
                        distribution of text type sources within each sub-category or label must be
                        provided.</p>
                    <p>The maximum number of texts encompassed is three - e.g. in the case of
                        Descriptions on the topic of 'Information infrastructure' (F6 category).
                        This distinction reflects both the larger amount of readings existent in the
                        corpus dealing with issues of this kind and the recurrence of this type of
                        rhetorical function employed in sub-division F6. In contrast, where no
                        samples are contained within a given sub-category, the reason is that the
                        model was either less developed or not included at all in the content of the
                        text (e.g. Conclusions in 'Perspectives on information' [F1], 'Media theory'
                        [D2], 'Media documentation' [C2], 'Automated Knowledge-based systems' [B3],
                        etc).</p>
                    <p>A final comment must be made regarding the importance of keeping a balance
                        with the representation of three academic genres - textbooks, reports and
                        research articles - in the construction of the corpus. The intent of this
                        arrangement is to offer a weighed basis for text selection and analysis.
                        Since the end of such an organizing procedure is to provide adequate ground
                        for lexical sifting, this text type sub-corpus should incorporate as many
                        different language and content settings - i.e. contextual factors - as
                        possible. In this sense, even some text units as characteristic of one
                        single genre as sections of research articles - Discussions and Conclusions,
                        in this case - can be located in the other two genres (e.g. a discussion
                        appearing in a textbook on Communication Theory [E1] or a conclusion taken
                        from a report on Software Programming [A1], as figure 4 shows).</p>
                    <p>The end results should thus be adequate and fitting for the design of both
                        written and oral lexical activities and tasks that reveal the importance of
                        academic and subject lexis, based on the analysis of common texts across
                        different disciplines.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
