<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">New Paths in Middle High German Lexicography:
                    Dictionaries Interlinked Electronically</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Johannes</forename>
                        <surname>Fournier</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Trier</name>, Germany <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Computational / Corpus Linguistics</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>I. Topic:</head>
                    <p>Since September 1997, a small team of lexicographers and computer scientists
                        at the University of Trier (Germany) have been developing an integrated
                        electronic dictionary of Middle High German applying TEI Guidelines. The
                        resulting integrated digital dictionary is expected to be finished by August
                        2000 and be published on CD-ROM as well as on the Internet. It is not only
                        meant to facilitate the simultaneous use of the dictionaries concerned, but
                        also to offer advanced query options to provide essentially new insights for
                        those involved in vocabulary studies, metalexicography, and the composition
                        of a new MHG dictionary.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>II. Digitization as a necessity:</head>
                    <p>The most important dictionaries of the MHG language were written in the last
                        century and need to be replaced urgently by a new major work. This necessity
                        arises not only from the enormous increase in the number of editions of MHG
                        texts since the end of the 19th century, but also from changed insights into
                        the structure of vocabulary and new ways of describing word usage.
                        Consequently five years ago, two teams of lexicographers at the Universities
                        of Trier and Goettingen started to lay the foundations for a new MHG
                        Dictionary by creating an electronic archive of texts and quotations. It
                        will probably take up to 25 years, however, for the whole dictionary to be
                        finished, thus scholars of all disciplines having to deal with MHG sources
                        will still have to use the older dictionaries for quite a while.</p>
                    <p>The dictionaries that already exist, i. e. the "Mittelhochdeutsches
                        Woerterbuch" by Georg Friedrich Benecke/Wilhelm Mueller/Friedrich Zarncke
                        (1854-1866), the "Mittelhochdeutsches Handwoerterbuch" with its supplement,
                        the "Nachtraege", by Matthias Lexer (1872-1878), and the "Findebuch zum
                        mittelhochdeutschen Wortschatz" by Kurt Gaertner et al. (1992), are very
                        closely interconnected and can only be used simultaneously, which is due to
                        the fact that they must be considered, briefly speaking, as a kind of series
                        of supplements to supplements to supplements. Therefore they were ideal
                        candidates for the composition of an integrated digital dictionary. One of
                        the major aims of the digitization is to make the lexicographical
                        information of the dictionary entries accessible via a database and thus to
                        enable sophisticated searches over all four dictionaries independently of
                        headwords. Applying TEI Guidelines to machine readable versions of the
                        printed dictionaries seemed the easiest and fastest way of creating the
                        digital "compound dictionary".</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>III. (Semi-)Automatically generated markup according to TEI
                        Guidelines:</head>
                    <p>The MHG dictionaries consist of eight volumes with about 1,100 printed pages,
                        containing more than 80,000 headwords. Therefore it is obvious that TEI
                        compliant markup of the dictionary entries had to be generated automatically
                        as far as possible. For the purposes of encoding we used TUSTEP, the
                        Tuebingen System of Text Processing Programs with its variety of
                        parameter-controlled functions for user-defined textdata-processing that
                        facilitate structured entry-input.</p>
                    <p>Some parts of the TEI design scheme were especially relevant for the
                        dictionary encoding. Some advantages and problems when applying TEI have to
                        be discussed in detail, such as the hierarchical embedding of elements
                        within the articles, the use of global attributes for the markup of a wide
                        range of lexicographical information, and the recoverability of articles. It
                        should also be mentioned that TEI Guidelines should be improved with regard
                        to the encoding of dictionaries of older stages of a language, for the
                        description of such languages poses some problems seldom encountered when
                        describing modern languages.</p>
                    <p>It is apparent, however, that most problems which arose when using TEI did
                        not stem from the application of TEI Guidelines as such, but were primarily
                        due to the fact that the dictionary entries often appeared to lack clear
                        structure and were rather discursive in style. This has often made automatic
                        SGML encoding a difficult task. In many cases only manual markup led to TEI
                        compliant documents. Nevertheless, the results achieved so far fully justify
                        the decision in favour of TEI Guidelines.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>IV. New ways of using dictionaries:</head>
                    <p>Through the electronic version, the MHG dictionaries can be used much more
                        easily and comfortably: hyperlinks connect all the corresponding headwords,
                        the search for cross-references only takes a mouse-click's time; pop-up
                        menus contain the relevant information about all sources of citation;
                        bookmarks and notes can be created easily. PostScript files of all
                        dictionary pages are interlinked with the electronic articles so that the
                        compound digital dictionary can be used and cited as a work of reference in
                        exactly the same way as its printed precursors.</p>
                    <p>Far more important is the access to a database containing the relevant
                        information for the entire contents of the four dictionaries within the
                        composite whole. Access via that database not only offers full-text
                        retrieval but also retrieval of selected information, e.g. of parts of
                        speech, of word forms in MHG quotations, of definitions or of strings in the
                        etymology sections of dictionary entries. Highly important for advanced and
                        complex query options is the linking of a list of all dictionary sources
                        with the electronic dictionary itself: all sources have been sophisticatedly
                        classified according to geographical provenance, chronology and genre,
                        categories that can be used to limit data base queries to a small,
                        self-defined corpus of texts cited within the entries. Which words were
                        directly borrowed from Italian, but not through Latin or French? Which words
                        are only quoted from sources concerning legal issues? Which MHG words denote
                        the same concepts? These are some of the questions that can now be answered
                        without great expense of time. What is still more, the integrated electronic
                        dictionary is especially important for the lexicographers involved in the
                        creation of the new MHG dictionary where the older dictionaries are used as
                        pointers to words for which references rarely exist.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>V. Institutional frame:</head>
                    <p>Some years ago, the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG = German Research
                        Council) initiated a program for the so-called "Retrospective Digitization
                        of Library Materials". The main goal of the program is to facilitate the
                        access to library holdings that may be rare or highly important for
                        scholarly interests by providing electronic versions of these holdings. From
                        the beginning, the program encouraged the use of SGML for full-text
                        encoding.</p>
                    <p>Since September 1997, the DFG has been funding the creation of an integrated
                        digital dictionary of Middle High German to be published on CD-ROM as well
                        as on the Internet. It is intended to serve as a prototype for the
                        digitization of other historical dictionaries, including the digitization of
                        the famous "Deutsches Woerterbuch" of Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References:</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Thomas</forename>
                                    <surname>Burch</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Johannes</forename>
                                    <surname>Fournier</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Kurt</forename>
                                    <surname>Gaertner</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Mittelhochdeutsche Woerterbuecher auf CD-ROM und im
                                Internet. Der Einsatz von SGML in der Retrodigitalisierung
                                lexikographischer Standardwerke</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Akademie-Journal. Mitteilungsblatt der Konferenz der
                                deutschen Akademien der Wissenschaften</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol"/>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">17-24</biblScope>
                                <date when="1998">1998/2</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Johannes</forename>
                                    <surname>Fournier</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Digitale Dialektik. Chancen und Probleme
                                mittelhochdeutscher Woerterbuecher in elektronischer Form</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <name>
                                        <forename type="first">Herbert</forename>
                                        <forename type="middle">Ernst</forename>
                                        <surname>Wiegand</surname>
                                    </name>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Woerterbuecher in der Diskussion IV. Vortraege aus dem
                                Heidelberger Lexikographischen Kolloquium</title>
                            <title level="s">(Lexikographica; Series Maior 100)</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Tuebingen</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Hrsg. von Herbert Ernst Wiegand</publisher>
                                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">85-108</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Thomas</forename>
                                    <surname>Burch</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Johannes</forename>
                                    <surname>Fournier</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Zur Anwendung der TEI-Richtlinien auf die
                                Retrodigitalisierung mittelhochdeutscher Woerterbuecher</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Ingrid</forename>
                                    <surname>Lemberg</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Bernhard</forename>
                                    <surname>Schroeder</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Angelika</forename>
                                    <surname>Storrer</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Probleme und Perspektiven computergestuetzter
                                Lexikographie</title>
                            <title level="s">(Lexikographica; Series Maior)</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Tuebingen</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="2000"> (forthcoming)</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
            <div>
                <note>Further information on the topic proposed is available at this location
                        &lt;<ptr target="http://gaer27.uni-trier.de/MWV-online/MWV-online.html"
                    />&gt; </note>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
