<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Technophobes, or the Nintendo Generation? A Study of
                    the Use of ICT in Teaching and Learning in Modern Languages</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Claire</forename>
                        <surname>Warwick</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Sheffield</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>The Electronic Classroom</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>This paper discuses the results of the application of a methodology typical
                        to information science to humanities computing. User studies are widely
                        performed in the library and information science community. However,
                        although some research has been carried out into the information needs of
                        researchers in the humanities, very little research has been done into the
                        actual use of electronic resources. (Warwick, 2000). Modern languages is an
                        area in which the usage of electronic resources in teaching is known to be
                        widespread. Yet the recent HEFCE report (1998) found that over one third of
                        universities felt that computer-assisted learning (CAL) and information and
                        communication technology (ICT) resources were being under-utilised. It
                        concluded that there is a need for more research into their use in HE and
                        recommends a "focus on the information and knowledge needs of the real
                        end-users". This paper seeks to address this need, and considers the way
                        that both teachers and students of Modern Languages use electric resources,
                        and what their perceptions about them are. It is based on work conducted in
                        the department by myself and a Masters student as part of her dissertation.
                        (Pine-Coffin, 1999). We argue that such research is an important
                        contribution to the area of humanities computing, since without an accurate
                        idea of the way in which resources are used and perceived it is impossible
                        to tell whether computer methodologies are useful and successful in aiding
                        teaching and learning. Without this type of user study it is difficult to
                        plan for possible future developments.</p>
                    <p><emph rend="bold">Methodology Research</emph> was of a mainly qualitative
                        nature, and was undertaken by means of structured interviews and
                        questionnaires. Questionnaires were given to students and both students and
                        academics were interviewed. Three university Modern language departments
                        were chosen as a sample, all of which were identified as having links with
                        humanities computing projects, Sheffield (Humanities Research Institute),
                        Hull (CTI Modern Languages) and Exeter (Project Pallas).</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Results and discussion</head>
                    <p><emph rend="bold">Use of ICT:</emph> We found a surprisingly small amount of
                        computer use by students. They used computers mainly for Word Processing,
                        reading foreign newspapers and accessing the internet. Despite the advice
                        available from the excellent CTI centre at Hull, the use of CAL packages at
                        all universities surveyed lagged behind all these generic applications in
                        terms of frequency of use. Despite promotion by libraries, there is also a
                        worryingly low level of use of library web pages and of subject gateways, of
                        BIDS and other bibliographic packages.</p>
                    <p><emph rend="bold">Attitudes to ICT usage:</emph> Preferences in terms of
                        computer use (ie what applications the students liked using) do not always
                        mirror frequency. For example, students found they often needed to use Word
                        Processors, but did not especially enjoy doing so. We also found that
                        despite what academics tend to assume, their students do not necessarily
                        enjoy using electronic resources. The 'Nintendo generation' is, it appears,
                        still technophobic and surprisingly conservative in its preference for paper
                        resources. We also found that students make 'tactical' use of resources.
                        Despite the perception amongst lecturers that students will enjoy playing
                        with computers, once introduced to them, we found that they tended to use
                        them only to the extent that they had been convinced of the necessity of
                        doing so. If they became convinced that they could pass an assignment by
                        limited use of an electronic resource, they were often unwilling to explore
                        further or practise the use of it, even when some packages had been
                        specifically designed for certain courses.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Departmental and academic attitudes</head>
                    <p>A constant theme of the research was that student reluctance to use
                        electronic resources can be combated, at least to some extent, by the
                        recommendations of their lecturers. This is not always easy to achieve,
                        however, as the attitude of academics themselves is vital. We found some
                        interesting and imaginative use of ICT, whether in the form of internet
                        usage or of CAL tutorials. It is perhaps not surprising that CAL is what
                        academics used most enthusiastically, since it could be used in a unique
                        fashion which printed resources could not replicate. However, we also found
                        a lack of awareness of ICT amongst academics, many of whom were also wary of
                        computer use. Many felt there was little incentive to use ICT when
                        traditional resources were adequate for the job in hand. With multiple
                        demands on their time, computer sceptics were also unwilling to give up time
                        to learn new ICT skills. Even those who were enthusiastic about the use of
                        computers were wary of publishing their research in e-journals. They
                        expressed anxiety about whether conservatism on RAE panels would lead to
                        electronically published articles being dismissed as insufficiently
                        prestigious. Some expressed a view that older, more established scholars who
                        tended not to use computers were likely to be on RAE and promotion panels,
                        and so computer enthusiasts might find their work was undervalued. This all
                        led to a sense of conservatism in research, even if in teaching they tended
                        to use ICT more widely.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Support</head>
                    <p>Even if students felt that the department was encouraging them to use ICT,
                        the most important factor in its successful use was support. However,
                        awareness of what support was on offer was still low, as was takeup of it.
                        Students often hesitated to ask for help, even when aware of it, and chose
                        always to ask friends for help in the first instance. They tended to prefer
                        human advice to online help and would rather receive help from their
                        academic tutors than computer support professionals. They tended to assume
                        that lecturers were more important than 'some bloke from the computing
                        services' who came in to show them how to use a package. Thus, if a lecturer
                        could demonstrate use of ICT him/herself, students tended to presume that
                        this was indeed important. The opposite assumption was also made, although
                        lecturers were often unaware of the messages they were involuntarily
                        delivering. We also found a large discrepancy between the level of support
                        which students perceived they needed, and which academics thought was
                        acceptable. Academics tended to assume that most students would cope easily
                        with computer use, because they thought that all teenagers were computer
                        enthusiasts who has been trained to a high level of ICT skill at school.
                        Many students, however, felt that the amount and level of support was too
                        low, and that they needed far more help than they received. In general the
                        level of confidence which students expressed in the use of ICT was
                        surprisingly low. Some students also felt that they lacked skills in
                        important areas such as internet searching. The librarians we interviewed
                        were aware of this problem, but the university lecturers tended not to be.
                        Unfortunately, the librarians were pessimistic about their role in the
                        official teaching of such skills, since they felt that students and academic
                        staff alike tended to undervalue the skills they had to offer, and there
                        seemed to be few channels of communication from librarians to academics.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Conclusions</head>
                    <p>The paper will discuss various conclusions which may be drawn from this data.
                        The most important one, however, seems to be that despite enthusiasm about
                        the potential of ICT in modern languages on the behalf of some academics and
                        many humanities computing professionals, there are several problems in its
                        practical implementation. It is only when user surveys are performed that
                        such problems come to light, and we discover the reality of the situation,
                        as opposed to what we think ought to be happening. Another strength of the
                        technique is to discover attitudes that users have to the technology
                        available, and we will argue that this is vital, since attitudes must shape
                        the way in which computers are used. Our research has also uncovered a
                        significant discrepancy between assumed and actual levels of usage and
                        enthusiasm. It is clear that despite the expectations and assumptions made
                        by lecturers, students do not necessarily enjoy using ICT, nor do they
                        always find it easy to use. This has important implications for the use and
                        support of ICT in the field of modern languages, and we will end the paper
                        by discussing how our findings might be used to improve the experience of
                        students and academics alike.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name type="org">HEFCE</name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="u">An evaluation of the Computers in Teaching Initiative
                                and Teaching and Learning Technology Support Network</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>Available at &lt;<ptr
                                target="http://www.niss.ac.uk/education/hefce_pub.html"/>&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Pine-Coffin</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">An investigation into the use of electronic resources
                                in the field of Modern Languages</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <edition>Unpublished M.A. Dissertation</edition>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>University of Sheffield</publisher>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Warwick</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">English literature, electronic text and computer
                                analysis: an impossible combination?</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol"/>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp"/>
                                <date when="2000">Forthcoming</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
