<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main"> Comparative Study of the Lexical and Orthographic
                    Variety in the Mediæval Slavonic Psalter</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Milena</forename>
                        <surname>Dobreva</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Institute of Mathematics and Informatics</name>,
                            Bulgaria <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Monia</forename>
                        <surname>Camuglia</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Pisa</name>, Italy <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>1. Introduction</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>1.1. Text variety in mediæval Slavonic texts</head>
                        <p>The mediæval Slavonic written tradition is characterised by a high level
                            of variety on all linguistic levels. This is usually explained with the
                            use of a vernacular language in the Mediaeval Slavonic texts. The spread
                            of the texts to regions with substantial differences from the language
                            in the region where the text originated reflected the transmission. In
                            this setting, the study of text variety is an important source of
                            information about the synchronic and diachronic development of the
                            Slavonic languages. However, up till now the study of text variety was
                            done by traditional research methods based extensively on human
                            collection and processing of scattered data. Taking into account the
                            substantial number of mediæval Slavonic manuscripts, one can imagine
                            that the bulk of the texts can not be physically covered by traditional
                            investigation.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>1.2. Case Study</head>
                        <p>The Psalter has always had a leading role among the religious texts since
                            its first appearance in the Slavonic countries, representing a very
                            important source in the process of the development of the Slavonic
                            written tradition.</p>
                        <p>Its importance is also linked to the didactic function it had in the
                            Slavonic lands where a new alphabet was recently introduced. This led to
                            the need to educate the scholars in the new literary environment. Due to
                            its own rhythm, to its diffusion, the Psalter was then studied by heart
                            by people in order to make acquaintance with the written culture.</p>
                        <p>That is why the Psalter has always been one of the most widespread texts
                            [Karaèorova 89]. Its tradition is considered constant by almost all the
                            researches, besides the structural differences that allow us to speak
                            about different typologies of Psalter (simple, with commentaries, etc.). </p>
                        <p>In the light of these considerations (wide dissemination and lower
                            variety due to its religious use), we decided to investigate some
                            textual peculiarities of the Psalter's transmission.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>1.3. Experimental Setting</head>
                        <p>We focussed our attention on six manuscripts, choosing the spatial and
                            temporal settings of each manuscript as reference points. The linguistic
                            peculiarities referring to an origination from a certain region are
                            reported using the term 'revision'.</p>
                        <p>We used the following manuscripts:<list type="bulleted">
                                <item>Sinaitic Psalter (10th c., written in the Glagolitic alphabet;
                                    all other witnesses were written in Old Cyrillic)</item>
                                <item>Bolonian Psalter (13th c., Bulgarian revision)</item>
                                <item>Norovian Psalter (13th c., middle Bulgarian revision)</item>
                                <item>Serbian Psalter (13th c., Serbian revision)</item>
                                <item>Kievian Psalter (14th c., Russian revision)</item>
                                <item>Gennadian Psalter (15th c., Russian revision)</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>We used as text excerpts 15 Psalms scattered through the Psalter (1, 39,
                            40, 41, 44, 45, 64, 73, 74, 75, 89, 91, 98, 102, 134; the exception is
                            the Serbian Psalter where the 1st psalm was damaged).</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2. Study of the lexical variety</head>
                    <p>We started with a study of the lexical variety in order to follow the
                        tradition of the Psalter diatopically and diachronically, to set out the
                        lexical variants and to verify the unity of its tradition.</p>
                    <p>We used for this study the DBT (<emph rend="italics">Data Base
                            Testuale</emph>), a program of textual analysis developed at the
                        ICL-Pisa, which produces different types of information in real time. Among
                        its functions, the DBT provides lists of alphabetical frequencies,
                        decreasing frequency order, concordances, co-occurrences, <emph
                            rend="italics">indices locorum</emph>, lists of suffixes and endings and
                        lemmatization procedure.</p>
                    <p>Comparing our witnesses we found the following:<list type="bulleted">
                            <item>We obtained 115 pairs of variant words. Of these 115 pairs, only
                                38 times does the word vary in only one manuscript (77 times the
                                same word varies in more then one manuscript).</item>
                            <item>The variants seem to be linked to some specific words and <emph
                                    rend="italics">realia</emph>.</item>
                            <item>The typology of the variant pairs shows that the most frequently
                                appearing are those whose semantics reflect <emph rend="italics"
                                    >eyesight</emph>, <emph rend="italics">desire</emph>, <emph
                                    rend="italics">law violation</emph> (in particular of the divine
                                one), <emph rend="italics">forgiveness</emph>, <emph rend="italics"
                                    >fire</emph> (as a symbol of purification), <emph rend="italics"
                                    >rebirth</emph>, <emph rend="italics">oil</emph>, and <emph
                                    rend="italics">unction</emph>. We can think that the scribe
                                inserted these variants since he felt them to be more correct, both
                                dogmatically and linguistically and, in any case, more specific for
                                the different ages and chessboard of the written tradition.</item>
                            <item>We notice a tendency to use synonyms or words with a very small
                                semantic difference from those of the Sinaitic Psalter.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>We can consider the chosen texts divided in 4 blocks: 1) Sinaitic Psalter; 2)
                        Bolonian and Serbian Psalters (the closest in time to the Sinaitic); 3)
                        Norovian Psalter; 4) Kievian and Gennadian Psalters. In 115 variants as
                        regards the Sinaitic Psalter, we noticed that:<list type="bulleted">
                            <item>78 belong to the Norovian Psalter (67%)</item>
                            <item>36 to the Serbian Psalter (31%)</item>
                            <item>29 to the Bolonian Psalter (25%)</item>
                            <item>57 to the Kievian Psalter (49%)</item>
                            <item>75 to the Gennadian Psalter (65%)</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>The Norovian Psalter is the text that more than the others is detached from
                        the Sinaitic and, as Cesko says "it's one of the first trials to normalize
                        the literary language thanks to a correction based on the Greek model"
                        [Cesko o77].</p>
                    <p>On the other side, the Serbian and Norovian Psalters show a lower level of
                        variants and they were written in a period very close to the creation of the
                        Sinaitic Psalter.</p>
                    <p>Concerning the two Russian Psalters, the Norovian and Gennadian Psalters have
                        almost the same number of variants (78 and 75). Thus we can think that they
                        belong to the same revision. But this is not true: of the 78 variants
                        present in the Norovian, 54 are different from those of the Gennadian, that
                        only 28 times offers variants different from those of the Kievian. We can
                        verify in this way the big linguistic similarity between the two Russian
                        texts and the atypicality of the Norovian Psalter in respect to this group
                        of texts.</p>
                    <p>In conclusion, we have the Norovian Psalter vs. all the others, that can be
                        very well accepted if we consider the basic homogeneity of all the examined
                        manuscripts and the declared adhesion of the Norovian to the Greek original. </p>
                    <p>This confirms the unity of the Psalter's tradition in the Slavonic countries.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3. Study of the Orthographic variety</head>
                    <p>We studied also a lower textual level - the orthographical one - in order to
                        investigate the correlation between revisions and quantitative data on
                        orthographic features. The traditional approach to the orthographic variety
                        study is a qualitative one. The decision about the time when a text was
                        written and the localization of its creation is based on the occurrences of
                        specific orthographic features. Such features reflect the use of the <emph
                            rend="italics">jers</emph>; nasal vowels and groups containing - <emph
                            rend="italics">r</emph> - and - <emph rend="italics">l</emph> - [OBG,
                        1993].</p>
                    <p>We studied the relative frequencies of all letters from the Old Cyrillic
                        alphabet and all strings belonging to such characteristic groups. We aimed
                        to check whether the qualitative characteristics relevant to the text origin
                        lead also to differences in the quantitative study of the texts. The data
                        were processed in STATISTICA for Windows. This data organization allowed us
                        to choose a subset of texts, and some of the letters or groups for analysis.
                        From the view-point of the specialist in Slavonic studies, this would mean
                        that we are able to study the usage of all or selected graphemes in a chosen
                        group of texts. We applied cluster analysis in order to check whether texts
                        belonging to different revisions are grouped correctly.</p>
                    <p>The cross-study of the texts leads us to the following conclusions:<list
                            type="bulleted">
                            <item>For experiments with texts from one revision the smallest size of
                                the text excerpt should be 5,000 letters</item>
                            <item>For experiments with text from different revisions the size of the
                                text excerpt leading to correct clustering is 2,000 letters</item>
                            <item>The best results are obtained when we use in the study the
                                relative frequencies of 5 experimentally approved vowels</item>
                            <item>The results showed that the regional differences within texts,
                                which form a common tradition in the mediaeval Slavonic literary
                                history, reflect the orthographic quantitative characteristics of
                                the texts</item>
                        </list></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>4. Conclusions</head>
                    <p>Our study showed the importance of conducting experiments on different
                        linguistic levels.</p>
                    <p>The first approach was oriented towards a study of lexical variance aimed at
                        investigating the distribution of synonyms in the different witnesses and at
                        forming groups of similarity between the witnesses. This study confirmed the
                        hypothesis about the unity of the Psalter's transmission amongst the
                        mediæval Slavs.</p>
                    <p>The second approach was oriented towards a study of quantitative data on the
                        distribution of orthographic characteristics.</p>
                    <p>The comparison of the results shows that the application of both approaches
                        could help the specialists in mediæval Slavonic textual studies to acquire
                        new data about the similarities and dissimilarities of their object of
                        study. Moreover, the complexity of the studied field presupposes the use of
                        methods applied to the different linguistic levels because they enlighten
                        different aspects of the studied written tradition.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct n="[Cesko o77]">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">V.</forename>
                                    <surname>Cesko</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Ob afonskoj redakcii slavjanskogo perevoda psaltyri v
                                ee otnoshenii k drugim redakcijam</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Jazyk i pismennost' srednebolgarskogo perioda</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Moskva</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1982">1982</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">77</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>(in Russian)</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="[Karaèorova 89]">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">I.</forename>
                                    <surname>Karaèorova</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Kym vyprosa za Kirilo-Metodievskija starobylgarski
                                prevod na Psaltira</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Kirilo-Metodievski Studii</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Sophia</pubPlace>
                                <biblScope type="vol">6</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">15-129</biblScope>
                                <date when="1989">1989</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>(in Bulgarian)</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book" n="[OBG 1993]">
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">I.</forename>
                                    <surname>Duridanov</surname> et al </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Gramatika na starobalgarskija ezik</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Sophia</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>(in Bulgarian)</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
