<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">A Wake Newslitter - Electronic Edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Ian</forename>
                        <surname>Gunn</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Napier University</name>,UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <p>The 'A Wake Newslitter - Electronic edition' reproduces in a hyperlinked and
                        searchable format the complete print run of the seminal journal on Joyce's
                            <title level="m">Finnegans Wake</title> which started out as a
                        mimeographed news-sheet passed between a few scholars in the early
                        nineteen-sixties. Large areas of the scholarship contained in these journals
                        has never been superseded and yet the journal itself is very hard to find as
                        it was not published or archived in traditional forums.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>The Genesis</head>
                        <p>The Wake Newslitter Project had its Genesis in a chance remark made on
                            the FWAKE-L electronic discussion list on the Internet in November 1996.
                            The FWAKE-L list and its companion list FW-READ have filled some of the
                            gaps left by the demise of 'A Wake Newslitter'. Although the expected
                            brevity of email messages precludes posting in-depth studies, these
                            lists have become effective forums for the discussion of both annotation
                            and explication of <title level="m">Finnegans Wake</title>.</p>
                        <p>It was in this context that a cry went up as to why 'A Wake Newslitter'
                            was not being reprinted and as to whether there were any enterprising
                            publishers prepared to take up the task.</p>
                        <p>Email inquiries were sent to Fritz Senn in Zurich and Clive Hart in Essex
                            to canvas their views and also to offer possible solutions. Fritz Senn
                            was amenable to the idea and Clive Hart actively supportive of any
                            project.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>The Problems</head>
                        <p>My own holdings of 'A Wake Newslitter' material were sparse and covered
                            mainly the later issues. Initial tests made it clear that the journals
                            would need to be retyped in order to digitise and edit the material.
                            Clive Hart informed me that all the Old Series were produced using
                            stencils and, even though I knew some of the issues were produced by
                            letterpress, I decided that the whole publication run would need to be
                            re-keyed into computers. A mammoth and error-prone task - I needed help. </p>
                        <p>So some issues were mimeographs; some issues were letterpress or litho
                            and some were typed and photocopied. But there was more - some issues
                            included illustrations, diagrams, tables and even a few halftone
                            photographs and illustrations - it would be necessary to scan, redraw
                            and source original material. <title level="m">Finnegans Wake</title>
                            scholarship and explication covers a very diverse range of cultures and
                            languages. The typing and printing limitations of the time of original
                            publication of the Newslitter meant that a large number of issues were
                            retouched by hand to provide the appropriate accents or signs. The
                            constantly changing methods of production had a strong impact on the
                            ability to maintain any consistent editorial and typographical style.
                            Typefaces, sizes, leading, paragraph styles and punctuation would vary
                            from issue to issue, printer to printer and even sometimes page to page.
                            Italic type was not always available and an overuse of bold face was
                            inevitable in the original publications including the use of some very
                            exotic faces in later volumes.</p>
                        <p>To compound all this 'A Wake Newslitter' had become a significant
                            reference source in <title level="m">Finnegans Wake</title> studies and
                            therefore its material had been heavily cited in critical literature.
                            Any new electronic edition would have to accommodate the pagination of
                            the originals due to critical - page-specific - citation. This was even
                            more daunting considering that the old series and the new series had
                            vastly different page sizes. The Old Series was mimeographed on crown
                            quarto paper (10x7.5in) with a text density of about 400 words per page.
                            New Series issues started on demy octavo (8.75x5.5in approx.) at a text
                            density of 450 words per page but by Volume X the page size was A5
                            (8.25x5.75in approx.) and the text density over 600 words per page. The
                            type size in parts of some issues was as small as 6 point.</p>
                        <p>It was decided to set all the issues in A5 format and a basic template
                            was created with running heads, rules and page numbers. This meant that
                            the Old Series material was condensed down to A5 - which due to the
                            monospaced original text was fairly easy - and a cover page conforming
                            to the New Series was added. A number of liberties had to be taken with
                            standard typographical practice in order to fit diverse material into
                            the new format. Some pages had to be hit quite hard with the 'digital'
                            equivalent of a mallet.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>The Collaboration</head>
                        <p>As some issues required retyping into computers and all material would
                            need proofreading, it was obvious I needed further help. I turned to the
                            same forum that had voiced the desire for 'A Wake Newslitter' to be made
                            available. An email was sent to the FWAKE-L requesting volunteers to
                            type, and eventually proofread A Wake Newslitter issues. The response
                            was immediate with about twenty volunteers coming forward in the first
                            few weeks. Reflecting the membership of FWAKE-L and demographic access
                            to the Internet the majority of the responses came from the United
                            States but there were also offers of help from Australia, England,
                            Finland, France, Italy and Thailand.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>The Technology</head>
                        <p>Electronic mail and the Internet were the main communications tools of
                            the project - enabling the speedy exchange of messages and the ability
                            to view the progress of the project itself on the World-Wide Web. There
                            was in excess of 700,000 words to be typed and then proofread by the
                            team and this ultimately would be achieved by using both old and new
                            technologies. Photocopies were posted to the members of the team and
                            electronic copy returned using FTP (File Transfer Protocol) to an
                            Internet drop zone.</p>
                        <p>As photocopies of the original issues were received from Clive Hart it
                            became evident that a larger proportion of the New Series issues than
                            had originally been expected were printed by letterpress or litho. This
                            raised the possibility of avoiding the retyping of all the issues. A few
                            trial issues were processed using scanners and OCR (Optical Character
                            Recognition) software and the results were encouraging. Although the
                            scanned material was by no means error-free the speed of input made the
                            scanning of the letterpress and litho printed material a viable
                            alternative to - the also error-prone - retyping option. Scanned
                            material processed using OCR software - while offering a faster input
                            mode - also requires more diligent proofreading due to the unique and
                            sometimes insidious errors created by such processes.</p>
                        <p>All material whether typed or scanned would require formatting and
                            typesetting using desktop publishing (DTP) software. Artwork and
                            diagrams were either redrawn on computer or scanned and tables were
                            rebuilt within the DTP software. Most accents and special characters
                            were available on the computer systems but the <title level="m"
                                >Finnegans Wake</title> sigla required the use and adaptation of a
                            Wake typeface which is under development as part of another project.</p>
                        <p>From the outset it was determined that the electronic reproduction would
                            be required to respect the pagination and layout integrity of the
                            original material. The mechanism chosen for this was Adobe Acrobat PDF
                            (Portable Document Format). Once the material has been desktop-published
                            this software enables the replication of the individual pages of a
                            publication within a single electronic document. The PDF format is
                            designed to be platform-independent and offers a range of features such
                            as indexing, keyword searching and hyperlinking. Another advantage of
                            this format is that all text is indexed and multiple documents can be
                            searched for keywords using Adobe Catalog software.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Editorial policy</head>
                    <p>The initial plan was to keep editing to a minimum with proofreading and
                        fidelity to the original being the main criteria. Italic type was
                        substituted where bold face had been overused and typographical features and
                        references, (AWN instead of the earlier WNL), were standardised. Variations
                        in punctuation and grammar were left untouched except in very obvious cases
                        of setting errors. Proofreading threw up some errors in the original
                        material, (Huge B. Staples instead of Hugh B. Staples), and these were
                        generally amended only when they were factual matters such as names, page
                        references and citations from <title level="m">Finnegans Wake</title>. These
                        citations were only corrected when it was obvious they were in error and
                        would have no possible impact on the article interpretation. An instance
                        reminiscent of the production of Ulysses occurred in New Series Volume III
                        No 3 pages 51-53 where the typesetter appears to have corrected Joyce's
                            <title level="m">Finnegans Wake</title> passages by altering
                        'figuratleavely' to 'figuratively' and 'yoursell' to 'yourself'. Where
                        corrections appeared in later issues these were only implemented in the
                        original if the corrections were supplied by the original author. Danis Rose
                        supplied an explanation of a correction to New Series Volume X No 3 page 45
                        which also updated the correction in Volume XI No 2 page 34. Roland McHugh
                        confirmed what initially looked like a typo in a transcription of a FW
                        notebook, ('girsl' in Volume XVI No 6 p83), and then on reflection and
                        consultation amended the original entry.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Conclusion</head>
                    <p>The 1968 Sydney University Press publication <title level="m">A Wake
                            Digest</title> has been added to the archive. This contained selected
                        and updated material from the Old Series of A Wake Newslitter along with
                        some new articles. The conversion of A Wake Newslitter to digital format
                        both preserves and opens up this valuable archive of material to a new and
                        wider audience of Joyce scholars. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
