<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Books into Bytes: The "Deutsches Wörterbuch" on CD-ROM
                    and on the Internet</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Ruth</forename>
                        <surname>Christman</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Trier</name>, Germany <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>I. Starting position, targets:</head>
                <p>Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm's "Deutsches Woerterbuch" (DWB) comprises the most
                    extensive documentation of the German language. Its outstanding position is
                    confirmed by its history: for more than one hundred years - the longest period
                    of publication for a German dictionary - generations of lexicographers have
                    contributed about 350,000 entries to the DWB, which is divided into 16 volumes
                    (bound as 32), containing a total of 67,744 columns.</p>
                <p>The DWB reflects more than one hundred years of political, cultural, and
                    institutional history. Moreover, it shows the influence of varying preferences
                    of numerous philologists concerning practical lexicography as well as changed
                    insights into philology and linguistics.</p>
                <p>Digitizing the DWB not only means preserving the outstanding achievements of
                    German lexicography but also opens up new possibilites in using the rich
                    dictionary material. Since November 1998, a project at the University of Trier
                    has been creating a computerized version of the DWB to be published on CD-ROM
                    and also made available via the Internet. It is intended to provide
                    user-friendly search and display software in order to get optimum opportunities
                    for data retrieval. It will as a result appeal to anyone interested in the
                    German language. In this way, the poor situation in the field of electronic
                    dictionaries of German when compared internationally will be decisively
                    improved.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>II. Technical issues:</head>
                <p>Taking into account the developments of international standards for text
                    encoding, TEI Guidelines are used for a structured markup of the dictionary.
                    This prepares the way for the production of the CD-ROM version by applying
                    special SGML tools: starting-point for the application of CoST (Copenhagen SGML
                    Tool) is our pool of SGML encoded files which have been created from the TUSTEP
                    (TUebingen System of Text Processing Programs) data and validated by an SGML
                    parser. CoST is a general-purpose SGML post-processing tool. It is a
                    structure-controlled SGML application, that is, it operates on the
                    element-structure information-set (ESIS) representation of SGML documents. CoST
                    provides a flexible set of low-level primitives upon which sophisticated
                    applications can be built. These include a powerful query language for
                    navigating the document tree and extracting ESIS information, an event-driven
                    programming interface, and a specification mechanism which binds properties to
                    nodes based on queries. On the one hand CoST generates a set of HTML pages for
                    displaying the dictionaries by traditional web browsers, on the other hand it
                    transforms the SGML data into command scripts for Tcl/Tk for the graphical user
                    interface of the CD-ROM. Tcl, the Tool Command Language, is a very simple
                    programming language. Tcl provides basic language features such as variables,
                    procedures, and control, and runs on almost any modern OS, such as Unix,
                    Macintosh, and Windows 95/98/NT computers. Tk is a Tcl extension, written in C,
                    designed to give the user a relatively high level interface to their windowing
                    environment. Finally CoST is used to set up a database that contains all the
                    information of the dictionary entries necessary to perform queries about the
                    different components that might be interesting to those concerned with studying
                    the German language from its very beginnings, such as etymology, language,
                    quotations, including of course traditional full-text retrievals. The database
                    is accessible from both platforms: the web browsers connect to it via CGI
                    scripting, and the CD-ROM GUI uses an integrated Tcl interface.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>III. Software demonstration:</head>
                <p>The software demonstration will present the way in which valuable information can
                    be extracted from an electronic version of the DWB by using full-text retrieval,
                    links, and a database that facilitates complex queries.</p>
                <p>The possibility of using different retrieval options enables the user of a CD-ROM
                    or Internet version of the DWB to search for certain phenomena in up to 33
                    substantial volumes, independently of headwords. The information hidden within
                    the different entries is made even more explicit in various ways: via
                    hyperlinks, the index volume will be connected with the references appearing in
                    the dictionary. The information needed in order to quote from the sources of the
                    DWB can thus be accessed very easily via pop-up windows. As a common feature of
                    electronic dictionaries, it will be possible by a preparation of a list of
                    headwords to look up every one of the headwords just by activating the
                    corresponding links and, moreover, to gain access to certain parts of the longer
                    articles separately by using the original organization of the entries. Specific
                    information as to the grammatical gender of headwords or sublemmata or the
                    occurrence of certain words in quotations from certain authors or literature
                    will be obtainable by a database generated from TEI compliant markup as
                    mentioned before.</p>
                <p>One of the major aims of the project is, however, not only to show the user
                    different means of making use of the DWB for lexicographical, historical, or
                    linguistic studies and to present the DWB in an appealing way, but to increase
                    the use of the DWB in general, i.e. as a book in several volumes to be read by
                    those interested in the German language and the history of German words. For
                    such purposes, it is absolutely necessary to allow the user an easy access both
                    to the electronic version of the DWB and to the information stored within the
                    entries, and to the printed version of the DWB as presented on screen via
                    PostScript files. Encoding the entries according to TEI Guidelines is as
                    important as presenting the characters of the different languages exactly as
                    they appear in print.</p>
                <p>The procedure of digitizing the DWB is very closely connected to that of one of
                    the other retrodigitization projects at the University of Trier, Digital Middle
                    High German Dictionaries Interlinked. As the Middle High German Dictionaries are
                    quoted very often within the DWB, it is also intended to include links to the
                    electronic version of these dictionaries. Their CD-ROM is meant as a prototype
                    for the retrodigitization of other historical dictionaries, thus the
                    presentation of the Dictionaries Interlinked may conclude the software
                    demonstration to show how the DWB will look in a final state.</p>
                <p>At the time of the conference, at least two major volumes of the DWB including
                    the index volume will be fully encoded, converted into a CD-ROM, and accessible
                    for searches. Questions to be discussed when presenting the DWB in its
                    prospective digital version might focus on the application of SGML/TEI to a
                    dictionary as heterogeneously structured as the DWB, on the necessity for
                    developing new entities for character representation, and the importance of a
                    digital DWB for future research.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Literature:</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Ruth</forename>
                                    <surname>Christmann</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Vera</forename>
                                    <surname>Hildenbrandt</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Thomas</forename>
                                    <surname>Schares</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Digitalisierung des Deutschen Woerterbuchs von Jacob
                                und Wilhelm Grimm</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Nicolas</forename>
                                    <surname>Castrillo Benito</surname>
                                </name> et al </editor>
                            <title level="m">TUSTEP educa. 6. ITUG-Jahrestagung. Burgos</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="2000">forthcoming, 2000</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
