<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">An Electronic Lexicon of Nominalizations:
                    NOMLEX</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Catherine</forename>
                        <surname>Macleod</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">New York University</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Ralph</forename>
                        <surname>Grishman</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">New York University</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Adam</forename>
                        <surname>Meyers</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">New York University</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Computational/Corpus Linguistics</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <p>New York University (NYU) has recently completed Nomlex, a dictionary
                        containing detailed syntactic information about 1000 common English
                        nominalizations. This dictionary, which has been developed for use in
                        natural language processing, is freely available from NYU.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>History:</head>
                    <p>Previous dictionary work at NYU includes COMLEX Syntax [Macleod'97], a large
                        syntactic dictionary with detailed information on the syntactic properties
                        of English words, especially with regard to complement structure. This
                        dictionary is available through the Linguistic Data Consortium (LDC) and is
                        being presently used by several natural language processing (NLP) groups. </p>
                    <p>Nominalizations present a special problem, in that one wants not only to
                        analyze their syntactic structure, but also to relate them to corresponding
                        verbal structures. This is essential for natural language interpretation in
                        applications such as question answering and information extraction. For
                        example, the answer to a question, "How badly was the city bombed?" could be
                        phrased "The city was destroyed completely" or "The destruction of the city
                        was complete." These answers though syntacticly diverse contain exactly the
                        same information.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Dictionary structure:</head>
                    <p>The challenge in designing the NOMLEX entries is to provide, in reasonably
                        compact form, all the lexically-specific syntactic information required to
                        relate nominal arguments to the corresponding verbal arguments. This task is
                        complicated because of the wide range of nominal argument structures, which
                        makes a direct enumeration of all possible correspondences hopelessly
                        unwieldy. In particular, the core arguments and oblique arguments behave
                        differently in this respect.</p>
                    <p>The core arguments of the verb (subject, object, indirect object) may appear
                        as possessive determiners (DET-POSS), noun noun modifiers (N-N-MOD) or in a
                        prepositional phrase commonly preceded by "of" (PP-OF). Examples of this
                        are: "His death" (where "his" represents the one who dies and therefore the
                        subject of the verb "die"), "the price adjustment" (where "price" is the
                        object of the verb "adjust"), and "the discussion of the case" (where "case"
                        is the object of the verb "discuss" and the analysis would be "X discuss the
                        case").</p>
                    <p>More complex verbal complementation such as sentential and verbal complements
                        are found following the nominalization and often retain the same structure.
                        For instance, the complement "that he came" is the same for the
                        nominalization as for the verb, seen in the following examples.</p>
                    <eg>"Someone report(ed) that he came."</eg>
                    <eg>"The report that he came."</eg>
                    <p>Some verbal complements must have an introductory preposition in order to
                        appear as nominalization complements. For example, "Someone questioned
                        whether it was a wise plan." versus "The question of whether it was a wise
                        plan". We encode all these possibilities in the lexical entries of the
                        nominalizations. The NOMLEX entry for "appointment" is as follows.</p>
                    <eg>(NOM :ORTH "appointment" 
                        :VERB "appoint" 
                        :PLURAL "appointments" 
                        :NOUN ((EXISTS)) 
                        :NOM-TYPE ((VERB-NOM)) 
                        :VERB-SUBJ ((N-N-MOD) (DET-POSS))
                        :SUBJ-ATTRIBUTE ((COMMUNICATOR)) 
                        :OBJ-ATTRIBUTE ((NHUMAN)) 
                        :VERB-SUBC ((NOM-NP:OBJECT ((DET-POSS) (N-N-MOD) (PP-OF))) 
                        (NOM-NP-PP:OBJECT ((DET-POSS) (N-N-MOD) (PP-OF)) 
                        :PVAL ("for" "to")) 
                        (NOM-NP-TO-INF-OC:OBJECT ((DET-POSS) (PP-OF))) 
                        (NOM-NP-AS-NP:OBJECT ((DET-POSS) (PP-OF)))))</eg>
                    <p>This sample entry, in combination with a set of defaults, provides us with a
                        lot of information, including the following:<list type="bulleted">
                            <item>A homograph noun of the nominalization "appointment" exists<list
                                    type="bulleted">
                                    <item>("a dental appointment" is not the act of
                                        "appointment")</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item>The subject of the verb tends to be a human, company or other
                                entity capable of communication.</item>
                            <item>The object of the verb is a human.</item>
                            <item>The nominalization is of type VERB-NOM, meaning that the
                                nominalization does not play the grammatical role of any of the
                                arguments of the verb. In contrast, "fighter" is a SUBJECT
                                nominalization and "interviewee" is an OBJECT nominalization.</item>
                            <item>The subject of the verb can occur in three positions:<list
                                    type="bulleted">
                                    <item>N-N-MOD - "The IBM appointment of Mary Smith"</item>
                                    <item>DET-POSS - "IBM's appointment of Mary Smith"</item>
                                    <item>PP-by - "The appointment of Mary Smith by the
                                        president"</item>
                                    <item>(PP-by is assumed as a subject marker by default.)</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item>When the verb is followed by one noun phrase and no other
                                complement phrases, that object may occur in the nominalized phrase
                                (NOM-NP) in one of three positions:<list type="bulleted">
                                    <item>DET-POSS - "Mary Smith's appointment"</item>
                                    <item>N-N-MOD - "The Mary Smith appointment" &lt;</item>
                                    <item>PP-OF - "The appointment of Mary Smith by the
                                        president"</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item>Object plus prepositional phrase complements ("for" and "to")
                                share the same object mappings as simple NP complements.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>In addition, the prepositions in the verb complement are realized as the same
                        preposition in the nominalization complement.<list type="bulleted">
                            <item>Complements consisting of an NP object plus either an infinitival
                                complement or an AS-NP complement allow only DET-POSS and PP-OF
                                complements. In addition, the verbal complement phrases TO-INF-OC
                                and AS-NP map to these same types of phrases in the nominalization
                                (by default).</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Due to space considerations, we must leave out a lot of detail regarding the
                        interpretation of this dictionary entry. In particular, we have a system of
                        rules and defaults which prevent spurious ambiguity and allow us to keep the
                        lexical entries compact. The example cited above is that PP-by is so often a
                        marker of the subject of the verb, that we treat this as a default, marking
                        nominalizations that do not allow this mapping with NOT-PP-by. For more
                        detail about NOMLEX, please see our web site: &lt;<ptr
                            target="http://cs.nyu.edu/cs/projects/proteus/nomlex/index.html"
                        />&gt;</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Using NOMLEX:</head>
                    <p>To demonstrate the utility of NOMLEX we constructed two NLP applications that
                        depend on NOMLEX entries to analyze nominalization phrases.<list>
                            <item>1. A program that transforms a nominalization phrase into one or
                                more sentences, corresponding to the possible senses of the
                                nominalization phrase. For example, "Rome's destruction of Carthage"
                                has exactly one sense, which our program would paraphrase as "Rome
                                destroyed Carthage". The program takes a grammatical analysis (a
                                parse) of a nominalization phrase as input and uses NOMLEX to create
                                grammatical analyses of the corresponding sentences, copying noun
                                phrases and complement phrases from the various nominal positions
                                (N-N-MOD, DET-POSS, post-noun, etc.) into the appropriate sentential
                                positions (SUBJECT, OBJECT, etc.). Actual sentences are then
                                generated from these parses. The output of this program could be
                                used as input to any NLP application designed to operate on full
                                sentences.</item>
                            <item>2. A program which converts an information extraction pattern
                                designed for sentences into a set of information extraction patterns
                                designed for nominalization phrases ([Meyers'98]). For our purposes,
                                an information extraction pattern is a pattern used to identify
                                events in text and correctly mark the participants of these events.
                                One such system extracts information about corporate hirings,
                                firings, resignations, etc., including the identification of who
                                left which company, who joined which company, the positions they
                                left, the positions they attained, dates, etc. Our program converts
                                a pattern that analyzes "IBM appointed Alice Smith as Vice
                                President" into a pattern that analyzes: "IBM's appointment of Alice
                                Smith as President", "Alice Smith's appointment by IBM", "IBM's
                                Alice Smith appointment", "IBM's appointee", "The appointee of IBM",
                                etc. Nomlex helps determine where information identified by a
                                sentence pattern would be found in a nominalization phrase. This
                                would enable an information extraction tool to easily extract
                                information from nominalizations.</item>
                        </list></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Process:</head>
                    <p>The menu-based entry program used for COMLEX was adapted to enter NOMLEX. As
                        for COMLEX, the entry program gave us access to a large corpus of text
                        (including the Brown Corpus and large amounts of newspaper articles) and we
                        had limited access to the British National Corpus (BNC) as well. Two
                        half-time ELFs (Enterer of Lexical Features) worked for 5 months and then
                        one half-time ELF completed the lexicon in two years.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Concluding Remarks:</head>
                    <p>We have created a dictionary with the goal of solving a pervasive problem in
                        NLP. Most grammatical analyses are designed to process sentences, but in
                        order not to miss information these need to be applied to nominalization
                        phrases, as well. NOMLEX provides a bridge in the form of: (1) a set of
                        rules and defaults; and (2) a dictionary record of idiosyncratic mappings
                        between nominalizations and their related verbs. Before the creation of
                        NOMLEX, developers and researchers have had to adapt processes which handle
                        sentences to enable them to handle nominalizations also. Due to the high
                        overhead of this endeavor, many systems do not handle nominalizations at all
                        or use simple, but imprecise heuristics. NOMLEX makes it less expensive to
                        fully integrate nominalizations into an NLP system.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Future work:</head>
                    <p>In order to make NOMLEX an even more useful resource, we plan to add support
                        verbs to the entries. The use of support verbs changes the relationship of
                        the nominal and verbal arguments. For example, in "his visit to Mary" the
                        possessive determiner is the subject of "visit" (i.e. "he visit Mary"); in
                        "he made a visit to Mary" the subject of the support verb "make" is now the
                        subject of "visit" (i.e. "he visited Mary."). The demonstration that this is
                        idiosyncratic and a matter for lexical interpretation is the appearance of
                        "he had a visit from Mary" where the object of the preposition "from" is the
                        subject of "visit" and the subject of the support verb becomes the object of
                        "visit" (i.e. "Mary visited him"). We have been exploring Mel'cuk's notation
                        as a means of capturing these relationships for NOMLEX.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Macleod</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Grishman</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Meyers</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">COMLEX Syntax: A Large Syntactic Dictionary for Natural
                                Language Processing</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Computers and the Humanities (CHUM)</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher>
                                <biblScope type="vol">31</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">6</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp"/>
                                <date when="1997">1997/1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Meyers</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Macleod</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Yangarber</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Grishman</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Barrett</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Reeves</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Using NOMLEX to Produce Nominalization Patterns for
                                Information Extraction</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Coling-ACL98 workshop Proceedings: the Computational
                                Treatment of Nominal</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
