<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-139">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Digital Humanities in the Classroom: Introducing a New Editing Platform for Source Documents in Classics</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Beaulieu, Marie-Claire</name>
                    <affiliation>Tufts University, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>Marie-Claire.Beaulieu@Tufts.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Almas, Bridget</name>
                    <affiliation>Tufts University, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>bridget.almas@tufts.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body><p>In this paper, I will introduce a new online teaching and research platform on which students can
                collaboratively transcribe, edit, and translate Latin manuscripts and Greek
                inscriptions, creating vetted open source digital editions. This platform was
                created by a group of faculty, software developers, and library professionals at
                Tufts University to enable students to work with original untranslated documents. By
                doing so, students not only develop their own language skills and research
                abilities, but they also contribute to the efforts of the scholarly community
                worldwide to meet the challenge of publishing large numbers of primary source
                documents online while preserving high editorial standards as described by Robinson
                (2010). The platform will be made available as open-source software and since it is
                language-independent, it can be used to edit and translate any source document in
                any language and any Humanities field.   </p>
            <p>The platform is an adaptation of Image J and Son of Suda Online (SoSOL). It allows
                students to transcribe ancient texts directly from a high-resolution digital image
                while mapping the text onto the lettering. The transcriptions thus produced are
                automatically encoded in accordance with the EpiDoc markup guidelines, a standard
                developed by an international consortium of scholars for the accurate description of
                inscriptions and manuscripts in TEI XML (see Sosin 2010). This ensures greater
                visibility for the collection and fosters scholarly dialogue since all documents
                published under the EpiDoc standard are compatible and can be exploited together in
                an open-access collaborative context (see Bodard 2008). The students’ work therefore
                contributes to a worldwide effort to make ancient manuscripts and inscriptions
                available online. To link all these resources and present the web interface, we used
                the CITE services (‘Collections, Indexes, and Texts, with Extensions’) developed by
                the Homer Multitext Project (see Blackwell and Smith 2009). We intend to investigate
                ways to take advantage of the chain of authority supported by the SoSOL environment
                to facilitate the process of the long-term archiving of the resources in the Tufts
                institutional Fedora repository. We will make the data from this project available
                to the broader humanities community through the Perseus Project.   </p>
            <p>Initially, the students will be working with Latin manuscripts (ranging in date
                between the 12th and 19th centuries) held in the Tufts University Library which have
                been digitized and published online. The students will also edit and translate
                ancient Greek funerary inscriptions which relate to Marie-Claire Beaulieu’s research
                on the poetics of Greek epitaphs. The collection created by the students will form a
                cohesive dataset of Latin and Greek texts which will be used at Tufts for ongoing
                research projects on ancient literature but will also be a valuable addition to
                corpora being developed by scholars worldwide such as the EpiDoc databases (see
                Cayless et al. 2009, esp. 34).   </p>
            <p>Students will begin their work with a high resolution image of a Latin or Greek
                document published in our online collection. After receiving training on the
                decipherment of ancient Greek and Latin scripts, they will transcribe the texts and
                map them onto the image of the document using the software described above. The
                transcription step is important since it allows for careful review: thanks to the
                direct visual link created by the software between the image of the document and the
                transcription, the instructor and the audience can instantly evaluate the accuracy
                of the transcription (see figures 1 and 2).   </p>
            <p>The second step is to produce a normalized edition of the texts, including the
                resolution of abbreviations and lacunae, wherever possible. At this stage, two
                important digital tool sets are integrated with each text. The Alpheios Greek and
                Latin tools provide interactive lexical and grammatical analysis of each word, and
                the Perseus tools compute dynamic word lists and help the students and their
                instructors keep track of the progress accomplished in language learning (see figure
                3). The Perseus tools can also be used to design personalized reading lists and
                exams for each student. Although this project uses Latin and Greek language tools,
                the design can easily accommodate the integration of similar tools for any language.
                  </p>
            <p>The third and final step is translation and annotation, which is crucial for making
                the texts accessible to a wide-ranging audience of students and scholars in other
                disciplines as well as the general public. At this stage, students will translate
                the texts into English and gather as much information as possible on each text,
                including its date and historical and literary significance. They will establish
                parallels with other similar texts, which can be implemented as hyperlinks. The
                entries are finally rounded out with a complete bibliography of the scholarship
                available on each text and credits naming all contributors to the entry.    </p>
            <p>After their publication online, the entries will be linked to the SAKAI/Trunk
                software, an open-access collaborative learning management resource that allows
                students to design personalized electronic portfolios. These portfolios can be used
                by instructors to evaluate a student’s overall performance and progress and can also
                serve in applications for grants, graduate school admission, or in the context of a
                job search. An entry in this online collection should feature prominently in a
                student’s portfolio, since it constitutes a valuable and quantifiable language
                learning experience as well as a piece of original scholarship on a previously
                unedited and/or untranslated text. Throughout this process, students participate in
                the efforts of the scholarly community worldwide while perfecting their own language
                and research skills, thus becoming true citizen scholars.</p>
            <p><figure>
                    <graphic url="img139-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                        mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    <head>Figure 1: The transcription step</head>
                </figure></p>
            <p><figure>
                    <graphic url="img139-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                        mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    <head>Figure 2: The submission and evaluation step</head>
                </figure></p>
            <p><figure>
                    <graphic url="img139-3.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                        mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    <head>Figure 3: The Alpheios tools provide interactive lexical and
                        grammatical analysis of each word</head>
                </figure></p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
                
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Blackwell, Chr., and D. N. Smith</hi> (2009). Homer Multitext
                    – Nine Year Update. <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities 2009 Conference
                        Abstracts</hi>, (June 2009): 6-8. <ref
                        target="http://www.mith2.umd.edu/dh09/wp-content/uploads/dh09_conferencepreceedings_final.pdf" type="external" 
                        >http://www.mith2.umd.edu/dh09/wp-content/uploads/dh09_conferencepreceedings_final.pdf</ref>
                        (accessed March 9, 2012).</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Bodard, G</hi>. (2008). The <hi rend="italic">Inscriptions of
                            Aphrodisias </hi>as Electronic Publication: A User’s Perspective and a Proposed Paradigm. <hi rend="italic">Digital
                            Medievalist</hi> 4. <ref target="http://www.digitalmedievalist.org/journal/4/bodard/" type="external"
                        >http://www.digitalmedievalist.org/journal/4/bodard/</ref>  (accessed March 9,
                        2012).</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Cayless, H., Ch. Roueché, T. Elliott, and G. Bodard</hi>.
                    (2009). Epigraphy in 2017. <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</hi> 3
                    (January 2009). <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/1/000030.html"
                        type="external">
                        >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/1/000030.html</ref> (accessed
                    March 9, 2012).</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Robinson, P.</hi> (2010). Editing Without Walls. <hi
                        rend="italic">Literature Compass</hi>, 7: 57-61. <ref
                        target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1741-4113.2009.00676.x" type="external"
                        >http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1741-4113.2009.00676.x</ref> (accessed March 9,
                    2012).</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Sosin, J</hi>. (2010). ‘Digital Papyrology.’ Congress of the
                    International Association of Papyrologists, Geneva, Switzerland. <ref
                        target="https://exchange.tufts.edu/owa/redir.aspx?C=582e4a9690a04632b2997bc4c6836f47&amp;URL=http%3a%2f%2fwww.stoa.org%2farchives%2f1263"
                        type="external">http://www.stoa.org/archives/1263</ref> (accessed March 12,
                    2012).</p>
                
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>