<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-289">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Differentiation of Genres in Eighteenth- and Nineteenth-Century English Literature</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Underwood, Ted</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>tunder@illinois.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Sellers, Jordan</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>eseller2@illinois.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Auvil, Loretta</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>lauvil@illinois.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Capitanu, Boris</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>capitanu@ncsa.illinois.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            
            <div>
            <p>The title of this paper has changed, because our
                    effort to answer one question (about linguistic register) exposed a larger
                    question with broad relevance to literary study, and indeed to the definition of
                    ‘literature.’</p>
                <p>To start where the process of inquiry actually began: what happened to English
                    poetic diction around 1800? William Wordsworth’s claim to have brought poetry
                    back to ‘the language of conversation in the middle and lower classes of
                    society’ in <hi rend="italic">Lyrical Ballads</hi> has long been represented as
                    a turning point in literary history. Given the weight attributed to this claim,
                    it is surprising that scholars haven’t tried to test it. Did the language of
                    poetry actually become more formal or specialized in the eighteenth century? And
                    if so, did the change reverse itself around 1798? Finally, was this phenomenon
                    restricted to poetry, or was it a broader transformation of diction that
                    affected other genres as well?</p>
                <p>We are increasingly in a position to answer questions like these. True, we can’t
                    ask eighteenth-century English speakers to demonstrate ‘the language of
                    conversation in the middle and lower classes of society.’ Moreover, standard
                    contemporary tests of difficulty (like the Flesch-Kincaid Readability Test) are
                    not very applicable to earlier periods, because they rely on sentence length.
                    Practices of punctuation have changed over time, making the average sentence
                    steadily shorter from the seventeenth century through the twentieth.</p>
                <p>It is more practical to assess the formality of diction. This assessment is
                    particularly easy to make in English because of an important peculiarity of its
                    history: English was for two hundred years (1066-1250) almost exclusively a
                    spoken language, while French and Latin were used for writing. Any English word
                    that survived this period had to be the kind of word that gets used in
                    conversation. Words that entered the language afterwards were often borrowed
                    from French or Latin to flesh out the learned vocabulary. Even today, the
                    distinction between these two parts of the lexicon remains an important aspect
                    of linguistic register. For instance, Laly Bar-Ilan and Ruth Berman have shown
                    that contemporary spoken English is distinguished from writing by containing a
                    higher proportion of words from Old English. Moreover, this differentiation
                    between writing and speech increases as students enter high school, where they
                    also learn to use a greater proportion of words from French and Latin in formal
                    expository prose than they do in written narrative (Bar-Ilan &amp; Berman
                    2007).</p>
                <p>If learned and informal registers were distinguished this way in the thirteenth
                    century, and the same thing holds true today, then one can reasonably infer that
                    it held true in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries as well (for further
                    evidence, see DeForest &amp; Johnson 2001). Thus an etymological approach to
                    diction can show us how the ‘register’ of a given genre changed across time,
                    becoming more conversational or more formal.</p>
                
                <p><figure><graphic url="img289-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 1</head></figure></p>
                <p>We have explored this question in a collection
                    of 3,724 volumes. The eighteenth-century part of the collection was manually
                    keyed by ECCO-TCP; the nineteenth-century part of the collection was digitized
                    by OCR, but has been corrected with a fuzzy-matching script that has a
                    machine-learning component and is extensively optimized for nineteenth-century
                    OCR (our strategy was based on Lasko &amp; Hauser 2002). More importantly, the
                    comparative logic of this inquiry largely factors out the false negatives
                    produced by imperfect OCR.</p>
                <p>Instead of distinguishing ‘Germanic’ and ‘Latinate’ diction, we have used the
                    first attested date for each word, choosing 1150 as a dividing line because it’s
                    the midpoint of the period when English was not used in writing. But
                    date-of-entry of course correlates strongly with the Germanic/Latinate division.
                    One can in fact simply measure the average length of words and produce very
                    similar results (the correlation between the pre/post-1150 ratio and average
                    word length is usually -.85 or lower). We exclude a generous list of stopwords
                    (determiners, prepositions, conjunctions, pronouns, and the verb to be). The
                    reason is that, as Bar-Ilan and Berman point out, ‘register variation is
                    essentially a matter of <hi rend="italic">choice</hi>’ (15). There is usually no
                    alternative to stopwords, so they may not reveal much about register. We also
                    exclude abbreviations, proper nouns, and words that entered the language after
                    1699.</p>
                <p>The results of this inquiry do suggest that the register of poetry took a new
                    turn in the late eighteenth century. In the course of the nineteenth century
                    older, pre-1150 words became dramatically more common in poetry. It is
                    reasonable to infer that poetic diction became more familiar and less overtly
                    learned. But this particular detail is hardly the most striking fact about Fig.
                    1. What’s salient is rather a broader process of generic differention from 1700
                    to 1899 that affected prose fiction and nonfiction as well as poetry. In the
                    year 1700, these genres each had their own peculiarities of diction, but they
                    didn’t belong to sharply distinguished registers of the language. By 1899, they
                    did. The ratio of pre- to post-1150 words became almost twice as high in prose
                    fiction as in nonfiction, and almost three times higher in poetry. This suggests
                    that the story usually told about Wordsworth may be misleading: far from
                    rebelling against specialized poetic diction, he was producing a manifesto for a
                    style that was – less recondite, to be sure – but also <hi rend="italic"
                        >more</hi> sharply differentiated from prose.</p>
                <p>This result matters, more broadly, because it bears an interesting relationship
                    to the emergence of ‘literature’ as a distinct cultural category in the same
                    period. In the early eighteenth century, ‘literature’ could encompass anything
                    read by the middle and upper classes, emphatically including nonfiction. By the
                    end of the nineteenth century, ‘literature’ was a category sharply distinguished
                    from nonfiction prose, and valued for special aesthetic qualities. If this
                    conceptual shift was also accompanied by a systematic transformation of diction,
                    we may be able to learn something about the nineteenth-century concept of
                    ‘literature’ by paying close attention to the way diction changed.</p>
                <p>To start a debate on this topic, we will present an argument with two parts.
                    First, we will show that the differentiation of genres was not merely a matter
                    of linguistic register. When we compare genres in a more general way (using
                    metrics like Spearman correlation and cosine similarity) it remains true that
                    poetry, fiction and, to some extent, drama became steadily less like nonfiction
                    prose in the period 1700-1899 (for the rationale behind these metrics, see
                    Kilgarriff 2001).</p>
                
                <p><figure><graphic url="img289-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 2</head></figure></p>
                <p>Second, we will begin to interpret the meaning of the
                    divergence, by examining lists of words that became relatively more (or less)
                    overrepresented in literary genres over this period. Briefly, we will suggest
                    that the transformation of literary diction dramatizes a transformation of the
                    logic of cultural capital. In the eighteenth century, literary diction
                    explicitly thematized the social status associated with fine writing (‘muse,’
                    ‘pomp,’ ‘taste,’ ‘applause,’ ‘genius,’ ‘merit,’ ‘talents.’) In the nineteenth
                    century, literary diction became more concrete, to be sure, and less explicitly
                    learned – but it also tended to disavow the social in favor of a pure
                    subjectivity embodied, for instance, in nouns and verbs of perception
                    (‘listened,’ ‘heard,’ ‘looked,’ ‘felt,’ ‘dream,’ ‘eye’). We propose that this
                    emphasis on subjectivity and immediacy in fact dramatizes a mode of cultural
                    capital associated with literature’s autonomy from other institutions (Ross
                    1998). We don’t pretend to have proven that hypothesis. There is room for a
                    great deal more study and argument. We do, however, claim to have shown that the
                    diction of poetry, fiction, and nonfiction prose differentiate from each other
                    over the period 1700-1899 – a puzzle that will need <hi rend="italic">some</hi>
                    kind of explanation. We offer the puzzle itself as an example of the way
                    text-mining is already beginning to shape debates in literary history and
                    critical theory.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <p/>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Acknowledgments</hi></p>
                <p>The arguments and methods in this paper have been deeply shaped by conversation
                    with Natalia Cecire, Tanya Clement, Katherine Harris, Ryan Heuser, Natalie
                    Houston, Matt Jockers, Benjamin Schmidt, John Unsworth, and Scott Weingart.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Funding</hi></p>
                <p>This work was supported by the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation grant, <hi
                        rend="italic">Expanding SEASR Services.</hi></p>
            </div>
            
            
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
           <head>References</head>

            <p><hi rend="bold">Bar-Ilan, L., and R. A. Berman</hi> (2007). Developing register
                differentiation: the Latinate-Germanic divide in English. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Linguistics</hi> 45: 1-35.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">DeForest, M., and E. Johnson</hi> (2001).The Density of Latinate
                Words in the Speeches of Jane Austen’s Characters. <hi rend="italic">Literary and
                    Linguistic Computing</hi> 16: 389-401.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Lasko, T. A., and S. E. Hauser</hi> (2002). Approximate String
                Matching Algorithms for Limited-Vocabulary OCR Output Correction. <hi rend="italic"
                    >US National Library of Medicine</hi><ref target="http://archive.nlm.nih.gov/pubs/hauser/Tompaper/tompaper.php" type="external"
                >http://archive.nlm.nih.gov/pubs/hauser/Tompaper/tompaper.php.</ref></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Kilgarriff, A.</hi> (2001). Comparing Corpora. <hi rend="italic"
                    >International Journal of Corpus Linguistics</hi> 6: 97-133.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Ross, T.</hi> (1998). <hi rend="italic">The Making of the English
                    Literary Canon.</hi> Montreal: McGill-Queen’s UP.</p>
            
                <p><hi rend="bold">Wordsworth, W.</hi> (1798). Advertisement. <hi rend="italic">Lyrical Ballads, with a Few Other
                    Poems,</hi> by William Wordsworth and S. T. Coleridge. Bristol: Biggs &amp;
                Cottle.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>