<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-210">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Networks of networks: a critical review of formal network methods in archaeology through citation network analysis and close reading</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Brughmans, Tom</name>
                    <affiliation>Archaeological Computing Research Group, University of Southampton, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>tb2g08@soton.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>This paper will argue that archaeological network researchers are not well networked
                themselves, resulting in a limited and sometimes uncritical adoption of formal
                network methods within the archaeological discipline. This seems to have followed
                largely from a general unawareness of the historicity of network-based approaches
                which span at least eight decennia of multi-disciplinary research. Many network
                analytical techniques that would only find a broader use in the last 15 years were
                in fact introduced in the archaeological discipline as early as the 1970s. This
                paper does not aim to argue that every archaeological network study should include a
                historiography. It merely wishes to stress the need to explore the full range of
                existing network techniques and models. I will illustrate that knowledge of the
                diversity of archaeological and non-archaeological network methods is crucial to
                their critical application and modification within archaeological research
                contexts.</p>
            <p>This paper will for the first time trace the academic traditions, network concepts,
                models and techniques that have been most influential to archaeologists. I will do
                this by combining a close reading of published archaeological network applications
                with citation network analysis techniques (Batagelj 2003; Hummon &amp; Doreian 1989;
                White 2011), an approach that has not been applied to archaeological literature
                before. A citation network was created consisting of over 10,000 publications and
                their internal citations. This network consists of all archaeological network
                analysis applications, all publications cited by them and the citations between
                those publications. This data was extracted from Web of  Knowledge (<ref
                    target="http://wok.mimas.ac.uk/" type="external">http://wok.mimas.ac.uk/</ref>)
                and manually when the publications were not included on Web of Knowledge.</p>
            <p>The analysis revealed a number of issues surrounding the current use of network
                methods in archaeology, as well as possible sources and explanations for these
                issues. They include the following: (1) Although many network techniques are rooted
                in graph theory, archaeological studies in graph theory were not influential at all
                to more recent archaeological network studies. The introduction of graph theory and
                social network analysis into the archaeological discipline happened largely
                independently and, unlike social network analysts, archaeologists did not
                collaborate with graph theorists to develop mathematical techniques tailored for
                their needs. (2) The potential of social network analysis techniques was explored
                (largely theoretically) by Cynthia Irwin-Williams no later than 1977. Many of the
                techniques she described were not applied in archaeological research until the last
                ten years, possibly because the limited availability of cheap and potent computing
                power and large digital datasets in the late 1970s. (3) Some social network analysis
                techniques (e.g. centrality measures) have received more attention than others (e.g.
                ego-networks). The popularity of these techniques seems to be related with their use
                by social network analysts rather than how archaeologists have used them before. (4)
                The archaeological use of complex network models is largely limited to the extremely
                popular small-world and scale-free models. Archaeologists have neglected to explore
                the potential use of alternative complex network models. (5) The availability of
                user-friendly software seems to determine the popularity of social network measures
                used by archaeologists. (6) On the other hand, simulations of complex network models
                by archaeologists are rare due to the required technological and mathematical
                skills.</p>
            <p>The results of the citation analysis expose the insufficiently explored potential of
                formal network-based models and techniques and points out publications in other
                disciplines that might have interesting archaeological applications. The paper
                concludes that in order to move towards richer archaeological applications of formal
                network methods archaeological network analysts should become better networked both
                within and outside their discipline. The existing archaeological applications of
                network analysis show clear indications of methods with great potential for our
                discipline and methods that will remain largely fruitless, and archaeologists should
                become aware of these advances within their discipline. The development of original
                archaeological network methods should be driven by archaeological research problems
                and a broad knowledge of formal network methods developed in different
                disciplines.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Batagelj, V. </hi>(2003). Efficient Algorithms for Citation
                    Network Analysis. <hi rend="italic">Arxiv preprint cs/03090 </hi>23: 1-27.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Irwin-Williams, C.</hi> (1977). A network model for the analysis
                    of Prehistoric trade. In T. K. Earle, and J. E. Ericson (eds.), <hi
                        rend="italic">Exchange systems in Prehistory</hi>. New York: Academic Press,
                    pp. 141-151.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Hummon, N. P., and P. Dereian</hi> (1989). Connectivity in a
                    citation network: The development of DNA theory. <hi rend="italic">Social
                        Networks</hi> 11(1): 39-63.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">White, H. D.</hi> (2011). Scientific and scholarly networks. In
                    J. Scott, and P. J. Carrington (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The SAGE handbook of
                        social network analysis</hi>. London: Sage, pp. 272-285.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>