<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-211">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The electronic ‘Oxford English Dictionary’, poetry, and
                    intertextuality</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Williams, David-Antoine</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Waterloo, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>david.williams@uwaterloo.ca</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Overview</head>
                <p>This paper will discuss recent research carried out in the context of two grant
                    projects: ‘Poetry and Contingency’ (funded by a Social Sciences and Humanities
                    Research Council of Canada [SSHRC] Insight Development Grant – Digital Economy
                    Priority Area) and ‘Applying search and stylometry techniques to <hi
                        rend="italic">OED2</hi> and poetic text corpora’ (funded by a UWaterloo
                    SSHRC Institutional Grant). It will discuss the processes and methods developed
                    for analyzing and comparing large, heterogeneous text datasets, as well as
                    preliminary results of these analyses and their applications in and implications
                    for traditional literary studies. With implications for digital humanities
                    research, computational approaches to language and literature, linguistics,
                    lexicography, poetics, and literary criticism, the paper will address conference
                    themes of ‘cultures, languages, and methods’ and several of their
                    intersections.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Context</head>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Oxford English Dictionary </hi>(<hi rend="italic">OED</hi>)
                    is widely considered to be the greatest philological and lexicographical
                    achievement in English. The core of the work is its 2.5 million quotations, a
                    significant portion of them from poetic and other literary texts, which both
                    shape and illustrate the various sense definitions of roughly 600,000 English
                    words and word forms. Conversely, since its publication, poets have relied on
                    the <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> to guide their deployments and arrangements of
                    English words in poems. This reciprocal intertextuality has led to two striking
                    facts which have received insufficient scholarly attention: 1) that the <hi
                        rend="italic">OED</hi>’s definitions of English words depend to a
                    significant degree on poetic language, which is striking because by any standard
                    account, poetic usage tends away from the denotative or definitional and towards
                    the connotative and metaphorical; and 2) that much English poetry of the last
                    hundred years contains a philological, etymological, and lexicographical
                    dimension, informed by the <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>.</p>
                <p>Although the Second Edition of the <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> (Murray et al.
                    1989) was among the earliest large books to be presented to public and academic
                    communities in digitized, marked-up form, and despite the ongoing comprehensive
                    rewriting of the Dictionary (Simpson &amp; Weiner 2000-) no version has ever
                    been marked for quotation genre, meaning that until now the reciprocal
                    influences between dictionary and author have been difficult to identify, and
                    impossible or impracticable to quantify with reference to specific literary
                    genres (e.g. poetry or verse drama, etc.). My projects use the 1989 electronic
                        <hi rend="italic">OED2</hi>, digitized at the University of Waterloo,
                    alongside electronic corpora of poetry, derived from Project Gutenberg,
                    Chadwyck-Healey, and other datasets, to generate quantitative and qualitative
                    assessments in two broad fields of inquiry: 1) What has been the influence of
                    poetry on the English language’s most comprehensive lexicographical work? and 2)
                    What influence has the <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> had on English-language
                    poetry? </p></div>
                <div>
                    <head>Work in Progress</head>
                    <p>The first prong of the project involves creating a parallel <hi
                            rend="italic">OED2</hi> in which poetic quotations are marked for genre,
                        to allow for advanced search and comparison of poetic quotations. Marking
                            <hi rend="italic">OED2 </hi>for quotation genre will allow for fast,
                        comparative analysis of the influence of poetic writing on the compilers of
                        the <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>. I will discuss the challenges of this task
                        and the methods developed to achieve it, as well as the search and
                        comparison scripts developed to query the new resource. I will give examples
                        and discuss the kinds of queries and comparisons made possible by this new
                        resource, and their implications for literary studies and
                        lexicography.</p>
                    <p>If the first prong is designed to generate questions and
                        answers about poetic influence on <hi rend="italic">OED2</hi>, the second
                        prong investigates a more intricate and subtle problem: the influence of the
                            <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> on poetry. For instance, it is a trivial
                        thing for a critic to suppose that Geoffrey Hill’s talk of ‘<hi
                            rend="italic">wrinching and spraining the text</hi>’ is a reference to
                        Milton, since it is contains nonstandard spelling, is italicized, and
                        appears in a poem with Milton in the title (Hill 2008: 5). But <hi
                            rend="italic">OED2</hi> also quotes exactly those words from <hi
                            rend="italic">Of Reformation</hi> (Milton 1698: 269) under both ‘wrench,
                        v.’, and ‘sprain, v.’ suggesting a second possible source text for Hill.
                        Testing an individual poem for potential <hi rend="italic">OED2</hi>
                        intertextuality requires a set of text comparison techniques plus an
                        appropriate method of applying these. The process can also be applied
                        systematically, to an electronic corpus (or several corpora) of poetry
                        written since c.1884, the year <hi rend="italic">OED1</hi> fascicles began
                        to be published. Relatively simple text-similarity approaches to the two
                        corpora (including, e.g., string, n-gram, functional n-gram, and
                        low-probability statistical approaches) will yield hundreds if not thousands
                        of instances such as these, without depending on the poet to flag his or her
                        source. More sophisticated stylometric techniques will give more promising
                        indications of potential poetic intertextuality with various dictionary
                        entries, including their etymology, definition, and quotation fields. Using
                        these tools, we can quickly identify a very large number of candidates for
                        intertextuality in English poems. I will discuss the comparison methods
                        developed, as well as preliminary results of these, and their implications
                        for literary studies.</p><p>A few facts make <hi rend="italic">OED2
                    </hi>intertextuality a special case, overlapping with cases of attribution or
                    allusion, but not identical to these. For one, <hi rend="italic">OED2 </hi>is
                    already a multiauthored and intertextual text, written and compiled by hundreds
                    of lexicographers over more than a hundred years, following varying practices
                    and relying on thousands of sources comprising millions of quotations. Secondly,
                    though <hi rend="italic">OED2 </hi>
                    carries linguistic information (such as pronunciations, etymologies,
                        definitions, etc.) as well as historical usage information (in the
                        quotations) about every English word that is likely to occur in a poem or
                        anywhere else, it is not often the only text to carry any one subset of this
                        information. This means that finding <hi rend="italic">OED2</hi> in poems
                        may point to another source for a poetic passage than (just) <hi
                            rend="italic">OED2</hi> itself. Comparing the etymology field of a word
                        in <hi rend="italic">OED2</hi> to its occurrence in a poetic text, for
                        instance, might point to an etymological play on words, without conclusively
                        attributing this to <hi rend="italic">OED2</hi>. Or comparing the quotation
                        fields may suggest an allusion to a text that <hi rend="italic">happens to
                            be</hi> quoted in <hi rend="italic">OED2</hi>, even if <hi rend="italic"
                            >OED2</hi> is not itself the source of the allusion. But it may also
                        point to true influence, in the form of a poetic allusion or reference which
                        has been occasioned by <hi rend="italic">OED2</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">and not the original text.</hi> I will discuss, with the
                        help of preliminary results, the value and implications of each type of
                        discovery, and ways of differentiating among these possibilities when
                        appropriate. This is, I will argue, a discussion which takes up the crucial
                        question of how, and to what extent, computing technologies can benefit the
                        field of literary criticism, as a species of literary scholarship with its
                        own goals and commitments.</p>
           
                </div>
            
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Brewer, C.</hi> (2008).<hi rend="italic"> Treasure-House of the
                        Language: The Living OED</hi>.  New Haven: Yale.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Brewer, C.</hi> (2009). Literary Quotations in the <hi
                        rend="italic">OED. Review of English Studies</hi> 61: 93-125.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Brewer, C.</hi> (2011). ‘Happy Copiousness’? <hi rend="italic"
                        >OED’s</hi> Recording of Female Authors of the Eighteenth Century. <hi
                        rend="italic">Review of English Studies </hi>62: 86-117.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Burchfield, R. W.</hi> (1989). <hi rend="italic">Unlocking the
                        English Language</hi>. London: Faber.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Forstall, C. W., and W. J. Scheirer </hi>(2010). Features from
                    Frequency: Authorship and Stylistic Analysis Using Repetitive Sound. <hi
                        rend="italic">Proceedings of the Chicago Colloquium on Digital Humanities
                        and Computer Science</hi>, 1(2). <ref target="https://letterpress.uchicago.edu/index.php/jdhcs/article/view/56/67" type="external">https://letterpress.uchicago.edu/index.php/jdhcs/article/view/56/67</ref> (accessed
                    March 2012).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Heaney, S.</hi> (1996). <hi rend="italic">Opened Ground: Poems
                        1966-1996</hi>. London: Faber.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Hill, G.</hi> (2008). <hi rend="italic">A Treatise of Civil
                        Power. </hi>London: Penguin.<hi rend="italic"> </hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Hollander, J.</hi> (1981). <hi rend="italic">The Figure of
                        Echo</hi>. Berkeley: U of California P.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Holmes, David I.</hi> (1998). The Evolution of Stylometry in
                    Humanities Scholarship. <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi>
                    13(3): 111-17.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Irwin, W.</hi> (2001).<hi rend="bold"> </hi>What is an Allusion?
                        <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Aesthetics and Art Criticism</hi> 59(3):
                    287-297.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Koppel, M., and J. Schler</hi> (2004). Authorship Verification as
                    a One-Class Classification Problem. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 21st
                        International Conference on Machine Learning</hi>, pp. 489-95.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Koppel, M., J. Schler, and E. Bonchek-Dokow</hi> (2007).
                    Measuring Differentiability: Unmasking Pseudonymous Authors <hi rend="italic"
                        >Journal of Machine Learning Research</hi> 8: 1261-1276. </p>
                <p><hi rend="italic"><hi rend="bold">Literature Online</hi></hi>. <ref
                        target="http://lion.chadwyck.com" type="external"
                        >http://lion.chadwyck.com</ref> (accessed March 2012).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Milton, J. </hi>(1698). <hi rend="italic">Historical, Political,
                        and Miscellaneous Works</hi>. Amsterdam.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Muldoon, P.</hi> (2001). <hi rend="italic">Poems, 1968-1998</hi>.
                    London: Faber.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Murray, J., et. al., eds.</hi> (1989). <hi rend="italic">Oxford
                        English Dictionary</hi>. 2nd ed., compiled by J. A. Simpson and E. S. C.
                    Weiner, 20 vols. Oxford: Oxford UP.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Neumann, P.</hi> Statistical metalinguistics and
                    Zipf/Pareto/Mandelbrot. <ref target="http://www.csl.sri.com/users/neumann/#12a" type="external">http://www.csl.sri.com/users/neumann/#12a</ref> (accessed
                    March 2012).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Project Gutenberg</hi>. <ref target="http://gutenberg.org"
                        type="external">http://gutenberg.org</ref> (accessed March 2012).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Ricks, C.</hi> (2002). <hi rend="italic">Allusion to the
                        Poets</hi>. Oxford: Oxford UP.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Ruthven, K. K.</hi> (1969). The Poet as Etymologist. <hi
                        rend="italic">Critical Quarterly</hi> 11(1): 9-37. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Simpson, J., and E. S. C. Weiner</hi> (2000-). <hi rend="italic"
                        >OED Online</hi>. 3rd ed., rev. J. A. Simpson et al. Oxford: Oxford UP.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Tompa, F., E. Blake, E., and T. Bray</hi> (1991). <hi
                        rend="italic">Shortening the OED: Experience with a grammar-defined
                        database</hi>.  Waterloo: UW Centre for the New Oxford Dictionary and Text
                    Research.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Trillini, R. H., and S. Quassdorf</hi> (2010). A ‘Key to All
                    Quotations’? A Corpus-Based Parameter Model of Intertextuality. <hi
                        rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi> 25(3): 269-86. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Vogel, C., and G. Lynch</hi> (2008). Computational Stylometry:
                    Who’s in a Play? <hi rend="italic">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</hi> 5042:
                    169-186. </p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>