<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-270">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Workflows as Structured Surfaces</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Radzikowska, Milena</name>
                    <affiliation>Mount Royal University, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>mradzikowska@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Ruecker, Stan</name>
                    <affiliation>IIT Institute of Design, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>sruecker@id.iit.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Rockwell, Geoffrey</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Alberta, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>grockwel@ualberta.ca</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Brown, Susan</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Guelph, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>susanirenebrown@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Frizzera, Luciano</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Alberta, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>lucaju@me.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>INKE Research Group</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Alberta, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>sruecker@id.iit.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>At DH 2011 in Stanford, we introduced the concept of structured surfaces, where we
                extended the metaphor of interactive digital pins on a digital map into interactive
                digital pins on any data visualization (Radzikowska et al. 2011). We proposed that
                such structured surfaces would provide a means for people working with digital
                collections to gain insight into their material while also providing them a means of
                formulating an argument about the data. </p>
            <p>More recently, in considering scholarly editions, we became interested in how the
                concept of the structured surface could be applied to the editorial process – in
                effect, producing an interface derived from the flowchart of activities that an
                editor can use to manage the movement of a submitted article or other item of text
                (such as a book review) through the stages from its initial appearance in the
                editor’s inbox to the final step where it is ready to send to the printer. </p>
            <p>Accordingly, we have designed and are in the process of producing experimental
                prototypes of a series of these workflow interfaces for different kinds of editorial
                jobs, including the publication of journal articles, the writing of XML-encoded
                original material based on Orlando biocritical entries on women writers, and the
                editing of a scholarly edition (e.g. Figure 1). In these designs, the structured
                surface consists of the flowchart used by the editor, and the pins represent the
                articles, with size of pin indicating length of article in words.</p>
            <p><figure>
                    <graphic url="img270-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                        mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    <head>Figure 1: This workflow diagram shows the movement of a journal article
                        through the publication process from the perspective of the journal editor
                        who is managing that process</head>
                </figure></p>
            <p>Numerous other systems exist for managing workflow in the context of digital text
                production, such as that devised by the Public Knowledge Project for its Open
                Journal Systems and its Open Monograph Systems. The interfaces here seek to retain
                the modularity and customizability associated with such systems but to combine them
                with a rich prospect visualization (Ruecker, Radzikowska &amp; Sinclair 2011) of the
                collection being managed than has hitherto been implemented. Recent work in
                computing science has focused both on workflow analysis (e.g. Schroeder 2009) and on
                algorithms for automatic layout (e.g. Albrecht et al. 2010).</p>
            <p>However, a workflow management tool, as useful it might be to the editor who has not
                had the advantage of using one yet, is in itself not a particularly interesting
                object. It is essentially a structured checklist, composed of a collection of stages
                with transitions, including occasional decision points between them. But once such a
                concept is available for interrogation, it can begin to introduce additional
                considerations.</p>
            <p>For example, why is the structure of the stages limited to a simple bucket? Would it
                not be useful to be able to distinguish different kinds of material moving through
                the system? It might possible, for instance, to automatically identify file types so
                that digital text is treated one way by the tool, while digital film is treated
                another. Or the editor may wish to produce a variant of the workflow for book
                reviews as opposed to peer-reviewed articles. So we have begun to experiment with
                ways of visually structuring the boxes that represent stages (Figure 2).</p>
            <p><figure>
                    <graphic url="img270-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                        mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    <head>Figure 2: An initial attempt to turn the workflow stage itself into a
                        kind of structured surface</head>
                </figure></p>
            <p>Once we have the concept of the system automatically doing something to the
                documents, it is a short step to recalling that the original goal of the structured
                surface project was to provide the user with a set of analytics in the form of a
                data visualization and an argument made by the superimposition of pins. In that
                context, it seems reasonable to consider what kinds of analytical processes might be
                applicable to various stages within the workflow, and also what kind of information
                might be useful to the editor at each stage. For example, when an article is with a
                reviewer, the editor is likely to be primarily interested in the following
                information:</p>
            <xmt:uList>
                <item>the title of the article</item>
                <item>the name and contact information of the reviewer</item>
                <item>the dates when the article went to the reviewer and when it is expected
                    back</item>
            </xmt:uList>
            <p>A rollover of the pin within the ‘at the reviewer’ stage should therefore by default
                produce this list of information, with access to further information relegated to
                the ‘more...’ link. At the next stage, however, when the article is back from the
                reviewer(s), what the editor would like to know is the results of the review. A
                rollover of the pin while in that bucket should therefore produce the title of the
                article and the name of the reviewer(s), but also the contents of the review.</p>
            <p>On the analytics side, there may be processes (like reviewing) where the article is
                passed to another person, but there may also be processes where the article is
                passed to some algorithmic treatment, such as an automated step of metadata
                enhancement where the system makes the first pass at named entity recognition for
                people and places. Since one of the affordances of the JiTR environment is that any
                collection or subset of a collection can be passed to a tool, perhaps the contents
                of the stages within the workflow could serve as subsets for this kind of treatment.
                An editor might then, for instance, decide to take a look at a KWIC concordance for
                a term in every article in the ‘accepted’ bucket for the current edition, or run a
                word cloud on all the articles that have been accepted or rejected. The wordcloud of
                acceptances might provide some guidance in writing an introductory editorial, for
                instance, while the latter might help the editor see whether there is a gap in
                reviewer expertise at work. Support for these sorts of curiosity-driven activities
                within the editorial process itself has the potential to change the nature of the
                task in a variety of ways.</p>
            <p>Finally, the concept of an interface that combines workflow management with analytics
                is of considerable interested to the Canadian Writing Research Collaboratory (CWRC)
                project, which seeks to lower the bar to participation in online resource creation
                and enhancement by mainstream scholars without significant expertise in digital
                humanities, and in so doing lower the overhead of producing scholarly materials on
                the web. In order to ensure quality control within a system such as CWRC’s, a
                workflow process needs to be highly intuitive as well as modular, robust, and well
                integrated with other interface components. For these reasons, CWRC is experimenting
                with the structured surfaces interface and the JiTR environment as a major component
                of its interface, seeing the potential of it for managing everything from query
                results to worflow management to membership coordination. The CWRC project has
                presented the interface to Collaboratory members at two workshops this year and is
                extending the prototype to handle Orlando-like workflows and interact with an
                external workflow engine.</p>
            <p>This presentation will outline the transfer of the structured surface concept to
                workflows, show the sketches and demonstrate the prototypes, and report on user
                feedback to date. It will provide an analysis of the implications of this approach
                to supporting the editorial process, suggesting that there are a number of potential
                new affordances that make the workflow a useful addition to the editor’s toolbox. An
                interface which integrates a tightly defined workflow alongside the ability to
                invoke other tools, we argue, can also encourage new kinds of thinking about
                possible improvements or additions to the workflow.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
                
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Albrecht, B., P. Effinger, M. Held, and M. Kaufmann</hi>
                        (2010). An automatic layout algorithm for BPEL processes. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Proceedings of the 5th international symposium on Software
                            visualization</hi> (SOFTVIS ’10). ACM, New York, NY, USA, 173-182.
                        DOI=10.1145/1879211.1879237
                        <ref target="http://doi.acm.org.login.ezproxy.library.ualberta.ca/10.1145/1879211.1879237" type="external">http://doi.acm.org.login.ezproxy.library.ualberta.ca/10.1145/1879211.1879237</ref> </p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Canadian Writing Research Collaboratory.</hi>  <ref
                        target="http://www.cwrc.ca" type="external">http://www.cwrc.ca</ref></p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Open Journal Systems Documentation.</hi>
                        <ref target="http://pkp.sfu.ca/files/OJSinanHour.pdf" type="external">pkp.sfu.ca/files/OJSinanHour.pdf</ref></p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Open Monograph Project.</hi>
                        <ref target="http://pkp.sfu.ca/omp" type="external">http://pkp.sfu.ca/omp</ref></p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Orlando Project.</hi>
                       
                        <ref target="http://orlando.cambridge.org" type="external">http://orlando.cambridge.org</ref></p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Radzikowska, M., S. Ruecker, S. Brown, P. Organisciak, and
                            the INKE Research Group</hi> (2011). Structured Surfaces for JiTR. Paper
                        presented at the <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities 2011 conference.
                            Stanford, June 19-21, 2011.</hi>   </p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Ruecker, S., M. Radzikowska, and S. Sinclair</hi> (2011). <hi
                            rend="italic">Visual Interface Design for Digital Cultural Heritage: A
                            Guide to Rich-Prospect Browsing. </hi>Farnham, Surrey: Ashgate
                        Publishing.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Schroeder, W.</hi> (2009). New tools for task workflow
                        analysis. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 27th international conference
                            extended abstracts on Human factors in computing systems</hi> (CHI EA
                        ’09). ACM, New York, NY, USA, 3877-3882. DOI=10.1145/1520340.1520587
                        <ref target="http://doi.acm.org.login.ezproxy.library.ualberta.ca/10.1145/1520340.1520587" type="external">http://doi.acm.org.login.ezproxy.library.ualberta.ca/10.1145/1520340.1520587</ref>.
                </p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>