<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-393">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Digital Language Archives and Less-Networked Speaker Communities</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Dobrin, Lise M.</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Virginia, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>dobrin@virginia.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>During the past decade, digital language archives have flourished as the field of
                language documentation has entered mainstream linguistics. Major international
                funding bodies, both public and private, support research on endangered languages,
                and it is now possible to publish practical and theoretical work on endangered
                languages and documentary methods in dedicated journals and book series. One of the
                themes that has emerged most clearly in this literature is that of <hi rend="italic"
                    >collaboration</hi>. It is now widely agreed that language documentation should
                be equally responsive to both the technical questions posed by linguists and the
                more immediate practical interests of speakers and their communities. Issues of
                rights and access are no longer anxious afterthoughts; they are fundamental matters
                for negotiation between researchers and speakers, mandatorily addressed in research
                agreements and funding proposals, and threaded through documentation projects from
                their very conception (see, e.g., Yamada 2007; Czaykowska-Higgins 2009). </p>
            <p>Yet paradoxically, this intense focus on collaborative methods seems to stop where
                the digital archiving of language data begins. Language archives are doing their
                best to ensure that source communities can in principle gain <hi rend="italic"
                    >access</hi> to the language materials they produce, but they are only just
                beginning to consider possibilities for formally integrating speaker communities
                into the process of archive curation. Such involvement could potentially transform
                language archives from repositories of static objects into sites for ongoing
                dialogue and exchange with living communities. </p>
            <p>The obstacles to collaborative archiving are particularly acute in the case of source
                communities located in hard-to-reach places – often the third world – where many of
                today’s small, minor, and endangered languages are spoken. As might be expected, a
                disproportionate percentage of documentary projects are being carried out in such
                locations (see, e.g.,
                <ref target="http://www.paradisec.org.au/blog/2010/09/where-does-the-dosh-go" type="external">http://www.paradisec.org.au/blog/2010/09/where-does-the-dosh-go</ref>), with their outputs
                being deposited into first world archives. It is imperative that western scholars
                and institutions be cognizant of the impact their documentation projects have on
                such communities. In Melanesia, which is arguably the world’s most linguistically
                diverse area, local value is validated through relationships with outsiders. If
                community input ceases once the fieldwork phase of a western-sponsored project is
                over, this can reinforce the feelings of marginalization that motivate language
                shift in the first place (Dobrin 2008). </p>
            <p>In April 2012, the University of Virginia’s Institute for Advanced Technology in the
                Humanities (IATH) is hosting an international group of scholars, technical experts,
                and community members for an intensive two-day meeting, sponsored by the National
                Endowment for the Humanities, to explore appropriate social and technical models for
                facilitating the ongoing involvement of less-networked source communities in the
                digital archiving of their endangered languages. Participants will present on the
                current state of the art in language archiving, the cultural and infrastructural
                situations of representative world regions (Papua New Guinea and Cameroon), and
                promising ‘bridging’ technologies. <hi rend="italic">This paper will report on the
                    results of the meeting, describing their implications for language archiving and
                    for the digital humanities more generally.</hi>        </p>
            <p>There are a number of reasons why digital language archives must begin to find ways
                to support direct, ongoing relationships with speakers and community members, and
                not just with data depositors or researchers. One of these is the unfolding nature
                and experience-dependence of informed consent. When speakers are first recorded,
                they may consent to certain levels of access for the resulting materials (full
                access, access with conditions, researcher-only, etc.; see
                <ref target="http://elar.soas.ac.uk/node/32620" type="external">http://elar.soas.ac.uk/node/32620</ref> and
                <ref target="http://www.mpi.nl/DOBES/archive_access/access_procedures" type="external">http://www.mpi.nl/DOBES/archive_access/access_procedures</ref>). But they cannot
                possibly foresee all potential future uses of the recordings. And where communities
                have little or no familiarity with the medium of distribution, how can they be
                expected to grasp even the most basic uses to which their material will be put?
                Given the opportunity to make their wishes known, judgments made by communities at a
                given time may be modified, refined, or even reversed later.</p>
            <p>Developing direct lines of communication between archives and communities will also
                improve the quality and discoverability of archived data. Changing circumstances may
                make possible the engagement of knowledgeable stakeholders who were formerly
                reluctant or inaccessible. Also, though linguists may be diligent about collecting
                detailed metadata when making recordings in the field, this process inevitably
                leaves gaps. After fieldwork is over, missing information, such as the identity of a
                speaker or dialect, might only be known by difficult-to-reach community members.
                Whole categories of metadata that once seemed irrelevant (details of local history,
                relationships between consultants, and so on) often take on new significance as
                projects evolve. By enabling mechanisms by which community members can identify and
                attach metadata to recordings that concern them or their communities, endangered
                language resources will be enriched, making them easier to find and more useful for
                all users. </p>
            <p>Finally, there is a practical need for the kind of direct relationships we are
                proposing to facilitate, as archives are now receiving expressions of interest from
                individuals who speak the languages of their collections. At the University of
                London’s School of Oriental and African Studies (SOAS), the Endangered Languages
                Archive (ELAR) has registered speakers of Bena and Pite Saami as users; IATH
                occasionally receives queries from town-dwelling Arapesh people interested in the
                Arapesh Grammar and Digital Language Archive (AGDLA). ELAR depositors sometimes
                specify that access to their deposit requires community approval; the Archive of the
                Indigenous Languages of Latin America (AILLA) sets up ‘community controlled’ as a
                systematic level of access (though at present this must be mediated through the
                institution). Increasingly, we can expect archives to be routinely receiving user
                account applications from individuals who were either directly involved as research
                participants or who have ancestors, family members, friends, or community associates
                who were involved in language documentation projects. But at present there is a
                clear disconnect between what depositors are able to achieve using the tools and
                systems provided by archives, and what community members are able to do – especially
                those with limited internet access.    </p>
            <p>Some digital language archives recognize these problems and are seeking to overcome
                them. Edward Garrett of ELAR has been experimenting with social networking
                technologies such as the open-source Drupal Content Management System in order to
                make their archive more user-centered; a desire to extend the ELAR system to include
                community members is one of the motivations for our meeting. The project BOLD-PNG
                (see <ref target="http://www.boldpng.info/home" type="external">http://www.boldpng.info/home</ref>) has begun putting digital recording equipment
                into the hands of community members in Papua New Guinea and training them in
                techniques of basic oral language documentation, giving people the resources to
                become data collectors, if not depositors. Kimberly Christen’s Mukurtu platform was
                designed to facilitate community-controlled archiving, digitally instituting
                traditional cultural protocols to manage access to archived objects (see, e.g.,
                Christen 2008). But none of these projects develops a generalizable approach to
                integrating communities without internet access in the ongoing curation of digital
                language materials they have produced.</p>
            <p>We are particularly interested in the possibilities afforded by the increasingly
                common presence of mobile communication technologies in areas where basic
                infrastructure such as electricity, running water, and even roads remain absent. In
                such areas, new social institutions involving cell phones have begun to evolve, for
                example, conventions for exchanging cell-phone minutes, or new gathering spaces
                defined by signal access. Exploiting this new form of technology, the non-profit
                organization Open Mind has developed a system called ‘Question Box’ (see
                <ref target="http://questionbox.org/about-mission" type="external">http://questionbox.org/about-mission</ref>) which allows remote communities to access
                information in critical domains such as health, agriculture, and business.  Google’s
                voice-based social media platform SayNow is being used to allow cell phone users in
                Egypt and elsewhere to leave voicemail messages that appear online immediately as
                Twitter audio feeds (<ref
                    target="http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/02/world/middleeast/02twitter.html"
              type="external">http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/02/world/middleeast/02twitter.html</ref>). We believe
                that similar methods are worth exploring as a means to creatively connect
                less-networked language communities with researchers and archives.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
            <head>References</head>

        <p><hi rend="bold">Christen, K.</hi> (2008). Archival Challenges and Digital Solutions in
            Aboriginal Australia. <hi rend="italic">SAA Archeological Recorder</hi> 8(2): 21-24.</p>
        <p><hi rend="bold">Czaykowska-Higgins, E.</hi> (2009). Research Models, Community
            Engagement, and Linguistic Fieldwork: Reflections on Working within Canadian Indigenous
            Communities. <hi rend="italic">Language Documentation and Conservation</hi> 3(1):
            15-50.</p>
        <p><hi rend="bold">Dobrin, L. M.</hi> (2008). From Linguistic Elicitation to Eliciting the
            Linguist. <hi rend="italic">Language</hi> 84: 300-324.</p>
        <p><hi rend="bold">Yamada, R.-M.</hi> (2007). Collaborative linguistic fieldwork: Practical
            application of the empowerment model. <hi rend="italic">Language documentation and
                conservati</hi><hi rend="italic">on</hi> 1(2): 257-282.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>