<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-353">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Trees of Texts – Models and methods for an updated theory of medieval text stemmatology</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Andrews, Tara Lee</name>
                    <affiliation>Katholieke Universiteit Leuven, Belgium</affiliation>
                    <email>tara.andrews@arts.kuleuven.be</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Macé, Caroline</name>
                    <affiliation>Katholieke Universiteit Leuven, Belgium</affiliation>
                    <email>caroline.mace@arts.kuleuven.be</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>The construction of a stemma codicum from the manuscript witnesses to a given text
                remains a somewhat divisive issue in philology. To a classical philologist, it is a
                necessary first step toward creating a critical edition of the text;<note>Maas 1957; Pasquali 1962; West 1973.</note> to a scholar who adheres to the principles of new
                philology, the assumptions inherent in the construction of a stemma are so
                fundamentally unsound that the exercise is pointless.<note> See, among many references on this question Cerquiglini 1989; Reeve
                    1986.</note></p>
            <p>The advent of digital philology demands a fresh look at the practice of stemmatology;
                indeed there has been a great deal of work in the past two decades on the subject,
                and in particular on the applicability of similar work from the field of
                evolutionary biology on the reconstruction of phylogenetic relationships between
                species.Among the numerous works on this subject are: <note>Cameron 1987; Howe et al. 2001;
                    Macé &amp; Baret 2006; Spencer &amp; Howe 2001.</note> More recent work has begun to overcome the
                limitations of these techniques when applied to manuscript texts, such as the
                biological assumption that no extant species is descended from another, or the
                assumption that any ancestor species has precisely two descendants, or the converse
                assumption that any descendant species has precisely one ancestor.<note>Roos &amp; Zou 2011.</note></p>
            
            <p>Despite this considerable methodological progress, the fundamental assumptions at the
                core of stemmatology have yet to be formalised, or even seriously questioned. The
                purpose of this paper is to revisit these assumptions and simplifications; to
                propose a model for the representation of texts in all their variations that is
                tractable to computational analysis; to set forth a method for the evaluation of
                stemma hypotheses with reference to text variants, and vice versa; and to discuss
                the means by which we can provide the field of stemmatology with a formal
                underpinning appropriate for the abilities that modern computational methods now
                provide us to handle vast quantities of data.</p>
           
            <div>
                <head> Modelling a text tradition</head>
                <p>The first step to computational analysis of any text tradition is to model it
                    programmatically. This act of object modelling is distinct from, and orthogonal
                    to, text encoding – the component texts may reach us in a variety of forms,
                    including TEI XML and its critical apparatus module, CSV-format alignment
                    tables, a base text and a list of variants exported from a word processor, or
                    even individual transcriptions that remain to be collated. All of these must be
                    parsed into a uniform computational object model for further programmatic
                    analysis.</p>
                <p>Our model is relatively simple, taking into account only those features of the
                    text that are computationally useful for our purposes. We define a tradition as
                    the union of all the versions of a text that exist, represented by its
                    witnesses. A collation is the heart of the tradition, representing in a unified
                    way the entire text with all its known variations. We have adapted the variant
                    graph model proposed by Schmidt and Colomb<note>Schmidt &amp; Colomb 2009.</note> for this
                    purpose. Whereas the Schmidt/Colomb model is a single graph, where readings are
                    represented along edges, ours is a pair of graphs, in which readings are
                    represented by vertices. The set of vertices is identical in both graphs; in the
                    ‘sequence’ graph, the witnesses themselves are represented as a set of paths.
                    Each witness path is directed and acyclic, taking a route through the reading
                    vertices from beginning to end, according to the order of its text. The witness
                    path may branch, if for example the text contains corrections by the original
                    scribe(s) or by later hands; the branches are labeled appropriately. If
                    transpositions are present, the graph as a whole is not directed and acyclic
                    (DAG); we have therefore found it most useful to represent transposed readings
                    as separate vertices, linked through a relationship as described below. A DAG
                    may then be trivially transformed into an alignment table, with transpositions
                    handled either as separate rows in the table or as variant characters within the
                    same row.</p>
                <p><figure><graphic url="img353-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 1: A portion of a variant graph, with directed witness paths and undirected relationships</head></figure></p>
                
                <p>The second graph concerns relationships between readings, or types of variation
                    that occur within the text. We may specify that two different readings are
                    orthographic or syntactic variants of the same root word, or that they have some
                    semantic relationship to each other. We may also specify transpositions in this
                    way. The result is an unconnected and undirected graph that adds extra
                    information to the sequence graph without compromising its properties. The
                    relationship information allows association and regularization of reading data,
                    producing thereby more exact versions of alignment tables for our statistical
                    procedures.</p>
              
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> Modelling a stemma hypothesis</head>
                <p>The goal of our research is to arrive at an empirical model of medieval text
                    transmission, and set forth a formalized means of deducing copying relationships
                    between texts. As such, we have two tasks before us. We must be able to evaluate
                    a stemma hypothesis according to the variation present in a text tradition, and
                    we must be able to evaluate variants in a tradition according to a given stemma
                    hypothesis.</p>
                <p>The problem becomes computationally tractable once we realize that a stemma
                    hypothesis is also a DAG. No matter the complexity of the stemma, no matter the
                    degree of ‘horizontal transmission’, a stemma can be represented as a connected
                    and rooted DAG, where each extant or hypothesized manuscript is a vertex, and
                    each edge describes a source relationship from one manuscript to another. (In
                    our model, any stemma has a single archetype; where multiple archetypes exist in
                    a text tradition, we must either consider a common theoretical origin for these
                    archetypes, or speak of multiple stemmata.) </p>
                <p><figure><graphic url="img353-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 2: An arbitrarily complex stemma, represented as a DAG</head></figure></p>
               
                <p>In cooperation with the Knowledge Representation and Reasoning group within the
                    KU Leuven Computer Science faculty,<note>Blockeel et al. 2012.</note> we have developed
                    a method for evaluating sets of variants against a stemma hypothesis of
                    arbitrary complexity, testing whether any particular set of variants aligns with
                    the stemma hypothesis, and measuring the relative stability of particular
                    readings (defined in terms of how often they are copied vs. how often they are
                    altered). In conjunction with the variant graphs of our text model, we are also
                    able programmatically to draw some empirical conclusions about the relationships
                    between readings as they are altered within the text.</p></div>
              
                <div>
                    <head> An empirical approach to text variation</head>
                <p>The idea of distinguishing ‘text-genealogical’ variants from the coincidental
                    sort is not new;<note>Salemans 2000. See also papers by Wachtel, van
                        Mulken, Schmid, Smelik, Schøsler, and Spencer et al in van Reenen et al. 2004.</note> with the exception of U. Schmid
                    (2004), however, none of the approaches taken have been empirical, in accordance
                    with text relationships known from outside the variant tables. Given the means
                    to quickly evaluate a stemma in detail according to the variants present in the
                    text, distinguishing those variants that follow the stemma from those that do
                    not, we should now easily be able to arrive at an empirical classification of
                    genealogically ‘significant’ and ‘insignificant’ variants. This threatens to
                    create a problem of circular logic: how to retrieve the genealogical variants in
                    the real world? We build hypotheses on the basis of variation; we accept or
                    reject variants as ‘genealogical’ based on the hypothesis. How do we break the
                    cycle?<note>See the critique of concerning the work of Salemans.</note></p>
                <p>We may adopt two approaches to anchor our methods in external results. First we
                    test our methods on artificial traditions that have been created for the testing
                    of stemmatological methods. These traditions are convenient in that the true
                    stemmata are known, but they cannot reflect the true conditions under which
                    medieval texts were copied. Thus we must also use ‘real’ text traditions, whose
                    true stemmata are not fully known; in many medieval traditions, however, some
                    paratextual information (e.g. colophon notations, physical damage or other
                    physical characteristics of the texts) survives and can be used to establish or
                    verify copying relationships. In our presentation we will discuss the results
                    obtained on three artificial traditions, and three real medieval traditions with
                    credible stemma hypotheses derived from external characteristics.</p>
               
                </div>
            <div><head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>When examining a medieval tradition, we can rarely be certain what the scribe has
                    copied in a text, and what has changed coincidentally or independently. To date,
                    stemmatic reasoning has relied on the question of whether the scholar finds it
                    likely that a given variant was preserved in copies. Given the models and
                    methods for analysis proposed herein, we have an opportunity to remove this
                    limitation of ‘assumed likelihood’ and take all the evidence of a text into
                    account, to build a statistical model independent of the constraints of
                    evolutionary biology, using statistical probability rather than scholarly
                    instinct alone.</p></div>
            
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Blockeel, H., B. Bogaerts, M. Bruynooghe, B. de Cat, S. de
                        Pooter, M. Denecker, A. Labarre, and J. Ramon</hi> (2012). Modeling Machine
                    Learning Problems with FO(·). <hi rend="italic">Submitted to the 28th
                        International Conference on Logic Programming.</hi>
                </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Cameron, H. D.</hi> (1987). The upside-down cladogram. Problems
                    in manuscript affiliation. In H. M. Hoenigswald and L. F. Wiener (eds.), <hi
                        rend="italic">Biological metaphor and cladistic classification : an
                        interdisciplinary perspective.</hi> Philadelphia: U of Pennsylvania P.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Cerquiglini, B.</hi> (1989). <hi rend="italic">Éloge de la
                        variante : histoire critique de la philologie, </hi>Paris: Éd. du Seuil.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Howe, C. J., A. C. Barbrook, M. Spencer, P. Robinson, B.
                        Bordalejo, and L. Mooney</hi> (2001). Manuscript Evolution. <hi
                        rend="italic">Trends in Genetics</hi> 17<hi rend="bold">:</hi> 147-52.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Maas, P.</hi> (1957). <hi rend="italic">Textkritik.</hi> Leipzig:
                    Teubner.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Macé, C., and P. Baret</hi> (2006). Why Phylogenetic Methods
                    Work: The Theory of Evolution and Textual Criticism. In C. Macé, P. Baret, A.
                    Bozzi, and L. Cignoni (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Evolution of Texts:
                        Confronting Stemmatological and Genetical Methods.</hi> Pisa, Rome: Istituti
                    Editoriali e Poligrafici Internazionali.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Pasquali, G.</hi> (1962). <hi rend="italic">Storia della
                        tradizione e critica del testo. </hi>Firenze: F. Le Monnier.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Reeve, M. D.</hi> (1986). Stemmatic method: ‘Qualcosa che non funziona?’ In P. F. Ganz (ed.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >The role of the book in medieval culture : proceedings of the Oxford
                            International Symposium, 26 September-1 October 1982.</hi> Turnhout:
                        Brepols.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Roos, T., and Y.
                            Zou</hi> (2011). Analysis of Textual Variation by Latent Tree
                        Structures. <hi rend="italic">IEEE International Conference on Data
                            Mining</hi>, 2011 Vancouver.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Salemans, B. J. P.</hi> (2000). <hi rend="italic">Building
                            Stemmas with the Computer in a Cladistic, Neo-Lachmannian, Way: The Case
                            of Fourteen Text Versions of Lanseloet van Denemerken.</hi> Ph.D.,
                        Katholieke Universiteit Nijmegen.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Schmid, U.</hi> (2004). Genealogy by chance! On the
                        significance of accidental variation (parallelisms). In P. T. van Reenen, A.
                        den Hollander, and M. van Mulken (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Studies in
                            Stemmatology II.</hi> Amsterdam: Benjamins.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Schmidt, D., and R. Colomb</hi> (2009). A data structure for
                    representing multi-version texts online. <hi rend="italic">International Journal
                        of Human-Computer Studies</hi> 67: 497-514.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Spencer, M., and C. J. Howe</hi> (2001). Estimating distances
                    between manuscripts based on copying errors. <hi rend="italic">Literary and
                        Linguistic Computing</hi> 16: 467-484.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">P. T. van Reenen, A. den Hollander, and M. van Mulken, eds.</hi>
                    (2004). <hi rend="italic">Studies in Stemmatology I.,</hi> Amsterdam:
                    Benjamins.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">West, M. L.</hi> (1973). <hi rend="italic">Textual Criticism and
                        Editorial Technique: Applicable to Greek and Latin Texts.</hi> Stuttgart:
                    Teubner.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>