<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-460">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Notes from the Collaboratory: An Informal Study of an Academic DH Lab in Transition</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Siemens, Lynne</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Victoria, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>siemensl@uvic.ca</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Siemens, Raymond</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Victoria, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>siemens@uvic.ca</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Digital Humanities (DH) as a discipline is highly collaborative and as such
                    requires a departure from typical humanities work patterns with its focus on the
                    lone scholar (Siemens 2009; Siemens et al. 2011). In particular, DHers must
                    develop new skills and knowledge and negotiate new ways of conducting research
                    and organizing people, financial resources, space and other factors (Scholars’
                    Lab 2011). In this regard, the Sciences and Applied Sciences can provide
                    guidance and suggest several models upon which DH can draw to achieve project
                    objectives.</p>
                <p>The Sciences use two primary models of organisation for conducting research. The
                    first model is the typical faculty-directed laboratory where the lead researcher
                    creates a research vision and hires staff to conduct the research. This
                    individual is ultimately responsible for research results, including
                    publications, patents, discoveries, and use of funds, to their department,
                    faculty, university, academic discipline, funders and others. Collaboration
                    occurs at the level of research vision execution, rather than the development of
                    that vision (Haynes et al. 2006). Ultimately, the lead researcher is evaluated
                    by traditional academic measures, including the number of articles, books,
                    patents, lines of software code, and level of grant funding (Cantwell 2011).
                    Many books and manuals are available to guide the new scientist on now to set up
                    and manage a lab, people and resources (Cohen &amp; Cohen 2005; Howard Hughes
                    Medical Institute &amp; Burroughs Wellcome Fund 2006).</p>
                <p>Alternatively, Big Sciences are using collaboratories to create ‘centres without walls’ where
                    researchers work together to create common access to data and instruments, such
                    as supercomputers, telescopes, and global history databases within an umbrella
                    research area, but do not necessarily work on the same research projects. These
                    collaborations are most successful when everyone contributes to the same degree
                    that they draw upon the common instruments and data (de Moor &amp; van Zanden
                    2008; Wulf 1993). Various studies have been conducted to evaluate the
                    productivity of these different models (Finholt 2003; Haynes et al. 2006).</p>
                <p>Alongside these well-evolved and understood models of collaboration – that is
                    those that follow patterns of the single-researcher directed ‘collaborat-ory’
                    and that of the multiple-researcher directed co-laboratory (Glasner 1996: 111) –
                    opportunities exist to create hybrid organisations and apply within the Sciences
                    and beyond to the Humanities and Social Sciences. But how do these models work
                    within DH? Can they be applied directly to DH or does this community need
                    collaborative research models that differ from those typically found in the
                    Sciences?</p>
                <p>This paper will examine the experiences of one academic DH
                    lab as it adapts these models, develops collaborative structures, meets its
                    research objectives and produces outputs that can be evaluated by traditional
                    academic measures. It will conclude with recommendations for other Digital
                    Humanists who are setting up their own labs or are collaborating on the creation
                    of new DH centres.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>A Case Study</head>
                <p>The case study focuses on the evolution a DH lab as it
                    experimented with different organisational forms to support collaboration over a
                    seven year period of growth, and three distinct stages of organisation and
                    operation. It initially operated as a single faculty-directed lab with graduate
                    research assistants, postdoctoral fellows, programmers, and others as staff in
                    its first four years. At that point, those who worked in the lab underwent a
                    research visioning exercise, the results of which suggested that a hybridised
                    ‘collaborator’ model would be the most appropriate organisational form, one that
                    would allow a fuller and more active participation of faculty, staff and
                    contractors in visioning, consensual decision-making, and leadership. Finally,
                    the lab returned to a more standard model, with a plan for more structured
                    growth in the future.</p>
                <p>Over all these transitions, the impacts of these
                    various internal operational models were tracked against standard academic and
                    funding agency benchmarks that included measurable research resource intake,
                    provision of teaching and service, and research outputs, such as books,
                    articles, conference papers, and other types of production, more DH-oriented
                    research outputs in the form of tools and prototype development, and further
                    issues – some measureable, such as documented internal and external complaints,
                    and some less so. As other labs have found, not meeting these targets can lead
                    to reduced grant funding and lack of research space (Cantwell 2011) and, so,
                    meeting such targets is directly tied to the ongoing operation of a lab.</p>
                <p>Particularly notable among the results discussed is that the lab’s
                    experimentation with a hybridised collaboratory model unintentionally introduced
                    a diffused accountability structure; many internal mechanisms and accountability
                    structures that allowed earlier successes were inadvertently removed as part of
                    the process of hybridising the two models. As a result, with the checks and
                    balances that ensured consideration of basic collaboration principles removed,
                    lab productivity by all measures fell drastically and almost-immediately, and
                    team functionality became severely handicapped. Formal accountability structures
                    themselves became viewed as contrary to collaborative principles and, without
                    those accountability structures in place, it became increasingly difficult for
                    team members to follow through on the development and implementation of project
                    plans; acts of planning became less meaningful in this context as well. Without
                    a set structure that ensured that those contributing resources and those who
                    were accountable to outside structures (Department, the Faculty, university and
                    funding agencies) enacted a leadership role, few sanctions for non-performance
                    existed (de Moor et al. 2008) and ‘free-riding’ became the chief mode of
                    interaction among staff and contractors. Further, an informal work culture
                    developed that was contrary to local and university policies as well as, in some
                    cases, funding agency guidelines; internal lab groups formed, striated,
                    clique-ified, and could not work together. This situation contributed to a
                    dramatic increase in personnel complaints.</p>
                <p>In the end, the experiment could be judged to be a failure as measured by many common benchmarks. Despite
                    attempts to fuse what the lab felt to be the most desirable features of the
                    single-researcher directed ‘collaborat-ory’ and that of the multiple-researcher
                    directed ‘co-laboratory’, the lab became neither. Upon the feedback from the
                    lab’s advisors, the research lead is moving towards [1] a return to the model of
                    the single-researcher directed ‘collaborat-ory,’ with [2] promise to implement
                    plans to become, more formally, a multiple-researcher directed ‘co-laboratory’ –
                    all the while retaining the strong internal operational structures and
                    hierarchies that were in place before the experiment.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>This case study contributes to ongoing discussions in DH about appropriate
                organization forms and accountability mechanisms (de Moor et al. 2008; Dormans &amp;
                Kok 2010; Warwick 2004) , roles, contributions, and status within projects
                (#alt-academy, 2011) , and the nature of collaboration (Siemens 2009) . It provides
                several lessons for consideration. First, Science models for collaboration and the
                creation of well-functioning labs can be applied within DH (Bland &amp; Ruffin IV
                1992; Haynes et al. 2006) . Second, some hierarchy is necessary, particularly when
                one individual is responsible for sourcing the money and other resources which
                sustains the lab. This lead researcher is accountable for these funds and ‘must have
                ultimate authority’ (Lawrence 2006; Rogers-Dilon 2005: 449). Having said this,
                    consensus and active participation in discussions around ways to achieve a lab’s
                    research direction can create an exciting and intellectually productive
                    environment and working relationships, as measured by staff satisfaction and
                    academic metrics. These roles must be backed up with clear objectives, tasks,
                    timelines and consequences for non-performance. Lastly, this case study serves
                    as a cautionary tale for new DH researchers who will be tasked with setting up
                    their own labs, managing staff and research, creating partnerships, while
                    remaining accountable to stakeholders inside and outside the university.
                </p>
                
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <head>References</head>

            <p><hi rend="bold">#alt-academy</hi> (2011). #alt-academcy: A media commons project <ref
                    target="http://mediacommons.futureofthebook.org/alt-ac/" type="external"
                >http://mediacommons.futureofthebook.org/alt-ac/</ref> [November 1, 2011].</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Bland, C. J., and M. T. Ruffin IV</hi> (1992). Characteristics of a
                productive research environment: Literature review. <hi rend="italic">Academic
                    Medicin, </hi>67(6): 385-397.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Cantwell, B.</hi> (2011). Academic in-sourcing: International
                postdoctoral employment and new modes of academic production. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Journal of Higher Education Policy &amp; Management </hi>33(2): 101-114.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Cohen, C. M., and S. L. Cohen</hi> (2005). <hi rend="italic">Lab
                    dynamics: Management skills for scientists</hi>. Cold Spring Harbor, New York:
                Cold Spring Habor Laboratory Press.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">de Moor, T., and J. L. van Zanden</hi> (2008). Do ut des (i give so
                that you give back): Collaboratories as a new method for scholarly communication and
                cooperation for global history. <hi rend="italic">Historical Methods </hi>41(2):
                67-80.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Dormans, S., and J. Kok</hi> (2010). An alternative approach to large
                historical databases. <hi rend="italic">Historical Methods </hi>43(3), 97-107.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Finholt, T. A.</hi> (2003). Collaboratories as a new form of
                scientific organization. <hi rend="italic">Economics of Innovation and New
                    Technology </hi>12(1): 5-25.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Glasner, P.</hi> (1996). From community to ‘collaboratory’? The human
                genome project and the changing culture of science. <hi rend="italic">Science and
                    Public Policy </hi>23(2): 109-116.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Haynes, L., S. Pfeffer, J. M. Boss, et al.</hi> (2006). Lab
                    management: Insights for the new investigator. <hi rend="italic">Nature
                        Immunology </hi>7(9), 895-897.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Howard Hughes Medical Institute &amp; Burroughs Wellcome Fund</hi>
                (2006). <hi rend="italic">Making the right moves: A practical guide to scientific
                    management for postdocs and new faculty</hi> (2nd ed.). Research Triangle Park,
                North Carolina: Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Burroughs Wellcome Fund.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Lawrence, K. A.</hi> (2006). Walking the tightrope: The balancing
                acts of a large e-research project. <hi rend="italic">Computer Supported Cooperative
                    Work: The Journal of Collaborative Computing </hi>15(4): 385-411.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Rogers-Dilon, R. H.</hi> (2005). Hierarchical qualitative research
                teams: Refining the methodology. <hi rend="italic">Qualitative Research </hi>5(4):
                437-454.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Scholars’ Lab</hi> (2011). The praxis program at the scholars’ lab
                    <ref target="http://praxis.scholarslab.org/" type="external">http://praxis.scholarslab.org/</ref>
                [September 12, 2011].</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Siemens, L.</hi> (2009). It’s a team if you use ‘Reply all’: An
                exploration of research teams in digital humanities environments. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing </hi>24(2): 225-233.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Siemens, L., R. Cunningham, W. Duff, et al.</hi> (2011). A tale of
                two cities: Implications of the similarities and differences in collaborative
                approaches within the digital libraries and digital humanities communities. <hi
                    rend="italic">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing </hi>26(3): 335-348.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Warwick, C.</hi> (2004). ‘No such thing as humanities computing?’ An
                analytical history of digital resource creation and computing in the humanities.<hi
                    rend="italic"> Paper presented at the Joint International Conference of the
                    Association for Computers and the Humanities and the Association for Literary
                    &amp; Linguistic Computing</hi>.
                tapor.humanities.mcmaster.ca/html/Nosuchthing_1.pdf [May 25, 2006].</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Wulf, W.</hi> (1993). <hi rend="italic">National collaboratories:
                    Applying information technology for scientific research</hi>. Washington, DC:
                National Academies Press.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>