<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-507">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>From Preserving Language Resources to Serving Language Speakers: New Prospects for Endangered Languages Archives</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Nathan, David John</name>
                    <affiliation>SOAS, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>djn@soas.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>This paper will describe seismic shifts that are
                    currently taking place in the field of endangered languages archiving, drawing
                    on research and implementation at the Endangered Languages Archive, together
                    with developments among other innovative archives reported at a recent workshop
                        <hi rend="italic">Language Documentation and Archiving</hi>. Endangered
                    languages archives, a new type of facility of which several have sprung up over
                    the last 15 years, have brought new considerations into account:</p>
                <xmt:uList>
                <item>endangered languages materials are predominantly in the language
                    documentation genre, newly created through fieldwork conducted in areas where
                    languages are threatened</item>
                <item>such language documentation material consists initially, fundamentally,
                            and crucially of media recordings (audio and video) of spontaneous,
                            naturalistic language use such as conversation (Himmelmann 1998)</item>
                <item>due to the nature and contexts of communities whose languages are
                            endangered, the identities of speakers and the content of their
                            recordings can be sensitive, so that nuanced access protocols must be
                            designed and implemented.</item>
                </xmt:uList>
                
                <p>These considerations have brought new types of participants into engagement with
                    each other, some for the first time. Linguists are now found to be working at
                    one moment with members of remote communities and soon after with audio-video
                    specialists, archive technicians, and even journalists and filmmakers. Over the
                    last decade, some researchers have advocated for more direct community
                    participation (e.g., Grinevald 2003), and some archives have steadily built up
                    trust relationships with communities. However, the field has generally remained
                    in a ‘steady state’, emphasising language as data and building infrastructure
                    for research interoperability, in a ‘language resources’ approach.</p>
                <p>Now, the situation is suddenly changing, largely as a result of shifting
                    expectations amongst language community members. Following projects funded by
                    DoBeS<note>Dokumentation bedrohter Sprachen, funded by the Volkswagen Foundation. <ref target="http://www.mpi.nl/DOBES" type="external">http://www.mpi.nl/DOBES</ref>.</note>, 
                    ELDP,<note>Endangered Languages Documentation Programme, SOAS, funded by the Arcadia Fund. <ref target="http://www.hrelp.org/" type="external">http://www.hrelp.org/</ref>.</note> 
                    and DEL,<note>Documenting Endangered Languages, National Endowment for the Humanities. <ref target="http://www.neh.gov/grants/guidelines/del.html" type="external">http://www.neh.gov/grants/guidelines/del.html</ref></note> more members of communities have been exposed to
                    language documentation and become aware not only of its potential but also of
                    its methods. Digital technologies central to language documentation – media
                    devices (including mobile phones), computers, and the World Wide Web – are
                    rapidly becoming available to people in language endangerment ‘hotspots’, such
                    as in much of Africa, Asia and South America. The shift has been precipitated by
                    growing expectations of participation, control, and personal and local
                    relevance, fostered by social networking platforms such as Facebook, Orkut,
                    YouTube and Twitter. In fact, many communities are first experiencing the
                    internet through these platforms and see the web as a more social, participatory
                    and personally relevant space than those who were ‘first generation’ netizens.</p>
                <p>While many communities are keen to participate in the new media landscape
                    (deliberately or incidentally as new providers of language documentation), the
                    challenge is to reconcile their contributions with the structures and policies
                    of archives. Mechanisms need to be created and monitored to determine if
                    increased access to a variety of naturalistic language recordings creates more
                    value for their audiences than is lost through perceived methodological
                    limitations in data collection (Trilsbeek &amp; König 2011). Despite the
                    potential problems of crowdsourcing, it provides a way for language speakers to
                    establish real links with resources, rather than being merely ‘participant
                    metadata’. Here is an example: the web is currently trending towards mash-up
                    pages, mobile ‘apps’, and aggregating portals. These gather resources based on a
                    particular user’s preferences, and display them according to topic, geographic
                    location, or language. But what happens when that user wants to view information
                    connected to a specific person, say language speaker X? Unless speaker X is a
                    true participant in the digital platform as a member, owner, or even curator,
                    rather than a mere meta-data-point, then such a speaker-centred page will be an
                    incomplete and insipid representation, with weak implementation of access
                    control because nobody except speaker X can properly decide who he/she wants to
                    share with. We are fortunate, therefore, to see the maturation and continual
                    rise of online and mobile social networking and innovative ‘apps’ which
                    personalise individuals’ interactions, provide further exemplars for
                    implementing participatory models, and organically solve protocol problems
                    through individually-managed access control.</p>
                <p>Mary Linn (2011), for example, has proposed a framework called Community Based
                    Language Archiving, in which the language community is involved in every step,
                    from documentation planning to curating to dissemination. It turns traditional
                    archiving on its head, because the primary curatorial task, namely
                    contextualisation, becomes about the context of <hi rend="italic">the users
                        themselves</hi>, because it is they (especially as community members newly
                    welcomed into the archive ecology) who ultimately determine the success of
                    archives in meeting their goals.</p>
                <p>Other proposals are for decentralised, web-based functions that allow language
                    speakers to interact with archives’ existing resources. They can add further
                    materials, comments, or contextualisation. They can identify themselves or their
                    relatives in order to claim their moral rights in recordings and other
                    materials, and make corrections to erroneous data, interpretations, and
                    attributions (Garrett 2011).</p>
                <p>Existing archivists also need to regain participatory roles. The era of the
                    engineer as the pace-setter is giving way to usage-driven design and evolution,
                    catering for the shifting interests of users. Archivists, whose job entails
                    understanding their audiences, can contribute not only to contextualisation of
                    materials and curation of exhibitions etc but also to software design issues.</p>
                <p>Participants at a workshop on language documentation and archiving (Nathan ed.
                    2011) came up with a number of emerging trends that can be expected to be
                    increasingly influential dynamics for our archives:</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Form of documentation:</hi> Despite extensive theorisation of
                    documentation in previous work, there has been little discussion of the <hi
                        rend="italic">form</hi> of documentation: its granularity, structure,
                    organisation, links, and how it is to be navigated. Archives which attempt to
                    provide attractive and usable interfaces that encourage user engagement will
                    find themselves frustrated with current models for language documentation, which
                    still see documentation as consisting of unstructured collections of data. New
                    genres of expression will be needed, and these will result from collaborative
                    efforts among documenters, archives, and contributors and users.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Community curation and contextualisation:</hi> ‘Community
                    curation’ represents a paradigm-changing challenge, changing roles within
                    archives. The original contributors and their language-learning community
                    members become the principal curators, presenting a radical but rational
                    inversion: the archive concept of ‘context’ is no longer that of the materials
                    or their (supposed) provenance, but of the <hi rend="italic">users, </hi>where
                    users are often the language speakers. Contextualisation of materials is at the
                    heart of archiving, but in many of our current archives, the art of
                    contextualisation has been replaced by the science of software development.
                    However, communities may wish to play a role in framing the interpretation of
                        <hi rend="italic">their</hi> materials to <hi rend="italic">others</hi> (cf.
                    Christen 2011: 197). Similarly, community access to materials is not reducible
                    to file transfer, but entails access to <hi rend="italic">meaning</hi> (Christen
                    2011: 194). Issues of quality control (Trilsbeek &amp; König 2011) become just
                    one of many elements to be renegotiated between technical ‘best practices’ and
                    community aspirations and activities.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Promotion:</hi> Archives need to do more than acquire, curate,
                    preserve and disseminate materials. To reach target audiences for language
                    revitalisation, archives also need to actively <hi rend="italic">promote</hi>
                    the materials they hold (Wilbur 2011; Woodbury 2011). Archives need to develop
                    relationships with their audiences that are not based purely on access to
                    language materials, for the success of archive outreach may depend on first
                    developing contact, relationships and trust in order to encourage usage or other
                    participation with the materials. Ultimately, social networking provides
                    promotion through social endorsement.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Publishing:</hi> Paradoxically, even as archives seem to become
                    fragmented and fluid as they respond to audience participation, they will come
                    to be seen less as archives and more as publishers, due to their increased
                    attention to genre, exhibitions, promotion, and other outreach.</p>
                <p>Endangered languages archives are an essential component of ethical and
                    effective responses to language endangerment. However, the ‘language resources’
                    approach is giving way to a participatory one, because neither the quality of
                    documentary materials, nor the effectiveness of technologies are meaningfully
                    measurable without considering audiences and usages. Full engagement with
                    language speakers through social networking will provide new sources of data for
                    researchers as well as new forms of cultural repatriation for communities, and
                    new ways of supporting threatened languages. </p>
                
            </div>
        </body>
        <back><div>
                <head>References</head>

            <p><hi rend="bold">Christen, K.</hi> (2011). Opening archives: Respectful Repatriation.
                    <hi rend="italic">American Archivist</hi> 74(1): 185-210.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Garrett, E.</hi> (2011). Web software for participant-driven language
                archiving. In D. Nathan, David (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of Workshop on
                    Language Documentation and Archiving</hi>. London: SOAS, pp. 71-72.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Grinevald, C.</hi> (2003). Speakers and documentation of endangered
                languages. In P. K. Austin (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Language Documentation and
                    Description</hi> 1: 52-71.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Himmelmann, N.</hi> (1998). Documentary and Descriptive Linguistics.
                    <hi rend="italic">Linguistics </hi>36: 161-195.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Linn, M. S.</hi> (2011). Living archives: A community-based language
                archive model. In D. Nathan (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of Workshop on
                    Language Documentation and Archiving</hi>. London: SOAS, pp. 59-70.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Nathan, D., ed.</hi> (2011). <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of
                    Workshop on Language Documentation and Archiving</hi>. London: SOAS.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Trilsbeek, P., and A. König</hi> (2011). Increasing the usage of
                endangered languages archives in the years to come. In D. Nathan (ed.), <hi
                    rend="italic">Proceedings of Workshop on Language Documentation and
                    Archiving</hi>. London: SOAS, pp. 45-49.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Wilbur, J.</hi> (2011). Think globally, archive locally:
                Opportunities and challenges in working with local archiving institutions. In D
                Nathan (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of Workshop on Language Documentation
                    and Archiving</hi>. London: SOAS, pp. 51-58.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Woodbury, A.</hi> (2011). Archives and audiences: toward making
                endangered language documentations people can read, use, understand, and admire. In
                D. Nathan (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of Workshop on Language Documentation
                    and Archiving</hi>. London: SOAS, pp. 11-20.</p>
        </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>