<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Poetic Prosthetics</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Queen's University</name>, Canada <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Michael</forename>
                        <surname>Levison</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Queen's University</name>, Canada <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Computational / Corpus Linguistics</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>1. Introduction</head>
                    <p>One of Chomsky's early distinctions separated 'rule-governed creativity' and
                        'rule-changing creativity'. In the first, applications of a rule within a
                        formal system produce new output, while in the second, some mechanism is
                        used to change the set of rules themselves. While the overall concept of
                        language as a rule-governed creative system has now gained general currency
                        in linguistics, the distinction itself has found less favour. One group,
                        however, which has used the concept, if not the term, is OuLiPo, the
                        'Ouvroir de Littérature Potentielle' (Potential Literature Working Group), a
                        group of French poets, novelists and mathematicians which for the past
                        several decades has dedicated itself to the exploration of constraints as a
                        device for enhancing poeticity. Most notable among them have been authors
                        like Raymond Queneau and Georges Perec. Two well-known examples of their
                        work are 'Cent mille milliards de poèmes' (One hundred billion poems) by
                        Queneau, which uses sheets of substitutable lines of a sonnet to produce 10
                        to the 14th power individual poems, and 'La Disparition' (The Disappearance)
                        by Perec, a 300 plus page novel in which the letter e never appears. (See
                        references for details.)</p>
                    <p>More generally, OuLiPo has set as its goal the formulation and
                        exemplification of a wide range of formal constraints which may be used to
                        enhance and enrich poetic production. In what follows, we will survey some
                        of the basic types of constraints. We will then show how some of these
                        constraints may be embodied in a natural language generation system. The
                        goal will be to illustrate how such a system may provide a prosthetic
                        extension to humans' ability to exhaustively draw out the implications of a
                        particular rule. Finally, we will show how such a system may also be used to
                        modify the constraints themselves.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2. A brief overview of some OuLiPo constructs</head>
                    <p>The operations described in OuLiPo texts may apply at all linguistic levels,
                        from phonemes, to letters, to words, sentences and texts. On the systemic
                        level, they include addition and subtraction of elements and restriction of
                        choices, while on the serial level they include concatenation and
                        permutation. Operations may be purely formal, or involve semantics as well.
                        Finally, the elements involved may be comparable or disparate. Let us
                        consider some examples:</p>
                    <div>
                        <head>Phonemes or letters</head>
                        <list type="bulleted">
                            <item><emph rend="underscore">Lipograms:</emph> texts in which one or
                                more letters is/are lacking (La Disparition, for example)</item>
                            <item><emph rend="underscore">Shared initial letter:</emph> le chat, le
                                chien, le chameau, ... for example, where all words in the list are
                                based on the orthographic constraint</item>
                            <item><emph rend="underscore">Sequences of letters:</emph> les agents,
                                les ballons, les cambrioleurs... for example</item>
                            <item><emph rend="underscore">Anagrams:</emph> for example, the various
                                permutations of a word such as 'rose', including 'eros'</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Lexical level:</head>
                        <list type="bulleted">
                            <item><emph rend="underscore">Synonymy:</emph> production of a text
                                followed by systematic replacement of an initial lexical choice by a
                                synonym</item>
                            <item><emph rend="underscore">S + 7:</emph> replacement of each noun in
                                a text by the seventh following noun in the dictionary</item>
                            <item><emph rend="underscore">Word formation:</emph> for example,
                                Raymond Queneau takes as a starting point the word 'dèvisager' (to
                                stare someone in the face - le visage) and replaces this particular
                                body part by two others: 'poitrine' (the chest) and 'jambe' (the
                                leg) to create the new words 'dèpoitriner' (to stare someone in the
                                chest) and 'dèjamber' (to stare someone in the leg). There is also
                                an ironic secondary sense of 'removal of a body part'.</item>
                            <item><emph rend="underscore">Word contamination:</emph> for example,
                                Queneau blends 'formation' (training) and 'sillon' (furrow or
                                groove) to produce 'formasillon', with its ironic identification of
                                training and the straight and narrow path.</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Syntactic level:</head>
                        <list type="bulleted">
                            <item><emph rend="underscore">Homosyntactic structures:</emph>
                                repetition of the same syntactic frame. La Disparition contains many
                                series of the sort, for example:<list type="bulleted">
                                    <item>L'Alhambra brûlait, l'Institut fumait, l'Hôpital
                                        Saint-Louis flambait. (The Alhambra burned, the Institute
                                        smoked, Saint-Louis Hospital flamed.)</item>
                                    <item>l'iris malin d'un cachalot colossal, narguant Jonas,
                                        clouant Cain, fascinant Achab. (the evil iris of an enormous
                                        sperm whale, mocking Jonas, striking Cain, fascinating
                                        Ahab)</item>
                                    <item>Suicida-t-il? Appuya-t-il un canon sur son zygoma?
                                        S'ouvrait-il au rasoir dans un bain chaud? Avala-t-il un bol
                                        d'acqua-toffana? Lança-t-il son auto dans un trou sans fond
                                        tourbillonnant sans fin jusqu'au soir du Grand Jour,
                                        jusqu'au jour du Grand Soir? (Did he commit suicide? Did he
                                        put a barrel to his zygoma? Did he open his veins in a hot
                                        bath? Did he swallow a bowl of acqua-toffana? Did he drive
                                        his car into a bottomless pit which swirled without end
                                        until the evening of The Day, or the day of The
                                        Evening?)</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3. Formalisation and generation of constructs</head>
                    <p>The examples described above are formalisable, but they have been generated
                        by humans, using their intuition at a particular point in space and time.
                        From the computational perspective, it is interesting to ask to what extent
                        the computer may provide us with a prosthetic device to exhaustively explore
                        the consequences of a particular construct. In this vein, we have used the
                        VINCI generation environment to model examples such as those above.</p>
                    <p>Briefly, VINCI is a collection of metalanguages which allows a linguist to
                        specify grammatical information, and an interpreter which produces
                        utterances based on the specification provided. It includes the following components:<list>
                            <item>a. Context-free phrase structure rules for specifying sequences.
                                These include terminals (N, V, etc.) and attributes (masc, human,
                                etc.). Output is in the form of structured trees. Generation of
                                successive levels may be controlled by the characteristics of the
                                parent level.</item>
                            <item>b.Transformation rules, which allow systematic modification of
                                initial trees.</item>
                            <item>c. A lexicon, including semantic information, formal
                                characteristics, and pointers to related forms (synonyms, antonyms,
                                etc.)</item>
                            <item>d. Word-formation rules, which may be applied either globally to
                                an entire lexicon, or dynamically.</item>
                            <item>e. Morphology rules, for inflexion.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Lessard and Levison (1995) and Levison and Lessard (1995) provide additional
                        details.</p>
                    <p>Most of the preceding examples can be captured by the VINCI formalism.</p>
                    <p>
                        <emph rend="underscore">Shared initial letter</emph>
                    </p>
                    <p>The following rule produces a sequence of masculine singular noun phrases,
                        where each noun begins with the letter 'm'.</p>
                    <eg rend="block">SN = DET[masc,sing,déf] N[masc,sing]/ "m*" </eg>
                    <p>Sample output includes:<lb/><eg rend="block">le moyen, le maillot, le malheureux, le
                            moment, le mètre, le mal</eg></p>
                    <p>
                        <emph rend="underscore">Lipograms in e</emph>
                    </p>
                    <p>These are more complex, since they require several steps, including a
                        pre-sorting of the lexicon, to remove words containing 'e' internally, as
                        well as those words whose morphology rule adds an 'e' (cf. grand - grande).
                        An additional step can include a device for choosing words which begin with
                        a vowel, thereby allowing the masculine article (cf. l'ami), or which are
                        feminine singular (la condition). The following simple rule illustrates a
                        specification of a small part of this:<lb/> 
                        <eg>SN =
                            
                            {Masculine singular human nouns starting in 'a'} ( DET[masc, sing] N[masc, sing, humain]/ "a*" ADJ[masc, sing, humain]
                            
                            | {or}
                            
                            {Feminine singular human nouns followed by adjectives whose feminin is identical to the masculine form ($13) thus avoiding 'e'} DET[fém, sing] N[fém, sing, humain] ADJ[fém, sing, humain]/$13
                            
                            | {or} {etc. etc.}
                            
                            Sample output includes:
                            
                            l'ami obscur, l'amant amusant, l'avocat assis, la condition citron
                            
                            S+7</eg></p>
                            
                            <p>This can be achieved by pre-processing the lexicon so that each noun points to its seventh successor. A transformation can then be applied which replaces each noun by the word pointed to. If the pointers are in lexical field 13 with tag s7, we may write:<lb/>
                            
                            <eg>ROOT = S7 : SN
                            
                            SN = choose Ge : Genre, No : Nombre; DET[Ge,No] N[Ge,No]
                            
                            S7 = TRANSFORMATION DET N : 1 2/ @13:s7</eg>
                       </p>
                    <p>For the sake of clarity, we ignore a possible gender change.</p>
                    <p><emph rend="underscore">Word formation</emph></p>
                    <p>VINCI possesses a rich set of devices for forming new words. For example,
                        given the example 'dèvisager' described above, the following rule
                        systematically searches a lexicon for nouns having the semantic trait
                        'partieducorps' (bodypart) and produces appropriate output:<lb/>
                        <eg>"*e"|N|partieducorps.suj|?|?|?| _makes_ ["dé" + #1 + "r"]|V| | | | | %
                        </eg><lb/>dévisager déventrer détêter dépoitriner dépatter déorganer
                        déoreiller démembrer délanguer délèvrer déjouer déjamber dégorger défoier
                        défacer déboucher débarber déailer déépauler</p>
                    <p>Again, we have left the rule underspecified. Additional steps are required to
                        add an -s before nouns beginning with a vowel.</p>
                    <p><emph rend="underscore">Homosyntactic structures</emph></p>
                    <p>It is clear that all the previous rules can be used iteratively to produce
                        multiple occurrences of the same syntactic structure.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>4. Meta-generation</head>
                    <p>In the cases discussed above, the goal has been to generate utterances based
                        on grammatical descriptions, the rationale being that humans are less good
                        than computers at exhaustively enumerating the products of a grammatical
                        rule. It is however possible to carry the process one step further. Since
                        VINCI grammatical specifications are themselves only text files, it is
                        possible to use VINCI itself to generate grammatical rules which in turn
                        generate new utterances. The advantage of such an approach comes in cases
                        where the computer can be made to generate a large number of potential new
                        rules, each of which generates a large number of possible products. The
                        result can be to cause the human to see previously unthought-of rule
                        possibilities.</p>
                    <p>To illustrate this, consider the following problem. Languages like French
                        (and English) allow for multiple prefixes to be added to a base form. For
                        example, Queneau uses the word 'archidyssymètrique', which has two prefixes,
                        while a form like 'non-anti-defoliant' is a possible English form. One way
                        of capturing such possibilities would be to enumerate all rule combinations
                        by hand. This would be tedious and prone to error. A better alternative
                        would be to allow a meta-rule to generate a large number of possible
                        prefixation rules and then to use these to produce typical examples. For
                        example, consider the following meta-rules:<lb/>
                        <eg>MANYPREFIXES = (PREFIX: MANYPREFIXES | PREFIX )
                            PREFIX = (PREFIX_NON | PREFIX_RE | ...)
                            ROOT = (MANYPREFIXES: N | MANYPREFIXES: V | MANYPREFIXES : ADJ )
                            
                            where PREFIX_NON etc. are transformations.
                            
                            When applied, these meta-rules produce grammatical rules like:
                            
                            ROOT = PREFIX_NON : N
                            ROOT = PREFIX_NON : PREFIX_RE : V
                            ROOT = PREFIX_RE : PREFIX_NON : ADJ
                            ROOT = PREFIX_NON : PREFIX_NON : PREFIX_RE : ... V </eg>
                        <lb/>and so on, which in turn can be used to generate actual
                        utterances. Obviously, additional elements would be required to control more
                        precisely the nature of the prefixes, but the essential principle should be
                        clear.</p>
                    <p>An intermediate step is also possible, in which VINCI hands control
                        temporarily back to a user. So, for example, a researcher might have put in
                        front of him or her a partially developed meta-rule and be asked to insert
                        particular values. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>5. Conclusions</head>
                    <p>We assume, with OuLiPo, that poeticity hinges at least partially on dynamic
                        playing with constraints. Similarly, we have as a premise that at least some
                        aspects of inspiration or creativity involve finding previously unseen
                        patterns. Given these premises, a device which puts potential patterns
                        before us (which prosthetically increases our power to envisage new devices)
                        is of interest.</p>
                    <p>In the proposed paper, we will illustrate these assumptions with a richer
                        range of examples and with a more detailed discussion of the theoretical
                        issues which underpin them.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <biblStruct type="book">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <name>
                                <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                <surname>Bens</surname>
                            </name>
                        </author>
                        <title level="m">OuLiPo 1960-1963</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Christian Bourgeois</publisher>
                            <date when="1980">1980</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct type="book">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <name>
                                <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                <surname>Bergens</surname>
                            </name>
                        </author>
                        <title level="m">Raymond Queneau</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Genève</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Droz</publisher>
                            <date when="1963">1963</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><name><forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                <surname>Lessard</surname></name></author>
                        <author><name><forename type="first">M</forename>
                                <surname>Levison</surname></name></author>
                        <title level="a">Le logiciel VINCI: lexigrammaire et génération
                            automatique</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <editor>
                            <name>
                                <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                <surname>Labelle</surname>
                            </name>
                        </editor>
                        <title level="m">Lexiques-grammaires comparès et traitements
                            automatiques</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace/>
                            <publisher>Université du Québec à Montréal</publisher>
                            <date when="1995">1995</date>
                            <biblScope type="pp">175-185</biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                    <analytic>
                        <author><name><forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                <surname>Levison</surname></name></author>
                        <author><name><forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                <surname>Lessard</surname></name></author>
                        <title level="a">New Words from Old: A Formalism for Word Formation</title>
                    </analytic>
                    <monogr>
                        <title level="j">Computers and the Humanities </title>
                        <imprint>
                            <biblScope type="vol">29</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="issue"/>
                            <biblScope type="pp">463-479</biblScope>
                            <date when="1995">1995</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct type="book">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <name type="org">OuLiPo</name>
                        </author>
                        <title level="m">Atlas de littérature potentielle</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Gallimard</publisher>
                            <date when="1981">1981</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct type="book">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <name type="org">OuLiPo</name>
                        </author>
                        <title level="m">La bibliothèque oulipienne</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Slatkine</publisher>
                            <date when="1981">1981</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct type="book">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <name>
                                <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                <surname>Perec</surname>
                            </name>
                        </author>
                        <title level="m">La Disparition</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Denoel</publisher>
                            <date when="1969">1969</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct type="book">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <name>
                                <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                <surname>Queneau</surname>
                            </name>
                        </author>
                        <title level="m">Oeuvres complètes</title>
                        <edition>Edition établie par Cl. Debon</edition>
                        <imprint>
                            <biblScope type="pp">tome I</biblScope>
                            <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Gallimard</publisher>
                            <date when="1989">1989</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <biblStruct type="book">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>
                            <name>
                                <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                <surname>Queneau</surname>
                            </name>
                        </author>
                        <title level="m">Chêne et chien</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Gallimard</publisher>
                            <date when="1969">1969</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
