<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">On Mock-scholarly, Faux-casual, and Cod Philosophy:
                    Patterns of Diachronic Change in a British Newspaper</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">Harald</forename>
                        <surname>Baayen</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Nijmegen</name>, The Netherlands <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Antoinette</forename>
                        <surname>Renouf</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Liverpool</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Stylistics</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>In British newspapers, various 'vogue' prefix-like forms regularly appear
                        (Renouf &amp; Baayen, 1998; see also Baayen &amp; Renouf, 1996, for standard
                        affixation). This study considers three such forms: MOCK, COD, and FAUX.
                        These forms are primarily used to modify nouns, as in <lb/>
                        <eg>(1) he explodes in mock-outrage chain belts, studded with faux gems
                            around the hips a quick snipe at the cod-mysticism </eg>
                        <lb/> and to modify adjectives, as in <lb/>
                        <eg>(2) a charmingly mock modest touch coming back on stage, faux sheepish a
                            Russian night club - cod-glamorous </eg>
                        <lb/> Occasionally, one finds instances of adverbial modification, <lb/>
                        <eg>(3) Rabelais at his most mock heroically cloacal ordered him out of the
                            house, faux-crossly </eg>
                        <lb/> and for MOCK, examples also exist of verbal modification:<lb/>
                        <eg>(4) he mock bows, gallantly he has to mock-apologise for his tedious
                            bleating </eg>
                    </p>
                    <p>This study addresses the productivity of MOCK, COD, and FAUX by investigating
                        their use in a British newspaper, The Independent, from a diachronic
                        perspective. To this end, we extracted all occurrences of these forms from a
                        corpus of this newspaper, compiled from 1988 onwards, and currently
                        containing some 360 million word forms. For each of the years 1989-1998, we
                        measured the type and token frequencies of these words in 4 successive
                        3-month chunks. For 1988, the last 3-month chunk was also taken into
                        account. The questions to be addressed are whether changes in the frequency
                        with which these vogue forms are used across time can be observed, and
                        whether the forms with a hyphen (as in FAUX-SHABBY) reveal different
                        patterns from the forms without a hyphen (as in FAUX SHEEPISH), which would
                        suggest that syntactic context would co-determine the productivity of these
                        combining forms.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Results</head>
                    <p>Figure 1 will summarize the results obtained. The solid lines and the dots
                        represent the numbers of tokens counted for the successive chunks. The
                        dashed lines represent the numbers of new types observed across sampling
                        time. Both line types were obtained using a non-parametric regression
                        smoother (Cleveland, 1979). For reasons of space, we defer discussion of the
                        type counts to the presentation at the conference. The left panels represent
                        the forms without a hyphen, the right panels the forms with the hyphen.</p>
                    <p>The top panels of Figure 1 show the results obtained for MOCK and MOCK-. The
                        left panel reveals a slow but steady increase for the token counts (r =
                        0.388, t(39) = 2.6294, p = .0122). The right panel suggests that the use of
                        MOCK- did not change in the last 10 years (r = 0.194, t(39) = 1.237, p =
                        .2234). A closer investigation of the MOCK data revealed that the increase
                        in the number of tokens is primarily carried by the lowest-frequency types -
                        the highest-frequency types have a relatively stable use across the years. </p>
                    <p>The central panels of Figure 1 concern COD (left) and COD- (right). For both
                        forms, we observe a reliable increase over time, which appears to be more
                        linear for COD- (r = 0.656, t(39) = 5.437, p = .0000) than for COD (r =
                        0.473, t(39) = 3.357, p = .0018). For both COD and COD-, an autocorrelation
                        analysis suggests a reliable correlation at short lags, suggesting that the
                        extent to which a form is used in a given month is co-determined by the
                        extent to which it was popular or unpopular in the preceding months.</p>
                    <p>The bottom panels of Figure 1 suggest that FAUX and FAUX- were hardly used
                        initially, but that in the second half of the sampling period they enjoyed
                        greater productivity. Both non-parametric regression lines and parametric
                        change point analysis suggest a breakpoint around the end of 1992, after
                        which FAUX and FAUX- began to become more and more productive. What we
                        probably are witnessing here is the birth of what may eventually become a
                        fully-fledged new prefix of English.</p>
                    <p>Intriguingly, all three left panels show a (local) minimum at this point in
                        time (marked in the plots by a vertical dotted line). Possibly, the general
                        fashion for vogue modification with any of the near synonyms MOCK, COD, and
                        FAUX reached an all-time low around the end of 1992, from which both MOCK
                        and COD recovered. Note that Figure 1 shows that both forms show an increase
                        in use during the immediately following chunks. This general fashion for
                        vogue modification may have led in its wake to the upsurge in productivity
                        of FAUX and FAUX-.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Conclusions</head>
                    <p>We have observed different patterns of diachronic change through an
                        investigation of vogue modification in The Independent: a steady state
                        (MOCK-), a linear increase over time (MOCK, COD-), a slightly oscillating
                        pattern (COD), and a birth pattern (FAUX). The forms of MOCK- (with hyphen)
                        show a clearly different pattern than the forms with MOCK (without hyphen),
                        which shows that forms with and without hyphen should not be lumped together
                        a priori. The syntactic contexts that favor hyphenation (e.g., modification
                        of a prenominal noun or adjective) lead to slightly different diachronic
                        patterns. Thanks to the accumulation of large diachronic computerized
                        corpora, it is, at the end of the second millennium, finally becoming
                        possible to directly monitor ongoing language change.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                        >Harald</forename><surname>Baayen</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Antoinette</forename>
                                    <surname>Renouf</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Chronicling The Times: Productive Lexical Innovations
                                in an English Newspaper</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Language</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">72</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">69-96</biblScope>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">W.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                        >S.</forename><surname>Cleveland</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Robust locally weighted regression and smooting
                                scatterplots</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">JASA</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">74</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">829-836</biblScope>
                                <date when="1979">1979</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>

                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Antoinette</forename>
                                    <surname>Renouf</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                        >Harald</forename><surname>Baayen</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Aviating among the hapax legomena: Morphological
                                grammaticalisation in current British newspaper English</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Renouf</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Explorations in Corpus Linguistics</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Rodopi</publisher>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">181-189</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
