<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Stephen Crane and the 'New-York Tribune': a Case Study
                    in Traditional and Non-traditional Authorship Attribution</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">David</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">I.</forename>
                        <surname>Holmes</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">The College of New Jersey</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Michael</forename>
                        <surname>Robertson</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">The College of New Jersey</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>This paper presents seventeen previously unknown articles that we believe to
                        be by Stephen Crane, published in the 'New-York Tribune' between 1889 and
                        1892. The articles, printed without byline in what was at the time New York
                        City's most prestigious newspaper, report on activities in a string of
                        summer resort towns on New Jersey's northern shore. Scholars had previously
                        identified fourteen shore reports as Crane's; these newly discovered
                        articles more than double that corpus. The seventeen articles, witty and
                        often hilarious, confirm how remarkably early Stephen Crane set his
                        distinctive writing style and artistic agenda; more than a century after
                        their publication in the 'Tribune' they remain delightful reading. Stephen
                        Crane began his career as a professional writer in the summer of 1888, when
                        he was sixteen <note n="1">1. Wertheim, S. and Sorrentino, P., eds. (1988).
                                <title level="m">The Correspondence of Stephen Crane</title>. 2
                            Vols. Columbia UP, New York.</note>. His assignment was to assist his
                        brother J. Townley Crane, Jr., almost twenty years older than Stephen, who
                        had established Crane's New Jersey Coast News Bureau in 1880 when he
                        arranged to serve as correspondent for the Associated Press and the
                        'New-York Tribune'. For three-quarters of the year, Townley Crane's duties
                        must have been light, as he ferreted out news in the sparsely populated
                        shore towns of Monmouth County. However, during the summer months, the news
                        bureau's duties exploded. New York City newspapers of the1880's devoted
                        remarkable amounts of space to chronicling the summer vacations of the
                        city's upper and upper-middle classes. Every Sunday edition of most New York
                        newspapers and, during July and August, most daily editions as well, carried
                        news articles from the summer resorts popular with the more affluent
                        citizens of Gilded Age New York. The format of these articles was
                        standardized: a lead proclaimed the resort's unique beauties and the
                        unprecedented success of the current summer season, a few brief paragraphs
                        recounted recent events, such as a fund-raising carnival or the opening of a
                        new hotel, and the article concluded with a lengthy list of names of recent
                        arrivals and where they were staying. Working within the boundaries of this
                        restrictive format, Stephen Crane developed a highly original, distinctive
                        style. His shore reports are as ruthlessly ironic as 'Maggie', the novel he
                        was writing during the same period, but, instead of directing his irony
                        towards the inhabitants of the Bowery, he aimed it at the hotel proprietors
                        and summer visitors of the New Jersey shore.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Discovery And 'Traditional' Attribution</head>
                    <p>During the 1940's and 1950's, scholars familiar with Crane's style and
                        interests were able to identify several other unsigned articles in the
                        'Tribune' as his. By coincidence, all of these articles originated in three
                        adjoining towns on the Jersey shore: Asbury Park, Ocean Grove and
                        Avon-by-the-Sea. When Fredson Bowers began editing his massive volume of
                        Crane's works <note n="2">2. Bowers, F. ed. (1973). <title level="m">Tales,
                                Sketches and Reports</title>. Vol. 8 of <title level="s">The
                                University of Virginia Edition of the Works of Stephen
                            Crane</title>. UP of Virginia, Charlottesville.</note> he evidently
                        decided to limit his search for additional unsigned 'Tribune' articles by
                        Crane to reports with datelines from those three resorts. Combing the
                        'Tribune' during the summer months from 1888 to 1892, Bowers identified as
                        Crane's three articles overlooked by previous scholars, bringing the total
                        of New Jersey shore reports to fourteen. No one questioned Bowers' decision
                        to focus on the three adjoining shore communities. However, during research
                        on a book concerning Stephen Crane's journalism, we came across an item in
                        the Schoberlin collection at the Syracuse University Library that threw into
                        doubt Bowers' procedure. A one-page prospectus for Crane's New Jersey Coast
                        News Bureau was found which provided evidence of an attempt by Townley Crane
                        to expand his business. In particular, the body of the prospectus lists
                        shore towns ranging from Atlantic Highlands in the north to Seaside Park in
                        the south. With this evidence of the Crane news bureau's wide geographical
                        range, we began to question why all of the shore articles attributed to
                        Stephen originated from Asbury Park and the two towns just south of it.
                        Would it not make sense for Townley to send his teenaged brother to cover
                        news in the resorts a few miles distant from their home base of Asbury Park
                        and save himself the trouble? We searched the 'New-York Tribune' for the
                        summers of 1888 to 1892, when Stephen was fired, looking for articles with a
                        dateline from the wider base of New Jersey shore towns named in Townley
                        Crane's prospectus. The Crane brothers' writing styles are widely divergent.
                        Reading Townley's articles (written before Stephen began his journalistic
                        career), it is evident that his style is that of brief, invariably
                        flattering prose, while Stephen delighted in gleeful irony. This search
                        revealed seventeen articles datelined from the shore towns of Long Branch,
                        Belmar, Spring Lake and Sea Girt that appear to have the style of Stephen
                        Crane. Hotel proprietors, baggage handlers and "summer maidens" are all
                        written about with disdain. The articles are so stylistically distinctive in
                        their irony and verbal inventiveness that they clearly look to be from
                        Stephen's hand rather than from Townley's.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>'Non-Traditional' Attribution: Stylometry</head>
                    <p>Stylometry provides an alternative and objective analysis. The stylometric
                        task facing us was to examine the seventeen articles and attribute them to
                        either Stephen or Townley Crane. Suitable control samples in more than one
                        genre are required, so, within the genre of fiction, several textual samples
                        of about 3,000 words were obtained from 'The Red Badge of Courage' and
                        Joseph Conrad's 'The Nigger of the Narcissus', the latter being chosen
                        because we know that Crane and Conrad read and admired each other's novels.
                        For journalistic controls, we turned to Richard Harding Davis and Jacob
                        Riis, who were, along with Crane, the most prominent American journalists of
                        the 1890's. Examples of Stephen Crane's New Jersey shore reports, New York
                        City journalism, and war correspondence were taken from the University of
                        Virginia edition of Crane's work; samples of Townley Crane's journalism were
                        taken from the 'New-York Tribune'. The seventeen anonymous articles were
                        first merged, the resultant text then being split into two halves of
                        approximately 1800 words each. The "Burrows" technique <note n="3">3.
                            Burrows, J. L. (1992). "Not Unless You Ask Nicely: The Interpretive
                            Nexus Between Analysis and Information". <title level="j">Literary and
                                Linguistic Computing</title>, 7, pp. 91-109. </note>, which works
                        with large sets of frequently occurring function words, is a proven and
                        powerful tool in authorship attribution. Essentially it picks the N most
                        common words in the corpus under investigation and computes the occurrence
                        rate of these N words in each text or text-unit. Multivariate statistical
                        techniques are then applied to the resultant data to look for patterns. The
                        first phase in the investigation was designed to establish the validity of
                        the Burrows technique on the known textual samples detailed above. Using
                        principal components analysis, the Crane and Conrad fiction samples are
                        clearly distinguishable from each other. Turning to the three genres within
                        Crane's journalism, the principal components analysis on the occurrence
                        rates of non-contextual function words shows, quite remarkably, how their
                        rates of usage differ between his New York City, shore and war journalism,
                        yet remain internally consistent within these genres. A final analysis
                        incorporating the samples of journalistic writing from Townley Crane,
                        Richard Harding Davis and Jacob Riis provides further validation of the
                        Burrows method with a clear distinction visible between the shore journalism
                        of Townley Crane and Stephen Crane. Discarding the control samples, which
                        have served their purpose, we then focus on the main task, namely the
                        attribution of the seventeen anonymous articles to either Stephen or
                        Townley. Both cluster analysis and principal components analysis provide
                        mutually supportive results in attributing the anonymous articles to the
                        youthful ironist Stephen Crane. The "non-traditional" analysis has supplied
                        objective, stylometric evidence which supports the "traditional" scholarship
                        on the problem of authorship. We believe that this joint interdisciplinary
                        approach should be the way in which attributional research is conducted.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
