<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">New Models for Electronic Publishing</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Ronald</forename>
                        <surname>Tetreault</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Dalhousie University</name>, Canada <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Digital Resources</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Roger Chartier rightly warns us that reading on a computer screen is not the same as
                reading a book when he says that <cit rend="block">
                    <quote>"electronic representation of texts completely changes the text's status:
                        for the materiality of the book, it substitutes the immateriality of texts
                        without a unique location [...] in place of the immediate apprehension of
                        the whole work, made visible by the object that embodies it, it introduces a
                        lengthy navigation in textual archipelagos that have neither shores nor
                        borders"</quote>
                    <bibl>(18).</bibl>
                </cit></p>
            <p>Hence any project in the electronic medium that lays claim to scholarly authority
                will require adaptations in both the presentation and the dissemination of its
                materials. My work on developing an electronic edition of Lyrical Ballads (by
                William Wordsworth and Samuel Taylor Coleridge, 1798-1805) helps illustrate how
                these changes may be realized. Bringing such an edition before the public has made
                it clear to me that the evolution of electronic publishing will necessitate
                innovations that are not just technological but also institutional.</p>
            <p>On the technical side, Peter Shillingsburg has set out the minimum requirements for a
                scholarly electronic edition. Such works need to have 1) "a full accurate
                transcription and full digital image of each source edition," 2) "a webbing or
                networking of cross-references connecting variant texts, explanatory notes,
                contextual materials, and parallel texts," and 3) "a navigational system" so that
                readers can thread their way through this complex hypertext environment
                (Shillingsburg 28). In preparing an electronic Lyrical Ballads we have tried to meet
                these standards, first by painstakingly transcribing in text files each of the four
                lifetime editions of the collection, and by gathering together digital images of
                every page of every edition. These images will complement our e-texts by being
                presented in windows set side-by-side on the computer screen. Second, our e-texts
                will be encoded using TEI-conformant SGML to ensure the preservation of their
                complex logical structure and to enable hypertext linking that will create a webbing
                of cross-references and make possible their distribution in a networked environment.
                The scholars engaged in this project have recently formed a decided preference for
                online delivery over CD-ROM distribution. Not only is Internet dissemination more
                efficient and cost effective, it also permits easy correction of errors that are
                likely to plague any scholarly edition. More important, the fluid nature of the
                World Wide Web will allow us to take ready advantage of new standards and new forms
                of interface as they develop. We can constantly add new materials and we can explore
                new paradigms for their presentation that will help accomplish Shillingsburg's third
                goal of ready navigation through a multiplicity of variant texts. Lately our new
                method of marshalling scholarly apparatus which I have called "dynamic collation"
                has been enhanced by the addition of popup windows generated by javascript which
                preview variant readings whenever the reader passes the cursor over a revised
                passage in the electronic text. This reconceptualization of how variant readings can
                be presented in the digital medium grounds in actual practice David Greetham's
                proposition that "dismembering scholarly apparatus" will be a consequence of the
                transition to the new medium (329).</p>
            <p>The real challenge for online publication, however, is what might be called the lack
                of mature institutional structures on the Web. So long as anyone can publish
                anything on the WWW, the quality of its materials remains questionable. Certainly,
                Matthew Kirschenbaum is right to remind us that "publication entails a great deal
                more than simply the act of making public." Hitherto, some degree of authority has
                been conferred on a website by its association with an institutional host such as a
                university, as well as by the reputation of its author. But the imprimatur of an
                established publisher would be an even greater guarantee of the reliability of these
                immaterial texts. We are in the midst of negotiations that would see the electronic
                Lyrical Ballads published under the auspices of Cambridge University Press, through
                the good offices of the website of "Romantic Circles", a reputable online journal
                hosted by the University of Maryland. By reporting on the progress of these
                negotiations and their outcome, I hope to indicate ways in which both the Net and
                established publishers will need to evolve in an electronic world in order to
                guarantee standards of authority.</p>
            <p>The future of electronic publishing depends upon us asking questions about more than
                technical standards. Online scholarly archives must also meet standards of peer
                evaluation, editorial practice, and institutional approval that have traditionally
                ensured the quality of print publications.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Roger</forename>
                                    <surname>Chartier</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Forms and Meanings: Texts, Performances, and Audiences
                                from Codex to Computer</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>University of Pennsylvania Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1995">1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Greetham</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Theories of the Text</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Matthew</forename><forename
                                        type="middle"
                                    >G.</forename><surname>Kirschenbaum</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">E-dissertations?</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">Online Posting. 4 Oct. 1998. Humanist Discussion Group.
                                6 Oct. 1988</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1988">1988</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;humanist@kcl.ac.uk&gt;.</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Peter</forename>
                                    <surname>Shillingsburg</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Principles for Electronic Archives, Scholarly Editions,
                                and Tutorials</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Richard</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Finneran</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">The Literary Text in the Digital Age</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Ann Arbor</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>The University of Michigan Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">23-25</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
