<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Text Structure vs. Encoded Structure - Dealing with
                    Mixed Genres and Ambiguous Texts</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Karl</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">Johan</forename>
                        <surname>Sæth</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Oslo</name>, Norway <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Ingrid</forename>
                        <surname>Falkenberg</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Oslo</name>, Norway <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Ellen</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">Margrete</forename>
                        <surname>Nessheim</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Oslo</name>, Norway <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Stine</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">Brenna</forename>
                        <surname>Taugbøl</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Oslo</name>, Norway <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Mette</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">Gismeroy</forename>
                        <surname>Ekker</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Oslo</name>, Norway <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Text Encoding</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction:</head>
                    <p>'Henrik Ibsen's Writings' aims at producing and publishing both an electronic
                        version and a book version of all Ibsen's writings: dramas, poems, drafts,
                        letters, articles, notes. All manuscripts and editions in Norwegian/Danish
                        from the playwright's lifetime will be encoded using SGML/TEI. Our encoding
                        is rather detailed, as we wish to reproduce every text witness in full
                        accuracy.</p>
                    <p>In this paper we will examine some empirical problems which have surfaced
                        when encoding text structure and textual features in Ibsen's plays. We will
                        relate these to problems concerning how to encode the textual features in
                        Ibsen's 'Norma' (1851). Based on genre one could define this text as a
                        drama, but it could also be considered a covert article. An analytical
                        perspective on the text would expose a good mixture of different genre
                        elements. The text's physical representation, i.e. typography, shares the
                        same ambiguity. These different approaches all form different 'logical'
                        structures which overlap each other, and either approach forces us to
                        consider an unfortunate priority in the encoding. To solve these problems we
                        have looked into different solutions for encoding text structure and
                        overlapping text features. Briefly we have asked the basic questions: What
                        is text, what defines structure and other textual features, and how does
                        this affect the encoding of texts?</p>
                    <p>These questions have been much discussed within the text encoding society in
                        the past, but the approach in this paper is somewhat different from much of
                        the earlier work. We will try to examine the questions from a more practical
                        point of view, with focus on the encoding of 'Norma', and we hope that we
                        thus will be able to add a new perspective to the discussion.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Ibsen's 'Norma':</head>
                    <p>The problems of overlapping and ambiguous textual features and structures are
                        particularly manifest when one has to deal with texts with mixed features
                        which cannot easily be combined. Ibsen's 'Norma', which was written and
                        published in the newspaper 'Andhrimner' in 1851, is an example of such a
                        text. Choosing which textual features to encode in 'Norma' is not easy, as
                        it is problematic to define the text as a drama, but even more problematic
                        to define it as something else. We have chosen to regard it as a drama, but
                        several textual elements in 'Norma' are difficult to incorporate in the
                        drama structure. Particularly problematic is e.g. a 'speech' from 'the
                        curtain' (which has no reference in the cast list) typographically rendered
                        not as speech, but as a stage direction. Other problems concern footnotes
                        (both in the cast list and in the speeches), speeches in brackets that do
                        not seem to be 'asides' (asides are marked by stage directions) etc. These
                        problems, and others like them, will be presented and further discussed at
                        the conference.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Encoding Text Structure:</head>
                    <p>The nature of a text has been much discussed, in several different contexts.
                        One answer to what a text is, is that it is made of several interwoven
                        features, or content objects, which together form 'a text'. The nature of a
                        text is thus complex, and it seems difficult, or even impossible, to find a
                        single structure that 'is' the text. Some would argue that texts even seem
                        to be able to include things 'outside' themselves. Another view on the text,
                        much discussed within the text encoding society, is the claim that 'text is
                        an ordered hierarchy of content objects', the so called OHCO-thesis. This
                        claim has been thoroughly examined by Renear et al. (1993), and further
                        discussed e.g. in Biggs &amp; Huitfeld (1997). We will leave this discussion
                        aside here, and only point out that the OHCO-thesis (at least in its
                        simplest form) may be appealing from a text encoding perspective, but that
                        it is far from unproblematic.</p>
                    <p>When encoding texts one generally chooses either declarative markup languages
                        based on SGML, or its subset XML. We are using SGML/TEI, but are considering
                        moving over to XML. As Sperberg-McQueen &amp; Huitfeldt (1998) have pointed
                        out, SGML markup in its simplest forms uses a straightforward model for
                        markup: elements nest within each other so that the SGML document forms a
                        hierarchical structure. The basic model of SGML associates single
                        occurrences of features with single SGML-elements. Tagging a textual element
                        as a SGML-element of a particular type and giving it particular attribute
                        values, thus claims that this element exhibits the textual features
                        associated with that same element type and those attribute values. The
                        relationship between SGML element types and text features depends, however,
                        on the encoder's understanding and interpretation of the genre, structure
                        and perspective of the text. The encoder defines text objects in elements
                        matching the chosen hierarchical structure.</p>
                    <p>One of the large challenges for application of SGML to existing texts is
                        finding suitable representations in SGML's tree-based data model for
                        multiple hierarchies and textual features which overlap each other. Such
                        overlapping textual features seem to be an inescapable fact of textual life,
                        but present a problem in the simple SGML-model because while two textual
                        features/hierarchies may overlap, two SGML-elements may not.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Encoding Overlapping Features:</head>
                    <p>The problem of overlapping features has been discussed before. In the TEI
                        Guidelines there are several ways to overcome some of the problems: one may
                        e.g. use 'milestone' elements, in which a feature is predicated by the span
                        of text between one milestone element and the next. Other techniques rely on
                        the fragmentation of one element into multiple SGML elements and then
                        knitting the fragments into a whole; this is the method used for example in
                        the part attribute of the &lt;l&gt;-element and in the &lt;join&gt;-element.
                        There are also several possibilities permitting 'true' overlapping features.
                        Within SGML/TEI the 'concur'-feature allows a document to be marked up
                        concurrently using more than one DTD, with each tag labelled with the name
                        of the DTD to which it belongs. Other none-SGML systems include MECS
                        (Multi-Encoding-System), a system developed at the Wittgenstein Archives at
                        the University of Bergen. MECS permits any two codes to overlap, but has on
                        the other hand no specific document grammar, and therefore no SGML-alike
                        document validation is possible.</p>
                    <p>We have chosen not to use such systems in our project, as they do not seem
                        suitable for our purposes, partly because they make text encoding too
                        complex. Furthermore, encoding 'true' overlapping structures with concur,
                        MECS, or similar systems, does not really solve the problem of deciding how
                        to structure the text: you have the possibility to encode overlapping
                        features, but you still have to decide which feature(s) to encode, and even
                        which not to encode.</p>
                    <p>The boundaries of the different features are not always clear and text
                        features seem to exist both dependent and independent of each other. Our
                        project uses the first printed editions as base texts for the edition. When
                        encoding texts, we try to reproduce these texts as accurately as possible.
                        When choosing to use standard TEI, we thus have to deal with the problem of
                        encoding the textual features into hierarchical SGML-documents. This also
                        means choosing which text features to encode and which not to encode, when
                        that is necessary.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Encoding 'Norma':</head>
                    <p>In the case of 'Norma' we have ended up encoding the text as an ordinary
                        drama. The additional features of the text that do not seem to be part of a
                        'normal' drama structure, but still can easily be encoded into the drama
                        structure (e.g. footnotes and speeches in brackets), are also incorporated,
                        even though this means 'violating' the logical structure of a drama. On the
                        other hand additional features that depend on redefining the whole
                        conceptualization of dramas (e.g. speeches in stage directions) so far are
                        ignored in the encoding (but documented elsewhere, e.g. in the header of the
                        document). 'Norma' is an ambiguous text, and while we want to incorporate as
                        much as possible of this ambiguity in the encoded version of it, not all
                        ambiguity can be kept, and however the encoding is done, the encoded text
                        could possibly be ambiguous in new ways.</p>
                    <p>It may seem like a paradox that the encoding of features necessary to give
                        possibilities for electronic processing and analysis of texts, at the same
                        time includes interpretation that may restrict the use of the texts. There
                        is no simple way out of this problem, but if the interpretation in the
                        encoding is restricted at a reasonable level, the encoding can open up the
                        text more than delimit it. Renear et al. (1993) state that 'It should be a
                        commonplace that machine-readable texts are "subjective" and "interpretive",
                        but not especially subjective or interpretative.', and that encoding a text
                        in this aspect is much like making a traditional edition.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Bibliography:</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Michael</forename>
                                    <surname>Biggs</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Claus</forename>
                                    <surname>Huitfeldt</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="a">Philosophy and Electronic Publishing. Theory and
                                Metatheory in the Development of Text Encoding</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Monist</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">80</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp"/>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://hhobel.phl.univie.ac.at/mii/mii/mii.html"
                            />&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Henrik</forename>
                                    <surname>Ibsen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Norma</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Andhrimner</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">9 &amp; 10</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp"/>
                                <date when="1851">1851</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Allen</forename>
                                    <surname>Renear</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Elli</forename>
                                    <surname>Mylonas</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">David</forename>
                                    <surname>Durand</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Refining our Notion of What Text Really Is: The Problem
                                of Overlapping Hierarchies</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first"/>
                                    <surname/>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m"/>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr
                                target="http://www.stg.brown.edu/resources/stg/monographs/ohco.html"
                            />&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Sperberg-McQueen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Claus</forename>
                                    <surname>Huitfeldt</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Concurrent Document Hierarchies in MECS and
                                SGML</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                              <title level="u">ALLC/ACH98, Debrecen</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.oasis-open.org/cover/sperbergACH98.html"
                            />&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Sperberg-McQueen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Lou</forename>
                                    <surname>Burnard</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Guidelines for Text Encoding and Interchange</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                                <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Text Encoding Initiative</publisher>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
