<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Image Description at the William Blake Archive</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Kari</forename>
                        <surname>Kraus</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Rochester</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Text Encoding</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The larger objective of this paper is to follow the lead of Matthew Kirschenbaum
                    and the participants in his panel at last year's ALLC/ACH conference in
                    Charlottesville, Virginia, in thinking about visual electronic resources as
                    structured data. More specifically, I propose to turn the spotlight on a
                    significant portion of the William Blake Archive's metadata: its SGML-encoded
                    image descriptions. Introductory remarks will emphasize the image descriptions
                    as a design feature intended to maximize use of and complement the Archive's
                    other image resources, but the balance of the paper will consider more
                    foundational issues: what exactly are image descriptions in formal terms? What
                    is their relationship to their first-order objects? What kinds of problems do
                    they present for the project team? What functions do they serve? My aim is to
                    provide a broad overview of our practices and the challenges we face (both
                    theoretical and practical) in describing images. The full version of this
                    presentation will attend closely to the discursive features of the image
                    descriptions and their principles of inclusion of pictorial data on the grounds
                    that they serve as a barometer of the general reliability of the search and
                    retrieval functions.</p>
                <p>The image descriptions and their characteristic terms - which are best considered
                    as a unit - are an integral part of the Archive's paradigm of image search and
                    retrieval. General descriptions are available via a link to a separate window
                    from all Object View pages in the Archive, and more specific descriptions are
                    returned in the course of an image search. The descriptive commentary is also
                    available to the user who invokes an Inote session from any of several windows
                    and pages. (Inote, which has received much press in humanities computing circles
                    since its public debut, is a java-based image annotation tool developed at IATH
                    that superimposes a four-quadrant grid on an image. Clicking an area of interest
                    opens a separate annotation viewer containing the editorial commentary targeted
                    to the selected region.) The image descriptions are conceptually inextricable
                    from the Archive's characteristic terms, a menu of which the user selects from
                    when launching an image search. Though it is tempting to devote a portion of the
                    paper to an evaluation of how the Archive's controlled vocabulary measures up
                    when compared to other established classification and vocabulary browsers (such
                    as IconClass, the Art and Architecture Thesaurus, and the Library of Congress
                    Thesaurus for Graphic Materials), that subject is sufficiently complex to
                    warrant separate treatment at some future date.</p>
                <p>Strictly speaking, the Archive's search engine consults only the SGML-encoded
                    characteristic terms when returning hits to a user. The exact function of the
                    prose that appears between &lt;illusobjdesc&gt; tags is more difficult to
                    define. My provisional account of the purpose of the descriptions is threefold:
                    first, they illustrate that the visual-to-verbal transposition isn't a simple
                    one-step operation: more complexly, images are first captured in prose and from
                    the prose we extract smaller searchable units. Second, the descriptions provide
                    a system of checks and balances that allow the user to cross-reference them with
                    the characteristic terms, making the underlying logic of the hits returned in
                    the course of a search session explicit. Third, they offer us a space where
                    Willard McCarty's metadata rule of disambiguation can be violated: as I will
                    explain in more detail in my talk, a fair amount of uncertainty and doubt is
                    built into the descriptions as a response to iconographic ambiguities in the
                    source material; this interpretive uncertainty is, if not effaced entirely, at
                    least diluted at the characteristic level. These functions aside, it is my sense
                    that the descriptions aren't being mined for information as effectively as they
                    could be, though the beta version of WBA 2.0, scheduled for public release later
                    this summer, should make it possible to harvest their data in new ways.</p>
                <p>Because the Archive's image search and retrieval software, Dynaweb, must consult
                    an SGML information base that is, of course, textual rather than pictorial in
                    content, the descriptions and their corresponding characteristic terms serve as
                    a verbal proxy for their visual objects. To put it otherwise, the annotations
                    function as metatext (rather than, as in conventional print relationships,
                    paratext) to the primary data, creating an unusual onus of responsibility for
                    the editors and assistants to provide descriptions and terms that show as much
                    fidelity as possible to the originals in order to guarantee optimum results for
                    the user searching across the visual collection.</p>
                <p>This process of faithfully, accurately, and thoroughly translating from one
                    medium (the visual) to another (the verbal) is, as one would expect, beset by
                    difficulties. But we are not without precedent or aid. In particular, the
                    problems we encounter in the course of composing our image descriptions can be
                    profitably understood by looking to the growing body of literature in Humanities
                    Computing on encoding transcripts of source materials. My suggestion assumes
                    that at heart the two endeavors (describing images and transcribing texts) are
                    first and foremost acts of <emph rend="italics">translation</emph> - the former
                    from pictorial data to linguistic data, the latter from - to take the example of
                    the Beowulf Project - chirographical marks in a codex manuscript to the
                    descriptive codes of SGML - and as such are prey to all the difficulties
                    inherent in the translation process.</p>
                <p>At last year's ALLC/ACH conference, Paul Caton and Julia Flanders raised the
                    issue of the measurability of data as an important consideration for project
                    teams interested in encoding renditional information: they stressed the
                    necessity of <cit rend="block">
                        <quote>"having a clear sense of what the units of information are, how to
                            identify and distinguish them consistently, and how to record them
                            accurately. It [the criterion of measurability] represents/requires an
                            attempt to decide . . . what threshold of perceptibility will be
                            maintained: . . . what will be considered either too small or too costly
                            or difficult to record."</quote>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>At the Blake Archive, our efforts to extract iconographic content from the source
                    material for the purposes of image description are routinely complicated by just
                    the kinds of measurability and perceptibility difficulties outlined by Caton and
                    Flanders. Should Blake's interlinear motifs be captured in as much detail as the
                    large-scale designs? Should the hatched lines that appear meaningless in the 100
                    dpi image but representational in the 300 dpi be described (and thus made
                    searchable)? Should we even avail ourselves at all of the 300 dpi images as
                    resources to transform our unaided human eyes into Argus eyes, or is this
                    approach contrary to the central tenets of diplomatic editing? What about the
                    left arm of that central figure on plate 16 in copy D of <title level="m">The
                        Marriage of Heaven and Hell</title>, which was printed but colored on the
                    impression so that it blends almost imperceptibly with the adjacent figure's
                    gown? Is that wispy line extending from the ascender of the letter "b" a bird or
                    a vine, or is it both? Indeed variations on the last question may reflect the
                    most common kind of perceptual ambiguity the annotator of Blake encounters,
                    attributable in part to Blake's almost profligate use of metaphors; his peculiar
                    syncretic insight makes it dangerous to ever rule out the possibility that a
                    design motif has multiple referents: flora and fauna are often
                    indistinguishable, a human figure may be a composite of several characters, and
                    a lock of hair easily morphs into a coiled serpent.</p>
                <p>The final version of the paper will address our working solutions to the problems
                    enumerated in the foregoing paragraph. I will conclude by briefly shifting the
                    emphasis from the creation of image descriptions to their potential use,
                    offering some parting thoughts and caveats on the kind of knowledge that the
                    image descriptions might produce when used in conjunction with the Archive's
                    other image tools and resources.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Paul</forename>
                                    <surname>Caton</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Julia</forename>
                                    <surname>Flanders</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Encoding Rendition in Primary Source Texts Using
                                TEI</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">Unpublished essay, 1999. Presented at ACH-ALLC 99.
                                University of Virginia, Charlottesville. 12 June 1999.</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Morris</forename>
                                    <surname>Eaves</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Robert</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">N.</forename>
                                    <surname>Essick</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Joseph</forename>
                                    <surname>Viscomi</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">The William Blake Archive</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/blake/"/>&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Inote. Software from the Institute for Advanced
                                Technology in the Humanities</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/inote/"/>&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name>
                                    <forename type="first">Matthew</forename>
                                    <surname>Kirschenbaum</surname>
                                </name> et al</author>
                            <title level="a">Refining Our Notions of What (Digital) Images Really
                                Are.</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">ACH-ALLC 99. University of Virginia, Charlottesville.
                                10 June 1999</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Willard</forename>
                                    <surname>McCarty</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Humanities Computing as Interdiscipline</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/hcs/mccarty.html"
                            />&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
