<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Innovations in Resources for Teaching History and
                    Archaeology</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Pauline</forename>
                        <surname>McCormack</surname>
                        <affiliation>DISH Project, <name type="org">University of Glasgow</name>
                            <email>pauline@arts.gla.ac.uk </email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Bergen</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bergen, Norway</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 1996</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Anne</forename>
                        <surname>Lindebjerg</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Espen</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                        <surname>Ore</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Øystein</forename>
                        <surname>Reigem</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>history</item>
                        <item>archaeology</item>
                        <item> databases</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The DISH (Design &amp; Implementation of Software for History) Project
                    provides computing resources and advice for historians (including art
                    historians) and archaeologists in six departments and three related institutions
                    at the University of Glasgow. In three laboratories containing 40 networked
                    microcomputers, DISH offers some of the most advanced facilities in the UK for
                    computing specific to the study of history and archaeology. Areas in which the
                    Project is particularly strong include the use of databases and historical
                    datasets for teaching and the provision of multimedia tutorials for
                    archaeologists.</p>
                <p>The Project also provides a number of specialist applications such as statistics
                    and mapping programs and is a beta test site for the international Remote Access
                    to Museum Archives (RAMA) project.</p>
                <p>DISH would demonstrate and discuss the setup, applications, datasets and
                    textbases used in day to day teaching, as well as the philosophy of including
                    the use of computers in teaching the humanities. In particular we would like to
                    talk about an on-going project involving the transfer of teaching data from DOS
                    platform databases to a Windows platform database. This exercise has brought
                    into focus issues such as: optimising commercial software for specialist use;
                    the difficulties in defining the boundaries between teaching the use of
                    computing tools for historical analysis and the analysis itself; the reluctance
                    of very busy academics to move away from tools which work.</p>
                <p>We would also demonstrate our wide range of archaeology tutorials which range
                    from the introductory package "Archaeology at Work" to more technically-specific
                    subjects including lithics, bones, archaeological statistics and grid
                    references.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
