<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The Wittgenstein Archives at the University of
                    Bergen</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Maria</forename>
                        <surname>Sollohub</surname>
                        <affiliation>The <name type="org">Wittgenstein Archives</name> at the <name
                                type="org">University of Bergen</name>
                            <email>maria.sollohub@hd.uib.no </email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Bergen</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bergen, Norway</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 1996</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Anne</forename>
                        <surname>Lindebjerg</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Espen</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                        <surname>Ore</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Øystein</forename>
                        <surname>Reigem</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>SGML</item>
                        <item>MECS</item>
                        <item>electronic facsimile</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>The aim of The Wittgenstein Archives at the University of Bergen is to make
                        the complete writings of the Austrian philosopher, Ludwig Wittgenstein,
                        available in the form of electronic facsimile and transcriptions.
                        Specialised software has been developed in order to facilitate the
                        preparation, presentation and analysis of the texts. At the ALLC/ACH
                        conference in Bergen in 1996 we would like to take the opportunity to
                        present our project by means of a poster and software presentation.</p>
                    <p>In cooperation with Oxford University Press, the Wittgenstein Nachlass will
                        be published in electronic form. The entire Nachlass will first be published
                        as an electronic facsimile on CD-ROM. This facsimile may then be
                        supplemented by transcriptions prepared at The Wittgenstein Archives in
                        Bergen. By the end of 1995, approximately 9,000 pages had been transcribed,
                        while transcription of the entire Nachlass is expected to be complete in
                        1999.</p>
                    <p>The Wittgenstein Archives was founded by the Senate of the University of
                        Bergen in 1990 as a research project at the Department of Philosophy. The
                        project is partly externally financed and has its own budget. The work at
                        the Archives is made possible through an understanding with the Trustees of
                        the copyright in the Wittgenstein Papers, Prof. G.E.M. Anscombe (Cambridge),
                        Sir Anthony Kenny (Oxford), Prof. Peter Winch (Urbana-Champaign, Illinois)
                        and Prof. Georg Henrik von Wright (Helsingfors).</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Poster and software presentation</head>
                    <p>The Wittgenstein Archives' transcriptions are encoded in a primary format
                        using a syntax called MECS (Multi-Element Code System). MECS defines the
                        syntax for the registration standard of The Wittgenstein Archives, MECS-WIT,
                        while MECS software enables the production of diplomatic and normalised
                        printouts, word lists, numerical and statistical data.</p>
                    <p>In identifying a relationship between MECS and SGML, all SGML documents are
                        formally MECS-conforming, but not vice versa. MECS contains some of the
                        properties of SGML, but it also contains additional, simpler mechanisms for
                        representing structures which can be cumbersome in SGML.</p>
                    <p>In a presentation of the work of The Wittgenstein Archives, we would like to
                        demonstrate both MECS-WIT as a successfully applied registration standard
                        and the software facilities provided by MECS. Sample images from the
                        forthcoming CD-ROM will be made available, together with active links
                        between the page images and the relevant transcriptions.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
