<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">CASTLE - Computer ASsisted Tutoring and Learning
                    Environment</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Bettina</forename>
                        <surname>Harriehausen-Mühlbauer</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">IBM Germany</name>, Science Center
                                <email>bettinah@vnet.ibm.com </email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Bergen</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bergen, Norway</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 1996</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Anne</forename>
                        <surname>Lindebjerg</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Espen</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                        <surname>Ore</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Øystein</forename>
                        <surname>Reigem</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>computer assisted language learning</item>
                        <item>electronic grammar and grammar tutor</item>
                        <item>multi-media in the classroom</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>CASTLE (= Computer ASsisted Tutoring and Learning Environment), our prototype for
                    the autodidactic acquisition of the English language, combines several modern
                    NLP (natural language processing) technologies in one intelligent system.</p>
                <p>The basic idea behind CASTLE is to bring a written medium, i.e. one or more books
                    (such as an exercise book for students, the teacher's manual, the relating
                    grammar, mono- and/or bi-lingual dictionaries) to an electronic platform.</p>
                <p>The appealing interface includes graphic features, such as scanned photos and
                    illustrations as bitmaps, video sequences with hot-spots to click on, and sound
                    in exercises of the type users might be familiar with from older language lab
                    applications or exercises, i.e. repeating speech or interacting with the system
                    in a speech-speech or writing-speech dialogue.</p>
                <p>Using hypertext technology, not only a clear structure of the entire system is
                    given, but also an intelligent, fast, and efficient combination of different
                    sources, e.g. an exercise book and a grammar tutorial, is implemented which the
                    user can use according to his/her individual demands.</p>
                <p>The different units of a book explain different grammatical structures which the
                    user can exercise, for example, by filling in the answers in the appropriate
                    boxes.</p>
                <p>In the background, the answer of the user is checked by a spell- and grammar
                    checker.</p>
                <p>According to a correct answer or type of error, the user gets the appropriate
                    feedback immediately - with different options of how to procede, i.e. the system
                    does not follow a rigid instruction path but rather leaves a lot of options and
                    choices to the user.</p>
                <p>The overall modular set-up of the entire system allows an easy exchange of single
                    modules of the system, i.e. this flexibility offers the possibility to use the
                    "body" of CASTLE for related applications as well, e.g. CALL systems for other
                    languages.</p>
                <p>CASTLE is presently running on any PC under Microsoft Windows 3.1.</p>
                <p>A demonstration will give insights into CASTLE's functionality and will give the
                    opportunity to get hands-on experience with this intelligent CALL system.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
