<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?RNGSchema = "file:schema/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">COLT on TACT A demonstration of the TACTweb software as
                    applied to the Bergen Corpus of London Teenage Language</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Kristine</forename>
                        <surname>Hasund</surname>
                        <affiliation>Dept. of English, <name type="org">University of Bergen</name>
                            <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Gisle</forename>
                        <surname>Andersen</surname>
                        <affiliation>Dept. of English, <name type="org">University of Bergen</name>
                            <email>gisle.andersen@eng.uib.no </email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Bergen</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bergen, Norway</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 1996</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Anne</forename>
                        <surname>Lindebjerg</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Espen</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                        <surname>Ore</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Øystein</forename>
                        <surname>Reigem</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>TACTweb search program</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Bergen Corpus of London Teenage Language (COLT) is the first large English
                    Corpus focusing on the speech of teenagers. It was collected in 1993 and
                    consists of the spoken language of 13 to 17-year-old boys and girls from
                    different boroughs of London.</p>
                <p>The aim of the COLT project is to compile a 500.000 word corpus of spoken teenage
                    language, and make it available for students of English at the University of
                    Bergen, as well as for language researchers world-wide.</p>
                <p>This poster presents the use of TACTweb on the COLT corpus. TACTweb, which
                    connects the text-retrieval program TACT to the World Wide Web, enables the user
                    to search in a database of spoken conversations for the location of words, word
                    combinations and word formation patterns. In the COLT database, TACTweb is
                    applied to give the distribution of an item in relation to certain
                    non-linguistic variables.</p>
                <p>Searches in the corpus are made possible through the indexing of the texts in the
                    database. The COLT database has the following indices: <list>
                        <item>1. Reference number for each text file (eg. &lt;REF&gt;
                            B132401) </item>
                        <item>2. who= index for speaker identity (eg who=1)</item>
                        <item>3. id= index for speaker turn number (eg id=1). This index is the same
                            as is used in the BNC (the British National Corpus)</item>
                        <item>4. speaker's age (eg &lt;AGE1&gt; 14)</item>
                        <item>5. speaker's gender (eg &lt;GEN1&gt; f)</item>
                        <item>6. speaker's socioeconomic group (eg &lt;SOC1&gt; 2)</item>
                        <item>7. speaker's occupation (eg &lt;OCC1&gt; student)</item>
                        <item>8. location of conversation (eg &lt;LOC&gt; Hackney)</item>
                        <item>9. setting of conversation (eg &lt;SET&gt; classroom)</item>
                        <item>10. number of participants (eg &lt;AUD&gt; 5) </item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Four different types of display systems are available for searches in the
                    corpus:</p>
                <div>
                    <head>KWIC - Key Words In Context</head>
                    <p>A KWIC display lists all the occurrences of a word with one line of context.
                        Here is an example that shows the occurrences of the word "Peter" see Figure
                        1.</p>
                    <p>The number in parentheses in the top line shows the total number of
                        occurrences of "Peter" in the entire corpus. The numbers at the front of
                        each line give the reference number, and then the turn number where the word
                        can be found. The target word appears in the middle of the line. Clicking on
                        the target word shows the full text, which allows a closer study of each
                        occurrence.</p>
                    <p>The KWIC display allows the user to quickly browse a large number of
                        occurrences to see how a particular word is used, or to search for a word
                        which has many occurrences.</p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Figure 1</head>
                    </figure>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Variable Context Display</head>
                    <p>Whereas the KWIC display gives only one line of context, the Variable Context
                        Display allows the user to control the amount of context in which a word is
                        to be displayed. For example, one can ask for the word "Peter" to be
                        displayed in a context of 3 lines before and 3 lines after the
                        occurrence:<figure/></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Distribution</head>
                    <p>This display allows the user to search for the occurrence of a word as it is
                        distributed across the variables speaker identity, age, gender,
                        socio-economic group, location, setting, occupation, and number of
                        participants. Here is an example of how the word "shit" is distributed
                        according to age</p>
                    <figure/>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Word List</head>
                    <p>The Word List display gives a list of all the words that match a particular
                        pattern. For instance, it is possible to produce a list of all words ending
                        in a particular letter or sequence of letters. This is particularily useful
                        for a researcher who is interested in the productivity of certain morphemes,
                        such as <emph rend="italics">-able</emph>:<list>
                            <item> unavailable (1)</item>
                            <item>unbelievable (4)</item>
                            <item> uncomfortable (2)</item>
                            <item> unfuckingtouchable (2)</item>
                            <item> unreliable (1)</item>
                            <item>unscrewable (1)</item>
                            <item> unsociable (1)</item>
                            <item>untouchable (1)</item>
                            <item>up-gradable (2)</item>
                            <item>vulnerable (4)</item>
                        </list></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <p>The purpose of the poster presentation is to demonstrate these and other
                        facilities, focusing on TACTweb as a useful tool for the linguistic
                        researcher. Moreover, an overview of ongoing research will be given.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
