<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">A ToolBook Application: Using Computer Puzzles To Teach
                    Critical-Thinking Skills</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Alfred</forename>
                        <surname>Benney</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Fairfield University</name>
                            <email>Benney@FAIR1.Fairfield.edu </email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Bergen</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bergen, Norway</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 1996</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Anne</forename>
                        <surname>Lindebjerg</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Espen</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                        <surname>Ore</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Øystein</forename>
                        <surname>Reigem</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>critical-thinking</item>
                        <item>computer puzzles</item>
                        <item>teaching strategies</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>The Problem</head>
                    <p>Students come to American Universities with critical skills that are
                        inadequate for college-level scholarship. It is essential not only for their
                        studies, but for their lives and careers that they learn to do analysis - to
                        get a clear understanding of the data before they begin to form their
                        opinions about it. In the preface to their book, <title level="m">Asking the
                            Right Questions</title>, Neil Browne and Stuart Keeley make the
                        following observation: <cit rend="block">
                            <quote>. . . we were dismayed at the degree to which students and
                                acquaintances showed an increasing dependence on "experts" -
                                textbook writers, teachers, lawyers, politicians, journalists, and
                                TV commentators. As the complexity of the world seems to grow at an
                                accelerating rate, there is a greater tendency to become passive
                                absorbers of information, uncritically accepting what is seen and
                                heard.</quote>
                            <bibl>
                                <note n="1">M. Neil Browne and Stuart M. Keeley, <title level="m"
                                        >Asking the Right Questions</title>, Englewood Cliffs, NJ:
                                    Prentice-Hall, Inc. (1990), p. ix. </note>
                            </bibl>
                        </cit></p>
                    <p>Humanities courses have a distinct advantage in providing an educational
                        environment for teaching analysis or some form of critical thinking. The
                        subject is fuzzy and represents the way most humans interact with their
                        world and with one another. Because of this, analytic skills learned in this
                        environment have applications in a variety of people-oriented careers such
                        as teaching, politics, business, mediation/negotiation, criminal law, etc.,
                        as well as the obvious uses for personal relationships and
                        communication.</p>
                    <p>Moreover, in today's world, there is increased pressure to evaluate education
                        with a "bottom line" mentality. Pressure is on teachers and students alike
                        to treat education as if it were only training to function in society. The
                        common comment to students "Oh, what are you going to do with your degree?"
                        illustrates normative thinking in American society. Unfortunately this has
                        led to two sorts of fallacies:<list>
                            <item>1. Humanities courses have little value because their main focus
                                is not a hands-on application;</item>
                            <item>2. In this so-called "Information Age" education is reduced to
                                "getting the answers to the questions."</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>In the second case, the fallacy is of course, that the questions are
                        apparent; that there is no skill involved in exploring the problem; and that
                        there is no need to understand nor evaluate the problem before we apply
                        solutions (that are expected to bring instantaneous results).</p>
                    <p>In the first case, the fallacy is that we have lost sight of what humanities
                        education really is. Without making this the focus of this exercise, let me
                        suggest that one way of thinking about this is that humanities courses
                        explore the messy business of learning how to analyze and evaluate the
                        questions that concern human beings.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The Approach</head>
                    <p>Gerald Bracey, reporting on the 1991 meeting of the American Psychological
                        Association, points out that technology has not paid attention to the most
                        recent findings of cognitive psychology. <cit rend="block">
                            <quote>. . . cognitive psychologists . . . have come to believe that
                                `metacognition' plays an enormous role in learning. In general,
                                metacognition refers to thinking about your own thinking, regulating
                                it, and directing it according to the changing conditions of your
                                environment.</quote>
                            <bibl>
                                <note n="2">Gerald Bracey, "Educational Technology Should Heed
                                    Cognitive Psychology," <title level="j">Electronic
                                        Learning</title>, vol. 11, no. 3, Nov./Dec. 1991, p. 19.
                                </note>
                            </bibl>
                        </cit></p>
                    <p>At Fairfield University, I introduce my students to the question of analysis
                        and problem solving by using in class a puzzle exercise which I designed
                        using ToolBook. By displaying a series of puzzles, I am able to elicit
                        immediate and direct response from nearly every student in the class and by
                        interrupting the process at strategic points can call attention to what it
                        is that they are doing as they attempt to solve these problems
                        (metacognition). It is easy to demonstrate, for example, how such things as
                        assumptions, artificial boundaries, distractions, patterns, lack of
                        information and failure to see the problem prevent us from accurately
                        analyzing a problem.<note n="3">For an interesting discussion of obstacles
                            to problem solving see: Rubinstein, Moshe F., <title level="m">Patterns
                                of Problem Solving</title>. Englewood Cliffs, N. J.: Prentice-Hall,
                            Inc., 1975.</note></p>
                    <p>In this exercise, the puzzles are presented on a large screen projection
                        system and both the type of puzzle as well as the timing of the presentation
                        is in my control; my objective is:<list>
                            <item>1. To involve the class/audience in responding to the
                                problem;</item>
                            <item>2. to create a competitive environment that rewards those who have
                                solutions, but keeps those who fail anonymous;</item>
                            <item>3. to pattern student thinking so that they discover how
                                distractions, artificial boundaries etc. inhibit their ability to
                                "think";</item>
                            <item>4. and to explore with them just what they/their minds are doing
                                when they are solving/trying to solve these relatively simple
                                problems.</item>
                        </list></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The "Technique"</head>
                    <p>It is important to understand that this is not a tutorial which simply
                        presents Puzzles (ideas/concepts) to the students. Rather it is the use of
                        technology to create a public event that involves the class in a common
                        enterprise. The teacher is most assuredly a guide in this enterprise.
                        Because of the nature of hypertext, it is possible to organize the structure
                        of the program based on the interaction of the students. The teacher must
                        learn how to use this strategy to effect the desired outcomes. Milton Glick
                        and others points out "that it is not what the teacher does but what he or
                        she gets the students to do that results in learning." <note n="4">Milton
                            Glick, "Integrating Computing into Higher Education: An Administrator's
                            View," Educom Review, vol. 25, no. 2 (1990), p. 35.</note></p>
                    <p>The use of the CRT to create an interactive information environment provides
                        what I would call "appropriate use," because it ". . . gives the . . .
                        [teacher] the ability to access and manipulate not just information products
                        (such as text, graphics, video), but information processes as well."<note
                            n="5">Katheryn Conway, <title level="m">Master Classrooms: Classroom
                                Design with Technology in Mind</title>. Research Triangle Park, NC:
                            Institute for Academic Technology (1990), p. 4.</note></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The Payoff</head>
                    <p>Presenting this project at a poster session makes it possible to discuss this
                        educational strategy with participants from a variety of disciplines as well
                        as to demonstrate the actual use of the puzzles to simulate a classroom
                        situation. In this setting it is also easier to respond to specific
                        questions about the authoring system (ToolBook 3.0a) as well as the design
                        of the "books" used. It also becomes possible to tailor the presentation to
                        the various needs of the participants.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
