<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">A Demonstration of the Linear Modeling Kit</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Larry</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
                        <surname>Stewart</surname>
                        <affiliation>English Department, The <name type="org">College of
                                Wooster</name>, Wooster, Ohio <email>Lstewart@acs.wooster.edu
                            </email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Peter</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
                        <surname>Havholm</surname>
                        <affiliation>English Department, The <name type="org">College of
                                Wooster</name>, Wooster, Ohio <email>Phavholm@acs.wooster.edu
                            </email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Bergen</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bergen, Norway</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 1996</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Anne</forename>
                        <surname>Lindebjerg</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Espen</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                        <surname>Ore</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Øystein</forename>
                        <surname>Reigem</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>software</item>
                        <item>pedagogy</item>
                        <item>literary theory</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>A Demonstration of the Linear Modeling Kit</head>
                <p>The Linear Modeling Kit, an application designed by the writers, is a compiled
                    program that allows users to make narrative generators. The generators produce
                    narratives made of user-created text strings arranged according to
                    user-specified rules. The software's authors use the LMK in literature courses
                    as a way of helping students think more deeply and precisely about narrative and
                    narrative theory. Students are asked to "program" their own understanding of a
                    narrative theory into the LMK, thus creating a narrative generator; and the
                    quality of the skeletal narratives the resulting generator can produce indicates
                    the powers of the students' understanding.</p>
                <p>Essentially, a Linear Modeling Kit generator is a simple computer program that
                    generates statements using a supplied vocabulary and rules about how vocabulary
                    pieces may be connected. The user may create any number and kind of categories.
                    For example, narrative categories might be called "exposition," "complication,"
                    "climax" and "denouement" or, in the context of Vladimir Propp's analysis,
                    "initial situation," "absentation," "interdiction," "violation," etc.</p>
                <p>The user may then enter any number of text strings which exemplify these
                    categories: for instance, "Two young children once lived in a large forest"
                    might be placed in the category "exposition." After having created categorized
                    lists of strings, the user would then create rules for their linking: for
                    example, a generator may be programmed to go from initial situation to
                    absentation and then to interdiction or, perhaps, to go from initial situation
                    either to absentation or to interdiction and then to loop back to an earlier
                    category. The generator randomly selects a text string from each category list
                    it visits, so the resulting narrative is a direct consequence of the analysis
                    represented by categories and combinatory rules.</p>
                <p>The LMK also allows the user to "mark" text strings for any attribute. For
                    example, a string could be marked masculine or feminine to ensure a continuity
                    of gender in the protagonist, or it could be marked on a scale of one to ten for
                    stylistic formality or violence or oral imagery or for any attribute deemed
                    relevant by the user.</p>
                <p>In our classes, we ask students to study a particular kind of narrative (for
                    instance, the <emph rend="italics">bildungsroman</emph> or the contemporary
                    romance) and to create a generator that will produce skeletal narratives of that
                    kind. The narratives, thus, become a kind of test of the students'
                    understanding? Do the narratives "sound like" skeletal versions of the <emph
                        rend="italics">bildungsroman</emph>? If not, what is missing in the theory
                    by which the generator was produced?</p>
                <p>We have found the pedagogy to be an extremely powerful one which urges students
                    to think about narratives and narrative theory with unusual precision.</p>
                <p>We will demonstrate the interactive creation of a narrative generator and show
                    examples of a wide variety of student-produced generators.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
