<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Demonstration of TATOE: Text Analysis Tool with Object
                    Encoding</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Melina</forename>
                        <surname>Alexa</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Integrated Publication and Information Systems
                                Institute</name>, GMD-IPSI <email>alexa@darmstadt.gmd.de </email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Lothar</forename>
                        <surname>Rostek</surname>
                        <affiliation><name type="org">Integrated Publication and Information Systems
                                Institute</name>, GMD-IPSI <email>rostek@darmstadt.gmd.de
                            </email></affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Bergen</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bergen, Norway</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 1996</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Anne</forename>
                        <surname>Lindebjerg</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Espen</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                        <surname>Ore</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Øystein</forename>
                        <surname>Reigem</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>semi-automatic text analysis tool</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <p>TATOE, a Text Analysis Tool with Object Encoding, is a support tool for
                        semi-automated text analysis. It has been designed and implemented at
                        GMD-PSI in order to assist various tasks related to the multilingual,
                        data-driven and multi-layered text analysis. TATOE is implemented in the
                        Smalltalk-based programming environment VisualWorks 2.0 (from ParcPlace).
                        For the data modeling we have used the Smalltalk Frame Kit (SFK), an object
                        oriented modeling tool which offers a spectrum of features to make model
                        descriptions operational (Fisher and Rostek, In Preparation).</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Various processes are supported:</head>
                    <p>
                        <list>
                            <item>1. structuring, compiling, importing and working with one or more
                                text corpora,</item>
                            <item>2. determining one or more, hierarchically or non-hierarchically
                                structured, categorization schemata to be used for on-text mark up, </item>
                            <item>3. importing or re-using an already existing categorization
                                schema, and (or) defining and structuring one's own categorization
                                schema,</item>
                            <item>4. enabling the integration of automatic tagging/encoding tools
                                for a supplementary annotation,</item>
                            <item>5. performing on-text annotation according to more than one
                                categorization schema concurrently,</item>
                            <item>6. flexible viewing of both annotated and non-annotated text
                                segments (this includes on the one hand selecting and arranging
                                according to different criteria - frequency of occurrences, encoded
                                category types, etc. - and on the other hand presenting by
                                meaningful layout styles - fonts, colours, etc.),</item>
                            <item>7. calculating different statistics on the basis of the text
                                corpora themselves, the encoded text segments and - if available -
                                the hierarchical relations within the categorization schema, e.g.
                                frequency of occurrence of word types, word tokens or categories or
                                how these are distributed in the text(s)</item>
                            <item>8. re-using the encoded information as input to further processing
                                by exporting it in an appropriate format, e.g. sgml.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>TATOE has been used for text type analysis of encyclopedic texts containing
                        artists' biographies and descriptions of archeological sites in order to
                        empirically extract the necessary information for the construction of text
                        type specifications for generating text sensitive to both text type and
                        envisaged user. More specifically, the text analysis task has been to
                        perform a register analysis (as defined in Systemic Functional Linguistics
                        (Halliday 1985)) by means of identifying in a corpus of texts belonging to
                        the same text type a number of situational features. Corpus-based register
                        analysis for text generation aims at identifying, determining and then
                        representing, where necessary, the mechanisms of correlation or constraint
                        between linguistic form (linguistic features) and communicative context
                        (situational features). The practical aim is to provide a text generation
                        system with information about situational features and what constraints
                        particular situational features impose on linguistic expression (see Alexa
                        1995).</p>
                    <p>Furthermore, TATOE is presently being used (and further developed) for the
                        analysis of a corpus of news messages (from the Deutsche Presse Agentur
                        (DPA)) in order to identify semantic patterns and annotate text segments
                        according to a domain dependent semantic categorization. Such information
                        can then be used to support fact extraction, the process of filling in the
                        DPA "fact cards" and the development of a "parliament" thesaurus.</p>
                    <p>The demonstration will illustrate the different needs of the specific text
                        analysis tasks by means of presenting the main functionalities of the tool.
                        It will be shown how the user can define the categorization schema or
                        schemata to be used for analysis. A number of techniques for maintaining the
                        schema will be demonstrated. For the specific application task different
                        classification schemata have been set up and used, in order to annotate and
                        extract information according to different levels of linguistic description.
                        Possibilities for either determining one's own classification schema or
                        importing one will be demonstrated.</p>
                    <p>The selection and on-text annotation procedures together with those for
                        updating, correcting and refining the annotation will be demonstrated. TATOE
                        assists mostly those tasks of the analysis which involve an intellectual
                        effort. However, it provides automatic support for extracting frequency of
                        occurrence information as well as frequency of already annotated words or
                        text segments according to a particular categorization schema. The different
                        possibilities for extracting and presenting frequency of occurrence
                        information will be presented.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Melina</forename>
                                    <surname>Alexa</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Making principled selections: A methodology for
                                register analysis and description for text generation</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">Presented at the 22nd International Systemic-Functional
                                Congress, Beijing, China, July 1995</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1995">1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Dietrich</forename>
                                    <surname>Fischer</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Lothar</forename>
                                    <surname>Rostek</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">SFK: A Smalltalk Frame Kit. Technical report</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>GMD/Institut fuer Integrierte Publikations- und
                                    Informationssysteme</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">(In Preparation, 1996)</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Michael</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>Halliday</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">An Introduction to Functional Grammar</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Edward Arnold</publisher>
                                <date when="1985">1985</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
