<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The limits to computer-based grammar checking for
                    foreign language learners of English?</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Philip</forename>
                        <surname>Bolt</surname>
                        <affiliation>Department of English, <name type="org">Hong Kong Polytechnic
                                University</name>
                            <email>egphbolt@hkpucc.edu.hk </email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Bergen</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bergen, Norway</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 1996</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Anne</forename>
                        <surname>Lindebjerg</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Espen</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                        <surname>Ore</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Øystein</forename>
                        <surname>Reigem</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>grammar-checking</item>
                        <item>lexical/syntactic data</item>
                        <item>structural features</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Although much work has been carried out in the areas related to computer-based
                    grammar checking programs (those wh ich specifically deal with syntactically
                    ill-formed input), the history of this endeavour is not an especially successful
                    one for either native speaker language or the possibly less complex language of
                    the English as a foreign language (EFL) learner.</p>
                <p>A number of factors militate against the development of a program about which we
                    can be confident in its capacity to identify faulty syntax and provide
                    linguistically appropriate reformulations. Yet, with sufficiently fine-grained
                    lexical and syntactic data and sensitive processes (including those involving
                    the learner to some degree), it is possible in some cases to identify the
                    syntactic aspects of a faulty sentence and to say, with reasonable confidence,
                    what is wrong. In many cases, it is possible to locate a problematic area,
                    rather than a single feature and to suggest one or more reformulations involving
                    that area, and possibly beyond. In other cases, however, the lexical and
                    structural complexities, the range of problems within and across phrase and
                    clause edges and the range of potential solutions make structural analysis, and
                    problem identification and reformulation, much more difficult. This suggests
                    that there might be a threshold (or rather series of different thresholds) of
                    complexity/corrigibility beyond which a grammar checker might not be
                    effective.</p>
                <p>ISCA (Interactive Sentence Constructor and Analyser) is a program which provides
                    the framework for the demonstration and discussion of what is involved in the
                    design, construction and operation of a grammar checking program for EFL
                    students, together with the features which collectively contribute to the above
                    thresholds. In addition to the graphical depiction of the program and related
                    issues provided by the poster, likely discussion will be approached through the
                    demonstration of a number of well and ill-formed sentences, which illustrate the
                    data and process involved in sentence construction, correction and the user's
                    contribution to these. It is suggested that these sentences illustrate a range
                    of structural features - including the number, nature and distribution of items
                    - word-form/word-class pairings - the directness of such pairings to phrases and
                    clause elements, the availability of a range of key words, and the range and
                    type of possible reformulations - which contribute to the notion of a number of
                    complexity/corrigibility thresholds. The use of the software will provide a
                    `hands-on' opportunity and complement the information provided on the poster.
                    Together, they will give those interested an opportunity for observation and
                    discussion of the program and its underlying philosophy and ontology.</p>
                <p>The presentation might appeal to a) those disdainful of the performance of
                    commercial grammar (style) checking programs, but who may not have fully
                    appreciated what is involved, b) those who have (or are) working on parsers and
                    grammar checking programs of their own, and, c) those who feel that syntax is
                    not important for writers and readers.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
