<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The Academy Electronic Editions of Australian
                    Literature</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Chris</forename>
                        <surname>Tiffin</surname>
                        <affiliation>English Department, <name type="org">Australian Defence Force
                                Academy</name>
                            <email>c.tiffin@mailbox.uq.oz.au </email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Paul</forename>
                        <surname>Eggert</surname>
                        <affiliation>English Department, <name type="org">Australian Defence Force
                                Academy</name>
                            <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Graham</forename>
                        <surname>Barwell</surname>
                        <affiliation>English Department, <name type="org">University of
                                Wollongong</name>
                            <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Bergen</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bergen, Norway</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 1996</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Anne</forename>
                        <surname>Lindebjerg</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Espen</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                        <surname>Ore</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Øystein</forename>
                        <surname>Reigem</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>scholarly editing</item>
                        <item>electronic books</item>
                        <item>TEI-SGML applications</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Academy Editions of Australian Literature based in Canberra, Australia, are a
                    series of classic Australian texts made available in electronic form for the
                    literary scholar.</p>
                <p>The Editions assume a conservative model of reading - that the texts were
                    intended to be read sequentially, and are still most successfully read in that
                    way. We do not believe that by encoding the texts electronically we are
                    developing fundamentally new methods of cognition, erasing Gutenberg, or
                    establishing world peace and democracy in the late capitalist era.</p>
                <p>However, electronic presentation offers the scholar powerful opportunities for
                    circumventing the limitations of the unitary version, and the Academy Electronic
                    Editions allow the juxtaposition of all lifetime states of the text in both
                    searchable text and digitized image forms as well as a critically-edited
                    version.</p>
                <p>Electronic format also allows the presentation of a large range of secondary
                    material from explanatory notes, maps, and contemporary book reviews to modern
                    stage and film adaptations, and the AEEs exploit this ability to store and
                    navigate compendious archival material. The pilot of this collaborative project
                    has taken two texts, one a single version manuscript journal and the other a
                    multi-version novel with major variation between the versions to identify and
                    solve the theoretical and practical problems in encoding the versions with
                    TEI-SGML for display, mapping them to digitized images, and developing a working
                    electronic book of a section of each text.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
