<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Combining corpus and experimental data: methodological
                    considerations </title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Inge</forename>
                        <surname>de Mönnink</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Nijmegen</name>
                            <email>I.deMonnink@let.kun.nl</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>corpus-based research</item>
                        <item>elicitation</item>
                        <item>methodology</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Over the last three decades the study of language use on the basis of corpus data
                    has been re-established in linguistics, while the use of corpora has also spread
                    to fields such as speech research, sociolinguistics and lexical studies where
                    corpora are nowadays widely used. So far, little attention has been given to the
                    methodological issues that arise with respect to the use of corpus data in any
                    of these (research) contexts. Corpora are exploited for both quantitative
                    (absolute and relative frequency of occurrence) and qualitative (distribution)
                    information. And while certain issues are being addressed, such as to how large
                    corpora and samples should (ideally) be, other, related and certainly no less
                    important issues are not being considered at all. One of these issues is the
                    appropriateness of the use of corpora for the study of relatively infrequent
                    phenomena. In this context questions must be raised such as whether and if so
                    how corpus data can or must be supplemented with experimental data.</p>
                <p>A good example of what appears to be an infrequent phenomenon is the variation in
                    the constituent structure of the noun phrase (de Mönnink, 1996). In handbooks on
                    English grammar the noun phrase has been described as comprising of an optional
                    determiner followed by zero of more premodifying elements, an obligatory head,
                    and zero or more postmodifying elements. However, as previous research shows,
                    there are several types of noun phrase that do not conform to this basic
                    pattern. Examples are: 1 shifted premodification: the premodifier occurs before
                    the determiner; 2 discontinuous modification: two constituents which are
                    intuitively felt to belong together are split up into two non-adjacent parts,
                    the first preceding the head, the second following it; 3 floating
                    postmodification: the postmodifier is not adjacent to the other constituents of
                    the noun phrase it modifies.</p>
                <p>Corpus-based studies generally comprise a qualitative and quantitative analysis.
                    The qualitative analysis aims at a detailed description of the phenomenon under
                    study. The quantitative analysis gives a precise picture of absolute and
                    relative (in)frequency of occurrence of the particular phenomenon. For the
                    qualitative analysis no generally accepted methodology exists. Which methods are
                    used depends on the phenomenon that is being studied, the findings of earlier
                    studies, hypotheses formulated by the researcher and (the nature of the
                    annotation in) the available corpus data. For the qualitative analysis, use is
                    made of generally accepted statistical methods. However, for some statistical
                    tests to be reliable a specific minimum frequency is needed (see e.g. de Haan,
                    1992). Thus, the quantitative analysis is particularly suitable for frequent
                    phenomena and less so (or perhaps not at all) for infrequent phenomena.</p>
                <p>This finding is confirmed by studies on the representativeness of corpora. It has
                    been observed (Biber, 1990, 1993; de Haan, 1992) that for infrequent structures
                    to be fully represented in the corpus, samples have to be large. It is, however,
                    difficult to predict beforehand how large a sample has to be. In turn, if you
                    want your corpus to contain various text types to identify linguistic variation
                    among texts, the corpus as a whole has to be very large. In other words, for the
                    (quantitative) study of an infrequent phenomenon by means of a corpus that is
                    representative of the population under study, the corpus has to be sufficiently
                    large. How large exactly depends on the actual frequency of the phenomenon.</p>
                <p>Table 1 gives the frequency of occurrence of (types of) NPs in a corpus of some
                    hundred and forty thousand words. The corpus contains four text types: fiction,
                    non-fiction, drama and spoken material. For a chi-square test to be reliable the
                    number of expected observations of a single variable cannot be lower than five.
                    For the three types of NP described above we see that only 20,000 word fiction
                    samples have a fair chance of containing enough occurrences of all three types.
                    For floating noun phrase postmodification 10,000 word samples are generally big
                    enough, for discontinuous modification 20,000 word samples and for shifted
                    premodification 30,000 word samples or even bigger samples for non-fiction and
                    drama.</p>
                <table rows="10" cols="7">
                    <head>Table 1: Number of occurrences of (types of) NPs in different genres </head>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">Genre</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Sample</cell>
                        <cell role="label">number<lb/>of words</cell>
                        <cell role="label">number<lb/>of NPs</cell>
                        <cell role="label">floating<lb/>postm.</cell>
                        <cell role="label">discont.<lb/>modifier</cell>
                        <cell role="label">shifted<lb/>prem.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">Fiction</cell>
                        <cell>BW</cell>
                        <cell>21,558</cell>
                        <cell>6318</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>MR</cell>
                        <cell>20,266</cell>
                        <cell>6382</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>CC</cell>
                        <cell>20,011</cell>
                        <cell>6136</cell>
                        <cell>34</cell>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">Non-fiction</cell>
                        <cell>CB</cell>
                        <cell>19,368</cell>
                        <cell>5788</cell>
                        <cell>26</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>CM</cell>
                        <cell>10,581</cell>
                        <cell>3282</cell>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>-</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">Drama</cell>
                        <cell>SI</cell>
                        <cell>14,022</cell>
                        <cell>4629</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>NC</cell>
                        <cell>5,642</cell>
                        <cell>1866</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>-</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell role="label">Spoken</cell>
                        <cell>Sp1</cell>
                        <cell>14,919</cell>
                        <cell>4548</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Sp2</cell>
                        <cell>15,938</cell>
                        <cell>5182</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>So far there appears to be a simple solution to use of corpora for the study of
                    infrequent phenomena: simply increase the corpus size. For a simple quantitative
                    analysis this would indeed be adequate. However, a quantitative analysis lacks
                    the descriptive richness of the nature of structures which a qualitative
                    analysis can provide. A qualitative analysis, on the other hand, can only give
                    subjective judgments about currency or rarity. For a corpus-based study of a
                    relatively infrequent phenomenon that wants to take into account both the
                    qualitative and the quantitative aspects, a major problem is constituted by the
                    fact that while large corpora are required, the detailed annotation of such
                    corpora is not feasible. Given the present state-of-the-art the detailed
                    annotation of corpora requires as yet a vast amount of handwork. Hand-annotation
                    is so time-consuming and subject to inconsistencies that the corpus has to
                    remain necessarily small. This demand is directly opposite the demand for large
                    corpora from quantitative approaches that take an interest primarily in the
                    quantitative information a corpus provides. Thus for the study of the nature and
                    frequency of a relatively infrequent phenomenon more is needed than the
                    combination of a qualitative and a quantitative analysis of corpus data.
                    Additional data has to be considered.</p>
                <p>In the past, elicitation data have been used to supplement corpus data (e.g.
                    Quirk and Svartvik, 1966, 1979; Greenbaum, 1970, 1973, 1984). When the
                    experiment is designed with care, elicitation including both performance and
                    judgment tests can form an important source to supplement corpus data. In de
                    Mönnink (forthcoming) I argue that the combination of corpus and experimental
                    data forms a valuable contribution to the description of language use. If a
                    phenomenon is too infrequent to be subjected to a corpus-based study alone,
                    elicitation tests enable the linguist to supplement his data, not only with the
                    native speakers' judgements on the general acceptability of structures, but also
                    with additional structures, either expected because they were predicted by the
                    grammar, or intuitively considered probable, or unexpected yet acceptable.</p>
                <p> Although experimental data have been combined with corpus data before, no
                    attention has so far been paid to the problems of combining these two in essence
                    very different approaches to gathering data. Each has its own methodology for
                    collecting, classifying, analysing and reporting the data in a systematic way.
                    While in de Mönnink (1996) I have discussed the design of elicitation
                    experiments that can be used for supplementation of corpus data, in this paper I
                    discuss ways for combining the two approaches on points of data classification
                    and analysis. I argue that this combination is not simply a matter of
                    integrating statistical outputs, but that it influences both methodologies in
                    such a radical way that it leads to an entirely new methodology for a
                    multi-method approach. I illustrate my findings with the study of non-regular
                    noun phrases.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <surname>Biber</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Methodological Issues Regarding Corpus-based Analysis
                                of Linguistic Variation</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">5</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">257-69</biblScope>
                                <date when="1990">1990</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <surname>Biber</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Representativeness in Corpus Design</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">8</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">243-57</biblScope>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Greenbaum</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Informant Elicitation of Data on Syntactic
                                Variation</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Lingua</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">31</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">201-212</biblScope>
                                <date when="1973">1973</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Greenbaum</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Corpus Analysis and Elicitation Tests</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Aarts</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Meijs</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Corpus Linguistics. Recent Developments in the Use of
                                Computer Corpora in English Language Research</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Rodopi</publisher>
                                <date when="1984">1984</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">193-201</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Greenbaum</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Quirk</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a"/>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Elicitation Experiments in English Linguistic Studies
                                in Use and Attitude</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Longman</publisher>
                                <date when="1970">1970</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>de Haan</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">The Optimum Corpus Sample Size?</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Leitner</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">New Directions in English Language Corpora</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Mouton de Gruyter</publisher>
                                <date when="1992">1992</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">3-19</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">I.</forename>
                                    <surname>de Mönnink</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">A First Approach to the Mobility of Noun Phrase
                                Constituents</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Percy</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">F.</forename>
                                    <surname>Meyer</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">I.</forename>
                                    <surname>Lancashire</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Synchronic Corpus Linguistics. Papers from the
                                sixteenth International Conference on English Language Research on
                                Computerized Corpora (ICAME 16)</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Rodopi</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">143-57</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">I.</forename>
                                    <surname>de Mönnink</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Using Corpus and Experimental Data: a Multi-method
                                Approach</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Ljung</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Papers from the seventeenth International Conference on
                                English Language Research on Computerized Corpora (ICAME 17)</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date>(forthcoming)</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Quirk</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Svartvik</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Investigating Linguistic Acceptability</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>The Hague</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Mouton</publisher>
                                <date when="1966">1966</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Quirk</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Svartvik</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">A Corpus of Modern English</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Bergenholtz</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">B.</forename>
                                    <surname>Schaeder</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Empirisch Textwissenschaft. Aufbau und Auswertung van
                                Textcorpora</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Koenigstein</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Scriptor</publisher>
                                <date when="1979">1979</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">204-218</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
