<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Mapping from objects to markup: a springboard for
                    multiple-strategy electronic publishing</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Gary</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">F.</forename>
                        <surname>Simons</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Summer Institute of Linguistics</name>
                            <email>gary.simons@sil.org</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>object-oriented databases</item>
                        <item>text markup</item>
                        <item>electronic publishing</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <p>One of the challenges of electronic publishing is getting the information
                        into the right format for the particular publishing strategy being pursued.
                        Another is keeping up with the fast pace of change as new technologies are
                        developed that offer more or better ways of electronically publishing
                        information.</p>
                    <p>This paper reports on the experience of the Summer Institute of Linguistics
                        in developing electronic publishing solutions for its LinguaLinks product
                        (SIL 1996). LinguaLinks is an electronic performance support system designed
                        to assist field workers with a wide range of tasks related to language
                        learning, language analysis, and language development.</p>
                    <p>The paper first introduces the LinguaLinks model of performance support and
                        CELLAR--the object-oriented database system that is used to implement it.
                        Our approach to electronic publishing is to first build the information as a
                        structure of objects in the database, and then to use multiple CELLAR
                        stylesheets to map the information onto multiple markup schemes. The object
                        database thus serves as a springboard that allows us to vault the
                        information into any number of formats for publishing.</p>
                    <p>The paper illustrates this approach to electronic publishing by focusing on
                        one application area that LinguaLinks supports, namely, lexical database
                        development. It first shows how the tutorial and reference documents that
                        give help on how to build a dictionary are mapped onto different markup
                        schemes for publication as a Folio Views infobase, a Windows help system,
                        and an HTML Web document. It then shows how the dictionaries that are built
                        by using LinguaLinks are mapped onto HTML markup to provide a display format
                        on the Web and onto TEI markup to provide a richer format for information
                        interchange and archiving.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>1. The LinguaLinks model of electronic performance support</head>
                    <p>The notion of electronic performance support systems (Gery 1991) is one that
                        is gaining momentum throughout industry. An EPSS seeks to support a
                        knowledge worker in performing his or her job by providing an electronic
                        working environment that integrates the software tools needed to do the job
                        with the tutorial and reference materials that are needed to know how to do
                        the job. This goes well beyond the typical help system of a software program
                        to include not just information on how to use the program but also a library
                        of background information on the problem domain.</p>
                    <p>LinguaLinks is designed to support tasks in the domains of anthropology,
                        language learning, linguistics, literacy, and sociolinguistics. Work
                        continues to add more and more resources in subsequent versions of the
                        product. In version 1.0, one of the areas that is most deeply developed is
                        lexical database management. This component includes a data management tool
                        that helps the user to build a lexical database and then to use the
                        information in that database to produce dictionaries for publication.</p>
                    <p>LinguaLinks takes advantage of the object-oriented paradigm to provide
                        performance support that is tailored to what the user is trying to do. One
                        of the hardest problems in offering electronic performance support is
                        knowing just what the user is trying to do. For instance, if a word
                        processing program were being used to write a dictionary, it would be very
                        difficult to implement performance support that could sense the context
                        within a dictionary entry and offer appropriate help. By building a
                        dictionary in an object-oriented database, however, two kinds of performance
                        support fall out naturally.</p>
                    <p>First, the software developers have performed an object- oriented analysis
                        (Coad and Yourdon 1991, Booch 1994) with domain experts in order to build
                        the conceptual model for the database. The definitions of object classes
                        (including their attributes) that make up this model provide performance
                        support by guiding the user to create dictionary entries that are structured
                        like ones the domain experts would have built; these definitions also
                        prevent ill-formed entries from being constructed.</p>
                    <p>Second, the software always knows what the user is working on by observing
                        what object and attribute is currently selected or being editing. Thus if
                        the etymology is being edited, the system knows to offer tutorial and
                        reference material on how to write etymologies when the user asks for help.
                        When the user switches focus to the part of speech, then the focus of help
                        also switches to that aspect of dictionary making, and so on for all the
                        parts of the conceptual model of a dictionary entry.</p>
                    <p>Section 2 of the paper gives an overview of the object- oriented database
                        system that is used to implement performance support in LinguaLinks. Section
                        3 describes how the object database is used as a springboard to markup for
                        electronic publishing. Section 4 then shows how the tutorial and reference
                        materials are mapped into markup in order to support multiple strategies for
                        providing performance support. Section 5 in turn shows how the dictionaries
                        built by users can be mapped into markup for multiple publishing
                        strategies.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2. An overview of the CELLAR object-oriented database system</head>
                    <p>The database system used to implement LinguaLinks is called CELLAR--for
                        Computing Environment for Linguistic, Literary, and Anthropological
                        Research. Developed by the Summer Institute of Linguistics, it is an
                        object-oriented database system for storing multilingual textual
                        information. A full discussion of the user requirements that motivated the
                        development of the system is given in Simons 1996. Rettig, Simons, and
                        Thomson (1993) discuss some of the significant ways in which CELLAR extends
                        the traditional object model.</p>
                    <p>An application in CELLAR is a declarative model of the problem domain. A
                        complete domain model has the following four components:<list
                            type="bulleted">
                            <item><emph rend="italics">Conceptual model</emph>. Declares all the
                                object classes in the problem domain and their attributes, including
                                integrity constraints on attributes that store values and built-in
                                queries on those that compute their values on-the-fly.</item>
                            <item><emph rend="italics">Visual model</emph>. Declares one or more
                                ways in which objects of each class can be formatted for display to
                                the user.</item>
                            <item><emph rend="italics">Encoding model</emph>. Declares one or more
                                ways in which objects of each class can be encoded in plain text
                                files so that users can import data from external sources or export
                                them.</item>
                            <item><emph rend="italics">Manipulation model</emph>. Declares one or
                                more tools which translate the interactive gestures of the user into
                                direct manipulation of objects in the knowledge base.</item>
                        </list></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3. Using CELLAR as a springboard to electronic publishing markup</head>
                    <p>The strategy for implementing multiple markup systems involves the visual
                        modeling component of CELLAR. For the single conceptual model of the
                        information, multiple visual models are defined. This approach has been
                        illustrated in another paper (Simons, in press) where multiple ways of
                        displaying tagged texts and critical texts are generated from the same
                        underlying database.</p>
                    <p>In this application, each visual model generates a display format that
                        happens to be a markup scheme for a particular electronic publishing system.
                        For each class of object, a view is defined that declares how the
                        information in that object is to be mapped onto the display format. All of
                        the views that cooperate to define a single visual model are collected
                        together into a stylesheet.</p>
                    <p>In this section, the full paper will present some source code examples that
                        illustrate how the views can be made to map objects onto markup.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>4. Strategies for publishing helps on building dictionaries</head>
                    <p>The tutorial and reference materials that provide performance support in
                        LinguaLinks are objects in the underlying CELLAR database. One strategy we
                        have followed for electronically publishing them is to present them in a
                        view that looks like a conventional document. But this is just one strategy.
                        We have followed three others as well:<list>
                            <item>1. In order to make jumps to the helps virtually instantaneous, we
                                have mapped them onto RTF markup and compiled them as a Windows help
                                system.</item>
                            <item>2. In order to offer full-text boolean search and retrieval access
                                to the library of helps, we have mapped them onto Folio Flat File
                                format and compiled them into a Folio Views infobase.</item>
                            <item>3. In order to offer access to these helps on the World Wide Web,
                                we have mapped them onto HTML markup.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>In this section, the full paper will present examples (with markup and screen
                        shots) of each of these.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>5. Strategies for publishing the resulting dictionaries</head>
                    <p>Similarly, the lexical database that the user builds in LinguaLinks is a
                        collection of objects in the underlying CELLAR database. One strategy for
                        electronically publishing a dictionary is to deliver it as a CELLAR database
                        with views that present it in conventional display formats. But this
                        strategy will not reach a wide audience. We have thus implemented two other
                        strategies as well:<list>
                            <item>1. In order to produce a dictionary that can be read on the World
                                Wide Web by any browser, we can map the objects onto HTML markup. </item>
                            <item>2. In order to produce a dictionary data file that can be archived
                                without any loss of structural information, we can map the objects
                                onto the TEI markup for print dictionaries (Sperberg-McQueen and
                                Burnard 1994).</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>In this section, the full paper will present examples (with markup and screen
                        shots) of each of these.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Grady</forename>
                                    <surname>Booch</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Object-oriented analysis and design with
                                applications</title>
                            <edition>2nd ed.</edition>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Redwood City, CA</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Benjamin/Cummings Publishing Co</publisher>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Peter</forename>
                                    <surname>Coad</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Edward</forename>
                                    <surname>Yourdon</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Object-oriented analysis</title>
                            <edition>2nd ed</edition>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Prentice-Hall, Inc.</publisher>
                                <date when="1991">1991</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Gloria</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Gery</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Electronic performance support systems</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Weingarten Publications</publisher>
                                <date when="1991">1991</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Marc</forename>
                                    <surname>Rettig</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Gary</forename>
                                    <surname>Simons</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">John</forename>
                                    <surname>Thomson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Extended objects</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Communications of the ACM </title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">36</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">8</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">19-24</biblScope>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name type="org">SIL</name>
                            </author>
                            <title>LinguaLinks: electronic helps for language field work</title>
                            <edition>(Version 1.0). CD-ROM</edition>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Dallas, TX</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Summer Institute of Linguistics</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>See also <ptr target="http://www.sil.org/lingualinks"/></note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Gary</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">F.</forename>
                                    <surname>Simons</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">The nature of linguistic data and the requirements of a
                                computing environment for linguistic research</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Dutch studies on Near Eastern languages and
                                literatures</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">2</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">111-128</biblScope>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>Also to appear in John Lawler and Helen Dry (eds.), <title level="m"
                                >Using computers in linguistics: a practical guide</title>.
                            Routledge.</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Gary</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">F.</forename>
                                    <surname>Simons</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Conceptual modeling versus visual modeling: a
                                technological key to building consensus</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol"/>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp"/>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>In press.</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Sperberg-McQueen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Lou</forename>
                                    <surname>Burnard</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Guidelines for electronic text encoding and
                                interchange</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Chicago and Oxford</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Text Encoding Initiative</publisher>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>

                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
