<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="panel">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Labour Issues in Humanities Computing</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Andrea</forename>
                        <surname>Austin</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Queen's University</name>
                            <email>3aja1@qucdn.queensu.ca</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">David</forename>
                        <surname>Halsted</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Michigan State University</name>
                            <email>halsted@h-net.msu.edu</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Perry</forename>
                        <surname>Willett</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Indiana University</name>
                            <email>pwillett@indiana.edu</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>labour</item>
                        <item>resources</item>
                        <item>management</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <p>Computing humanists often point to the potential of information technologies
                        in academia by citing the emerging roles of scholars as creators and
                        maintainers of vast, digital archives, as facilitators of communication
                        amongst other scholars, and as innovators in the use of technology in the
                        teaching process. A central question remains, however: how exactly is all
                        this work to be accomplished? Labour issues are a key factor in the rate of
                        the integration of information technologies into humanities teaching and
                        research. This series of papers explores three aspects of the managing of
                        labour in humanities computing: the administration of a large, online
                        distributed project involving humanities e-mail lists; the creation of
                        quality electronic texts; and the establishment of professional support for
                        discipline-specific humanities computing. David Halsted details the
                        management strategies effectively used by H-Net, a project consisting of
                        over 75 academic e-mail lists and an official web site, and centrally
                        administrated at Michigan State University. Perry Willett describes the
                        challenges of creating a collection of electronic texts for the Victorian
                        Women Writers Project at Indiana University. Andrea Austin discusses hiring
                        trends and support models that respond to the increasingly specialized
                        computing needs of separate disciplines within the humanities. Particularly
                        in the current climate of fiscal restraint, solutions to problems of labour
                        in humanities computing are critical; these three papers, each from within a
                        different specific context, describe significant labour problems and present
                        possible solutions.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>Managing Labor and Managing Management in a Distributed Online
                            Humanities Project: The H-Net Experience</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">David Halsted</p>
                        <div>
                            <p>H-Net is a large online Humanities project with a highly distributed
                                structure. Our 75 academic e-mail lists reach over 54,000
                                subscribers around the globe, and our Web site was receiving 200,000
                                hits weekly as of late September 1996. H-Net's lists are edited by
                                250 volunteer academics from all over the world. Policy is set by
                                the H-Net Executive Committee, which meets primarily by e-mail; the
                                Executive Committee is elected by H-Net editors and staff. Labor,
                                administration, list maintenance and Web site design and maintenance
                                are all centralized at Michigan State University. The H-Net project
                                thus provides an interesting model for large and highly distributed
                                collaborative online projects in the Humanities. It may be a useful
                                example for smaller collaborative projects as well.</p>
                            <p>H-Net began as a relatively small project in 1993 (three e-mail lists
                                with 500 subscribers and a handful of editors). As we have grown we
                                have had to develop ways of coping with that growth. One major step
                                came in the fall of 1995, when H-Net MSU began to hire a large staff
                                of part-time student workers. This new work force brought a host of
                                new difficulties (payroll, management, supervision, training, etc.),
                                each of which has had to be addressed. In the meantime, the growth
                                of the H-Net editorial community from a few individuals to the
                                current corps of 250 has meant that we have had to develop
                                mechanisms for training editors and providing them with technical
                                help.</p>
                            <p>Our rapidly-growing subscriber base requires a different form of
                                technical help from the help we offer our editors, and subscribers
                                require the academic equivalent of customer service. Individual
                                projects, such as the H-Net review project and H-Net's Job Guide,
                                require training, staffing, and their own customer service. Finally,
                                the establishment of the Gopher and Web sites, which account for the
                                bulk of our labor costs, has generated new needs in training,
                                supervision and quality control. The Web site in turn generates
                                inquiries from new potential subscribers as well as current H-Net
                                participators, causing us to create yet another level of response to
                                customer concerns.</p>
                            <p>My paper will briefly summarize the challenges we face and the
                                solutions we have reached, in the hope both of providing an example
                                to others (even if only a negative one) and of learning from other
                                projects. I will discuss the following major areas:</p>
                            <p>1) Software</p>
                            <p>To reduce labor costs, we have found that it is crucial to make the
                                best use possible of tracking databases and project management
                                systems. Unlike some other major Humanities computing projects, we
                                write our own software, which reduces upfront costs and increases
                                our ability to customize; however, writing the software places an
                                added burden on our technical staff. It is also important to keep
                                abreast of potentially labor-saving developments in the commercial
                                software world; for example, we are moving to using three or four
                                different programs for different purposes in the mark-up
                                process.</p>
                            <p>2) Customer Service</p>
                            <p>Customer service, or the academic equivalent, is a major concern and
                                should be taken very seriously from the beginning of any online
                                project with a potentially large audience, since a large audience
                                will inevitably include a number of "newbies" who will need help to
                                use online resources effectively. Large distributed projects will
                                have to consider providing effective and prompt technical help to
                                customers (like our subscribers) and collaborators (like our
                                editors) alike.</p>
                            <p>3) Equipment</p>
                            <p>Every Humanities project with which I am familiar faces considerable
                                challenges when it comes to keeping up equipment. Equipment
                                purchasing and on-going maintenance must be taken into account in
                                planning for labor costs. On-going costs are generated by
                                improvements in technology (students really prefer working on
                                Pentiums to working on 486 machines; next year, no doubt, they'll
                                want Pentium Pros), by the ever-increasing memory demands of
                                contemporary software packages, and by the simple fact that complex,
                                delicate machines used by a number of users just plain break a
                                lot.</p>
                            <p>4) Training and turnover</p>
                            <p>Training and turnover in a student workforce are also typical
                                difficulties for online Humanities projects housed in universities.
                                Students who already know what you need them to know can often
                                command much higher salaries off-campus than a Humanities project
                                can muster; students also have an annoying tendency to graduate.
                                This creates an on-going turnover and training problem. Training a
                                workforce is a problem that must be addressed early if student
                                staffers are going to be used. Training for management should also
                                be considered.</p>
                            <p>5) Decision-making structures</p>
                            <p>The clearer the hierarchy and the division of decision-making powers
                                is, the better a distributed project will work. My guess is that
                                there will be a certain amount of ambiguity about hierarchy in any
                                collaborative academic project of any size, even where shared
                                enthusiasm generates good will among collaborators. Shared
                                Web-authoring, for example, can lead to conflicts over content,
                                aesthetics, and the exact scope and purpose of a site or sites.
                                Since the vision of what Web sites can do is evolving so rapidly, it
                                may be too much to expect a binding a priori statement for new
                                projects, but a shared sense of vision and some understanding of the
                                division of responsibilities will turn out to be crucial as projects
                                (inevitably) evolve.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>E-Text Creation as Cottage Industry: The Victorian Women Writers
                            Project</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">Perry Willett</p>
                        <div>
                            <p>The creation of electronic texts is a labor-intensive process. The
                                amount of effort and skill required to create accurately transcribed
                                and encoded electronic texts is not trivial, and may seem daunting
                                to anyone contemplating such a project. Many projects have large
                                budgets derived from grants, endowments and other sources, to pay
                                for work by students or typing agencies. Such projects generally
                                have a wide scope, looking to create electronic collections from
                                across period or national boundaries.</p>
                            <p>The Victorian Women Writers Project at Indiana University has
                                operated so far with almost no budget, using a number of creative
                                strategies. By creating undergraduate internships, involving
                                volunteers, finding small university research grants, and drawing
                                from hourly budgets, the Project has been able to create a growing
                                collection of important and scarce works by 19th century British
                                women writers. This approach, closer in spirit to the cottage
                                industries of the period rather than industrial production, draws on
                                enthusiam both for this period and for the WWW.</p>
                            <p>By focusing only on texts from the Victorian era (1837-1901), the
                                Project has had more impact with its scant resources, albeit on a
                                narrow range of scholars, than if its scope had been broader. There
                                is a large (and seemingly growing) interest in the literature,
                                history, fashion and culture of Victorian England, involving many
                                people both inside and outside of the academy. Their enthusiasm has
                                made the Victorian Women Writers Project site very popular, with
                                almost 20,000 visits in its first year. By drawing on this interest,
                                the Project has included the effort of several volunteers who have
                                donated their time to preserving and making available works by women
                                of this period. Funds have been found in various parts of the
                                library's budget to hire part-time students for the typing and
                                preparation of electronic texts.</p>
                            <p>The English Department at Indiana University has a strong interest in
                                Victorian Studies, and in support of the Project has created an
                                undergraduate internship, similar to its internships for academic
                                journals. Students who apply for the internship receive credit for
                                creating, editing and proofreading electronic editions, and in the
                                process learn about the World Wide Web, SGML and HTML, and women's
                                writing of the period. One industrious student received a small
                                university research grant for his work during the summer.</p>
                            <p>The process of creating an electronic edition is time-consuming. Each
                                etext is transcribed, encoded and proofed by either students or
                                volunteers. Some of the participants have been trained in the TEI
                                Guidelines, while others use a simplified encoding scheme. The
                                General Editor then verifies the accuracy of the encoding and
                                transcription by proofing the text again, and creates digital images
                                of title pages and illustrations. Every step of this process can be
                                accomplished using relatively inexpensive or free software available
                                on most university computing networks.</p>
                            <p>The Project is overseen by an Advisory Board made up of seven
                                prominent Victorianists from universities across the country. They
                                volunteer their time and expertise out of their desire to make
                                literature by women of this period more widely available. Using
                                e-mail as the primary mode of communication, the board has reached
                                decisions concerning general direction as well as specific decisions
                                concerning authors and editions to include. The board plans to meet
                                at conferences, such as the annual Modern Languages Association
                                Convention in December 1997 in Washington D.C.</p>
                            <p>The General Editor has applied for grants for further expansion, but
                                believes that the model established for this Project can be used by
                                many other librarians and scholars with few available resources.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>Discipline-Specific Humanities Computing: Whose Job Is It?</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">Andrea Austin</p>
                        <div>
                            <p>With higher education institutions experiencing unprecedented growth
                                in distributed computing, pressures to support the needs of
                                students, faculty, administrators and staff using these systems in
                                various and diverse ways have also increased substantially. In
                                particular, there has been an increasing awareness that if faculty
                                are going to integrate IT into teaching and students to benefit from
                                the full potential of IT in their individual programs, support for
                                discipline-specific computing must be implemented and maintained.
                                The big question for most institutions has been "who is to provide
                                this support?" This paper presents several models that have been
                                adopted for providing computing support to humanities faculty, and
                                focuses on the following key issues as spelling the success or
                                failure of these models: ability to provide adequate support at the
                                departmental level, at present and in the future; demand on faculty
                                time and energy; credentials and range of responsibilities of
                                professionals providing the support. Examples of models in use at
                                specific universities are offered where appropriate (in the interest
                                of brevity, reference to these examples has been omitted from the
                                abstract). Ultimately, the paper ends with an endorsement of
                                decentralized support models</p>
                            <p>While budget restraints have driven a trend towards centralization in
                                the administration of computing services, an equally influential
                                trend towards decentralization has been driven by the complexity of
                                resources required to meet the needs of diverse users. In providing
                                humanities computing support, many institutions have opted for what
                                has been called an "intermediary solution" ("Integrating Information
                                Services in an Academic Setting: The Organizational and Technical
                                Challenge," <title level="j">CAUSE/EFFECT</title> 17:3, 1994),
                                either establishing a humanities computing center or delegating to
                                certain computing center personnel the specific task of responding
                                to the needs of humanities faculty. These support personnel work
                                more closely with humanities faculty than has traditionally been the
                                case with generalized computing services personnel, taking on the
                                responsibilities of helping faculty to upgrade computing skills,
                                making faculty aware of computing resources that might be of
                                specific interest to them, and working with faculty in designing
                                course materials that take advantage of such resources.</p>
                            <p>Administrators cite the numerous advantages of such models. They do
                                more towards getting IT staff out of the office and into the work
                                environment where the services are actually being used, increasing
                                the support professional's ability to understand the computing goals
                                of humanities faculty and interpret requests for help from them.
                                This semi- centralized support system is also often seen as more
                                cost effective than allowing each department to establish and
                                maintain its own computing services system. Hiring only a few
                                professionals can meet the needs of several departments at once,
                                both avoiding duplication of services and resources expenditures and
                                having the likelihood of avoiding expensive interoperability
                                problems down the road. The combination of enhanced ability to
                                respond to increasingly complex user demand and at the same time
                                stay within budget, or even save money, make these models especially
                                attractive.</p>
                            <p>Administrators cite the numerous advantages of such models. They do
                                more towards getting IT staff out of the office and into the work
                                environment where the services are actually being used, increasing
                                the support professional's ability to understand the computing goals
                                of humanities faculty and interpret requests for help from them.
                                This semi- centralized support system is also often seen as more
                                cost effective than allowing each department to establish and
                                maintain its own computing services system. Hiring only a few
                                professionals can meet the needs of several departments at once,
                                both avoiding duplication of services and resources expenditures and
                                having the likelihood of avoiding expensive interoperability
                                problems down the road. The combination of enhanced ability to
                                respond to increasingly complex user demand and at the same time
                                stay within budget, or even save money, make these models especially
                                attractive.</p>
                            <p>There are some disadvantages to the semi-centralized approach,
                                however, most of which stem precisely from its status as an
                                intermediary solution. In practice, these models often do not go far
                                enough towards providing the level of discipline-specific support
                                that enables faculty to develop exciting and innovative use of IT
                                resources. Similar tendencies as those at work in general computing
                                services centers exist, primarily a factor of there still being too
                                few people to meet too large a number of demands. More time is often
                                spent on basic upgrading of faculty computing skills and on
                                introducing faculty to resources than it is in developing
                                discipline-specific applications. At the same time, such models
                                often tend to draw almost as heavily on un(der)paid student labour
                                as general computing services centers, with the professional
                                humanities computing support staff acting as administrators and
                                coordinators, rather than interacting with faculty at the individual
                                level. As a result of this still-inadequate human resources supply,
                                faculty wishing to move beyond more basic applications are
                                frequently left to muddle along by themselves, shifting the load
                                back again to also already-overworked faculty. An additional problem
                                is that currently few departments have developed a defined system
                                for evaluating and rewarding the activities of faculty who decide to
                                devote time and energy to such tasks, having the effect of
                                already-overworked faculty taking on what is therefore tantamount to
                                extra, unpaid labour. Add to this the suspicion among faculty in
                                many departments that "real" jobs are somehow being lost to
                                computers or "techies" ( "Reengineering Teaching and Learning in
                                Higher Education: Sheltered Groves, Camelot, Windmills, and Malls,"
                                R. Heterick, Jr., ed., <title level="s">CAUSE Professional Paper
                                    Series #10</title>) and it is easy to see how, though a
                                cost-effective solution, the semi-centralized approach can be less
                                strategically effective than it might seem.</p>
                            <p>A more thoroughly decentralized approach, and currently the less
                                common approach, is that of hiring a faculty member who specializes
                                in humanities computing into each department. Responsibilities could
                                range from teaching humanties computing courses specifically
                                focussed for that discipline, to developing discipline-specific
                                applications and courseware, to maintaining departmental servers and
                                administrating departmental IT resources; responsiblities could also
                                involve peer support and encouragement in adopting IT for teaching.
                                Advantages of this model include the obvious gain of truly
                                discipline-specific support, putting the needed service as close to
                                the end user as possible. Economically, the hiring of humanities
                                computing faculty members for each department may not be as wasteful
                                as it sounds. When faculty are told that there is not enough money
                                for both additional IT resources and another faculty member, if
                                given the choice, they will usually opt for the faculty member
                                ("Using Information Technology to Enhance Academic Productivity," W.
                                Massy and R. Zemsky, <title level="u">Educom Conference, June,
                                    1995</title>). Indeed, these "in-house" humanities computing
                                specialists could--and at some institutions, do--also teach courses
                                in the department's main discipline. For the price of one professor,
                                an English department could, for example, gain both a humanities
                                computing specialist and an eighteenth-century literature
                                specialist. With both sets of duties being officially defined as
                                part of the faculty member's position, professional rewards for work
                                done and a more equitable workload may be more likely to be
                                achieved.</p>
                            <p>Disadvantages of this model consist primarily of interoperability
                                problems and duplication of services, two of the issues that the
                                semi-centralized model does address well. These disadvantages are
                                not inevitable, however; coordinated efforts on the part of
                                departments, schools or divisions, and computing services, occuring
                                in the context of an institution-wide general IT strategy, can
                                eliminate most of these problems. Well-defined roles for each level
                                of support would then become a crucial issue; computing services
                                providing skills upgrading and general connectivity support, for
                                instance, with departments providing the bulk of discipline-specific
                                support and application development and schools or divisions running
                                introductory humanities computing courses, possibly team-taught or
                                taught alternately by faculty members from different departments who
                                would also teach more discipline-specific computing courses aimed at
                                upper-year students would be an example of an effective work
                                arrangement between the different levels. A more serious
                                disadvantage, at this point in time, is the lack of candidates for
                                such a position; as department heads have pointed out, finding
                                Ph.D-ed potential faculty members who are also sufficiently
                                qualified in humanities computing can be a daunting task ("Jobs for
                                Computing Humanists," E. Johnson, <title level="j">Computers and the
                                    Humanities</title>, 27.2,1993). I believe, however, that this is
                                a problem in the process of righting itself, as more and more
                                faculty and graduate students become involved--and credentialed,
                                either by way of degree program or publication--in humanities
                                computing.</p>
                            <p>Higher education institutions are currently at a crossroads in
                                balancing what services they can afford with what services they
                                really do need. One thing is clear: more and more faculty are going
                                to move beyond basic computing abilities, and more and more students
                                thoroughly conversant with information technologies are going to
                                enroll. Humanities computing support models are going to have to
                                keep pace with these changes.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
