<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The Online Reference Book for Medieval Studies</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Carolyn</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">P.</forename>
                        <surname>Schriber</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Rhodes College</name>
                            <email>schriber@rhodes.edu</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>website</item>
                        <item>medieval studies</item>
                        <item>teaching</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The "heart" of The Online Reference Book for Medieval Studies (ORB) is an
                    encyclopedia that provides original essays written by leading scholars in each
                    field. These introductory remarks, designed for entry-level college students,
                    are supplemented by bibliographic essays that lay out the state of current
                    scholarship in the field and discuss research methods. Specialized essays on
                    related topics expand each field for more advanced students. Links to other ORB
                    sections flesh out the encyclopedia. We provide detailed bibliographies, maps,
                    original source material in translation, diagrams, works of art, sound clips,
                    and photographs. Instructors can also find sample syllabi, teaching aids, lists
                    of related websites, addresses of specialized scholarly organizations, journals,
                    and discussion groups. These are the building blocks, from which instructors can
                    design individual courses that meet the specific needs of their students.</p>
                <p>Current holdings have expanded to over 90 megabytes. We have 123 contributing
                    writers from 10 countries. Materials are primarily in English, but we also carry
                    entries in German, French, and Latin. We have affiliated websites around the
                    world; these allow our topic editors to maintain their materials at their own
                    universities while retaining full accessibility through ORB. Our Sourcebook,
                    which contains over 300 short teaching selections, resides at Fordham. The
                    library of book-length translations remains at Kansas and is mirrored at
                    Berkeley. The section on Late Antiquity is at Nipissing University in Ontario.
                    The Anglo-Saxon section, appropriately enough, runs from the Center for
                    Computing at Oxford. Medieval Spain is at Little Rock. The Encyclopedia of Early
                    Christianity is at Evansville. The database on women's religious houses is at
                    Mt. Holyoak. The database of liturgical imprints is at the University of
                    Michigan. Old English literature is at Georgetown, the Scots language and
                    Literature project is at the university of Glasgow, the Dante site is located in
                    Berlin, and the material on the Low Countries is centered in Amsterdam.</p>
                <p>ORB has received favorable reviews in <title level="j">The Chronicle of Higher
                        Education</title> and in a publication of the University of Wisconsin at
                    Madison. It has been catalogued for inclusion on OCLC and MARC--a sign of its
                    acceptance among librarians as a valuable research tool. ORB, of course, will
                    never be finished. It is an on-going project, in which materials are added and
                    updated on a regular basis. It will expand in step with our own increasing
                    technological capabilities. Of course the crucial question is whether these
                    materials are being used. At the moment the Rhodes server alone is receiving
                    over 6000 hits per day. That works out to over four connections per minute, 24
                    hours a day. Inquiries and comments come from all over the world. We are still
                    actively recruiting writers and expanding our coverage of topics. This
                    conference seems to be an ideal place to inform scholars of the resources we
                    offer and to encourage others to contribute to our efforts.</p>
                <p>As editor of The Online Reference Book for Medieval Studies (ORB), I am very
                    interested in presenting our year-old WorldWideWeb project to participants in
                    the Joint International Conference of ACH-ALLC'97. I would be happy to present a
                    poster session and to conduct live demonstrations of our website at <ptr
                        target="http://orb.rhodes.edu"/>.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
