<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">In Defense of Invalid SGML</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">David</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Birnbaum</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Pittsburgh</name>
                            <email>djbpitt+@pitt.edu</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>SGML</item>
                        <item>DTD</item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>SGML was developed primarily for encoding new texts, an environment in which the
                    rigorous adherence to a DTD ensures that the resulting documents will observe a
                    coherent structure. For example, if a dictionary is divided into, among other
                    things, lexical entries, which consist of a keyword followed by a phonetic
                    transcription followed by examples, this structural feature can be represented
                    partially by the following declaration: <lb/>
                    <eg>&lt;!ELEMENT entry - - (keyword, phonetic, example+)&gt;</eg></p>
                <p>Users who create new dictionaries based on this DTD will be required by their
                    SGML editing and validating tools to include exactly one keyword followed by
                    exactly one phonetic transcription followed by at least one example. The SGML
                    software is not, of course, able to ensure that the #PCDATA content of these
                    component elements is correct, but it can guarantee, for example, that the
                    element <emph rend="italics">phonetic</emph> will precede, and not follow, the
                    element <emph rend="italics">example</emph>.</p>
                <p>This model is appropriate in an environment where SGML tools are used to create
                    structured documents, but it is far less well suited to a different environment
                    that happens to be extremely common in humanities computing: producing
                    electronic versions of preexisting documents. The problem is that preexisting
                    documents that were created outside SGML editors may, because of the fallability
                    of human editors, violate the overall logical structure of those documents,
                    leaving the editor of the electronic edition with three unattractive choices: 1)
                    "correct" the original text during transcription, 2) create a loose DTD that
                    does not enforce a strict element order, or 3) create an invalid document that
                    violates its DTD.</p>
                <p>The first of these alternatives, "correcting" errors in the original source
                    document, is unattractive because transcriptions of (to continue the original
                    example) existing print dictionaries have two essences: they are new and
                    functional electronic dictionaries and they are electronic records of existing
                    archaeographic materials, viz. print dictionaries. While "correcting" errors
                    observes the spirit of the first of these essences, it runs counter to the
                    second.</p>
                <p>The second alternative, creating a loose DTD that does not enforce a strict
                    element order (by, for example, replacing the commas with ampersands in the
                    content model portion of the element declaration above), is unattractive because
                    it sacrifices structural information. If the evidence clearly points to the
                    transgression of a structure involving strict order, rather than to conformity
                    to a loose structure that does not require strict order, a DTD based on the
                    latter conceals information about the document, viz. what is regular and what is
                    exceptional.</p>
                <p>The solution that best preserves the integrity of the original source while
                    simultaneously encoding the difference between norm and violation of norm is the
                    third alternative, the creation of an invalid document that violates its DTD.
                    This solution is unavailable, and, indeed, almost kinky or subversive in an SGML
                    context because our perception of SGML as a way of modeling document structure
                    assumes both that documents may be structured and that if they are structured,
                    that structure should be represented by the DTD. The weakness in this
                    perspective is that documents created in obvious conformity to a very explicit
                    structure (such as dictionaries), but created without the assistance of SGML
                    tools, may occasionally violate their structure through human error. These
                    violations are informational, at least from an archaeographic perspective, and
                    should be preserved. And what should be preserved is not merely that the
                    offending portions observe a different structure, and certainly not that the
                    overall document structure is generally loose. What should be preserved is what
                    document analysis reveals: the document has a highly-structured DTD and the
                    offending portions are conceptual DTD violations, rather than alternative valid
                    structures.</p>
                <p>I do not advocate, of course, that we prepare and publish invalid SGML, or that
                    SGML processing software be enhanced to react affirmatively not only to valid
                    SGML events, but also to SGML errors. But I would suggest that when we perform
                    document analysis on existing texts, we recognize that some oddities may at
                    least logically (although perhaps not practically) be represented not as
                    document structure, but as violations of document structure.</p>
                <p>The requirement that SGML be valid seems in most contexts so obvious that it
                    would never be questioned, but if document analysis of existing documents
                    reveals violations of structure, the most appropriate model of this information
                    in SGML terms involves invalid SGML. If the creation of invalid SGML is
                    foreclosed for practical reasons, our most honest alternative is to enrich
                    whatever solution we do adopt with annotations in markup that tell the truth:
                    what we are encoding are the equivalent of parser error messages, and the fact
                    that our document violates its basic structure in specific places is
                    informational.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
