<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Marking up in TATOE and exporting to SGML - Rule
                    development for identifying NITF categories</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Lothar</forename>
                        <surname>Rostek</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">GMD - Integrated Publication and Information Systems
                                Institute</name>
                            <email>rostek@darmstadt.gmd.de</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>semantic mark up</item>
                        <item>proper noun extraction</item>
                        <item>SGML</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>We have analyzed a corpus of German news messages with the general aim of
                        extracting semantic information. More specifically, we have focused on the
                        automatic categorization of proper nouns relating to persons, organizations,
                        locations as well as numeral and temporal expressions. Proper noun
                        identification and classification has been examined for different languages,
                        such as English, Chinese or Japanese ((Wakao et al. 1996), (Chen and Lee
                        1996) Kitani and Mitamura (1994) among many others). As far as German is
                        concerned two features which are idiosyncratic of the language and
                        complicate this task are first, German makes no surface distinction in the
                        spelling of both proper nouns and common nouns, i.e. common nouns are also
                        spelled with the first letter capitalized. Second, compounds in German can
                        be long, without any word boundaries or hyphenation between the contained
                        nouns and are therefore relatively difficult to identify.</p>
                    <p>This work belongs to a project which aims at a real-world application and due
                        to this reason the categories of the SGML-based standard News Industry Text
                        Format (NITF) have been applied. NITF was developed by the International
                        Press Telecommunication Council (IPTC) for the exchange of news messages. An
                        interesting feature of the NITF standard is that besides structural mark up,
                        it allows also semantic encoding. Our aim in this project has been twofold:
                        first, to develop an algorithm for the automatic identification of those
                        phrases in new incoming messages which contain semantic information, e.g.
                        names of persons, organizations, places, weekdays etc. Second, to mark up
                        the messages according to the respective NITF categories and export the
                        marked up messages as an NITF conformant SGML text. The degree of
                        correctness of the automatic marked up texts is decisive for the
                        applicability of this method for the daily practice.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The general application context</head>
                    <p>The task reported above is part of the CLIP-ing project, a national
                        collaborative project supported by DeTe-Berkom (a subsidiary of the German
                        Telekom AG). One of the partners of the consortium is the German press
                        agency (dpa), which provided us with the corpus of news messages. IPTC is
                        another partner and has had a strong interest in the possibility of
                        automatic semantic encoding using the NITF standard. The goal of the
                        CLIP-ing project is to support the linking of different agency services as
                        well as the planning and managing of the news production and to add further
                        value to news content by means of content indexing, and to conform to
                        standards. It is envisaged that in that way news agencies may provide their
                        clients with news reports which are semantically marked up according to the
                        NITF standard. This creates an additional value to information sources of
                        news agencies and provides for richer information requirements which news
                        agencies clients may have.</p>
                    <p>Within the CLIP-ing project a specific work area relevant to content indexing
                        concerns the investigation of ways to analyze machine-readable news texts
                        for the automatic identification and semantic classification of proper
                        nouns, e.g. 'Hans Albrecht', 'Ontario', 'UNICEF', as well as temporal
                        expressions and phrases denoting person roles, e.g. 'Anfang Oktober 1996'
                        (beginning of October 1996), 'Bildungsminister' (minister of education).
                        This task bears similarities to the general text analysis systems which are
                        reported in the message understanding conference proceedings (Grishman and
                        Sundheim 1996, MUC-3, MUC-5). Our task here is not to develop a full blown
                        information extraction or text analysis system, but rather to extract only
                        certain application-related information from the news messages and render it
                        in a standard format, embedding it thus in the workflow process.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Methodology</head>
                    <p>A corpus of 483 raw dpa news messages drawn from the dpa text database has
                        been analyzed. In order to have an evaluation basis for the automatic
                        extraction the whole corpus has been marked up by human coders. Given that
                        the main source of information for the development of the extraction rules
                        has been the news messages corpus itself, it has been important to have
                        flexible means for inspecting and viewing corpus words and the contexts they
                        occur in. Furthermore, and abstracting from the single word type level,
                        enabling the display of selective concordances by means of syntactic and/or
                        semantic patterns is of course advantageous. To enable the definition of
                        syntactic patterns, we have used GERTWOL, a morphological analysis tool for
                        German from Lingsoft, Finland (<ptr target="http://www.lingsoft.fi"/>). With
                        regards to the semantic information, our aim has been to define mechanisms
                        for filtering out relevant words according to part of speech categories and
                        then classifying them semantically.</p>
                    <p>For the analysis tasks described above we have used the Text Analysis Tool
                        with Object Encoding (TATOE) (Alexa &amp; Rostek 1996). Two features of
                        TATOE which are important for this kind of work are: TATOE enables the
                        analyst to develop corpus-based pattern rules for parsing and marking up a
                        corpus of texts according to a categorization schema (Alexa &amp; Rostek
                        1997). The other feature is that TATOE enables analysis and mark up of the
                        corpus texts according to different categorization schemata concurrently.
                        Since TATOE did not support the export of mark up into SGML encoded text, an
                        export procedure has been defined for the particular application context.
                        This is presented later on in this paper.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Semantic mark up</head>
                    <p>The dpa corpus which we imported in TATOE contains 483 dpa messages with
                        20,407 word types and 124,691 word tokens. We have defined and used two
                        categorization schemata in TATOE. Each schema contains categories which are
                        based on the NITF categories for semantic markup. One of the schemata has
                        been used in order to mark up all the texts intellectually with such NITF
                        categories as PERSON, FUNCTION, CITY, CHRON, etc. Additionally to the
                        standard NITF categories, we have defined more specific ones in order to
                        allow for more detailed information; for example, the categories PCHRON and
                        FCHRON for distinguishing between past and future temporal phrases or
                        FUNCPERS for those phrases which express a named person <emph rend="italics"
                            >together</emph> with his/her role. This intellectual mark up has been
                        used as a test basis for the evaluation of the correctness of the automatic
                        mark up.</p>
                    <p>The second schema consists of the same categories (although its categories
                        are spelled slightly different to enable comparisons) and has been used for
                        storing and displaying the automatically performed mark up. A set of pattern
                        rules have been defined in order to parse and mark up the texts
                        accordingly.</p>
                    <p>The evaluation of the correctness of the automatic mark up is then a
                        comparison between the mark up of the two schemata, i.e. it measures the
                        differences between the intellectual and the automatic mark up.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Exporting performed semantic mark up into SGML</head>
                    <p>Each marked up position in TATOE is stored into an object representing the
                        paragraph it belongs to. This object contains also the text of the
                        paragraph. This storing mechanism separating the text from its mark up
                        positions has the advantage of enabling fast selection and display of all
                        mark up according to the current schema selected by the user. In addition,
                        multiple and overlapping mark up does not pose a problem. However, if one
                        wants to export the mark up into an SGML format, first the mark up positions
                        need to be selected, then sorted and finally the SGML tags need to be
                        inserted into the original text. Furthermore, this process has to respect
                        the dependencies between the marked up elements. For example, in the text
                        shown below, the system has stored two marked up phrases, namely
                        'Regisseurin' and 'Regisseurin Andrea Breth'; however, it needs to be
                        recognized that there is an interdependence between the two phrases, that
                        is, the first phrase is part of the second and that for this text an element
                        called FUNCTION should be inserted inside the PERSON element.</p>
                    <eg>&lt;NITF&gt;&lt;HEAD&gt;&lt;TOBJECT&gt;&lt;/TOBJEC&gt;&gt;T&gt;
                        &lt;IPTC7901.WIREHEAD IPTC7901.PRIORITY="5" IPTC7901.TIMEDATE="281434
                        Aug 91" IPTC7901.SVCID="bas" IPTC7901.OPTINFO="vvvvb dpa 260 "
                        IPTC7901.KEYWORD="Theater" IPTC7901.MSGNUM="362"
                        IPTC7901.CATEGORY="ku"&gt;&lt;/HEAD&gt;
                        &lt;BOD&gt;Y&gt;&lt;HEDLINE&gt;&lt;HL1&gt;&lt;PERSON&gt;Andrea
                        Breth&lt;/PERSON&gt; in künstlerischer Leitung der
                        &lt;ORG&gt;Berliner
                        Schaubühne&lt;/ORG&gt;&lt;/HL1&gt;&lt;/HEDLINE&gt;
                        &lt;DATELINE&gt;&lt;LOCATION&gt;Berlin&lt;/LOCATION&gt;&lt;/DATELINE&gt;
                        &lt;P&gt;Die
                        &lt;PERSON&gt;&lt;FUNCTION&gt;Regisseurin&lt;/FUNCTION&gt;
                        Andrea Breth&lt;/PERSON&gt; gehört mit Beginn der Spielzeit
                        &lt;CHRON NORM="19920101"&gt;1992&lt;/CHRON&gt; /
                        &lt;NUM&gt;93&lt;/NUM&gt; der künstlerischen Leitung der
                        &lt;ORG&gt;Berliner Schaubühne am Lehniner Platz&lt;/ORG&gt;
                        an, teilte das &lt;ORG&gt;Theater&lt;/ORG&gt; am
                        &lt;CHRON NORM="19910827"&gt;Dienstag&lt;/CHRON&gt; mit. Sie
                        übernimmt die unbesetzte Stelle von &lt;PERSON&gt;Jürgen
                        Gosch&lt;/PERSON&gt; , von dem sich das
                        &lt;ORG&gt;Theater&lt;/ORG&gt; zum Jahresende &lt;CHRON
                        NORM="19890101"&gt;1989&lt;/CHRON&gt; vorzeitig getrennt hatte.
                        &lt;PERSON&gt;Andrea Breth&lt;/PERSON&gt; inszeniert derzeit
                        an der &lt;ORG&gt;Schaubühne&lt;/ORG&gt;
                        &lt;PERSON&gt;Arthur Schnitzlers&lt;/PERSON&gt; Stück "Der
                        einsame Weg". Die Premiere ist für den &lt;CHRON
                        NORM="19900930"&gt;30. September&lt;/CHRON&gt; angekündigt. Die
                        38jährige &lt;FUNCTION&gt;Regisseurin&lt;/FUNCTION&gt;
                        arbeitet auch noch am &lt;ORG&gt;Wiener
                        Burgtheater&lt;/ORG&gt;&gt; unter dem
                        &lt;PERSON&gt;&lt;FUNCTION&gt;Intendanten&lt;/FUNCTION&gt;
                        Claus Peymann&lt;/PERSON&gt;
                        .&lt;/P&gt;&lt;/BODY&gt;&lt;/NITF&gt;</eg>
                    <p>During the generation of the SGML expression for each paragraph in a text we
                        calculate an inclusion lattice of the marked up phrases to order the
                        overlapping elements and to determine the insertion points. In that way mark
                        up export from TATOE in SGML is enabled.</p>
                    <p>For the temporal information marked up as CHRON elements the system following
                        the NITF guidelines creates an SGML attribute NORM which has as value the
                        concrete date of the temporal phrase in a normalized form. In the text above
                            <emph rend="bold">&lt;CHRON
                            NORM="19910827"&gt;Dienstag&lt;/CHRON&gt;</emph> means that
                        Dienstag (German for Tuesday) was 27th August 1991 calculated from the fact
                        that the Tuesday before the date of the message (28.8.91).</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Conclusions</head>
                    <p>We have defined this export procedure from TATOE to SGML specifically for the
                        CLIP-ing application context. Clearly, a general solution for this
                        requirement has to be provided, whereby a general descriptive formalism
                        within TATOE is specified in order to determine the mapping from mark up
                        into some SGML tagged text. Nevertheless we feel that the defined export
                        procedure is an important step towards that direction.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Melina</forename>
                                    <surname>Alexa</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Lothar</forename>
                                    <surname>Rostek</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Pattern concordances - TATOE calls XGrammar</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">Paper to be presented at ALLC-ACH97, Kingston, Canada.
                                June 1997</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Melina</forename>
                                    <surname>Alexa</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Lothar</forename>
                                    <surname>Rostek</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Computer-assisted corpus-based text analysis with
                                TATOE</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">Presented at ALLC- ACH96, Bergen, Norway</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>Abstracts, pp. 11-17.</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Hsin-Hsi</forename>
                                    <surname>Chen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Jen-Chang</forename>
                                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Identification and classification of proper nouns in
                                Chinese Texts</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Proceedings of COLING-96</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">Vol. 1</biblScope>
                                <pubPlace>Kopenhagen, Denmark</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">222-229</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Ralph</forename>
                                    <surname>Grishman</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Beth</forename>
                                    <surname>Sundheim</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Message Understanding Conference - 6: a brief
                                history</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Proceedings of COLING-96</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">Vol. 1</biblScope>
                                <pubPlace>Kopenhagen, Denmark</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">466-471</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <surname>Kitani</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <surname>Mitamura</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">An accurate morphological analysis and proper noun
                                identification for Japanese text processing</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Transactions of Information Processing Society of
                                Japan</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">35</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">404-413</biblScope>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first"/>
                                    <surname/>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">MUC-3: Proceedings of the Third Message Understanding
                                Conference (MUC-3), August 1991</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>San Diego, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Morgan Kaufmann Publishers</publisher>
                                <date when="1991">1991</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">MUC-5: Proceedings of the Fifth Message Understanding
                                Conference (MUC-5), August 1993</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>San Diego, CA, USA</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Morgan Kaufmann Publishers</publisher>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Takahiro</forename>
                                    <surname>Wakao</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Robert</forename>
                                    <surname>Gaizauskas</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Yorick</forename>
                                    <surname>Wilks</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Evaluation of an Algorithm for the Recognition and
                                Classification of Proper Nouns</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Proceedings of COLING-96</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">Vol. 1</biblScope>
                                <pubPlace>Kopenhagen, Denmark</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">418-423</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
