<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="panel">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Applying the TEI: Problems in the classification of
                    proper nouns</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Julia</forename>
                        <surname>Flanders</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Brown University</name>
                            <email>Julia_Flanders@brown.edu</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sydney</forename>
                        <surname>Bauman</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Brown University</name>
                            <email>Sydney_Bauman@brown.edu</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Paul</forename>
                        <surname>Caton</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Brown University</name>
                            <email>Paul_Caton@brown.edu</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Mavis</forename>
                        <surname>Cournane</surname>
                        <affiliation>Computer Center, <name type="org">University College
                                Cork</name>
                            <email>mavis@eolas.ucc.ie</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Willard</forename>
                        <surname>McCarty</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Kings College London</name>
                            <email>Willard.McCarty@kcl.ac.uk</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">John</forename>
                        <surname>Bradley</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Kings College London</name>
                            <email>john.bradley@kcl.ac.uk</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>name</item>
                        <item>TLH</item>
                        <item>WWP</item>
                        <item>TEI</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Abstract</head>
                    <p>The testing of the TEI Guidelines since their release has thus far taken a
                        somewhat private form. Scholarly text encoding projects have availed
                        themselves of the Guidelines' exceptional richness and nuance, but with the
                        aim of doing the greatest possible justice to the complexity of their own
                        data, or the particular needs of their own users, rather than with any
                        concern for developing consistency between projects. To a certain extent
                        this is justifiable; the point of a flexible standard is precisely that it
                        can accommodate the multiple needs of its various users. However, where
                        divergence is only the result of random choice among equivalent options,
                        rather than being motivated by real constraints, it serves no purpose and
                        only impedes the exchange and use of data. Now that the Guidelines have been
                        in use long enough to create a substantial base of encoded data, projects
                        whose source material and encoding strategies are similar can benefit from
                        comparing approaches to common problems, and assessing whether their
                        divergences are justified by differences in data or philosophy, or merely
                        represent unnecessary variation in the application of the TEI.</p>
                    <p>One area of primary source transcription which deserves examination along
                        these lines is the classification of proper nouns and similar words and
                        phrases, using the elements described in Chapter 20 of the <title level="m"
                            >TEI Guidelines</title>: &lt;name&gt;, &lt;rs&gt;, and
                        the suite of more specific elements such as &lt;placeName&gt;,
                        &lt;orgName&gt;, &lt;foreName&gt;, &lt;surName&gt;,
                        &lt;roleName&gt;, etc. These elements describe a set of phenomena
                        whose retrieval and processing are important to the scholarly user of the
                        encoded text, but whose boundaries are quite fluid and often involve the
                        application of theoretical considerations quite unrelated to text encoding.
                        (For example, is "God" a personal name?)</p>
                    <p>The proposed session will present several perspectives on this problem, with
                        several aims: first, of allowing the participating projects (and those
                        represented in the audience) to compare practices and discuss the status of
                        their variation; second, of situating the specific problem of encoding
                        proper nouns within the context of scholarly analysis, so as to create a
                        more precise sense of the needs which the encoding is intended to address;
                        and third, to think more broadly about the pressures and constraints on
                        classification systems in text encoding.</p>
                    <p>Two of the three papers in this session come from encoding projects which use
                        the TEI, and which have used Chapter 20 in particularly detailed and
                        carefully considered ways. The first of these is the Brown University Women
                        Writers Project, in a paper co-authored by Julia Flanders, Paul Caton, and
                        Sydney Bauman, which will address the WWP's approach to the use of Chapter
                        20, and its attempt to balance scholarly needs and cost-effectiveness. The
                        second is the Thesaurus Linguarum Hiberniae (TLH) project, discussed by
                        Mavis Cournane, who will examine TLH's use of TEI to classify and specify
                        different kinds of proper nouns within TLH's corpus of writing in Ireland.
                        The last paper, by Willard McCarty and John Bradley, will consider these
                        issues from the perspective of a non-TEI project dealing intensively with
                        names and their classification, <title level="m">An Analytical Onomasticon
                            to the <title level="m">Metamorphoses</title> of Ovid</title>. This
                        paper will discuss the encoding of names in relation to the complex issues
                        of literary criticism and analysis, with an in-depth exploration of examples
                        from the <title level="m">Metamorphoses</title>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>Nouns Proper and Improper: Using the TEI for primary sources</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">Julia Flanders</p>
                        <p rend="presenter">Sydney D. Bauman</p>
                        <p rend="presenter">Paul Caton</p>
                        <div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Introduction</head>
                                <p>The TEI approaches the encoding of names as a problem having
                                    largely to do with the need to give labels to existing
                                    phenomena: Chapter 20, "Names and Dates", begins by saying that
                                    the elements provided therein offer the encoder "a detailed
                                    substructure" and the ability "to distinguish explicitly between
                                    names of persons, places or organizations" [P3, p. 583]. The
                                    elements offered in this section and elsewhere in the TEI are
                                    indeed sufficient to encode most if not all of the name-related
                                    phenomena found in the texts with which the Women Writers
                                    Project is concerned. However, this sufficiency on the SGML side
                                    of the equation does not assist with the other side: the fact
                                    that the encoder must in fact "distinguish explicitly" between
                                    the names of persons, places, organizations, mythical creatures,
                                    objects, and the like. That is, we must decide what the thing is
                                    before we can encode it, and this is not always easy.</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>The Women Writers Project</head>
                                <p>The WWP has an additional challenge, however, which is that in
                                    working with older texts we are confronted with a set of
                                    phenomena which the text itself identifies--by typographical
                                    emphasis of some sort--as being of linguistic or rhetorical
                                    importance. In texts printed in the 17th and 18th centuries,
                                    this set includes the elements discussed in Chapter 20, but also
                                    some related textual features such as abstract nouns and
                                    adjectives derived from proper nouns. Thus texts from this
                                    period themselves identify a set of features in which a scholar
                                    might well be interested, but which shade into one another and
                                    may be difficult to identify and classify with any certainty.
                                    For example, if one wants to distinguish names of persons from
                                    abstract nouns, one runs into challenges in the case of allegory
                                    or moral poetry, where virtues may be apostrophized as if they
                                    were human, or may be identified with a human agent, or may be
                                    in fact the name of that agent. Similarly if one wishes to
                                    distinguish names of persons from the names of other kinds of
                                    things (such as non-human creatures or objects) one needs not
                                    only the encoding equipment to label these but also a clear
                                    definition of what it means to be human. Test cases here might
                                    be the Medusa, the Minotaur, mermaids, centaurs, Niobe after her
                                    transformation into a stone, and the vexed question of the human
                                    status of various deities. An additional challenge arises in the
                                    case of adjectives which are derived from proper names, like
                                    Caesarian or Plutonic; for these there is not even a clear TEI
                                    element for the purpose, since &lt;rs&gt; is technically
                                    reserved for nouns.</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Problems of Classification</head>
                                <p>Discussion of these issues often verges on the whimsical, for
                                    instance when one is forced to articulate what a "person" is
                                    (human from the neck up? able to speak or write? able to mate
                                    with humans?), but also engages with more serious issues
                                    concerning the nature of naming. If one does not wish to make
                                    naming and reference the centerpiece of one's encoding system
                                    (as would be appropriate for a text like the <title level="m"
                                        >Metamorphoses</title>, but not for an eclectic collection
                                    like the WWP's), one needs to draw a line between the category
                                    of names and the other things which shade into them: for
                                    instance epithets, vocatives like "Milady", or terms like "the
                                    Cockatrice" whose unique reference is vitiated by the presence
                                    of an article, and the whole range of apostrophes to abstract
                                    qualities like "Fair Virtue". Without such a line, it is hard to
                                    know where to stop, and the result is a huge set of features
                                    from which it is impossible to retrieve the information one
                                    wants. The natural response to this problem is to attempt to
                                    classify these in turn, for instance with type attributes, an
                                    approach which other projects (CURIA for instance) have taken
                                    with success.</p>
                                <p>The WWP has found, however, that for our texts it is very
                                    difficult to create a sufficiently comprehensive and unambiguous
                                    set of values to categorize these features in a way that would
                                    allow researchers actually to do systematic work on them. The
                                    WWP's path to this conclusion involved several attempts to
                                    create a system which <emph rend="italics">could</emph> do
                                    justice to this complexity. We tried dividing our field of
                                    features into names of persons (using &lt;persName&gt;
                                    and its various components), names of non-persons (using
                                    &lt;name&gt;), and non-name references to both persons
                                    and non-persons (using &lt;rs&gt;). This last category
                                    was especially baroque, since it included the most heterogeneous
                                    group (abstractions, epithets, personifications of inanimate
                                    things, symbols, apostrophes, and references to mythical or
                                    imaginary creatures), and in fact each iteration of the
                                    classification process proved again that a substantial challenge
                                    lay in what to do with the residuum, the things which are only
                                    alike in being unlike some other, more clearly delimited
                                    category. The conclusion we found ourselves drawing was that
                                    although the concepts we were dealing with were fairly distinct,
                                    their application to specific textual phenomena was not by any
                                    means straightforward. Furthermore, although the components of
                                    the "residuum" were easily identifiable as categories which did
                                    not fit into the other two (personal and non-personal names), we
                                    were not confident that they represented categories which would
                                    be useful for scholarly study, though we were confident that
                                    trying to use them would prove to be extremely time-consuming
                                    and hence expensive. As a result, we eventually decided to use a
                                    simplified system which made no attempt to classify things
                                    beyond the element level; we now distinguish between personal
                                    names and the names of non-persons, and any other kind of
                                    reference which the text identifies as a proper noun is encoded
                                    using &lt;rs&gt; without a type attribute.</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Conclusion</head>
                                <p>The conclusion which emerges from this attempt seems to be that
                                    despite the various provisions of the TEI for encoding these
                                    complex textual phenomena, the limiting factor really is human
                                    use and the ability to define and enforce categorization. The
                                    question which leads from this is one of how to regard and apply
                                    the TEI: if it is imagined as a system for accounting to one's
                                        <emph rend="italics">own</emph> satisfaction for what one
                                    finds in the text, then the complexity available is essential.
                                    However, if the TEI is regarded as a method of communicating
                                    textual information to others, as long as the text itself is
                                    allowed to determine the encoding solution we will find this
                                    communication extremely difficult. Put another way, if an
                                    encoding project develops a TEI-based encoding system based on
                                    the assumption that its own data has unique requirements, that
                                    very assumption limits drastically the possibility of
                                    integrating that data with that of other projects to build
                                    larger resources, or the possibility of users being able to make
                                    common assumptions about how data will be treated. As a
                                    strategic matter, these possibilities are best kept open by the
                                    counterassumption that data <emph rend="italics">can</emph> be
                                    treated similarly (even if that counterassumption is to some
                                    degree false). At this stage in the TEI's development, projects
                                    working on similar undertakings (similar materials, similar
                                    methodologies) have had the opportunity to discover the
                                    uniqueness of their own data and to revel in it, and they need
                                    to turn their attention to finding ways to share it. The
                                    ultimate goal of this session is therefore to discuss the degree
                                    to which this is possible, and the costs of doing so. </p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                        <div>
                            <head>The application of SGML/TEI to the reality of Irish Texts</head>
                            <p rend="presenter">Mavis Cournane</p>
                            <div>
                                <div>
                                    <head>Abstract</head>
                                    <p>This paper will look at how the TEI DTD is used to encode
                                        names in Irish texts. Most of the questions and difficulties
                                        encountered by the TLH encoder of names will have presented
                                        themselves to others. Some of the problems of encoding are
                                        generated by the TEI DTD itself, while others are due to the
                                        inherent complexity of the texts themselves. In addressing
                                        the problems, I hope to take encoding decisions out of the
                                        realm of the arbitrary. The proposed solutions will
                                        demonstrate how the TEI DTD can be manipulated and the need
                                        for consistency in encoding.</p>
                                </div>
                                <div>
                                    <head>Introduction</head>
                                    <p>The TEI DTD is a descriptive DTD rather than a prescriptive
                                        one. The descriptive nature of the TEI DTD is problematic
                                        for the encoder because very little in TEI is mandatory, and
                                        the encoder is given several choices of how to encode
                                        various textual features. From the outset the would-be
                                        encoder is faced with problem of what to encode, how to
                                        encode, and who to encode it for.</p>
                                    <p>The target audience determines the degree of markup necessary
                                        in a text and also strongly influences the way in which you
                                        mark something up. Irish texts by nature are rich in prose,
                                        poetry, chivalry, hagiography, linguistic, genealogical, and
                                        historical data. They appear in five languages, Old Irish,
                                        Old Norse, Norman French, Latin, and Hiberno-English and
                                        contain some transliterated Hebrew and Greek. Consequently,
                                        their encoding requires a great depth and variety of markup.
                                        The application of the theoretical world of TEI to the real
                                        world of text presents challenges and problems. These are
                                        particularly acute in the encoding of names. TEI puts at
                                        your disposal several elements for naming people and things,
                                        all of which would work, or appear reasonable. You are
                                        provided with tags such as &lt;name&gt;,
                                        &lt;persname&gt;,&lt;surname&gt;,
                                        &lt;forename&gt;, &lt;rolename&gt;,
                                        &lt;addname&gt;, &lt;genname&gt;,
                                        &lt;namelink&gt;, and &lt;placename&gt;. The
                                        encoder then has to decide which of these best suit her
                                        needs. Close attention also has to be paid to the nesting
                                        requirements within TEI. For example one cannot simply
                                        decide to encode a name as a &lt;forename&gt;
                                        without first nesting it within a &lt;persname&gt;.
                                        The same holds true for &lt;surname&gt;,
                                        &lt;rolename&gt;, &lt;addname&gt;,
                                        &lt;genName&gt; and &lt;namelink&gt;.</p>
                                </div>
                                <div>
                                    <head>The problems</head>
                                    <p>1. What needs to be encoded?</p>
                                    <p>2. How much needs to be encoded?</p>
                                    <p>3. Should there be a difference between encoding the names of
                                        sacred personages, people and objects?</p>
                                    <p>4. In historical texts which span centuries, personal names
                                        are dynamic. What denoted a forename in the 11th century
                                        indicated a surname by the 13th century. How can markup be
                                        consistent yet reflect the semantic accuracy of the
                                        text?</p>
                                    <p>5. Placenames present the same difficulty. Their function can
                                        change over time. For example the place <emph rend="italics"
                                            >Armagh</emph> functioned intially as a church, then it
                                        graduated to a monastery, a monastic town, then a church and
                                        in a 20th century context it denotes a town and is also the
                                        seat of the archbishops. For example: 
                                        <eg>&lt;pn type="church"&gt;Ard Macha&lt;/pn&gt; d' fothuccadh 
                                            &lt;pn type="monastery"&gt;Ard Macha&lt;/pn&gt; do losccadh 
                                            &lt;pn type="town"&gt;Ard Macha&lt;/pn&gt;</eg></p>
                                    <p>Further inconsistency occurs for search purposes when there
                                        is variation in the spelling of placenames. If a place can
                                        be spelt eight different ways and have had a dynamic
                                        function over eight centuries, how is the untrained person
                                        to conduct meaningful searches?</p>
                                    <p>6. In non-English historical texts it can be problematic to
                                        distinguish between &lt;placename&gt; and
                                        &lt;orgName&gt;. Many elements have been abbreviated
                                        in TLH for ease of reading when markup is on display. For
                                        example, &lt;orgName&gt; is abbreviated to
                                        &lt;on&gt;. It is used to markup organizations in
                                        the widest possible sense, be they historical groups,
                                        parties, lineages etc. In many instances it is not always
                                        clear if one should encode a name as a place or
                                        organization. Many placenames take their name from dynastic
                                        names. This poses problems not only for the encoder, but
                                        also for the user. As much encoding in this instance is
                                        subjective, the user, seeking to search the database, will
                                        have her own prejudices and expectations. For example:
                                            <eg>(1)&lt;on type="people/dynasty" &gt;Connacht&lt;/on&gt;</eg>
                                        
                                        <eg>(2)&lt;pn type="kingdom"&gt;Connacht&lt;/pn&gt;</eg>
                                        
                                        <eg>(3)&lt;pn type="province"&gt;Connacht&lt;/pn&gt;</eg></p>
                                    <p>In example (1) it is the dynasty Connacht which is being
                                        referred to and in (2) and (3) it is the place, the kingdom
                                        or province Connacht which is in question. These ambiguities
                                        meant that close attention has to be given to the semantics
                                        of the text to discern how to encode.</p>
                                </div>
                                <div>
                                    <head>Solutions</head>
                                    <p>(1) the development of an encoding scheme based on a
                                        scholarly rationale rather than one legitimized by <emph
                                            rend="italics">Lust und Laune</emph>.</p>
                                    <p>(2) greater use of the attributes provided by TEI to further
                                        categorise, regularise and normalise encoded text.</p>
                                    <p>These solutions need not be mutually exclusive.</p>
                                </div>
                                <div>
                                    <head>Conclusion</head>
                                    <p>Names in Irish texts are dynamic, and ambiguous. Their
                                        encoding will only serve a meaningful purpose for the end
                                        user, if regularisation and consistency guide the marking up
                                        process. Without due consideration of these factors search
                                        and retrieval would be a complicated, unsatisfactory
                                        exercise.</p>
                                </div>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                        <div>
                            <head>Theft of fire: meaning in the markup of names</head>
                            <p rend="presenter">Willard McCarty</p>
                            <p rend="presenter">John Bradley</p>
                            <div>
                                <p>Our subject is what happens when a computational metalinguistic
                                    tagging scheme is imposed on a poetic text in order to make a
                                    subset of the data accessible to automatic processing. In our
                                    case, tagging is employed to mark 'names' in the broadest sense,
                                    i.e. all devices of language by which persons are identified.
                                    Our text is the <title level="m">Metamorphoses</title>, a highly
                                    complex mythological compendium written by the Roman poet Ovid
                                    during the reign of Augustus. Its 12,000 lines of Latin
                                    hexameter contain approximately 50,000 such devices, a
                                    systematic accounting of which is the aim of the project. The
                                    result, generated automatically by software from the tagged
                                    text, is <title level="m">An Analytical Onomasticon to the
                                            <title level="m">Metamorphoses</title> of Ovid</title>.
                                    This is a new kind of reference work designed to help Ovidian
                                    specialists figure out how the poem might cohere. For humanities
                                    computing, however, the primary interest lies in the radical
                                    'loss in translation' when ambiguous poetic phenomena are
                                    rendered as meta-linguistic tags, and in how this loss is turned
                                    to advantage.<note n="1">[1] An early stage of the research is
                                        described in McCarty 1996 (paper submitted 1992); for more
                                        recent reports, see McCarty 1993 and 1994. An introduction
                                        with illustrations of the output is available on the Web,
                                            <ptr
                                            target="http://ww
                                    w.kcl.ac.uk/kis/schools/hums/ruhc/wlm/Onomasticon/"
                                        /> (Europe) or <ptr
                                            target="http://www.princeton.edu/~mccarty/Onomasticon/"
                                        /> (N. America). For a broader view of tagging and text, see
                                        Sperberg-McQueen 1991; Renear 1992; Renear, Durand, and
                                        Mylonas 1996. </note></p>
                                <p>As one of us has argued elsewhere, the translation model is quite
                                    useful in thinking about the literary and linguistic
                                    consequences of tagging a poetic text (McCarty 1994). The
                                    radical poverty of tagging 'languages' makes the discussion
                                    about loss-in-translation, pervasive in the literature,
                                    especially valuable (Barnstone 1993). The question of this loss
                                    devolves into the more fundamental one of expression itself,
                                    where it takes the useful form of meditations on that which
                                    seems curiously to be in but not of language - George Steiner's
                                    "flame of the spirit in the momentary fixity of the
                                        letter".<note n="2">[2] See Steiner 1975. For the ineffable
                                        in language see also Liu 1988, Burdick and Iser 1989.</note>
                                    What happens to this flame in the act of translation? What
                                    happens to it when the target is a computational
                                    pseudo-language, therefore radically deficient for representing
                                    the rich ambiguities of poetry?</p>
                                <p>A computing project that attempts to render what we loosely call
                                    'meaning' into processible form faces such questions at every
                                    working moment. The struggle is, of course, central to computing
                                    as a whole insofar as it models complex realities or perceptions
                                    of them with crude mechanical constructs (McCarty 1994: 278-81).
                                    For humanities computing as such, the crudity of our methods is
                                    a central issue; it is only avoided, not answered, by construing
                                    the computer as a 'mere tool' or by taking refuge in progress.
                                    Arguably we step over the most significant threshold in (or
                                    rather into) the field when we realise that the inevitable
                                    failure of all such modeling is anything but a death-sentence to
                                    our common project, but rather the source of its integrity and
                                    power. What we lose in tagging is in a sense what we gain.</p>
                                <p>In this paper we will focus closely on how the construction of a
                                    taxonomy for naming simultaneously falsifies and illuminates the
                                    text. Using quite specific examples from the <title level="m"
                                        >Metamorphoses</title> we will demonstrate in detail how the
                                    application of such a taxonomy to a text, in the process of
                                    encoding it, itself constitutes a kind of literary
                                    criticism.</p>
                                <p>The central problem that the Onomasticon is intended to address,
                                    the coherence of the <title level="m">Metamorphoses</title> as a
                                    work of literature, will require brief explication in the paper
                                    to demonstrate how well the poem serves the interests of
                                    humanities computing. Briefly, we will argue that because Ovid's
                                    poem reflects the central problem of tagging literary text -
                                    seeking "the flame of the spirit" as it transmigrates through
                                    "the momentary fixity" of bodies - the <title level="m"
                                        >Metamorphoses</title> presents in a radically stubborn form
                                    just the kind of challenge our common project needs to advance
                                    intellectually.</p>
                                <p>For the <title level="m">Metamorphoses</title>, the spoor of this
                                    transmigrating spirit is supplied by numerous kinds of language
                                    data through which apparently disparate narrative elements are
                                    associated. For a manageable subset, we chose all references to
                                    persons, i.e. names, because persons are to be found in every
                                    story of the poem and each reference to a person can be exactly
                                    identified with particular elements of the the textual data.
                                    (The same could not consistently be said, for example, of
                                    metaphors, allusions, or themes.) No particular theory on how
                                    the <title level="m">Metamorphoses</title> is or could be
                                    constructed was assumed, although a theory arguing for multiple,
                                    simultaneous constructions is offered in the book.</p>
                                <p>Details of the mark-up scheme and of how tags are processed are
                                    available but mostly irrelevant for present purposes. Our focus
                                    is rather on the taxonomy and how well it works, or rather how
                                    well it fails and in failing serves a scholarly purpose.</p>
                                <p>The basic taxonomy is simple. Onomastic devices are classified
                                    under the headings of proper names (including patronymics,
                                    matronymics, toponyms, et sim.), nominals (nouns and adjectives,
                                    including phrases), pronouns, verbs, and personal attributes,
                                    i.e. nominals referring to anything that in context is closely
                                    enough associated to evoke the person. Text quoted in the tag is
                                    lemmatised insofar as the syntax of the quoted segment will
                                    permit, given a taxonomic type, and assigned to the person.
                                    (More precisely, the onomastic device is given a 'standard
                                    name', or editorial lemma that in most cases is simply the name
                                    of the character but is used to identify synonymous references,
                                    to declare disparate references as such, and otherwise to assign
                                    an identity to something, such as a metamorohosed being.)
                                    Although interpretative problems occur at every step, the most
                                    interesting ones are in assigning names to persons. This should
                                    not be surprising for a poem in which people become things and,
                                    less often, things people, but the particular demands of markup
                                    turn the expected into a surprisingly complex and revealing
                                    operation.</p>
                                <p>At root is the question of what constitutes a person. For a
                                    majority in the <title level="m">Metamorphoses</title> the
                                    answer is as obvious as in daily life, but for a large number of
                                    doubtful instances, we found that the most useful way to
                                    approach the question was to look for ontological shift. Hence,
                                    any sub-human entity (animal, vegetable, mineral) is regarded as
                                    a person, and so tagged, if it undergoes metamorphosis up the
                                    'chain of being' or is otherwise personified; if it reverts to
                                    sub-human state, it ceases to be a person and so is not tagged.
                                    Any anthropomorph that has undergone downward metamorphosis
                                    (including a god that has temporarily changed shape) is said to
                                    be a different through closely related person,
                                    'X-in-the-form-of-Y'. Certain figures of speech that suggest but
                                    do not manifest ontological shift are similarly marked by
                                    assigning a distinct but closely related standard name: similes,
                                    'X-compared-to-Y', and multiple persons having a corporate
                                    identity by acting as one, 'X-and-Y-and-Z'. Dis-personification
                                    of entities formerly persons (e.g. <emph rend="italics"
                                        >venus</emph> for sexual passion, <emph rend="italics"
                                        >bacchus</emph> for wine) is treated by dropping the entity
                                    as a person but including the reference as his or her
                                    attribute.</p>
                                <p>Persons, then, are treated in essence as momentary constructions,
                                    apt to appear as such under certain conditions of language, or
                                    to change identity or vanish altogether when those conditions
                                    change. Thus much is obvious given the text under consideration.
                                    For the <title level="m">Analytical Onomasticon</title> to be
                                    useful, however, the tagging must be governed rigorously by
                                    consistent editorial policies that specify these conditions of
                                    language. The first of these specifies a fundamental binary
                                    state: a textual phenomenon is either identified with a person
                                    or not; no 'weights' or degrees of identity are allowed. Beyond
                                    that, our policies have evolved inductively, through a long
                                    series of heuristic intermediaries, almost continuously revised
                                    during the work. Although they are to be reviewed in the final
                                    stage of the project, they are mostly stable now and will be
                                    described briefly in the paper. The <title level="m">Analytical
                                        Onomasticon</title> contains a long theoretical introduction
                                    in which they are discussed in great detail.</p>
                                <p>Apart from the fact that these policies are fundamental to the
                                    usefulness of the <title level="m">Analytical
                                        Onomasticon</title>, they enable the user intelligently to
                                    criticise the work, and since plans are to publish all the
                                    component materials in electronic form, to modify the tagged
                                    text effectively and so to regenerate the book along different
                                    lines. (The scope of our paper unfortunately does not allow
                                    further discussion of the publishing aspects.) More importantly
                                    for the subject of this paper, these policies by nature aim
                                    explicitly to specify how certain well-known but imperfectly
                                    understood literary phenomena actually happen. Personification
                                    has, for example, been well studied, both within and well beyond
                                    classical studies, but nowhere does one find an attempt to spell
                                    out its linguistic conditions. Similarly, metamorphosis is an
                                    obvious and well-studied topic, yet one does not find an
                                    empirical guide to its boundaries, when it can be said to occur,
                                    when not, and while it is happening, of what the process exactly
                                    consists. Tagging forces one to say, or more precisely, to make
                                    the attempt.</p>
                                <p>In the paper, explication of particular examples will demonstrate
                                    such attempts and in particular focus on the literary-critical
                                    value of their failure: (1) the personification of Sol in the
                                    story of Phaethon, <title level="m">Met.</title> 1.751ff, and
                                    the dis-personification of Bacchus and Venus at various points
                                    throughout; (2) Apollo's pursuit and metamorphosis of Daphne,
                                    1.525-567, and her ambiguous status as the laurel tree later in
                                    the poem; (3) rhetorical strategies in the contest of arms
                                    between Ajax and Ulysses (13.1-398). </p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div type="bibliography">
                            <head>Works cited</head>
                            <listBibl>
                                <biblStruct type="book">
                                    <monogr>
                                        <author>
                                            <name>
                                                <forename type="first">Willis</forename>
                                                <surname>Barnstone</surname>
                                            </name>
                                        </author>
                                        <title level="m">The Poetics of Translation: History,
                                            Theory, Practice</title>
                                        <imprint>
                                            <pubPlace>New Haven</pubPlace>
                                            <publisher>Yale University Press</publisher>
                                            <date when="1993">1993</date>
                                        </imprint>
                                    </monogr>
                                </biblStruct>
                                <biblStruct type="book">
                                    <monogr>
                                        <editor>
                                            <name>
                                                <forename type="first">Sanford</forename>
                                                <surname>Burdick</surname>
                                            </name>
                                        </editor>
                                        <editor>
                                            <name>
                                                <forename type="first">Wolfgang</forename>
                                                <surname>Iser</surname>
                                            </name>
                                        </editor>
                                        <title level="m">Languages of the Unsayable: The Play of
                                            Negativity in Literature and Literary Theory</title>
                                        <imprint>
                                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                                            <publisher>Columbia University Press</publisher>
                                            <date when="1989">1989</date>
                                        </imprint>
                                    </monogr>
                                </biblStruct>
                                <biblStruct type="book">
                                    <monogr>
                                        <author>
                                            <name>
                                                <forename type="first">James</forename>
                                                <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                                <forename type="middle">Y.</forename>
                                                <surname>Liu</surname>
                                            </name>
                                        </author>
                                        <title level="m">Language, Paradox, Poetics. A Chinese
                                            Perspective</title>
                                        <editor>
                                            <name>
                                                <forename type="first">Richard</forename>
                                                <forename type="middle">John</forename>
                                                <surname>Lynn</surname>
                                            </name>
                                        </editor>
                                        <imprint>
                                            <pubPlace>Princeton</pubPlace>
                                            <publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
                                            <date when="1988">1988</date>
                                        </imprint>
                                    </monogr>
                                </biblStruct>
                                <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                    <analytic>
                                        <author>
                                            <name>
                                                <forename type="first">Willard</forename>
                                                <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
                                                <surname>McCarty</surname>
                                            </name>
                                        </author>
                                        <title level="a">Encoding Persons and Places in the <title
                                                level="m">Metamorphoses</title> of Ovid. Part 1:
                                            Engineering the Text</title>
                                    </analytic>
                                    <monogr>
                                        <title level="j">Texte</title>
                                        <imprint>
                                            <biblScope type="vol">13/14</biblScope>
                                            <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                            <biblScope type="pp">121-72</biblScope>
                                            <date when="1993">1993</date>
                                            <date when="1994">[published 1994]</date>
                                        </imprint>
                                    </monogr>
                                </biblStruct>
                                <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                    <analytic>
                                        <author>
                                            <name>
                                                <forename type="first">Willard</forename>
                                                <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
                                                <surname>McCarty</surname>
                                            </name>
                                        </author>
                                        <title level="a">Encoding Persons and Places in the <title
                                                level="m">Metamorphoses</title> of Ovid. Part 2: the
                                            Metatextual Translation</title>
                                    </analytic>
                                    <monogr>
                                        <title level="j">Texte</title>
                                        <imprint>
                                            <biblScope type="vol">15/16</biblScope>
                                            <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                            <biblScope type="pp">261-305</biblScope>
                                            <date when="1994">1994</date>
                                            <date when="1995">[published 1995]</date>
                                        </imprint>
                                    </monogr>
                                </biblStruct>
                                <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                                    <analytic>
                                        <author>
                                            <name>
                                                <forename type="first">Willard</forename>
                                                <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
                                                <surname>McCarty</surname>
                                            </name>
                                        </author>
                                        <title level="a">Peering Through the Skylight: Towards an
                                            Electronic Edition of Ovid's <title level="m"
                                                >Metamorphoses</title></title>
                                    </analytic>
                                    <monogr>
                                        <editor>
                                            <name>
                                                <forename type="first">Susan</forename>
                                                <surname>Hockey</surname>
                                            </name>
                                        </editor>
                                        <editor>
                                            <name>
                                                <forename type="first">Nancy</forename>
                                                <surname>Ide</surname>
                                            </name>
                                        </editor>
                                        <title level="m">Research in Humanities Computing</title>
                                        <imprint>
                                            <biblScope type="vol">4</biblScope>
                                            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                                            <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
                                            <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                            <biblScope type="pp">240-262</biblScope>
                                        </imprint>
                                    </monogr>
                                </biblStruct>
                                <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                    <analytic>
                                        <author>
                                            <name>
                                                <forename type="first">Allen</forename>
                                                <surname>Renear</surname>
                                            </name>
                                        </author>
                                        <title level="a">Representing Text on the Computer: Lessons
                                            for and from Philosophy</title>
                                    </analytic>
                                    <monogr>
                                        <title level="j">Bulletin of the John Rylands University
                                            Library of Manchester</title>
                                        <imprint>
                                            <biblScope type="vol">74</biblScope>
                                            <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                            <biblScope type="pp">221-48</biblScope>
                                            <date when="1992">1992</date>
                                        </imprint>
                                    </monogr>
                                </biblStruct>
                                <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                                    <analytic>
                                        <author>
                                            <name>
                                                <forename type="first">Allen</forename>
                                                <surname>Renear</surname>
                                            </name>
                                        </author>
                                        <author>
                                            <name>
                                                <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                                <forename type="middle">G.</forename>
                                                <surname>Durand</surname>
                                            </name>
                                        </author>
                                        <author>
                                            <name>
                                                <forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                                <surname>Mylonas</surname>
                                            </name>
                                        </author>
                                        <title level="a">Overlapping Hierarchies of Text Objects:
                                            Refining our Notion of What Text Really Is</title>
                                    </analytic>
                                    <monogr>
                                        <editor>
                                            <name>
                                                <forename type="first">Susan</forename>
                                                <surname>Hockey</surname>
                                            </name>
                                        </editor>
                                        <editor>
                                            <name>
                                                <forename type="first">Nancy</forename>
                                                <surname>Ide</surname>
                                            </name>
                                        </editor>
                                        <title level="m">Research in Humanities Computing</title>
                                        <imprint>
                                            <biblScope type="vol">4</biblScope>
                                            <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                                            <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
                                            <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                            <biblScope type="pp">263-80</biblScope>
                                        </imprint>
                                    </monogr>
                                </biblStruct>
                                <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                    <analytic>
                                        <author>
                                            <name>
                                                <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                                <forename type="middle">M.</forename>
                                                <surname>Sperberg-McQueen</surname>
                                            </name>
                                        </author>
                                        <title level="a">Text in the Electronic Age: Textual Study
                                            and Text Encoding with Examples from Medieval
                                            Texts</title>
                                    </analytic>
                                    <monogr>
                                        <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                                        <imprint>
                                            <biblScope type="vol">6</biblScope>
                                            <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                            <biblScope type="pp">34-46</biblScope>
                                            <date when="1991">1991</date>
                                        </imprint>
                                    </monogr>
                                </biblStruct>
                                <biblStruct type="book">
                                    <monogr>
                                        <author>
                                            <name>
                                                <forename type="first">George</forename>
                                                <surname>Steiner</surname>
                                            </name>
                                        </author>
                                        <title level="m">After Babel: Aspects of Language and
                                            Translation</title>
                                        <imprint>
                                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                                            <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
                                            <date when="1975">1975</date>
                                        </imprint>
                                    </monogr>
                                </biblStruct>
                            </listBibl>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
