<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="panel">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Writing, Publishing and Preserving Electronic Documents
                    related to the Visual Arts</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Pierre</forename>
                        <surname>du Prey</surname>
                        <affiliation>Department of Art, <name type="org">Queen's University</name>
                            <email>hopea@qucdn.queensu.ca</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Blair</forename>
                        <surname>Martin</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Kingston Learning Systems</name>, Kingston, Ontario,
                            Canada <email>martinbl@kos.net</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Daniel</forename>
                        <surname>Greenstein</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">King's College London</name>
                            <email>daniel.greenstein@ahds.ac.uk</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>architecture</item>
                        <item>interactive</item>
                        <item>publication</item>
                        <item>archive</item>
                        <item>collection</item>
                        <item>standards</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Session Topic</head>
                    <p>This session will include papers by two Kingston-based collaborators engaged
                        in electronically writing, designing and publishing an interactive
                        introduction to the history of the Classical tradition in architecture.
                        Apart from its text, this project has an important visual component
                        consisting of the images electronically reproduced in close conjunction with
                        the ongoing verbal narrative. In addition the two papers (and the
                        presentation that will accompany them) demonstrate the role of certain
                        interactive functions growing out of, and intended to re-enforce, the text
                        as well as the images. These new interactive techniques, in addition to
                        tried and true cross referencing methods, invite the participation of the
                        reader to an unheralded extent. Aimed at a wide range of potential users,
                        the publication captures the sometimes serendipitous excitement of the
                        classroom. The third paper introduces the Arts and Humanities Data Service
                        in the UK whose mandate is to coordinate access to, and facilitate the
                        creation and use of, electronic resources. Attention will be paid to the
                        role of the AHDS's Visual Arts Data Service in a world of rapidly
                        proliferating digital images and image collections. Strategies will be
                        discussed regarding the creation, accessibility, preservation and
                        intellectual "rights" related to digital images.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>Re-creating the Crucible of the Classroom through Electronic
                            Publication</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">Pierre du Prey</p>
                        <div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Abstract</head>
                                <p>The classroom is a crucible. The active ingredients in it are
                                    normally the lectures of the professor, the interventions of the
                                    students and the interaction between the two. To this
                                    quasi-chemical equation teachers in the visual arts add the
                                    factor of images – usually in the form of slides or actual works
                                    of art, but increasingly in the form of digitized images on a
                                    monitor. This paper seeks to analyze the mixture in the crucible
                                    with special reference to the history of architecture and an
                                    electronic publication in progress devoted to the Classical
                                    tradition from Antiquity to the present day. By discussing
                                    certain story-boarding techniques, familiar from the art of the
                                    cinema, the paper shows how the classroom's stimulating but
                                    unpredictable atmosphere of inquiry can be electronically
                                    approximated through the appropriate juxtaposition of words and
                                    images. A prototype presentation will accompany this paper, and
                                    relates to others in the same session. Under the working title,
                                        <emph rend="italics">A History of the Classical Tradition in
                                        Architecture</emph>, the first phase of the current project
                                    has been underway for almost 8 months as part of a three-year
                                    research grant funded by the Social Sciences and Humanities
                                    Research Council of Canada (SSHRC). The primary source material
                                    consists of lecture texts from an introductory course to the
                                    history of architecture formulated over the past six years. In
                                    addition, about 1500 of the projected 2500 slides have already
                                    been photographed by the author and some have been digitized.
                                    The images also include material from the rare book, prints and
                                    drawings collection of the Canadian Centre for Architecture in
                                    Montreal, which is a partner in the venture. In this way, and
                                    because of the special copyright status of buildings, the
                                    electronic publication will be relatively free of copyright
                                    restrictions.</p>
                                <p>To facilitate "navigation" through the document, the electronic
                                    publication relies heavily on geography, a natural enough choice
                                    when dealing with works of architecture. Buildings discussed are
                                    located in time and space and are interrelated to one another to
                                    form an integrated, balanced, and harmonious whole, as suits the
                                    Classical subject matter. A principal path through the material
                                    permits users at all levels of interest and computer literacy to
                                    read the text and images much as in a book. But numerous
                                    "alleyways" off to all sides of the principal path form the
                                    heart of the interactive and specifically electronic nature of
                                    the publication, and challenge the more adventurous user. Some
                                    of these interactive techniques currently under exploration
                                    include the following:<list type="bulleted">
                                        <item>split screen comparisons of two or more images</item>
                                        <item>historical documents category giving archival
                                            information, photographs or other images, that
                                            illustrate artistic process or deterioration but free
                                            the principal path from too much documentation</item>
                                        <item>critical sources category providing pertinent
                                            bibliography, original source quotations (visual and
                                            sound), as well as alternate critical opinions to those
                                            presented in the principal path</item>
                                        <item>maps and time lines to orient the user at all points
                                            along the principal path</item>
                                        <item>"magic carpet" displays that roll out multiple images
                                            of a single building or place in order to convey
                                            three-dimensionality more fully</item>
                                        <item>periodic tests or quizzes</item>
                                        <item>illustrated glossary of architectural terms "hot
                                            spotted" directly to images as well as to the
                                            text</item>
                                        <item>possibility of "zooming" in on selected details</item>
                                        <item>gazetteer of places mentioned in the text</item>
                                        <item>analytic index arranged by concepts as well as names
                                            of architects, places etc.</item>
                                        <item>full list of illustration sources where not already
                                            mentioned on the individual captions</item>
                                        <item>cross referencing whereby the user may search
                                            backwards and forwards in time for related images by
                                            architect, building type etc.</item>
                                        <item>assembling images to create architect profiles or
                                            illustrate specific cityscapes</item>
                                        <item>summaries that recapitulate in point form the
                                            principal items covered in a chapter</item>
                                        <item>"you were there" techniques using sound and images to
                                            recreate the sense of historical context.</item>
                                    </list></p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Conclusion</head>
                                <p>Throughout the publication the interactive capabilities remain in
                                    balance with the demands of the textual narrative. Neither one
                                    overrules the other, nor restricts readership. For a beginner
                                    the publication opens the doors to the enjoyment of
                                    architecture. For the armchair traveler the text and images
                                    provide happy recollections or excite anticipation. For the
                                    experienced student, architect or scholar the publication
                                    creates challenging new ways of looking at architecture, its
                                    creative process, and the relevance of past to present and
                                    future. In the final analysis, the publication also reflects the
                                    personality of its author: his education; his travels; his
                                    publications; his enthusiasms; and last but not least the impact
                                    of electronic publication upon his way of writing.. (The
                                    principal path has not been a one way street.) By taking into
                                    account the flexibility of the electronic medium, the material
                                    is arranged with unheralded ease, thus bringing to light
                                    overarching and even unexpected typologies or themes. In this
                                    way the new medium actually suggests new ways of looking at
                                    familiar material, because the interpolation of text with images
                                    has a rationale all its own. The reader is invited to question
                                    these themes, to explore them in new ways, and thereby to become
                                    increasingly engaged in the subject of architectural history.
                                    Above all, by using the electronic medium creatively, the
                                    present project underscores both visually and verbally the
                                    publication's central thesis of continuity within the Classical
                                    tradition.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>Humanising Electronic Publications</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">Blair Martin</p>
                        <div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Abstract</head>
                                <p>Electronic publications are now part of everyday life. Yet many
                                    of them fail to engage their users effectively. Why so?</p>
                                <p>If you are thinking of producing an electronic publication, what
                                    can you do to ensure its users find it easy and enjoyable to
                                    use?</p>
                                <p>How can the publication guide its users and emulate the absent
                                    teacher?</p>
                                <p>This paper describes some of the issues involved, and sets forth
                                    principles for designing attractive yet functional user
                                    interfaces. It shows examples from various existing electronic
                                    publications, and from a CD-ROM on the Classical Tradition in
                                    Architecture currently under development at Queen's
                                    University.</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Primary Topics</head>
                                <list type="bulleted">
                                    <item>The electronic publication: is it a book? Should it behave
                                        like a book? Is the "book" metaphor good enough?</item>
                                    <item>How can it reveal richness of content without losing the
                                        users in detail?</item>
                                    <item>How can it engage with users who have different levels of
                                        interest? </item>
                                    <item>How can it adapt itself to users with varying degrees of
                                        computer literacy?</item>
                                    <item>Meeting user expectations; expectations developed by
                                        books, television, and computer games</item>
                                    <item>Are there design standards that should be followed? Who
                                        sets the standards? How can standardisation, pedagogical
                                        purpose, and aesthetic appeal work together?</item>
                                    <item>The teacher is not present. What does a teacher do? How
                                        can a teacher's monitoring and assistive skills be emulated
                                        in an electronic publication?</item>
                                </list>
                                <p><emph rend="italics">
                                        <emph rend="bold">Note:</emph>
                                    </emph> Dr. du Prey's paper will address the last point in much
                                    more detail.</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Technical Topics</head>
                                <div>
                                    <head>Screen layout </head>
                                    <list type="bulleted">
                                        <item>graphic design and typographic issues</item>
                                        <item>use of windows</item>
                                        <item>placement and identification of screen controls</item>
                                        <item>visual feedback techniques</item>
                                        <item>aesthetic values</item>
                                    </list>
                                </div>
                                <div>
                                    <head>Multimedia components: (images, sound, animation,
                                        movies)</head>
                                    <list type="bulleted">
                                        <item>sound: as pedagogical content, as user-friendly
                                            function, or just for decoration?</item>
                                        <item>animation: a powerful tool (not to be wasted on
                                            distracting screen toys)</item>
                                        <item>how to use the "multi" in multimedia </item>
                                        <item>other visualisation techniques (3-D, panning,
                                            walk-through)</item>
                                    </list>
                                </div>
                                <div>
                                    <head>Navigation: (enabling the user to explore the subject
                                        matter)</head>
                                    <p>Letting the user choose a direction; lighting the way;
                                        charting the way; mid-course side-trips, and changing
                                        course....</p>
                                    <list type="bulleted">
                                        <item>What the user sees first — the splash screen</item>
                                        <item>Main menu</item>
                                        <item>Sub-menus</item>
                                        <item>Screen titling</item>
                                        <item>Preferred paths</item>
                                        <item>Icon-based cross-linking</item>
                                        <item>Hypertext links</item>
                                        <item>Alphabetical indexes</item>
                                        <item>Contextually relevant indices and diagrams</item>
                                        <item>Navigation maps</item>
                                        <item>Active images</item>
                                    </list>
                                </div>
                                <div>
                                    <head>Questions and answers; quizzes and games</head>
                                    <list type="bulleted">
                                        <item>How users learn to use the program, get help, and gain
                                            confidence while doing so.</item>
                                        <item>Methods of extending the scope of the publication's
                                            interactivity beyond its own content matter</item>
                                        <item>Matching the publication to the capabilities of the
                                            users' computers</item>
                                    </list>
                                </div>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>References</head>
                            <p>The references will include:<list type="bulleted">
                                    <item>Current work on multimedia techniques and interface design
                                        at Canadian universities</item>
                                    <item>NRC projects on image capture and visualisation</item>
                                    <item>Ben Schniederman, University of Maryland (noted expert on
                                        user interface design)</item>
                                    <item>Software company design guidelines (Microsoft, Macromedia,
                                        Asymetrix, etc.)</item>
                                    <item>Electronic equivalents of the <title level="m">Chicago
                                            Manual of Style</title></item>
                                    <item>A list of electronic publications we feel are
                                        representative of good interface design</item>
                                    <item>A list of current electronic publications on architecture
                                    </item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>Some references will include the URLs of relevant sites on the World
                                Wide Web, which are now as significant to the development of
                                electronic publications as references to print publications.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Demonstration</head>
                            <p>A demonstration of multimedia software features will be central to
                                the presentation of this paper. Many of the topics would be hard to
                                understand without it.</p>
                            <p>We will be using a dual-screen computer-driven presentation. It will
                                include examples of good and bad design from existing publications.
                                We will also show early models of screen designs for our forthcoming
                                CD-ROM on the Classical Tradition in Architecture.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>Conclusion</head>
                            <p>Come June, the conference participants will be able to judge our
                                early development efforts for themselves.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>Digital Images and Virtual Scholarly Collections</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">Daniel Greenstein</p>
                        <div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Abstract</head>
                                <p>The development of increasingly affordable digital imaging
                                    technologies combined with the extension of the Internet and of
                                    the worldwide web, has resulted in an outpouring of highly
                                    distributed digital images and image collections with
                                    significant cross-disciplinary and secondary use value for
                                    humanities scholars. That value, however, cannot be realised
                                    unless digital images are created, documented, and maintained in
                                    a manner which permits their ready location, interchange, and
                                    secondary use. The challenge is only partly methodological and
                                    technical. We may also need to explore new and creative ways to
                                    manage relations between those who "own" rights in image
                                    resources and those who have an interest in acquiring access to
                                    them.</p>
                                <p>This paper will introduce the Arts and Humanities Data Service
                                    (AHDS) — a new national service established in the UK to
                                    coordinate access to and facilitate the creation and use of
                                    electronic resources in the arts and humanities. The AHDS is a
                                    distributed service comprising a managing Executive and five
                                    Service Providers respectively serving the interests of
                                    archaeology, history, the performing arts, textual studies, and
                                    the visual arts. Each of the Service Providers will collect,
                                    catalogue, manage and preserve digital collections which are of
                                    interest to particular scholarly constituencies, while the
                                    Executive will take on a managing and integrating role. Given
                                    the distributed, mixed media, and interdisciplinary nature of
                                    its digital collections, the AHDS may anticipate developmental
                                    trajectories for virtual scholarly collections.</p>
                                <p>Focusing in particular on the work of the AHDS's Visual Arts Data
                                    Service, the paper will outline the AHDS's programme for:<list
                                        type="bulleted">
                                        <item>developing interdisciplinary collections of digital
                                            images, which it seeks to do in part in collaboration
                                            with private- and public-sector partners;</item>
                                        <item>managing image collections — an activity which will
                                            rest on its identification and adoption of
                                            community-wide information interchange standards;</item>
                                        <item>providing uniform on-line access to highly varied and
                                            interdisciplinary electronic holdings.</item>
                                    </list></p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Conclusion</head>
                                <p>The paper will conclude by inviting discussion with a view to
                                    establishing strategic and cross-national partnerships. For
                                    further information, visit our web site at <ptr
                                        target="http://ahds.ac.uk/"/></p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
