<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="panel">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The Orlando Project: Humanities Computing in
                    Conversation with Literary History </title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Susan</forename>
                        <surname>Hockey</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Alberta</name>
                            <email>Susan.Hockey@UAlberta.ca</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Terry</forename>
                        <surname>Butler</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Univeristy of Alberta</name>
                            <email>Terry.Butler@UAlberta.ca</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Susan</forename>
                        <surname>Brown</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Guelph</name>
                            <email>SBrown@UoGuelph.ca</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sue</forename>
                        <surname>Fisher</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Alberta</name>
                            <email>Sue.Fisher@UAlberta.ca</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>literary history</item>
                        <item>SGML</item>
                        <item>hypertext</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Session Abstract</head>
                    <p>The Orlando Project, based at the Universities of Alberta and Guelph, is
                        producing the first full scholarly history of British women's writing in
                        printed and electronic form. Under the direction of Patricia Clements, the
                        Orlando team comprises five co-investigators, two post-doctoral fellows, a
                        project librarian and eight graduate research assistants. Orlando has
                        received a SSHRC Major Collaborative Research Initiative grant for $1.6
                        million over five years beginning in July 1996, and is also supported by the
                        Universities of Alberta and Guelph.</p>
                    <p>Orlando is using computing technology and SGML at all stages within the
                        project, but one of its key contributions to humanities computing
                        methodologies is the use of SGML to encode interpretive information in basic
                        research notes as the research is being carried out. The authors of the
                        printed volumes will draw on this database of SGML-encoded information as
                        they write. The database will also be used to create a number of hypertext
                        products for research and teaching.</p>
                    <p>Because of the scope of the project, Orlando sets a significant and
                        challenging test for some basic humanities computing tenets:<list>
                            <item>(1) that SGML has the flexibility to encode sophisticated and
                                subtle electronic text</item>
                            <item>(2) that scholarly information can be stored and managed in
                                systems which will not soon be blind-sided by technological
                                change</item>
                            <item>(3) that our networked computer landscapes can facilitate
                                substantial collaboration that overcomes the limits of both place
                                and time.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>In short, our project depends upon the confidence that systems and tools are
                        now mature in the field of humanities computing. Our experiences over the
                        first two years of this project will be examined in light of these
                        themes.</p>
                    <p>Our three papers address these issues in various ways. The first paper, "The
                        Orlando Project: Origins and Aims," provides an explanation of the
                        intellectual aims of the project, and develops the rationale for our use of
                        SGML as the primary vehicle for data capture. The iterative process, by
                        which the capabilities of our computer systems challenge and limit the
                        scholarly work, is explored.</p>
                    <p>The second paper, "SGML and the Orlando Project: Theorizing Descriptive
                        Markup," delves more deeply into SGML, and explores the innovative
                        characteristics of our project's use of it. A signal feature is our
                        development of DTD's <emph rend="italics">prior</emph> to the writing of the
                        scholarly research text (known fondly to the team members as "document
                        analysis without documents"). Key to our SGML development have been document
                        analysis sessions aimed at integrating the subjects, themes, and issues of
                        research into documents that do not give short shrift to the demands of
                        discursive prose. The paper focuses on our experiences balancing structural
                        and content-based SGML markup within our documents in a manner that will
                        provide the most comprehensive access to our material when our final
                        delivery systems are in place.</p>
                    <p>Our third paper, entitled "Eluding the Chains of Technology: Computer Systems
                        for Orlando," explores other dimensions of our computer systems, and their
                        interaction with the research procedures and scholarly practices of the team
                        members. Our initial choice of operating systems and hardware arose out of a
                        matrix of factors: users' existing skills; their computer apprehensions;
                        limited time to train; and the expectation of significant staff turnover.
                        Some of those decisions have evolved in year two, as the expertise and
                        confidence of the team increases. Web-based tools have been developed to
                        handle the document management process. The difficulty of managing SGML
                        documents with SGML-ignorant tools has been borne strongly upon us; but we
                        have created some useful systems none the less. We rely extensively on
                        network-based tools, such as e-mail and mailing lists, for inter-project
                        communication. The degree to which the project can remain "in synch" between
                        Alberta (where most of the project team members reside) and Guelph (where
                        one principal investigator and her two research assistants work) depends in
                        large measure on the effectiveness of these tools and our intelligent use of
                        them. Some practical lessons learned from this process will be expounded. A
                        major challenge of year two of the project has been to model the electronic
                        delivery system -- who is our audience, what will their needs, abilities,
                        and desires be?</p>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>The Orlando Project: Origins and Aims</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">Susan Brown</p>
                        <div>
                            <p>The Orlando Project--formally titled "An Integrated History of
                                Women's Writing in the British Isles"--is a five-year project
                                approaching the end of its second year. Our name derives from
                                Virginia Woolf's fantastic narrative of the writer through several
                                centuries of British history. We are employing computing technology
                                in a number of innovative ways, integrating the literary research
                                with computing methodology at every stage. By the norms of
                                humanities research and humanities computing, this is a large-scale
                                effort: the project is supported by a SSHRC Major Collaborative
                                Research Initiative grant for $1.6 million. The purpose of this
                                paper is to provide an overview of the project's intellectual aims
                                and what we have accomplished to date.</p>
                            <p>We will first outline our intellectual aims and the reason we decided
                                to integrate computer technologies with our research from the
                                outset.</p>
                            <p>Our use of computer technology is intimately bound up with the way we
                                conceive of literary history. Critics have charged traditional
                                literary history with contributing to a totalizing or linear view of
                                the past, and we thus seek to mobilize multiple arguments which
                                foreground process and the degree to which the components of a
                                history are always in flux. We see our history as bringing together
                                a number of distinct fields: writing by women in the British Isles,
                                the conditions of their lives, writing by men and writing from
                                outside the British Isles, historical processes, and the broader
                                social and cultural environment. Following as we do the last several
                                decades of vigorous activity in the recovery and reassessment of
                                women's writing, we will be drawing on an immense body of prior
                                research as well as adding to it our own discoveries and
                                conclusions. Our aim is to pay particular, but not exclusive,
                                attention to the complex and changing construction of gender, and
                                always to keep it in dialogue with other constituents of identity
                                and other historical and cultural factors. Our historical
                                methodologies and inquiries both draw on and test themselves against
                                the conclusions of other disciplines, including history.</p>
                            <p>In the Orlando project we are using computer tools, and particularly
                                SGML--Standard Generalized Markup Language--to bring together the
                                diverse fields of inquiry that combine in our vision of literary
                                history: not as a stable unity but as a series of complex
                                relationships. Our tagging structures and makes available a large
                                quantity of research in the areas of women's writing and women's
                                history, much of it subject to contestation. We are using SGML as
                                the basis for a presentation of these details that will allow
                                complications and contradictions to emerge from the connections and
                                narratives which we will be offering. We believe our tagging will
                                enable us to make visible the patterns and meanings immanent in this
                                mass of detail, in addition to calling attention to the gaps, the
                                discontinuities, and the unknowable silences in the history of
                                women's writing. We are thus in the process of creating a textbase
                                and a delivery system that attends to the theoretical concerns of
                                recent literary historiography, which includes consideration of
                                generic inclusiveness, the politics of canon formation, and the
                                multiplicity of theoretical paradigms that make sense of the past.
                                The bane of literary history is oversimplification and stereotyping:
                                our electronic tools seek to emulate the fluidity, flexibility, and
                                nuance of continuous prose while incorporating the structure and
                                complex searchability of a database.</p>
                            <p>One particularly innovative feature of this project is that, rather
                                than planning and conducting the research and writing first, driven
                                only by the considerations of the humanities scholar, and deciding
                                on the electronic delivery system once the research is nearing
                                completion, we are designing our data structure as part of the
                                process of research and writing, which means that the research
                                process and the computing practices of the project are
                                indistinguishable and indeed thoroughly integrated. Our process,
                                which you will be hearing about in more technical detail shortly,
                                has been to combine SGML encoding which structures and "adds value"
                                to the textual material we are writing with hypertext linking.</p>
                            <p>This means that our electronic literary history can be interactive
                                and respond minutely to particular users' interests and levels of
                                expertise. Users of our end-product will be able to find their way
                                to information of which they not yet aware; to generate their own
                                time-lines for the life-histories of individual authors, of genres
                                (like the epistolary novel, or detective fiction), or of historical
                                processes as they impinge on writing (like the suffrage campaign or
                                the shifting practices around childbirth). SGML allows us to tag
                                various kinds of information to make it accessible to analysis and
                                retrieval, but users will be able to shape the information according
                                to their own interests, whether they are students, scholars, or
                                general users. To do this we needed to work out a complex set of
                                content tags, quite unlike the kind of structural tags, such as
                                paragraph markers or address information, for which SGML is
                                typically used. We have been developing a series of SGML Document
                                Type Definitions, or DTD's, related to the different kinds of
                                material that our history will incorporate. This aspect of the
                                project will be the focus of the second paper in this session.</p>
                            <p>Our process of developing the document coding scheme has been obliged
                                to be innovative. Because the research document design is being
                                developed at the same time the research program is being formulated,
                                we have an unusual situation -- we are performing document analysis,
                                which is the usual way of developing SGML coding, but there are no
                                extant documents to analyze! Document analysis normally seeks to
                                find features of interest to tag in a corpus of texts. Our process
                                is rather a collaborative enterprise in which the intention for the
                                research directs the creation of a suitable vehicle for its
                                expression and capture. The past two years have involved us in
                                intense discussion, debate, and negotiation over what the
                                information that we are collecting consists in and how to understand
                                and organize it.</p>
                            <p>Early on, we identified several primary areas of inquiry in which the
                                work will proceed: biography, the writing lives and textual
                                histories of the works, and their cultural, social, and historical
                                contexts: in short, women, their writing, and the world. The
                                document design process has lead us to formalize the definition of
                                hundreds of tags for each of these axes, to structure, organize, and
                                interrelate the research information. The tags encourage precision
                                in the collection of information, and consistency in its
                                preparation; and they will facilitate searching and display by
                                end-users which will be both more precise, and much deeper, than
                                what has previously been made available in electronic information
                                products.</p>
                            <p>We will briefly outline what we see as the major components of the
                                project: a complex and highly manipulable chronology of women's
                                writing; lots of brief, informative documents on topics ranging from
                                the biographical summaries and discussions of literary genres to
                                short explanations of historical events or cultural phenomena;
                                lengthier discussions treating major developments in women's
                                literary history; mapping capabilities drawing on SGML structures;
                                the generation of webs of association and connection; sound clips;
                                images; and possibly some video. All of these facets of the project,
                                while diverse in many respects, will be integrated by the SGML
                                structures we have devised and the complex cross-referencing,
                                linking, and thesaural systems that we are developing to bring them
                                together. This project, of incorporating the intellectual concerns
                                and, perhaps, the conceptual structures of our arguments into the
                                structure of our markup, remains our biggest challenge.</p>
                            <p>Having outlined the nature and scope of the project, we will then
                                briefly discuss some of our conclusions resulting from the two years
                                of this conversation between literary history and humanities
                                computing.</p>
                            <p>The tools of humanities computing are helping us achieve an
                                unprecedented degree of searchability given the complex structuring
                                of our data. We anticipate our literary history hypertext will be
                                used in ways impossible with a print text, and for specialized ends
                                we may not anticipate. Yet there are also ways in which the
                                diversity of the intellectual aims of our project mean that we find
                                ourselves having to consider carefully the constraints and
                                structures that the use of SGML and our plans for hypertext delivery
                                dictate. We will thus, for instance, consider the implications of
                                SGML's hierarchical structures for our project and the overall
                                impact that adopting SGML has had on the way we have approached the
                                research. We will reflect on the implications of combining documents
                                tagged according to the Text Encoding Initiative, or TEI, with
                                documents structured using non-TEI conformant SGML. We will also
                                consider the possible drawbacks, as well as the advantages, of
                                hypertext linking for a project that wants to bring large amounts of
                                information together with complex and sustained argumentation.</p>
                            <p>The Orlando Project is thus attempting, in developing a textbase for
                                a literary critical history of British women's writing, to adapt the
                                existing tools of humanities computing to suit an interlocking set
                                of methodological and intellectual aims. We think SGML offers the
                                greatest flexibility for our purposes, as well as the hope of
                                longevity. It allows us to build relational database-like structures
                                for chronological and other granular data, while also supporting
                                multiple levels of encoding specificity for framing critical
                                arguments and for interlinking both data and argument in a hypertext
                                system. It will also allow us to link our project with the growing
                                corpus of primary works on-line that are tagged in TEI-conformant
                                SGML.</p>
                            <p>Our two years of integrating literary historical research with
                                humanities computing design have brought home to us the magnitude of
                                what we are attempting. We have been grappling hands-on with the
                                attempt to make computer tools address the myriad needs of
                                contemporary scholarship in the humanities. In developing our
                                tagging systems, we have had substantial experience of ways that
                                this process differs from traditional approaches to literary
                                research. One thing that has become clear is that our use of
                                computing tools is radically intensifying the collaborative nature
                                of the project. Instead of a single researcher needing to
                                communicate effectively and clearly with one or more research
                                assistants, we have a research collective that together had to
                                develop a shared view of the project's research aims. We have
                                already learned that explicitness is paramount. We are continually
                                forced, in ways both frustrating and beneficial, to articulate our
                                various assumptions about our purpose, our methods, our theoretical
                                frameworks, more explicitly and more frequently than, say, a
                                traditional co-editing or co-authoring project would demand. Every
                                term in use needs ample discussion, to ensure we have a common
                                understanding of its scope and import, and every new tag produces a
                                body of discussion and debate about its purpose, use, and
                                application.</p>
                            <p>One of the many challenges that remains for the future, of course, is
                                what kind of delivery system or systems we can develop to reflect
                                the project's aims, which is the focus of the third paper in this
                                session. We hope to deliver, along with accessibility and
                                flexibility, the same degree of explicitness and self-reflexivity
                                that this process is forcing on us. We want the users to be able to
                                construct their own narrative trajectories of women's writing and
                                create their own web of history. Our challenge is to enable as many
                                seen and unforeseen, imagined and unimaginable, understandings of
                                women's literary history as possible.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>SGML and the Orlando Project: Theorizing Descriptive Markup</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">Sue Fisher</p>
                        <div>
                            <p>This paper will describe how the Orlando Project is using Standard
                                Generalized Markup Language (SGML) to develop document type
                                definitions (DTD's) based on both descriptive markup and
                                comprehensive subject and critical/interpretive markup. The paper
                                will begin by defining what we feel are the distinctions and
                                similarities between descriptive markup and the content-based
                                critical/interpretive structures central to our project. These
                                definitions will then be followed by discussions of the project's
                                approach to document analysis, SGML authoring, and the integration
                                of our research for delivery as an electronic reference tool. As an
                                initial measure of the success and limitations of our approach to
                                SGML, the paper will conclude with an account of our experience
                                training graduate research assistants (GRA's) in tagging with our
                                project-specific DTD's.</p>
                            <p>The computing mandate for the Orlando Project is unique in the world
                                of SGML. Like other projects, we are interested in SGML's <emph
                                    rend="italics">descriptive</emph> markup capabilities for
                                delimiting the structural components of our material; marking such
                                information as chapter divisions, paragraphs, and long quotations
                                for the purposes of systematic display and search and retrieval is
                                key to ensuring the flexibility of our information. Also, like other
                                projects we are interested the rudimentary content tagging that
                                comes hand in hand with descriptive markup: names, dates, and titles
                                of books provide information that goes beyond the simple structure
                                of the document at hand. Unlike other humanities computing projects,
                                however, we want to exploit the possibilities of SGML to systematize
                                and foreground the interpretive models that underlie our literary
                                history. Such interpretive structures vary from the seemingly
                                objective keyword labeling of historical events such as women's
                                suffrage to tagging the central issues in our history as they occur
                                in our documents. For example, we want to be able to mark all
                                instances where we discuss women's relationships to economic
                                institutions, regardless of what line of argument the person writing
                                the document adopts. Such tagging will allow us to foreground the
                                positions taken by the multiple voices that make up the Orlando
                                Project.</p>
                            <p>Most SGML-based humanities computing projects use descriptive markup
                                to identify information that has meaning within the context of the
                                document itself. Our extended use of descriptive markup allows us to
                                tag content that has referential meaning to the world beyond our
                                documents. In theorizing and pushing the limits of descriptive
                                markup, we recognize that the world we wish to label cannot be
                                viewed objectively; rather, we are presenting that world as
                                contextualized in a specific time and place, a world seen through
                                critical lens of the project's researchers.</p>
                            <p>To create our DTD's we have spent much time in document analysis
                                sessions. But because we feel it important that our documents be
                                researched, written, and tagged in an integrated process, our
                                document analysis sessions have <emph rend="italics">preceded</emph>
                                the creation of our documents. This situation has been both
                                frustrating at times, in that we lack concrete models from which to
                                derive the hierarchical models for our DTD's, and freeing at other
                                times, in that it has forced us to examine the research aims of the
                                project in constant dialogue with the possibilities offered by the
                                computing tools. In such sessions, the project's co-investigators
                                discuss the aims of their research, what they want the project's
                                hypertext to accomplish, and how these aims relate to individual
                                areas of research, such as women's biography, writing lives, world
                                chronology and the like. Based on these sessions, we create
                                hierarchical structures that reflect the overall patterns of
                                thinking in such meetings. These hierarchical structures are then
                                revisited by a sub-committee representing the co-investigators, the
                                SGML authors, the project's postdoctoral fellows, and the GRA's who
                                do the research and tagging. Once all the components in these
                                hierarchical models have been defined, documented, and scrutinized,
                                we design DTD's based on both the structural and research areas of
                                document analysis. These DTD's will then be tested by creating real
                                research documents, in dialogue with the needs of the document as
                                defined by the DTD.</p>
                            <p>In creating the structural shell for our DTD's we are indebted to the
                                work of the Text Encoding Initiative. Its understanding of document
                                divisions, paragraph components, linking mechanisms, and expressions
                                for dates, names and places have sharpened our thinking in these
                                areas. Furthermore, the cataloguing principles inherent in the TEI
                                header have been of great use to us in our SGML authoring. The
                                structural principles in place in the TEI have been modified by our
                                project, however, in order to accommodate our research needs. Such
                                extensions include structural components for chronology items,
                                research and scholarly notes, and the ability to blend our subject
                                tagging within our structural hierarchies.</p>
                            <p>Integrated within our TEI-like structural shell are all our content
                                and critical and interpretive tags. Layering structural and content
                                tags has forced us to negotiate the difficulties of wedding multiple
                                hierarchies in SGML. Consequently, some of our content tags have
                                been integrated into the structural hierarchical model of the DTD's
                                while others have been rendered as location-specific inclusions.</p>
                            <p>Although this paper will have, to this point, referred to the
                                project's DTD's as they exist independent of one another, we have
                                devised several mechanisms for making documents created with
                                multiple DTD's and existing in thousands of files participate in our
                                hypertext web of history. The overlying architecture for our
                                hypertext will be the use of linking tags, such as the TEI's ptr,
                                ref, xptr, and xref. Combined, these tags will present paths through
                                our documents that the end-user can follow according to her wishes.
                                Such links are not adequate in creating a complex electronic
                                reference tool, however, as the hypertext trails have been blazed
                                according to the wishes of those creating the links, not according
                                to the needs of those following them. In order to enhance this
                                hypertext model, we have planned other access routes to and through
                                our information. We will provide hierarchically organized
                                subject-specific indexes based on the content and
                                critical/interpretive elements within our documents. We will also
                                label information according to a series of keywords developed by our
                                literary researchers as pertaining to the key areas of subject
                                interest on the project. Thus an end-user will be able to search for
                                information in all documents having to do with, for example,
                                politics--activism. Finally, for all items labeled as pertaining to
                                chronology, we will assign keywords and values for relevance so that
                                end-users will be able to produce subject- and period-specific
                                chronologies. We feel that these DTD design strategies will allow
                                search and retrieval of our information to go far beyond simple text
                                string searching.</p>
                            <p>To date, we have DTD's for biography and women's writing lives in
                                place and in use by our graduate research assistants. Since January
                                1996, our GRA's have been carrying out the integrated processes of
                                researching, writing, and tagging documents about British women
                                writers. Their experiences have been the true test of our approach
                                to SGML. The first two months of GRA tagging quickly revealed to us
                                the numerous shortcomings in our DTD design. Key among these was the
                                awkward blend we afforded the admixture of tabular information and
                                discursive prose. Once such problems were addressed, however, we
                                found that our GRA's were creatively adapting the tags to the
                                information at hand. What is now the biggest ongoing issue facing
                                our taggers is the ability to manage all the practice decisions that
                                have been made regarding proper use of our SGML. We continue to work
                                with how our SGML has been put into practice in order to ensure that
                                8 GRA's in two separate provinces are creating documents that have a
                                consistency in readability and tagging practice. </p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>Eluding the Chains of Technology: Computer Systems for Orlando</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">Terry Butler</p>
                        <div>
                            <p>The intellectual aims and timelines of the Orlando Project create
                                some difficult challenges for the design of the computing systems
                                which support them. How can the information we capture be shaped,
                                stored, searched, and displayed, when we are five years away from
                                the actual delivery systems? How do we avoid technological
                                dead-ends? How much time and effort can we invest in computer tools
                                which may well be transient? How can we use network communication
                                tools in ways which go beyond simple "conveying of information" to
                                achieve real and intense collaboration? How can we model the
                                electronic delivery systems -- who are the audience, what will their
                                information needs and expectations be? -- and how can we move toward
                                "building" a system when we cannot project the specifics of its
                                technology at this time?</p>
                            <p>The decisions taken with regard to operating systems and hardware, at
                                the start of the project, had an interesting admixture of
                                crystal-ball gazing, given the five-year timelines of our grant.
                                Projecting backward from 1995 five years, we know we would have
                                completely overlooked the relevance of the World Wide Web, and
                                probably hotly debated whether Macintosh or DOS/Windows would be the
                                best beast to ride to the promised land of academic computing. And
                                we knew in 1995 that the pace of change in the underlying
                                technologies was increasing, and that dramatic changes, not just
                                gentle evolutions, had been and would be characteristic of our
                                future.</p>
                            <p>Our central choice, which was not a difficult one, was a commitment
                                to use SGML to capture our research information and build the data
                                collection toward the end product, which will be both print (volumes
                                of literary history and a chronology) and electronic (a hypertext/
                                on-line searchable electronic text). To match this intention up with
                                specific tools, we chose Windows for Workgroups as our underlying
                                operating system, and conventional Intel hardware as our base
                                platform . This tandem was much less expensive, pound for pound,
                                than a Macintosh-based one. There were already in 1995 no shortage
                                of SGML and hypertext/ multimedia tools available for these systems,
                                and we believed that the unholy alliance of SGML riding on Bill
                                Gates shoulders would provide us with an upgrade path to new tools
                                and systems over the following five years.</p>
                            <p>Decisions as to specific tools followed, with the same logic. Our
                                choice of an SGML editor was crucial, for virtually all the team
                                members would use it extensively, and the research assistants would
                                have it for their regular daily work tool. Several SGML editors
                                attracted our attention at the beginning: the add-on to Microsoft
                                Word; Soft Quad's Author/Editor; and WordPerfect's SGML edition. But
                                we attended to our own arguments which took into account the
                                existing team's computer skill levels and experience (as well as
                                their cheerfully disguised computer apprehensions); the limited time
                                available to train our professors in the tool's use; and the
                                likelihood of significant staff turnover among the cadre of 8
                                graduate students. Inquiries about other SGML projects showed that
                                Word Perfect SGML was successfully in use where the users were
                                "amateurs" in various senses, while Author/Editor success stories
                                were often where the tool users were using it for their entire
                                writing job, or could be put under "orders" to do so (technical
                                writing environments, for example). So our decision to use WP SGML
                                edition leveraged by the existing familiarity with Word Perfect
                                which most of our team had, and made it a more "comfortable"
                                learning curve (quickly renamed the "learning cliff" when the
                                complexities of our DTD's were unveiled to the taggers). Our steeply
                                discounted academic price for the product didn't hurt either.</p>
                            <p>Our year one experiences with WP SGML have been generally positive;
                                our taggers have learned to use it well, and have been productive
                                with it. It has not been without its rough edges, of course. We ran
                                the WP version 6.0 beta for most taggers under Windows 3.11, and
                                tried the integrated Corel WP 7.0 under Windows 95. The program at
                                first appeared unstable, but carefully controlling our procedures
                                for saving and opening documents, and being "gentle with it" (as one
                                tagger aptly said), reduced the problems to a tolerable level.
                                Recently, our taggers have been tested the latest version of
                                Author/Editor, and have expressed enthusiasm for it. It is fair to
                                speculate that they are now more like the "pros" than they were in
                                year one. The price gap between the two products is no longer as
                                large as it once was, and we have now purchased copies of
                                Author/Editor for all the team. Both programs will be in our
                                arsenal, but we think experienced taggers will be more productive
                                with Author/Editor.</p>
                            <p>The value of our SGML commitment is already proving itself, as the
                                change of authoring tools makes clear. We are managing and massaging
                                our documents with a number of SGML-aware tools: the most valuable
                                of these is SGMLS. As we have begun to enhance what we can do with
                                our documents, through style-sheets in WP SGML, and through
                                style-sheets and webs in Panorama Pro, the principal investigators
                                and research assistants have become more assertive in their clamour
                                for "more". The SGML tagging was really not meaningful to the
                                taggers until we could pop a viewable version of the document up in
                                Panorama for them: then the coin dropped, and our mixed content and
                                hierarchical tagging began to be used to tell the intended story.
                                But the counterbalancing danger is that seeing the document in this
                                form tended to reify it -- and a Panorama view of one of our
                                documents is far from what we intend and imagine as our final
                                delivery system. So taggers are certainly now "writing for Panorama"
                                in a sense, and we are all to some extent judging the success and
                                adequacy of our work by how it looks ... for now.</p>
                            <p>The empowerment of the taggers pulls us in another direction: besides
                                multiple views of a document, they want views of multiple selections
                                out of our growing document "text base". We are only beginning to
                                build some computer systems which can respond to these requests. The
                                question arises: how much time and effort should we invest in such
                                tools, which may well be transient? Our exploration of SGML-savvy
                                document management systems concluded, at least by November 1996,
                                that there are none that are really mature and fit our needs (which
                                include the need to manage and deliver documents to distributed
                                sites) -- at least, not that fit into the budget of even a
                                generously-funded humanities computer project.</p>
                            <p>We have exploited some ad-hoc tools to manage our SGML data: VEdit (a
                                programmable editor) in the DOS environment; Perl and shell scripts
                                in Unix. These tools have proved useful for making simple programs
                                which generate and manipulate our SGML files. But it must be firmly
                                said: SGML data is <emph rend="italics">very</emph> opaque to
                                non-SGML tools. It is very hard to extract useful information out of
                                an SGML document instance, because the SGML character-stream spans
                                from one line to another, and any program which tries to navigate
                                into the sea of SGML structure does so very inconsistently, unless
                                it is (or has access to) an SGML parser. By using SGMLS (a shareware
                                SGML parser) and Perl scripts, we have been able to extract
                                components from our documents. We have our complete document
                                collections, and subsets of our documents, loaded into a LiveLink
                                searching program, for our team's use.</p>
                            <p>An example of a useful document management tool which we built is a
                                web-based document checkin/checkout system. The system was built to
                                give equal access to our central (Alberta) and remote site (Guelph),
                                as well as our users who are at times working in libraries, or from
                                home. The system stores documents on our Unix server, and provides a
                                Web interface for searching the document archive, submitting a
                                document, or checking a document out. This provides a central
                                project repository for the documents, as well as version control and
                                back-up of them.</p>
                            <p>Year two of our project (1997) also brings the task of integrating
                                our SGML documents with non-SGML data. At the start of the project,
                                we began capturing chronology information in a Microsoft Access
                                database of our own devising; and we have been capturing
                                bibliographic citations with Pro-Cite. The design of these databases
                                has all along been synchronized with our document analysis, with the
                                intention of ultimately folding them into our SGML document
                                collection. This process has been completed, but the management of
                                information as granular as a single "event" in a chronology, or a
                                single bibliographic reference, is difficult. We are currently
                                exploring the use of the Oracle database management system as
                                repository for these documents, so they can be viewed as a database
                                collection or worked on singly or in clusters, from any one of our
                                locations.</p>
                            <p>Our networked communications have extensively relied upon e-mail, and
                                several electronic lists, for information sharing and exchange. The
                                volume of traffic on these lists is impressive, and they are the
                                main vehicle for conveying detailed practice issues about the
                                tagging to the team. The lists work very well as a written vehicle
                                to convey the "how do I ..." and "here's how you do ..." exchanges.
                                Everyone involved is trying to achieve the discipline of <emph
                                    rend="italics">always</emph> using the list, when just a shout
                                across the hall is so much easier: but the shout evaporates into
                                silence, while the posting with its answer becomes an important
                                element of the team's documented procedures. This communication
                                works well when the questions asked are current and the "need to
                                know" is warm: it is less useful when the need has cooled, and the
                                tagger recollects "I saw something about that just last month ..."
                                We needed better indexing of the e-mail messages themselves (again
                                requiring discipline by the sender in keeping each message to a
                                single topic, and giving a full subject line to it) and better and
                                more various ways to index and access the on-line documentation of
                                tagging procedures, including an World Wide Web-searchable format.
                                These indexes have been mounted: using MHonArch for the e-mail
                                messages, and LiveLink for the documentation.</p>
                            <p>As far as policy issues, and in-depth collaborative work goes, our
                                use of e-mail, FTP, and shared file spaces has been ambitious, but
                                far from resoundingly successful. Sometimes the details trip us up:
                                FTP that won't "T", messages which get missed among the many others
                                on our screens, and so on. There is a sense of consensus which
                                develops over issues at the Alberta centre, that is neither explicit
                                or defined in any particular conversation or meeting, so conveying
                                this evanescent sense to Guelph, or securing their participation in
                                it, is elusive. We all feel strongly that we work much better, and
                                get much more done, when we all are present face-to-face.</p>
                            <p>Our final computing challenge, at this stage of our project, is to
                                bring the modelling of the electronic delivery system into a much
                                sharper focus, to translate it from "wouldn't it be nice ..." into
                                "it will look and work like this ...". We have said bold things: the
                                user will produce maps on the fly, which will locate events
                                (controlled by selection criteria of time, place, and topic) in a
                                geographic display. Our scholars are excited by the power and
                                potential of such a system, and the new connections and links that
                                users will be able to make with it. We are presently capturing place
                                information with a considerable degree of exactitude in our data; we
                                now must delve into Geographic Information Systems, base maps, and
                                coordinate systems, to work toward a realization of this goal.</p>
                            <p>The delivery system will embody a sophisticated text searching
                                engine, which will be able to exploit the richness and complexity of
                                the hierarchies we have embedded in our texts. The users' interests
                                will have to be brought into contact with our purposes and
                                intentions, the story we want to tell, the emphases we wish to make,
                                the misconceptions (some of a monumental nature) we wish to redress.
                                The process of modeling (picturing, imagining) what our system will
                                do and what it will be, significantly shapes the scholarly text
                                which we are now researching and writing, and will shape the final
                                computer product, about which we can be only, at present,
                                dreaming.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
