<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The Feasibility of Incremental Linguistic
                    Annotation</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Hans</forename>
                        <surname>van Halteren</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Nijmegen</name>
                            <email>hvh@let.kun.nl</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>linguistic annotation</item>
                        <item>corpus linguistics</item>
                        <item>syntactic analysis</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Abstract</head>
                    <p>This paper examines the feasibility of incremental annotation, i.e. using
                        existing annotation on a text as the basis for further annotation rather
                        than starting the new annotation from scratch. It contains a theoretical
                        component, describing basic methodology and potential obstacles, as well as
                        a practical component, describing experimental use of incremental
                        annotation.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>In both the linguistic and the language engineering communities it is
                        generally accepted that corpora are important resources and that their
                        usefulness increases with the presence of linguistic annotation. The added
                        value of annotation depends not only on what type of markup is present
                        (morpho-syntactic, syntactic, semantic, etc.) but also on the quality of
                        that markup:<list>
                            <item>- how (un)ambiguous is the markup, i.e. have only the contextually
                                appropriate markers been selected from among the potential ones or
                                has some of the ambiguity been retained (either explicitly or in the
                                form of underspecification)?</item>
                            <item>- how consistent is the annotation, e.g. is it in accordance with
                                an annotation manual?</item>
                            <item>- how correct is the annotation, i.e. will others agree with the
                                applied markup (given the stated meaning of the markers)?</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>When we examine the demands that linguistic and language engineering research
                        makes on the annotation with regards to these three points, we see that
                        fully automatic annotation is generally not an option. Beyond morpho-syntax
                        (i.e. wordclass tagging), the currently available computer software does not
                        contain sufficient knowledge about language to pinpoint the contextually
                        appropriate markup for a large enough percentage of most types of text.</p>
                    <p>This means that linguistic annotation of corpora entails human involvement
                        and, given the size of present day corpora, an enormous amount of it. In
                        recognition of the fact that the amount of work that needs to be done
                        usually exceeds the amount of work that can be done during a project
                        (because of lack of manpower, funding or whatever), the international
                        community is propagating the reuse of corpus resources. Users are encouraged
                        to use annotated corpora already in existence and annotators are encouraged
                        to perform their annotation in such a way that reuse is possible. An
                        important factor in reusability is obviously standardization of annotation
                        practices (as far as this is feasible), a fact which has led to initiatives
                        such as EAGLES (cf. Calzolari and McNaught, 1996).</p>
                    <p>If the principle of reusability really works, one can imagine taking a
                        well-annotated corpus and adding a further layer of annotation, which of
                        course should itself also be reusable. This can then be repeated, leading to
                        a cyclic process which in the end yields a corpus which is annotated for a
                        very large number of aspects. We call this process incremental annotation.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Deliberations</head>
                    <p>Incremental annotation seems to be the ideal solution for a wide-spread
                        problem: researchers can produce the data they need with much less work. In
                        practice, unfortunately, there are still some obstacles to overcome. When
                        somebody wants to add a new layer of annotation to an already annotated
                        corpus, the question always is to which degree the existing annotation is of
                        any real use. Most decisive are two properties of the existing annotation:
                        quality (i.e. (un)ambiguity, consistency and correctness) and compatibility
                        with the projected new annotation.</p>
                    <p>The importance of quality is obvious: if the existing annotation cannot be
                        trusted, checking and correcting it may be as much work as starting from
                        scratch. Furthermore, since quality is extremely complicated to measure, it
                        often really is a question of trust. It would be good if all definitions of
                        annotation standards would also include a clear-cut description of a
                        procedure to measure the quality of an annotated corpus which uses that
                        standard. Until such measurements become available, anyone planning to reuse
                        an annotated corpus had better take some random samples from it and decide
                        for himself if the quality is sufficiently high.</p>
                    <p>A high quality annotation corpus is no guarantee for unproblematic reuse,
                        though. Even unambiguous, consistent and correct annotation is only useful
                        if it provides the kind of information which is needed for the new layer.
                        Insufficient information can be supplemented, of course, (cf. Black, 1994)
                        but contradictory information will tend to be more of a problem, e.g. the
                        Lancaster Treebankers always mark the word "it" as a noun phrase but this
                        may lead to problems if the new annotation is supposed to describe an
                        anticipatory "it" as a syntactic marker. Compatibility is as hard to measure
                        as quality, maybe even harder (cf. Atwell et al, 1994). Incompatibilities
                        between annotation schemes are often found at a level of detail which goes
                        beyond superficial documentation and are usually highly context dependent.
                        As a result, only outright incompatibility can be recognized easily and
                        quickly, whereas partial incompatibility will only be noticed after
                        substantial work has already been done.</p>
                    <p>The final complication in judging the usefulness of an existing annotation is
                        that quality and compatibility are not independent. It is here that the
                        difference between correctness and consistency becomes relevant. If the
                        existing annotation has to be adapted to be useful, it may be more important
                        that it is consistent than that it is correct. In order for the existing
                        annotation to be useful, adaptations should preferably be made automatically
                        and this is very difficult if there is a high level of inconsistency.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Methodology</head>
                    <p>The deliberations above may well appear to stress potential problems for
                        incremental annotation over potential gains. If this is so, it is because we
                        feel the gains are already obvious. We certainly do not want to give the
                        impression that incremental annotation is a hopeless cause and should not
                        even be attempted. However, we do want to temper the unbridled optimism that
                        tends to accompany references to the reusability principle. The choice to
                        commit oneself to incremental annotation should always be made only after an
                        increase in efficiency and/or quality for any new annotation has been
                        demonstrated. The feasibility of such an increase depends to a large extent
                        on the way in which the incremental annotation is implemented. In general,
                        we can distinguish two methodologically different approaches to incremental
                        annotation: the planned and the opportunistic approach.</p>
                    <p>In the planned approach, all layers of annotation are designed to be
                        compatible (which includes being sufficiently consistent and correct). This
                        will usually mean that more work will have to be put into layer X in order
                        to be compatible with layers X+1, X+2, etc., but the extra work is amply
                        paid back by the decrease of work for those layers. Obviously, the planned
                        approach can only be used (fully) if one starts out with a raw corpus.
                        Furthermore, there should be a certain amount of confidence that all layers
                        of annotation will eventually be applied as planned, since otherwise the
                        extra effort for the initial layers may be lost. Such confidence can be
                        boosted by making the annotation design into a standard, but for the time
                        being such cross-layer standards are not to be expected, given the lack of
                        consensus for most types of linguistic annotation.</p>
                    <p>The opportunistic approach is less structured. Its basic tenet is that any
                        existing annotation can be useful. Following the opportunistic approach
                        means looking for the most promising data available and using that as a
                        starting point. After the data has been located, there are two ways of using
                        it. One could design the new annotation layer to be compatible with the
                        existing annotation, in effect a post hoc planned approach. Usually,
                        however, one will already have one's own ideas about what the new annotation
                        should look like. These ideas tend to imply specific requirements for the
                        existing annotation, which will then have to be adapted, corrected and
                        extended in order to serve as the foundation for the new annotation layer.
                        As already indicated above, such reuse can lead to tremendous gain over
                        annotation from scratch but can equally well lead to complete disaster.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Experimentation</head>
                    <p>In order to illustrate the difference between the approaches we have
                        performed an experiment in which parts of the Spoken English Corpus (MARSEC;
                        cf. Arnfield, 1996 and UCREL, 1996) are annotated with TOSCA/ICE syntactic
                        analysis trees. The planned approach is represented by the use of the
                        traditional TOSCA analysis system (cf. van Halteren and Oostdijk, 1993) for
                        this material. The opportunistic approach is represented by the use of an
                        adapted and extended version of that same analysis system which takes the
                        Lancaster Treebank analyses (cf. Leech and Garside, 1991) of the same
                        portion of MARSEC as input.</p>
                    <p>This paper describes the activities involved in the adaptation, examines the
                        experiences with both approaches and evaluates whether the use of the
                        Treebank data as the starting point for the analysis indeed leads to a gain
                        over the traditional method.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename>S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Arnfield</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">MARSEC: The Machine Readable Spoken English
                                Corpus</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>
                            <ptr target="http://midwich.reading.ac.uk/speechlab/marsec/marsec.html"
                            />
                        </note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Atwell</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Hughes</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Souter</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">AMALGAM: Automatic Mapping Among Lexico-Grammatical
                                Annotation Models</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Klavans</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Proceedings of the ACL Workshop on The Balancing Act:
                                Combining Symbolic and Statistical Approaches to Language</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New Jersey</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>ACL</publisher>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Black</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">An experiment in customizing the Lancaster
                                Treebank</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">N.</forename>
                                    <surname>Oostdijk</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>de Haan</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Corpus-based research into language</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Amsterdam/Atlanta</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Rodopi</publisher>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename>N.</forename>
                                    <surname>Calzolari</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename>J.</forename>
                                    <surname>McNaught</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">EAGLES Editor's Introduction (EAG-EB-FR1)</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>
                            <ptr target="http://www.ilc.pi.cnt.it/EAGLES96/edintro/edintro.html"/>
                        </note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">H.</forename>
                                    <surname>van Halteren</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">N.</forename>
                                    <surname>Oostdijk</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Towards a syntactic database: the TOSCA analysis
                                system</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Aarts</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>de Haan</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">N.</forename>
                                    <surname>Oostdijk</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">English Language Corpora: design, analysis and
                                exploitation</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Amsterdam/Atlanta</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Rodopi</publisher>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Leech</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Garside</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Running a grammar factory: The production of
                                syntactically analysed corpora or "treebanks"</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Johansson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Stenström</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">English Computer Corpora</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Berlin/New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Mouton de Gruyter</publisher>
                                <date when="1991">1991</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name type="org">UCREL</name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">UCREL Projects: The Machine Readable Spoken English
                                Corpus</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>
                            <ptr
                                target="http://www.comp.lancs.ac.uk/computing/users/paul/ucrel/project.html#marsec"
                            />
                        </note>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
