<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Hand-to-Hand Wrestling with Small Linguistic
                    Corpora</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Arienne</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">M.</forename>
                        <surname>Dwyer</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Universität Mainz</name>
                            <email>dwyer@goofy.zdv.uni-mainz.de</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>linguistic corpora</item>
                        <item>encoding</item>
                        <item>databases </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Overview</head>
                    <p>This is a description of a small corpus linguistics project from start to
                        (well, nearly) finish, undertaken entirely by one not particularly
                        computationally-adept linguist. I focus not just on the end results, but
                        also on the various options and obstacles encountered at each stage of the
                        project. As such it illustrates in a nutshell the strengths and weaknesses
                        of some of the current data- and text-management methodologies and tools for
                        non-specialists. It also may provide a useful model for other linguists and
                        linguistic anthropologists facing similar issues.</p>
                    <p>With such an illustrative example I hope to (1) show that a <emph
                            rend="italics">properly constrained</emph> corpus linguistics project
                        does not necessarily have to have a huge team of computer scientists to be
                        realized. I also hope to initiate a discussion which (2) looks at ways of
                        bridging the gap between information specialists and information
                        gatherers/analyzers, and which also (3) looks at ways of making linguistic
                        computing applications and methodologies more accessible to non-(computing)
                        specialists.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>Much of academic work has become specialized to the point where one person
                        collects the data (a field worker or a text historian), another processes it
                        (an information/data specialist), and still another consumes it (other
                        academics). In general, field workers or textual scholars know little about
                        computing, while data specialists know little about the significance of the
                        data. The two are, however, interdependent: the data specialist depends on
                        the scholar to do all the analytical markup, and the linguist/text scholar
                        depends on the data specialist to make the data consistent, accessible, and
                        manipulable.</p>
                    <p>As a data gatherer and analyzer, I want my materials in a variety of formats,
                        to be accessible to people in a variety of fields (e.g. linguistic
                        anthropology, folklore, history), as well as to the speakers of the
                        language. Secure long-term storage of the data is also crucial. This paper,
                        then, follows the trail of one linguist bumbling through the thickets of
                        text encoding and relational database management.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>An Example of a Small Linguistic Corpus: The Salar Project</head>
                    <p>Salar is an unwritten Turkic language spoken primarily in northern Tibet. The
                        corpus of ca. 40,000 words consists of transcriptions of field recordings of
                        a variety of spoken language forms: conversations, stories, speeches, and
                        ballads.</p>
                    <p>The aims of the project were: (1) to archive such examples of language use as
                        separate texts; (2) put the data in a queryable format (e.g., a database) to
                        extract linguistic information; (3) to design a dictionary with an
                        electronic interface, based on this queryable format; and (4) to write a
                        usage-based grammar of the language, based on examples pulled out of the
                        data.</p>
                    <p>Linguistic analysis, here broadly conceived, includes not only phonological,
                        morphological, and grammatical analysis, but also sociolinguistic analyses
                        as well. It aims above all to examine the usage of language on the basis of
                        spoken discourse (rather than on an idealized or standardized language), in
                        order to reveal the patterns or schemata by which speakers construct
                            language.<note n="1">Michael Barlow (1996), <title level="a">Corpora for
                                Theory and Practice</title> (<title level="j">International Journal
                                of Corpus Linguistics</title> 1.1:1-37; Paul J. Hopper (1987),
                                <title level="a">Emergent Grammar</title> (<title level="m">Berkeley
                                Linguistics Conference</title> 13:139-157.</note></p>
                    <p>Linguistic markup requirements include phonological features (phonemes in the
                        International Phonetic Alphabet (IPA), secondary articulations
                        (preaspiration, devoicing, epenthesis), prosodic features (stress,
                        intonation contours, length of pauses), morphosyntactic features
                        (derivational suffixation, cliticization, government, etc.), and
                        etymological features. Metalinguistic markup requirements include a
                        reference number, title, speaker(s) (with cross-references to speaker age,
                        gender, education level), recording date, locale, and any mid-text switch of
                        speakers.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Issues</head>
                    <p>Linguistic corpora from unwritten languages present a different set of
                        problems from a typical legacy text analysis project. There is much more
                        information packed into an audio recording of speech than there is in a
                        written text. Recordings can be transcribed and re-transcribed into text in
                        a variety of ways based on the interests of the transcriber. But once the
                        transcriptions are encoded as primary data in a corpus, they take on an
                        almost unjustified permanence.</p>
                    <p>Some Central Asian epics, including those of the Salars, feature a
                        nine-headed monster called a <emph rend="italics">Mangus</emph>. When
                        wrestling with a linguistic corpus, the core issues[AMD1] of data
                        representation, text encoding, and text searching often raise their fearsome
                        heads before the unwary field linguist. Each of these is discussed in turn
                        with examples drawn from the Salar project:</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Data representation</head>
                    <p>Consists of self-designed International Phonetic Alphabet fonts, mapped
                        according to Unicode mapping tables (<title level="m">The Unicode
                            Standard</title>, v.1, v.2, The Unicode Consortium). </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Text encoding</head>
                    <p>Based on TEI-conformant SGML (The Text Encoding Initiative, P3). I weigh its
                        advantages and disadvantages, including, for example, the large amounts of
                        metatextual information required in the header of such a spoken text (e.g.
                        speaker, locale, and recording information).</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Text Searching</head>
                    <p>Two approaches are demonstrated and assessed here: (1) text is chunked into a
                        sample Foxprow relational database with a dictionary-like queryable front
                        end[2]; (2) text files marked up in SGML are queried via the MULTEXT
                        Project's query language interpreter MtSgmlQL (CNRS et al. 1996, cf. <ptr
                            target="http://www.lpl.univ-aix.fr/projects/multext/mql1.html"/>).</p>
                    <p>I compare the range of queries possible in both formats, as well as their
                        ease of use. In demonstrating the two approaches, I discuss certain
                        (linguistic) problems: the concordance (or linking, in the database) of
                        several transcription-versions of the text to each other, and to
                        multilingual free translations of the texts (here, in English and Chinese).
                        With regard to the database approach, I discuss whether the average
                        non-computer specialist can make do with general purpose off- the-shelf
                        database software such as Foxprow or Access, or whether an investment in
                        CELLAR (Summer Institute of Linguistics, 996) is preferable.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Conclusions</head>
                    <list>
                        <item>1. The above example of the Salar corpora suggests that it is
                            necessary to store and present such linguistic (and/or
                            anthropological/folkoristic) data in a variety of formats. The
                            queryable-SGML file and/or the SGML- based database is one prototype
                            data-analysis/management system for other linguistic corpora.</item>
                        <item>2. Departments with doctoral programs in linguistic anthropology and
                            linguistics would do well to (1) offer a specific computing course
                            tailored to the needs of linguists, perhaps in conjunction with the
                            university's humanities computing center or computer science department;
                            and (2) require its (post-)graduate students to undertake a very small
                            sample project (e.g. with a collection of ten utterances) using
                            humanities computing tools.</item>
                        <item>3. Individual scholars need more training opportunities in humanities
                            computing; we need more, and more varied, specialized courses such as
                            the excellent CETH seminar. (The latter unfortunately lacks a corpus
                            linguistics track.)</item>
                        <item>4. Individual scholars need to forge connections with data specialists
                            to learn methodologies and tools specific to their project. This will
                            improve the quality of the project itself and contribute to the
                            development of better tools and methods (or at l east the refinement of
                            existing ones). (One of the reasons data-gatherers-and-analyzers
                            (scholars) are rarely motivated to stand shoulder-to-shoulder with data
                            specialists and seize the proverbial means of production is of course
                            due to the current tenure system, which at present usually declines to
                            recognize work in electronic form as legitimate publications.)</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
