<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Pedagogy goes to the movies: hypermedia in the cinema
                    class room.</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Adrian</forename>
                        <surname>Miles</surname>
                        <affiliation>Department of Communication Studies <name type="org">RMIT
                                University</name>
                            <email>adrian.miles@rmit.edu.au</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Virginia</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, VA</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1999</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <forename type="middle"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Bonza is a colloquial Australian term that means, more or less, "great" or
                    "excellent," and is the name of an undergraduate cinema studies project at RMIT
                    University (<ptr target="http://bonza.rmit.edu.au/"/>). This project is an
                    applied research subject where students develop and exercise significant
                    research skills in a discipline area, and then apply this research in the
                    writing (or production) of complex, interlinked, hypermedia essays. In all
                    aspects of the project great care has been taken to ensure that the technologies
                    used are affordable, available, and scalable.</p>
                <p>Cinema studies as a field of teaching has always availed itself of new
                    technologies. It was among the first humanities disciplines to actively use the
                    VCR, and regularly employs what are now known as 'multimedia' technologies to
                    assist in teaching. The use of new digital technologies by cinema studies, in
                    particular online learning resources and hypermedia, has followed what is now
                    the established paradigm for such work with content being distributed in various
                    electronic formats (CDROM and WWW for instance) but with the result that
                    students' experience of writing on the cinema remains firmly entrenched in a
                    conservative paradigm of textual description and theoretical application.
                    Through a peer owned online relational database, combined with hypermedia
                    writing, students in the bonza project are able to significantly alter their
                    perception and practice of cinema studies, but more generally a teaching
                    methodology is being explored that encourages students to develop link
                    'competency' producing 'knowledge objects,' which in rare instances demonstrate
                    'deep' linking and cognitive understanding.</p>
                <p>Bonza consists of two related practices, the first involves students undertaking
                    primary research in a self nominated field relating to Australian cinema studies
                    where they are encouraged to use as many resources and media types as available.
                    This material is digitised, and all bibliographic, biographical, and production
                    information entered into the appropriate database. As these databases are
                    relational, direct connections between their own, and each others, research
                    becomes apparent. This allows students to not only pursue particular research
                    themes with ease, but it encourages collaboration as they find related material
                    contributed by their peers. In addition the connections that the database
                    establishes automatically amongst material encourages students to recognise the
                    manner in which their object of study is strongly interrelated (thematically,
                    institutionally, theoretically) and not actually a discrete or individual
                    entity.</p>
                <p>This can be described as 'shallow' link building, as the connections being found
                    are generally literal and the result of simple string matches based on names,
                    and while much of the primary research students undertake has already made
                    significant contributions to Australian cinema historiography, it is the
                    possibility of writing 'deep' link structures in hypermedia that best expresses
                    a student's understanding of their research material.</p>
                <p>This is a key feature of the pedagogy employed in this project, as it is the
                    ability to write with, and amongst, media types, and to link them freely, that
                    distinguishes hypermedia writing from other digital pedagogic practices. This is
                    the method developed by the RMIT HyperText Project where digital literacy is
                    defined as a writing practice rather than a reading or delivery methodology.</p>
                <p>As the subject seeks to encourage the development of research skills and the
                    production of link rich 'knowledge objects' students can write up their research
                    adopting whatever authorial voice or style they wish. This is a pragmatic
                    response to the manner in which the 'traditional' academic essay tends to stymie
                    students in their novel use of hypermedia as a writing tool, particularly their
                    desire (and anxiety) to demonstrate, argue for, and legitimate a specific
                    theoretical thesis. The linearity that usually results, and their anxiety about
                    the 'outside' of their writing -- that is all that is marginal, contrary, or
                    simply unable to be incorporated due to media type or size -- is an aspect of
                    formal and traditional writing practices, that a free authorial voice partially
                    bypasses.</p>
                <p>However, it is in the performance of what could be described as 'link
                    competency,' that is the recognition that links are not merely navigational aids
                    within a work but represent rhetorical or cognitive associations that are able
                    to generate and express logical metastructures, that students develop 'deep'
                    linking and write what Entwistle and Marton have described, in another context,
                    as "knowledge objects" (Entwistle and Marton, 1993). Research, in this model,
                    becomes contextually rich and writing becomes a game or strategy of bricolage --
                    more or less successful, which at its best is exemplary (Gee, 1998), and its
                    worse produces radial texts that tend towards reportage (Lim, 1998).</p>
                <p>While most student work tends towards the two extremes of the radial and the
                    saturated (Lim, 1998 and 36, 1998) what remains to be developed, and it isn't
                    yet clear how this will be achieved in the short term, is an adequate pedagogy
                    of 'deep linking' where students are able to build these knowledge objects
                    through not only combining media types or maximising link use but through the
                    development of coherent thematic and contextual associations across writing and
                    media types. What is apparent to date is that students require considerable time
                    writing their material for this to happen, where rewriting needs to become a
                    continual rebuilding of the relations between already established parts.</p>
                <p>This difficulty is hardly surprising given students unfamiliarity with the
                    medium, and the paucity of academic examples available. That this is the case in
                    cinema studies only exacerbates what could be characterised as the tyranny of
                    the word (and node) in academic hypertext practice, and while bonza is a
                    beginning along this path, it is hoped that new pedagogies may develop that are
                    able to facilitate the students' construction and identification of relations
                    between parts. It is clear that if we regard the digital as only a mechanism for
                    the delivery of pedagogy then we are not only constraining the learning that our
                    students might achieve, but we remain fixed within conservative genres of what
                    constitutes a possible academic writing practice.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Eloise</forename>
                                    <surname>36</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Helen Twelvetrees</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">bonza</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr
                                target="http://bonza.rmit.edu.au/essays/1998/twelvetrees/index.html"
                            />&gt; Accessed April 23, 1999.</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Jay</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">David</forename>
                                    <surname>Bolter</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Writing Space: The Computer, Hypertext, and the History
                                of Writing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Hillsdale (N.J.)</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher>
                                <date when="1991">1991</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">John</forename>
                                    <surname>Eklund</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Cognitive Models for Structuring Hypermedia and
                                Implications for Learning from the World-Wide Web</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">AusWeb95</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr
                                target="http://www.scu.edu.au/sponsored/ausweb/ausweb95/papers/hypertext/eklund/index.html"
                            />&gt; Accessed May 1, 1998. </note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Noel</forename>
                                    <surname>Entwistle</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Ference</forename>
                                    <surname>Marton</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Knowledge Objects: Understandings Constituted Through
                                Intensive Academic Study</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">EQARD Occasional Paper</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">93</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">4</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp"/>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Caroline</forename>
                                    <surname>Gee</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Desert Landscape in Australian Feature Films</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">bonza</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://bonza.rmit.edu.au/bonza98/desert/index.html"
                            />&lt; Accessed April 23, 1999.</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first"/>
                                    <surname/>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Institute for Advanced Technology in the
                                Humanities</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/"/>&gt; Accessed October
                            17, 1998.</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Michael</forename>
                                    <surname>Joyce</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">New Stories for New Readers: Contour, Coherence and
                                Constructive Hypertext</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Ilana</forename>
                                    <surname>Snyder</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Page to Screen: Taking Literacy into the Electronic
                                Era</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Sydney</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Allen and Unwin</publisher>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">David</forename>
                                    <surname>Kolb</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Socrates in the Labyrinth: Hypertext, Argument,
                                Philosophy</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Watertown</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Eastgate Systems</publisher>
                                <date>n.d.</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>Computer Software</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">George</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Landow</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Hypertext: The Convergence of Contemporary Critical
                                Theory and Technology</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1992">1992</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Diana</forename>
                                    <surname>Laurillard</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Rethinking University Teaching: A Framework for the
                                Effective Use of Educational Technology</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Routledge</publisher>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Penny</forename>
                                    <surname>Lim</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Peter Doyle</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">bonza</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://bonza.rmit.edu.au/bonza98/doyle/index.html"
                            />&gt; Accessed April 23, 1999. </note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Peter</forename>
                                    <surname>Ling</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Evaluating Teaching Initiatives which Employ Resource
                                Based Learning: Draft For Review and Discussion</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">UltiBase: A World Wide Web Service for Tertiary
                                Educators</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://ultibase.rmit.edu.au/Articles/lingp1.html"
                            />&gt; Accessed July 24, 1998. </note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Adrian</forename>
                                    <surname>Miles</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Deb</forename>
                                    <surname>Verhoeven</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">bonza</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://bonza.rmit.edu.au/"/>&gt; Accessed December
                            12, 1998.</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Adrian</forename>
                                    <surname>Miles</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a"><title level="m">Singin' in the Rain</title>: A
                                Hypertextual Reading</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Postmodern Culture</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol"/>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp"/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>Accessed May 8, 1998. Vol. &lt;<ptr
                                target="http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/pmc/v008/8.2miles.html"/>&gt;
                            mirrored at &lt;<ptr target="http://cs.art.rmit.edu.au/singing/"
                            />gt;.</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Adrian</forename>
                                    <surname>Miles</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">RMIT Communication Studies HyperText Project</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://hypertext.rmit.edu.au/"/>&gt; Accessed
                            December 12, 1998. </note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Ilana</forename>
                                    <surname>Snyder</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Page to Screen: Taking Literacy into the Electronic
                                Era</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Sydney</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Allen and Unwin</publisher>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
