<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Interdisciplinary Humanities Scholars and Hybrid
                    Information Environments</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Carole</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
                        <surname>Palmer</surname>
                        <affiliation>Library and Information Science <name type="org">University of
                                Illinois</name>
                            <email>palmer@alexia.lis.uiuc.edu</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Laura</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Neumann</surname>
                        <affiliation>Library and Information Science <name type="org">University of
                                Illinois</name>
                            <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Virginia</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, VA</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1999</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <forename type="middle"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>This paper reports on a study of how interdisciplinary humanities scholars
                        find and use information. It is part of a series of studies we have
                        conducted over the past five years addressing information use in fields
                        ranging from literary studies to artificial intelligence[7], [9], [10]. As
                        information scientists we are interested in how information is gathered,
                        used, synthesized, disseminated, and the impact of technology on these
                        processes. While some of our recent work has been directed at the use of
                        digital materials, our overall program of research is designed to build a
                        holistic understanding of the interplay between various types and formats of
                        information in scholarly work. Hence, our interest in understanding the many
                        facets of scholarship and research that predate digital systems as well as
                        how scholars make the transition to new formats and the functions they
                        provide.</p>
                    <p>Information science has produced a large body of literature on information
                        use, most of which has concentrated on scientific information and
                        communication. However, the results of science user studies can have limited
                        applicability to other fields that differ in their modes of inquiry. While
                        we have found that certain information practices hold constant for
                        interdisciplinary research across the sciences and humanities, we have also
                        identified critical variations. Moreover, many of the current science-based
                        initiatives may not be cogent for research traditions that rely on
                        contextual richness. For instance, important aspects of document modularity,
                        terminology exchange, and collaborative information spaces will differ in
                        the humanities, presenting unique problems and priorities. Recently in our
                        field, investigators have begun to stress the social, ecological, and
                        content-oriented nature of information and knowledge, focusing on the
                        differing cultures, communication patterns, and vocabularies of
                        literature-producing subject fields [3], [8], [15]. Our approach follows
                        this trend and is grounded in studies of knowledge creation and work
                        practices that focus on the role of information in relation to material
                        resources, work practices and environments, and intellectual communities
                        [12], [13].</p>
                    <p>We are concentrating on humanities scholars in this phase of our research
                        because we believe that their work reflects fundamental processes that
                        should be supported in existing and future libraries. In particular, we are
                        concerned with the ability to sustain humanists' reliance on a range of
                        primary and secondary materials, in both physical and digital formats [6],
                        as well as their deep engagement with texts, artifacts, and other forms of
                        information. These features may ultimately distinguish working research
                        libraries from storehouses of physical and digitized materials. By targeting
                        a subset of interdisciplinary humanists, this study foregrounds the
                        complications of accessing, managing, and integrating information from both
                        heterogeneous subjects <emph rend="bold">and</emph> sources.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The Study</head>
                    <p>This study examines the practices and experiences of humanities scholars
                        whose work requires crossing the boundaries built into our institutions and
                        information systems. As in our previous work on interdisciplinary
                        scientists, analysis is based on in-depth interviews with researchers who
                        fit the conceptual requirements of the study. The scholars have been
                        recognized for their interdisciplinarity by receiving an appointment at a
                        respected research institute. They have spent time in-residence at the
                        facility, which devotes extensive resources to promoting cross-disciplinary
                        work. The group represents a range of fields, incorporating many different
                        subject areas, methods, and theoretical perspectives.</p>
                    <p>We conducted semi-structured interviews with twenty-five center affiliates.
                        Ten of the scholars were targeted for more in-depth case study, which
                        included follow-up interviews and content and citation analysis of published
                        papers, which is ongoing. The interviews covered how the scholars gather and
                        keep up with information, communicate with colleagues, their reliance on
                        computers and electronic information systems, and their overall scholarly
                        work practices. The sessions averaged about 60 minutes and were audio
                        recorded. Textual accounts of each interview were constructed based on
                        partial transcription of the tapes and field notes. Iterative rounds of
                        descriptive and thematic coding were performed with ATLAS.ti, software
                        designed for qualitative data analysis and theory building. The resulting
                        codes were brought together into conceptual networks that describe
                        strategies, interactions, conditions, and consequences--relations considered
                        significant for grounded theory development [14].</p>
                    <p>Three specific points that relate to computing and the scholarly process
                        emerged from our data. First, digital texts are not widely used, but online
                        bibliographic materials play a consistent yet minor role in the information
                        routines of the scholars. Selected computer-based systems are being adopted
                        with continued heavy reliance on conventional libraries, personal
                        collections, and information gathered through colleague networks. Second,
                        web-based descriptive materials such as catalogs and guides are highly
                        valued, especially in preparation for travel to research collections. They
                        allow scholars to explore the material that surrounds certain items in an
                        archive or library and can provide a path to other relevant sources beyond
                        the boundaries of the collection. Third, information technologies play a
                        significant role in personal communication, information management, the
                        writing process, and the generation of ideas. The interpretation and
                        integration that results from interacting with research materials are
                        embedded in these activities.</p>
                    <p>While it is possible that these findings are representative of humanities
                        scholars in general, the resources and practices of these interdisciplinary
                        researchers are best understood as part of the "dialectic process" that is
                        the true method of interdisciplinary work [5]. The scanning, gathering,
                        compiling, consulting, and verifying of evidence and ideas garnered from
                        texts, people, and other sources are instrumental to this process of
                        exchange and synthesis. In order to work across multiple intellectual
                        domains, these scholars develop strategies for extending the scope of their
                        information field. For example, they are eclectic readers and active
                        browsers who regularly probe for leads in outside domains. At the same time
                        they place particular emphasis on what might be called "push" information
                        sources that deliver diverse information directly into their work routines
                        through channels such as listserves, editorial and reviewing activities, and
                        cross-disciplinary colleague relationships sustained through e-mail and
                        conferences. As a result, potentially fortuitous discoveries in peripheral
                        subject areas increase, and scholars develop links with reliable sources and
                        "locals" to assist in explaining and validating material from unfamiliar
                        territories. Likewise, basic resources such as reference works and textbooks
                        are essential for verification and self-education. As would be expected,
                        complications related to language and audience are pronounced. The natural
                        language used in the humanities is much less effective for communicating and
                        identifying analogies [1], [2] across domains than the more cryptic
                        representations used in scientific discourse.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Conclusion</head>
                    <p>Complex arrays of interrelated activities, information, and intellectual
                        communities are formed through the practice of interdisciplinary
                        scholarship. The composites constructed through the work of these scholars
                        can serve as a schematic of the content, functions, and relationships that
                        are vital to information environments designed for interdisciplinarians in
                        the humanities. Our long-term studies of both interdisciplinary and more
                        discipline-based humanities scholars will continue to document their
                        transition to the evolving "hybrid library" [11]. As we continue to follow
                        scholars, over time we hope to be able to discern anticipated changes in the
                        dynamics of knowledge creation, exchange, and distribution [4], as they
                        emerge.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="1">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">David</forename>
                                    <surname>Bawden</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Information Systems and the Stimulation of
                                Creativity</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Journal of Information Science</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">12</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">203-216</biblScope>
                                <date when="1986">1986</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="2">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Kenneth</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Cory</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Discovering Hidden Analogies in an Online Humanities
                                Database</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Computers in the Humanities</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">31</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">1-12</biblScope>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="3">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Birger</forename>
                                    <surname>Hjorland</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Hanne</forename>
                                    <surname>Albrechtsen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Toward a New Horizon in Information Science: Domain
                                Analysis</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Journal of the American Society for Information
                                Science</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">46</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">6</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">400-425</biblScope>
                                <date when="1995">1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter" n="4">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Susan</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"/>
                                    <surname>Hockey</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Computer Networking and Textual Sources in the
                                Humanities</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Teresa</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Harrison</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <forename type="first">Timothy</forename>
                                <surname>Stephen</surname>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Computer Networking and Scholarly Communication in the
                                Twenty-First-Century</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>ALbany, NY</pubPlace>
                                <publisher> State University of New York</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">83-93</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book" n="5">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Julie</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">Thompson</forename>
                                    <surname>Klein</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Crossing Boundaries: Knowledge, Disciplinarities, and
                                Interdisciplinarities</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Charlottesville and London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>University Press of Virginia</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="6">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">David</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Levy</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Cathy</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Marshall</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Going Digital: A Look at Assumptions Underlying Digital
                                Libraries</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Communications of the ACM</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">38</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">4</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">77-84</biblScope>
                                <date when="1995">April 1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="7">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Laura</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Neumann</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Ann</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Bishop</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">From Usability to Use: Measuring the Success of
                                Testbeds in the Real World</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Proceedings of the 35th Annual GSLIS Clinic, March 22-
                                24, 1998</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Urbana, IL</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Graduate School of Library and Information
                                    Science</publisher>
                                <date when="2000">forthcoming</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="8">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Carole</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Palmer</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Aligning Studies of Information Seeking and Use with
                                Domain Analysis</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Journal of the American Society for Information
                                Science</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol"/>
                                <biblScope type="issue">(50th anniversary issue)</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp"/>
                                <date when="1999">forthcoming</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>

                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter" n="9">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Carole</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Palmer</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">The Information Connection in Scholarly
                                Synthesis</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Raymond</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>McInnis</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Discourse Synthesis: A Volume Dedicated to the History
                                and Theory of Knowledge Cumulation</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Westport, CT</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Greenwood Press</publisher>
                                <date when="2001">forthcoming</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="10">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Carole</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Palmer</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Structures and Strategies of Interdisciplinary
                                Science</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Journal of the American Society for Information
                                Science</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">50</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">242-253</biblScope>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="11">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Chris</forename>
                                    <surname>Rusbridge</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Towards the Hybrid Library</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">D-Lib Magazine</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol"/>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp"/>
                                <date when="1998">July/August 1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr
                                target="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/july98/rusbridge/07rusbridge.html"
                            />&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter" n="12">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Susan</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">Leigh</forename>
                                    <surname>Star</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Working Together: Symbolic Interactionism, Activity
                                Theory and Information Systems</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Yrjo</forename>
                                    <surname>Engestrom</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">David</forename>
                                    <surname>Middleton</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Communication and Cognition at Work</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">296-318</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="13">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Susan</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">Leigh</forename>
                                    <surname>Star</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Karen</forename>
                                    <surname>Ruhleder</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Steps towards an Ecology of Infrastructure: Design and
                                Access for Large Information Spaces</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Information Systems Research</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">7</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">111-134</biblScope>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book" n="14">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Anselm</forename>
                                    <surname>Strauss</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Juliet</forename>
                                    <surname>Corbin</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">The Basics of Qualitative Research: Grounded Theory
                                Procedures and Techniques</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Newbury Park, CA</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Sage</publisher>
                                <date when="1990">1990</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="15">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Howard</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">D.</forename>
                                    <surname>White</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Katherine</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">W.</forename>
                                    <surname>McCain</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Visualization of Literatures</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Annual Review of Information Science and
                                Technology</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">37</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">99-168</biblScope>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
