<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Mapping 18th Century Structures of Knowledge: the
                    Renvois System in Diderot's <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title></title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Gilles</forename>
                        <surname>Blanchard</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Ecole Normale Supérieure</name>, France <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Mark</forename>
                        <surname>Olsen</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Chicago</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Computational / Corpus Linguistics</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>One of the crowning achievements of the 18th century Enlightenment was the <title
                    level="m">Encyclopédie ou Dictionnaire raisonné des sciences, des arts et des
                    métiers, par une Société de Gens de lettres</title>, edited by Diderot and
                d'Alembert. Published in Paris between 1751 and 1772, in 17 volumes of text and 11
                volumes of plates, it contains 74,000 articles written by more than 140
                contributors. The <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title> was a massive reference work
                for the arts and sciences, as well as a <emph rend="italics">machine de
                    guerre</emph> which served to propagate Enlightened ideas. The impact of the
                    <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title> was enormous. Through its attempt to
                classify learning and to open all domains of human activity to its readers, the
                    <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title> gave expression to many of the most
                important intellectual and social developments of its time.</p>
            <p>The scale and ambition of the <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title> inspired the
                editors to adopt three modes of organization: dictionary, encyclopedic, and the
                    <emph rend="italics">renvois</emph>. The interaction of these three modes has
                led modern scholars to describe the <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title> as the
                "ancestor of hypertext" and depict Diderot as "l'internaute d'hier"<note n="1">1.
                    Brian, Eric (1998). "L'ancêtre de l'hypertexte". <title level="j">Les Cahiers de
                        Science et Vie</title>, 47 (oct. 1998), pp.28-38. </note>. Diderot makes the
                importance of the organization of knowledge explicit in the <title level="m"
                    >Discours Preliminaire</title>:<cit rend="block">
                    <quote>As an <emph rend="italics">Encyclopedia</emph>, it is to set forth the
                        order and connection of the parts of human knowledge. As a <emph
                            rend="italics">Reasoned Dictionary of the Sciences, Arts, and
                            Trades</emph>, it is to contain the general principles that form the
                        basis of each science and each art ... and the most essential facts that
                        make up the body and substance of each.</quote>
                    <bibl>
                        <note n="2">2. English translation cited in Nelly Hoyt and Thomas Cassier,
                            "Introduction" to <title level="m">Encyclopedia</title> (1965), p. xxiii
                            (our emphasis). </note>
                    </bibl>
                </cit>
            </p>
            <p>Of the three modes of organization, the dictionary mode (organization of entries in
                alphabetical order) is certainly the simplest. The second mode of organization is
                encyclopedic, where each entry is assigned a "class of knowledge", placing it within
                the "order" of human knowledge, as was described by d'Alembert's <title level="m"
                    >Systême Figuré des connoissances humaines</title>. Reflecting Enlightenment
                theories of epistemology, the tree of knowledge has a three-fold trunk comprised of
                memory, reason, and imagination, from which spring many branches, twigs, and leaves
                (Image of Pank's tree). Simply placing an entry into this hierarchy of knowledge was
                insufficient to indicate the inter-connections of knowledge. Thus, Diderot created
                an extensive system of <emph rend="italics">renvois</emph> (cross-references), the
                third mode of organization, providing a lattice of inter-connections between
                individual leaves of the tree as well as between classes of knowledge. The reader is
                encouraged to follow the <emph rend="italics">renvois</emph>, which unite fields of
                knowledge into what was hoped to be a seamless totality.</p>
            <p>The ARTFL Project's creation of a computer implementation of the Enlightenment's "war
                    machine"<note n="3">3. Andreev, Leonid et al (1999). "Re-engineering a War
                    Machine: ARTFL's <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title>". <title level="j"
                        >Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> Vol 14, No. 1 1999, pp.
                    11-28.</note> has attempted to provide this three-fold access and navigation to
                scholars and researchers. Furthermore, the electronic <title level="m"
                    >Encyclopédie</title> provides a unique tool to study the interactions of these
                three modes of organization of knowledge. Systematic examination of Diderot's
                hypertext is important not only for the light it sheds on the function and
                construction of the <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title> itself and the contours of
                18th century knowledge, but may also be informative for modern conceptions of
                hypertext.</p>
            <p>The two first modes of organization (dictionary order and encyclopedic classification
                of knowledge) can be envisioned directly by the reader of the <title level="m"
                    >Encyclopédie</title>. The third, the structure of the <emph rend="italics"
                    >renvois</emph>, is impossible to grasp as a whole because of its more diffuse
                nature. The 61,700 individual <emph rend="italics">renvois</emph> are unevenly
                distributed across the 74,000 articles of the <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title>,
                reflecting the wide variation in size and scope of articles. 22,955 articles or
                subarticles have one or more <emph rend="italics">renvois</emph>. As might be
                expected, articles with <emph rend="italics">renvois</emph> are significantly longer
                (568 words) than those without (158 words). The <emph rend="italics">renvois</emph>
                simply refer to one or more articles by head word. Thus, these connections are what
                might be termed leaf to leaf (or node to node), which allow the user to traverse
                leaves, without regard to the classes of knowledge. As a reader, one can only see
                the links stemming locally from a particular entry: much as someone hiking in a
                chain of mountains, it is not possible to step back and get a general vision of the
                whole landscape.</p>
            <p>The online version of the <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title> allows us to draw a
                very coarse first map of the links "landscape". Our methodology was to group the
                entries into the classes of knowledge to which they belong and to measure the
                strength of relationships of all of the <emph rend="italics">renvois</emph> between
                these classes of knowledge using a simple Z-score calculation. The resulting graph
                shows the statistically significant (or "privileged") links between classes of
                knowledge. A given <emph rend="italics">renvois</emph> does not specify a precise
                sense of the word we should look for, and for any given word one often finds several
                distinct entries corresponding to different classes of knowledge (polysemy). There
                is no automatic way to determine the "true" link initially intended by the author -
                assuming that the author had a single sense in mind. However, a statistical study
                taking into account several independant <emph rend="italics">renvois</emph> between
                classes allows us to get a more reliable picture and to disregard insignificant
                links.</p>
            <p>The encyclopedic landscape shows some striking features. First, there is a high local
                connectivity between close classes - in other words, there are several different
                ways to go from "physique" to "géometrie", for example. Secondly we can see a clear
                division of the links landscape into two "hemispheres", namely, knowledge related to
                direct observation of nature (histoire naturelle), heuristic sciences (chimie,
                médecine), rural life (économie rustique) on the one hand; and knowledge related to
                or contructed by the human mind on the other (abstract sciences such as mathematics;
                philosophy; history; laws of human society). Not surprisingly, the "human
                hemisphere" is much more important than the "natural hemisphere" in terms of sheer
                size.</p>
            <p>The general structure of the <emph rend="italics">renvois</emph> can be related to
                the encyclopedic order pictured in d'Alembert's <title level="m">Systême
                    Figuré</title>. For example, mathematics, geometry, and arithmetic are closely
                grouped in our landcape drawn from the <emph rend="italics">renvois</emph> and in
                the encyclopedic order defined by d'Alembert. The two hemispheres detected in this
                preliminary examination, however, do not clearly correspond to d'Alembert's general
                schema. The power of the Encyclopédie's "hypertextuality" arises from the
                combination of a general map of the structures of knowledge and the lattice of
                related cross-references. Rather than conceive of the renvois as simply node to node
                links, Diderot's hypertext assumes an abstract representation of knowledge. He
                writes, in the <title level="m">Discours Préliminaire</title>,<cit rend="block">
                    <quote>On a tâché que l'exactitude &amp; la fréquence des <emph rend="italics"
                            >renvois</emph> ne laissât là - dessus rien à desirer; car les <emph
                            rend="italics">renvois</emph> dans ce Dictionnaire ont cela de
                        particulier, qu'ils servent principalement à indiquer la liaison des
                        matieres; au lieu que dans les autres ouvrages de cette espece, ils ne sont
                        destinés qu'à expliquer un article par un autre. [...] Ainsi trois choses
                        forment l'ordre encyclopédique; le nom de la Science à laquelle l'article
                        appartient; le rang de cette Science dans l'Arbre; la liaison de l'article
                        avec d'autres dans la même Science ou dans une Science différente; liaison
                        indiquée par les <emph rend="italics">renvois</emph>...</quote>
                    <bibl>
                        <note n="4">4. <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title>, Vol 1, p. xviii.
                        </note>
                    </bibl>
                </cit></p>
            <p>The key role that abstract representation of knowledge plays in the construction of
                Diderot's hypertext may be particularly instructive for current hypertext designers.
                In addition to node to node links, hypertext design may be enhanced by working
                within the context of organizational framework such as Diderot's representation of
                classes of knowledge.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
