<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">LOOKSEE: Software Tools for Image-Based Humanities
                    Computing</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Matthew</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">G.</forename>
                        <surname>Kirschenbaum</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Kentucky</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>This poster will document LOOKSEE, a Web site and discussion list for image-based
                    humanities computing &lt;<ptr target="http://www.rch.uky.edu/~mgk/looksee/"
                    />&gt; (first announced at the 1999 ACH/ALLC in Charlottesville). Its primary
                    focus is not imaging and image acquisition - areas with well-established
                    technical literatures - but rather the creation and manipulation of images as
                    structured data in digital editions, archives, and libraries.</p>
                <p>LOOKSEE is therefore intended as a community focal point for discussion and
                    development of next generation image-based humanities computing projects.
                    Although the term "image-based" humanities computing has been in circulation for
                    some time, we are now approaching a watershed: a number of pioneering projects
                    (many of them begun in the early nineties) whose promise could heretofore be
                    discussed only in speculative terms are now coming to fruition, while new
                    software tools and data standards (notably JPEG 2000) are poised to redefine the
                    way we create, access, and work with digital images. All of this activity,
                    moreover, is transpiring at a moment when there is an unprecedented level of
                    interest in visual culture and representation in the academic humanities at
                    large.</p>
                <p>At present, LOOKSEE consists of:<list>
                        <item>1. The Web materials at the URL above, collecting resources ranging
                            from computer science to medical informatics to art history, as well as
                            demos and proofs of concept to create a kind of sketchbook for
                            image-based humanities computing.</item>
                        <item>2. A listserv discussion forum. Though the list is (technically)
                            unmoderated, it is run as a structured discussion in which topics are
                            brought forward at set intervals for the participants' consideration.
                            The first discussion, held in November and December of 1999, revolved
                            around humanities applications of techniques in medical image display
                            and image processing; a second discussion (February/March 2000) will
                            feature artist Johanna Drucker's Wittgenstein's Gallery, a series of
                            over one hundred conceptual drawings constituting a working model of
                            vision, perception, and (re)cognition. (We will use Drucker's work as
                            the basis for a discussion of computer-assisted image analysis.) Later
                            discussions will be given over to producing specs for a suite of open
                            source image analysis tools and will attempt to identify the range of
                            activities that can be supported by computational tools.</item>
                        <item>3. The LOOKSEE Web site will then expand to include source code,
                            demos, and documentation.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>A poster at ALLC/ACH will allow for an opportunity to present preliminary results
                    - both technical experiments and conceptual formulations - to the international
                    humanities computing community while (just as importantly) enlisting
                    participants and establishing contacts with others working with images in
                    humanities settings.</p>
                <p>LOOKSEE is edited and directed by Matthew G. Kirschenbaum and hosted by the
                    collaboratory for Research in Computing for Humanities at the University of
                    Kentucky.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
