<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Image Analysis as a Tool for Automating the Integration
                    of Editorial Hypertext with Facsimile-based Digital Editions: the Experience of
                    the Electronic Edition of Ruskin's <title level="m">Modern Painters
                    I</title></title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Lawrence</forename>
                        <surname>Woof</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Lancaster University</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Digital Resources</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>Since 1997, the Ruskin Programme at Lancaster University have been exploring
                        various technical options in order to create a facsimile-based edition of
                        John Ruskin's <title level="m">Modern Painters</title> vol I. Editorially,
                        we were above all interested in showing the history of the writing process
                        and the context of the many revisions Ruskin made to this work over a twenty
                        year period. We wanted to allow the user to choose, and toggle between, all
                        the important editions of this work in facsimile, at the same time as
                        bringing the editorial commentary to his or her attention. We wanted to do
                        this in a way that did not impinge on the historical veracity of these
                        facsimiles; we wished to find an unobtrusive way of displaying hyperlinks
                        that did not result in a visually-compromised facsimile-based edition. At
                        the same time the feature of central importance for any potential technical
                        solution for our project was that it should allow us to automate the
                        creation of this environment. There are around 500 pages in this work and as
                        we are using five different editions (plus some manuscripts) there are over
                        2,500 images of pages, all of which will need to display editorial
                        information to the user. After looking into commercially-available software
                        options, we decided that the best solution was to build our own tools. With
                        the help of computer scientists, we have now designed a suite of tools that
                        allow us to analyse images of text in a variety of ways. We are now in a
                        position to automate the production of our edition. This paper details what
                        we required of these tools, looks at how we went about creating them,
                        demonstrates their use in a high-volume processing environment and finally
                        suggests further potential developments that could come out of this
                        research, such as the possibility of enhancing searches of digitised
                        resources that use facsimile images, and the possibility of automating
                        mark-up of spatial textual features, such as paragraphs, indented verse,
                        footnotes etc..</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The Interface</head>
                    <p>In order to preserve the authenticity of the facsimile texts, the interface
                        that suited our needs was one that did not impose hypertext links directly
                        onto these images, but rather placed the hyperlinks beside the text, on the
                        right-hand side of the screen, parallel to the pertinent word or phrase.
                        These editorial links are not displayed as text; rather, in the interests of
                        concision, an icon indicates which type of hypertext note (e.g. whether it
                        concerns People, Places or Works) is available to the user, with a
                        'mouse-over' facility to display the title of the note should there be any
                        uncertainty about the destination of these links (e.g. if there were more
                        than one of a given category of note in a given line).</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Creation of Resources</head>
                    <p>To adapt the facsimiles of the various editions of the printed book into this
                        format, we needed three types of information: first, electronic versions of
                        the texts containing mark-up indicating page and line breaks; second, the
                        desired location and type of each note (which edition, page and line it
                        belongs to) and which kind of note it is (e.g. People, Places or Works);
                        finally we need to know the pixel co-ordinates of each individual line of
                        text in each image (for 2,500 pages, that is around 100,000 sets of
                        co-ordinates).</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The electronic text</head>
                    <p>The electronic text is being produced by hand-checking OCR-generated versions
                        of specific editions. A manually-generated collation of all editions is also
                        being produced. This has been entered into a database, and this information
                        is automatically compared with the various OCR-generated electronic
                        versions. Mismatches between the various versions/collations and lists of
                        note titles are then investigated and resolved manually.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Note identification</head>
                    <p>The identification of the location and type of hypertext links is achieved
                        through codes associated with each note that contributors to the edition
                        integrate into their submissions. These codes were established before any
                        notes were written, but as the sequence of the notes is of importance within
                        the automation process, we built into the code enough flexibility to allow
                        us to add additional notes later while still maintaining the relationship
                        between the linear succession of notes and the alphanumeric sequence of the
                        codes.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Locating the pixel references within the images</head>
                    <p>We found Java the most suitable language for analysing images. First we wrote
                        a program to straighten and crop the scans automatically. Once correctly
                        aligned, the program then analyses the average colour values of horizontal
                        lines of pixels to distinguish one line of text from the white space that
                        follows it. The co-ordinates of each line of text are identified in this way
                        and recorded in a database. Other procedures extend this paradigm.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Constructing the interface</head>
                    <p>The program loads in a page of facsimile, and ascertains whether there are
                        any hyperlinking icons required for that page. By combining the information
                        from the note identification codes and the electronic texts, the program can
                        paste the appropriate icon(s) next to the appropriate lines of text and give
                        them the desired functionality. A similar process allows context-specific
                        information about collation to be pasted onto the right-hand side of the
                        facsimile.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Conclusions </head>
                    <p>These tools are fairly flexible, and could be adapted to most printed
                        material where appropriate (several projects have expressed an interest in
                        utilising some of the tools we are developing). As this kind of procedure
                        becomes increasingly straightforward, it can be envisaged that the pixel
                        co-ordinates of any line (or word, or even letter) of a text could become a
                        generally accepted aspect of mark-up for the digital scholarly edition
                        (using the &lt;MILESTONE&gt; tag, for instance, and/or extended pointers).
                        Certainly through automating and formalising the linking of the word to its
                        original physical image, it will become possible to historicise electronic
                        texts in an immediate and unambiguous way. Through integrating this analysis
                        with mark up, we can facilitate a host of bibliographic analyses of texts
                        that place 'traditional' modalities of scholarly work right at the centre of
                        humanities computing.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
