<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Griffith in Context: a Multimedia Exploration of <title
                        level="m">The Birth of a Nation</title></title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Gregory</forename>
                        <surname>VanHoosier-Carey</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Georgia Institute of Technology</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Ellen</forename>
                        <surname>Strain</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Georgia Institute of Technology</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Summary:</head>
                    <p>D.W. Griffith's film <title level="m">The Birth of a Nation</title> has the
                        distinction of being at once one of the most revered and most criticized
                        films in cinema's history. This conflicted reputation stems from the film's
                        combination of pioneering technical innovations and racial propaganda; the
                        result was a visual epic of the Civil War and Reconstruction that had
                        far-reaching cultural effects. <title level="m">The Birth of a
                            Nation</title> helped establish new cinematic conventions as well as
                        cinema's reputation as a serious artistic medium; at the same time, the film
                        incited race riots, helped rationalize legal segregation and rampant
                        lynching, and added momentum to the revitalization of the Ku Klux Klan. </p>
                    <p>Despite the significance of <title level="m">The Birth of a Nation</title> as
                        a cultural document, the film is under-utilized as a learning tool within
                        academic areas to which it is directly relevant: film studies, American
                        studies, African-American studies, and history. The factors responsible for
                        the under-representation of <title level="m">Birth</title> in undergraduate
                        humanities classrooms include the film's length, its political volatility,
                        and its unwieldiness in terms of contextualization. Our multimedia
                        application <emph rend="italics">Griffith in Context</emph>, sponsored by
                        the [American] National Endowment for the Humanities and currently under
                        development at the Georgia Institute of Technology, addresses these
                        difficulties by delivering clips from the film and contextualizing corollary
                        materials in an interactive format that makes the film's impact tangible.
                            <emph rend="italics">Griffith in Context</emph>, in fact, presents the
                        film's cultural and cinematic impact as inseparable; it was the film's
                        artistic and emotional power coupled with its racism that brought issues of
                        race and American identity to the attention of the nation.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>User-Centered Learning Through Multimedia:</head>
                    <p>Many of the instructors who have been most successful in conveying a sense of
                            <title level="m">The Birth of a Nation</title>'s subtleties and
                        significance typically use documents from the same era to historically
                        situate the film. Lauren Rabinovitz at the University of Iowa uses Library
                        of Congress materials and regional newspaper coverage to illustrate how the
                        debate around the film got imbricated into local events such as Chicago's
                        1916 mayoral election. At Stanford University, Henry Breitrose uses a 1914
                        history textbook and the African-American press's critique of the film's
                        historical portrait to demonstrate the collision of incredibly disparate
                        notions of history that occurred with <title level="m">Birth</title>'s
                        release. The challenge then is to build on the success of such strategies by
                        making such materials available to all instructors while still developing an
                        application that supports a diversity of learning goals and teaching
                        methods.</p>
                    <p>The multimedia affordances of <emph rend="italics">Griffith in Context</emph>
                        allow us to meet these challenges by incorporating a diversity of materials
                        pertinent to various undergraduate courses. The program handles the
                        challenge of contextualizing the film by providing a means for students,
                        outside of classtime, to develop their understanding of the film's cultural
                        context. After viewing the film, students can to use <emph rend="italics"
                            >Griffith in Context</emph> to review representative scenes and
                        important issues, to investigate primary and secondary research material,
                        and to experiment with editing techniques. Also, instructors can use modules
                        of the program in class to help them illustrate lecture points about
                        specific technical or contextual issues.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Organization And Interface:</head>
                    <p>The organization and interface of <emph rend="italics">Griffith in
                            Context</emph> differ in important ways from most other
                        humanities-oriented multimedia programs - differences that we believe
                        enhance student engagement with the program's humanities content. The
                        primary goal of the program is to assist students in understanding that the
                        "meaning" of this artifact is dependent on the cultural context in which it
                        was produced and viewed and to explore specific discursive aspects of this
                        context - the conversations, debates, representations, and responses - that
                        surrounded the film's creation and early performance. To facilitate this
                        process of understanding, we have organized the application around the
                        material artifact in question - the film <title level="m">The Birth of a
                            Nation</title> - rather than allowing textual commentary about the
                        subject to dictate the student's path through the application. Thus, instead
                        of dividing the program into topic areas, we have mapped out nine sections,
                        each corresponding with a three to four minute clip from the film. Within
                        each of these sections, the student accesses the information and relevant
                        documents through interaction with the film itself, using the following
                        interface elements and accompanying modules:<list>
                            <item><emph rend="bold">1. The Annotated Filmstrip:</emph> This module
                                allows a user to move back and forth through one of the nine
                                selected filmclips and closely examine a particular sequence of
                                frames; the filmstrip interface allows one to move the cursor to the
                                right or left over the filmstrip, thereby controlling both the speed
                                and direction of the filmstrip's movement. The user can stop the
                                strip on any frame and begin playing the clip from that point.
                                Surrounding the filmstrip are hypermedia links featuring a specific
                                topic tied to the frames present on the screen at that moment; each
                                of these links is associated with one of the program's four indices
                                of analysis: filmic technique, historical re-creation, racial
                                representation, and literary origins. When selected, each link
                                brings up an expert interview on the stated topic which features
                                primary documents, illustrations and photographs as well as
                                scholarly commentary in audio form.</item>
                            <item><emph rend="bold">2. The Editing Room:</emph> Some of the
                                hypermedia links associated with filmic technique bring up
                                particular exercises that allow students to experience editing
                                principles featured in the film and discussed in the expert
                                interviews. Students will use this module's unique interface to
                                re-edit Griffith's own footage and, in so doing, analyze differences
                                in visual effect and cultural reaction that such re-editing might
                                produce.</item>
                            <item><emph rend="bold">3. The Timeline:</emph> This module allows users
                                to access historical information associated with the period depicted
                                in a particular film clip. The timeline, like the annotated
                                filmstrip, provides links to documents, historical accounts, and
                                expert interviews pertaining to certain historical events depicted
                                in the film. Students can use these divergent view of events to
                                analyze Griffith's attempt to recreate history via film narrative
                                and visual representation. Additionally, students can scroll through
                                the timeline to access information about the film's production, its
                                "road show" distribution, and the reaction it prompted as it moved
                                from upscale symphony halls to smaller, inner-city segregated
                                theaters.</item>
                            <item><emph rend="bold">4. The Document Server:</emph> This module is an
                                archive of the documents, photographs, illustrations, and interviews
                                presented throughout the program. It allows users to directly access
                                these materials without going to the particular place in the program
                                where they are presented. Students can quickly locate and review
                                previously encountered contextual material. Each document or image
                                referenced in the Timeline or presented within the Annotated
                                Filmstrip module is marked with a document tag which may be used to
                                relocate the artifact using the Document Server. The Document Server
                                can be reorganized according to document name, document type,
                                author, subject area, or date of publication/distribution. As a user
                                moves the cursor over the name of a document, the cursor changes to
                                a thumbnail image of the document, allowing users to confirm their
                                selection by visual appearance.</item>
                        </list></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
