<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">A Formal Model for Lexical Information</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Nancy</forename>
                        <surname>Ide</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Vassar College</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Adam</forename>
                        <surname>Kilgarriff</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">ITRI Brighton</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Laurent</forename>
                        <surname>Romary</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">LORIA/CNRS</name>, France <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Text Encoding</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>1. Introduction</head>
                    <p>The structure and content of lexical information has been explored in
                        considerable depth in the past, primarily in order to determine a common
                        model that can serve as a basis for encoding schemas and/or database models.
                        For the most part, descriptions of lexical structure have been informed by
                        the format of printed documents (e.g., print dictionaries), which varies
                        considerably over documents produced by different publishers and for
                        different purposes, together with the requirements for instantiation in some
                        encoding format (principally, SGML). However, the constraints imposed by
                        these formats interfere with the development of a model that fully captures
                        the underlying structure of lexical information. As a result, although
                        schemas such as those provided in the TEI Guidelines exist, they do not
                        provide a satisfactorily comprehensive and unique description of lexical
                        structure and content.</p>
                    <p>We believe that in order to develop a concrete and general model of lexical
                        information, it is essential to distinguish between the formal model itself
                        and the encoding or database schema that may ultimately instantiate it. That
                        is, it is necessary to consider, in the abstract, the form and content of
                        lexical information independent of requirements and/or limitations imposed
                        its ultimate representation as an encoded or printed object. This is
                        especially important since these eventual representations will vary from one
                        application to another; in particular, lexical information may be encoded
                        not only for the purposes of publishing in print or electronic form, but
                        also for creating computational lexicons, terminology banks, etc. for use in
                        natural language processing applications. It is therefore essential to
                        develop a model that may be subsequently transformed into a variety of
                        alternative formats.</p>
                    <p>In this paper, we outline a formal model for lexical information that
                        describes (a) the structure of this information, (b) the information
                        associated with this structure at various levels, and (c) a system of
                        inheritance of information over this structure. We then show how the
                        structure may be instantiated as a document encoded using the Extended
                        Markup Language (XML). Using the transformation language provided by the
                        Extensible Style Language (XSL), we then demonstrate how the original XML
                        instantiation may be transformed into other XML documents according to any
                        desired configuration (including omission) of the elements in the original.
                        Because of its generality, we believe our model may serve as a basis for
                        representing, combining, and extracting information from dictionaries,
                        terminology banks, computational lexicons, and, more generally, a wide
                        variety of structured and semi-structured document types.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2. Overview of the theoretical model</head>
                    <p>The underlying structure of lexical information can be viewed as embedded
                        partitions of a lexicon, in which no distinction is made among embedded
                        levels. A model of lexical information can be thus described as a recursive
                        structure comprised, at each level, of one or more nodes. This structure is
                        most easily visualized as a tree, where each node may have zero or more
                        children. That is, at any level n, a node is either a leaf (i.e., with no
                        children) or can be decomposed as:<eg rend="block">T=[T1, T2, ...,
                        Tn]</eg>where each Ti is a node at level n+1.</p>
                    <p>Properties may be attached to any node in the structure with the prop
                        predicate: <eg rend="block">PROP(T,P)</eg>indicates that the property P is
                        attached to node T.</p>
                    <p>Properties are associated with nodes either by explicit assignment, or they
                        may be inherited from the parent node. The object of our model is to
                        identify the ways in which properties are propagated through levels of
                        structure. For this purpose, we consider properties to be Feature-Value
                        pairs expressed as terms of the form FEAT(F,V), where F and V are tokens
                        designating a feature (e.g., POS) and a value. In the simplest case, values
                        are atomic (e.g., NOUN) but may also consist of sets of feature-value pairs.
                        This representation is consistent with the base notation associated with
                        feature structures, a common framework for representing linguistic
                        information.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3. Propagating information across levels</head>
                    <p>We define three types of features:<list type="bulleted">
                            <item>Cumulative features that may take more than one value and may be
                                thus inherited and combined along the structure. For example, for a
                                cumulative feature DOMAIN, if the property FEAT(DOMAIN,NAVIGATION)
                                is associated with a node at level n and FEAT(DOMAIN,LAW) is
                                associated with its child at level n+1, by inheritance the node at
                                level n+1 will be assigned the property FEAT(DOMAIN,NAVIGATION +
                                LAW).</item>
                            <item>Overwriting features that take only one value at a time. This
                                implies that only one instance of an overwriting feature may appear
                                at a given node and that the corresponding properties are propagated
                                along the structure unless and until a new value is specified for
                                that feature. In such a case, the new value "overwrites" the earlier
                                one and is subsequently propagated to nodes in its subtrees.</item>
                            <item>Local features, which apply only at the node with which they are
                                associated; i.e., they are not propagated through the structure.
                                Cross-references are an example of a local feature, since they apply
                                only to the level of description with which they are directly
                                associated.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>The full paper will provide details of this formalism.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>4. Creating representations</head>
                    <p>Lexical information can be represented as a tree structure reflecting, in
                        large part, the natural hierarchical organization of entries found in
                        printed dictionaries. This hierarchical organization (e.g., division into
                        homographs, senses, sub-senses, etc.) enables information to be applied over
                        all sub-levels in the hierarchy, thus eliminating the need to re-specify
                        common information.</p>
                    <p>For example, consider the following definition from the Collins English
                        Dictionary (CED):<lb/><term>EX.1: overdress</term><lb/><gloss>overdress vb.
                            (zzzz) 1. To dress (oneself or another) too elaborately or finely. ~n.
                            (yyyy) 2. A dress that may be worn over a jumper, blouse,
                        etc.</gloss></p>
                    <p>This information can be represented in tree form as follows :<lb/><eg rend="block">[ orth
                            : overdress] [ pos : verb pron : zzzz def: To dress (oneself or another)
                            too elaborately or finely] [ pos : noun pron : yyyy def : A dress that
                            may be worn over a jumper, blouse, etc.]</eg></p>
                    <p>Each node in the tree represents a partition of the information in the entry,
                        and information is inherited over sub-trees. Thus in this example, the
                        orthographic form "overdress" appears at the top node and applies to the
                        entire entry; the entry is then partitioned into two sub-trees, for verb and
                        noun, each of which is associated with specific information about part of
                        speech, pronunciation, and definition.</p>
                    <p>The final paper will provide similar examples from dictionaries as well as
                        terminological data banks.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>5. Extracting information from the tree</head>
                    <p>We define a tree traversal as any path starting at the root of the tree and
                        following, at each node, a single child of that node. A full traversal is a
                        path from the root to any leaf; a partial traversal extends from the root to
                        any node in one of its subtrees.</p>
                    <p>As a tree is traversed, each node is associated with a set of features
                        including: (a) features associated with the node during tree creation, and
                        (b) features determined by applying the rules for propagating overwriting,
                        cumulative, and local features. Thus, at any node, all applicable
                        information is available for some unique partition of the lexical space.
                        Nodes near the top of the tree represent very broad categories of partition;
                        leaf nodes are associated with information for the most specific usage of
                        the entry.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>6. Encoding the information in XML</head>
                    <p>We define an XML encoding format for the structures described above:</p>
                    <div>
                        <head>Elements</head>
                        <p>&lt;struct&gt; represents a node in the tree. &lt;struct&gt; elements may
                            be recursively nested at any level to reflect the structure of the
                            corresponding tree. &lt;struct&gt; is the only element in the encoding
                            scheme that corresponds to the tree structure; all other elements
                            provide information associated with a specific node.</p>
                        <p>&lt;alt&gt; alternatives are bracketed in parallel &lt;alt&gt; elements,
                            which may appear within any &lt;struct&gt;. &lt;brack&gt; is a
                            general-purpose bracketing element to group associated features.</p>
                        <p>Base elements corresponding to various features, such as (for
                            dictionaries) orth, pron, hyph, syll, stress, pos, gen, case, number,
                            gram, tns, mood, usg, time, register, geo, domain, style, def, eg, etym,
                            xr, trans, and itype, (analogous to dictionary elements defined in the
                            TEI Guidelines.) &gt;</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Attributes</head>
                        <p>Attributes are used to provide information specific to the element on
                            which they appear and are not inherited in a tree traversal. </p>
                        <p>The following shows the corresponding XML encoding for "overdress":<lb/>
                            <eg>&lt;struct&gt; &lt;orth&gt;overdress&lt;/&gt; &lt;struct&gt;
                                &lt;pos&gt;verb&lt;/&gt; &lt;pron&gt;zzzz&lt;/&gt; 
                                &lt;def&gt; To dress (oneself or another) too elaborately or
                                finely&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt; &lt;struct&gt; &lt;pos&gt;noun&lt;/&gt;
                                &lt;pron&gt;yyyy&lt;/&gt; &lt;def&gt; A dress that may be worn over
                                a jumper, blouse, etc.&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt;&lt;/&gt; </eg></p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>7. Transforming the XML document</head>
                    <p>The Extensible Style Language (XSL) is a part of the XML framework that
                        enables transformation of XML documents into other XML documents. The
                        best-known use of XSL is the formatting of documents for display on web
                        browsers. However, XSL also provides a powerful transformation language that
                        can be used to convert an XML document describing lexical information by
                        selecting, rearranging, and adding information to it. Thus, a document
                        encoded according to the specifications outlined in the previous section can
                        be manipulated to serve any application that relies on part or all of its
                        contents. The current version of the XSL transformation language is
                        available at &lt;<ptr
                            target="http://metalab.unc.edu/xml/books/bible/updates/14.html"/>&gt;. </p>
                    <p>Lack of space prevents providing examples; the final paper will include
                        these.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
