<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The "Biblioteca Italiana Telematica" Project (<ref
                        target="http://cibit.unipi.it">http://cibit.unipi.it</ref>): a Progress
                    Report</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Mirko</forename>
                        <surname>Tavoni</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Pisa</name>, Italy <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Eugenio</forename>
                        <surname>Picchi</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">CNR</name>, Italy <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Computational / Corpus Linguistics</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <p>The Biblioteca Italiana Telematica (Italian Library Online) is a digital
                        library of representative texts of the Italian cultural tradition from the
                        Middle Ages to the 20th Century (literature, language, history, philosophy,
                        art, music and cultural history in its general sense). The library aims to
                        be a major research and teaching facility at the service of researchers and
                        students of Italian language and culture throughout the world.</p>
                    <p>The library has been set up by the CIBIT (Centro Interuniversitario
                        Biblioteca Telematica Italiana), which includes interdisciplinary research
                        groups in 16 Italian universities and also sees to the library's management.
                        The project's software implementation has been entrusted to Eugenio Picchi
                        of the Institute of Computational Linguistics (ILC) of the Italian National
                        Research Council (CNR).</p>
                    <p>The project is financed by the Italian Ministry of Higher Education (MURST):
                        research programmes of relevant national interest, Biblioteca Telematica
                        Italiana: the Italian cultural tradition on the Internet (1998-99), and
                        Textual memory: editions, studies and tools for computer analysis of the
                        Italian heritage (2000-2001).</p>
                    <p>The design of the Biblioteca Telematica Italiana has been quite complex due
                        to the many different functions that had to be developed for and integrated
                        within it. The purpose of the present paper is to illustrate:<list
                            type="bulleted">
                            <item>the project's objectives;</item>
                            <item>the competencies deemed to be necessary and how they have been
                                provided for;</item>
                            <item>system choices made and development procedures performed up to
                                now;</item>
                            <item>the results achieved to date; further lines of ongoing
                                development.</item>
                        </list></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Objectives</head>
                    <p>The objectives established for the project can be summarised as follows:<list
                            type="bulleted">
                            <item>to create an online reference and research tool that satisfies the
                                demands of a broad public of varying characteristics, including:
                                    <list type="bulleted">
                                    <item>the simple student or general user interested in
                                        retrieving a text, obtaining bibliographical information on
                                        it, reading and/or downloading it;</item>
                                    <item>the researcher aiming at philological and linguistic
                                        research on single texts or on sub-corpora of texts that can
                                        be defined dynamically on the basis of numerous selection
                                        parameters;</item>
                                    <item>the researcher interested in carrying out advanced
                                        philological and linguistics research on particular
                                        sub-corpora of texts marked up according to various criteria
                                        (grammar, metrics, concepts, etc.);</item>
                                </list></item>
                            <item>managing texts that include graphics and sound;</item>
                            <item>bringing the whole textbase into conformity with SGML-TEI
                                standards;</item>
                            <item>to endow the library with a true catalogue, that is, a rich
                                professional body of bibliographical information on the texts; this,
                                for two reasons:<list type="bulleted">
                                    <item>to furnish multiple access points for the selection of
                                        sub-corpora to be queried according to the most varied
                                        research demands;</item>
                                    <item>creating a catalogue able to interface with the online
                                        catalogues (OPAC) of the large libraries with the aim of
                                        integrating the data and making consultation of the
                                        Biblioteca Italiana Telematica available from such
                                        OPACs;</item>
                                    <item>securing the textbase by restricting download of texts
                                        through suitable login procedures and, possibly, download
                                        charges.</item>
                                </list></item>
                        </list></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Competencies</head>
                    <p>The project includes three main kinds of specialised expertise:<list
                            type="bulleted">
                            <item>content-related (literature, language, history, philosophy, art,
                                music, etc.), spread widely throughout the research project
                                participants;</item>
                            <item>linguistic-computational (the team directed by Eugenio Picchi at
                                the ILC-CNR);</item>
                            <item>bibliographical - library science (A. Petrucciani, University of
                                Pisa - A. Scolari, University of Genoa);</item>
                            <item>digital graphics (Studio X-Lab, Pisa).</item>
                        </list></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>System choices and development procedures</head>
                    <p>Particular attention has been paid to the quality of the services offered and
                        their optimisation. Besides offering the possibility of reading and
                        downloading texts, we have also aimed to provide online all of those
                        text-analysis tools offered in stand-alone linguistics, philology and
                        computational lexicography applications. We hold such tools to be crucial
                        features for the very concept of an online library.</p>
                    <p>The procedures for storage, analysis and querying of the chosen text corpus
                        is the DBT system (Data Base Testuale) developed at the Pisa ILC by Eugenio
                        Picchi. The main efforts in integrating the text-analysis tools with the
                        telematics library have been directed at providing the same functionality
                        and uses as the local programs over a network connection.</p>
                    <p>Procedures for reading and querying texts are by far the services demanded
                        most frequently. The utmost attention has therefore been devoted to response
                        times, the ability to serve the greatest number of users contemporaneously,
                        and to offering the maximum possible guarantee of recovery from most
                        problems that may arise. Such considerations underlie the decision to
                        develop the consultation and query system in the Java language, as it is
                        able to satisfy a wide range of requirements: it is a stable tool on both
                        the server and client ends; it makes the service accessible to all
                        Internet-capable hard- and software platforms through a suitable browser; it
                        provides state-sensitive sessions, that is, able to maintain information
                        regarding the dynamics of the varied requests made by each user. A set of
                        specialised applets is therefore able to guarantee access to the library's
                        consultation functions: searching the catalogue of the available e-texts in
                        order to select the desired text and/or sub-corpora using a whole series of
                        pre-set bibliographical selection keys; reading single texts; querying the
                        selected texts through the typical querying and text-analysis procedures of
                        DBT. The applets have been developed with the aim of maintaining the
                        greatest possible compatibility with the DBT system, to which many users are
                        accustomed.</p>
                    <p>While for the foregoing, most-used functions, our efforts were largely
                        directed at providing optimal service, for other, more specialist functions,
                        it was decided instead to favour simplicity of use, a feature furnished more
                        readily by a development and access technology other than Java. The
                        techniques adopted here are ISAPI/CGI scripts, which enable establishing
                        lighter client/server connections, with on-the-fly creation of HTML pages in
                        response to different user requests and interactions. Such scripting has
                        been applied to the querying of lemmatised texts, that is, texts for which
                        morpho-syntactic analysis and classification have been performed beforehand.
                        Queries can thereby be launched also on the para-textual data containing a
                        wide range of information on each word, such as: its lemma, the lemma's
                        grammatical classification, the form's morpho-syntactic classification. Such
                        a wealth of information stored in a text allows for qualitatively more
                        precise and far more productive search functionality.</p>
                    <p>Particular tools for the online querying of texts with metric markers have
                        been developed using MS-Access. In anticipation of the forthcoming Java or
                        ISAPI applications necessary to make such tools directly available online,
                        they have for the moment been implemented using the Windows NT Terminal
                        Edition that, through a special plug-in, allows browser access to the
                        server-side OS through an Internet connection.</p>
                    <p>Finally, by integrating the contributions of the different specialists
                        outlined in the preceding section, we have set up the Biblioteca Telematica
                        Italiana Web site (<ptr target="http://cibit.unipi.it"/>), within which easy
                        access to the different functions has been organised ergonomically from four
                        fundamental points of entry: Reading, Catalogue, Collections and Advanced
                        Searches.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Results</head>
                    <p>The textbase currently online (Dec. 1999) contains about 900 texts. The
                        Biblioteca Italiana Telematica currently offers the following services
                        through the Internet:<list type="bulleted">
                            <item>consulting the general catalogue through different cross-indexed
                                access points (Author, Prose/Poetry, Literary genre, Language,
                                Chronology); these stem from a relational database of records
                                containing bibliographical information concerning the text itself,
                                its reference edition and its electronic edition;</item>
                            <item>consultation of the graphics catalogue;</item>
                            <item>accessing the texts and relative text-attributes, iconographic and
                                sound add-ons (through the DBT Java applet described above);</item>
                            <item>querying individual texts with advanced computational-linguistics
                                search functions (through the DBT Java applet);</item>
                            <item>querying the entire corpus or selected subsets (through the DBT
                                Java applet);</item>
                            <item>querying a sub-corpus (Dante Alighieri's vernacular and Latin
                                works) with grammatical markers (through the lemmatised ISAPI/CGI
                                DBT application described above);</item>
                            <item>querying a sub-corpus (medieval-Renaissance lyric poetry) with
                                metric markers (through the Windows NT Terminal Edition described
                                above);</item>
                            <item>downloading texts in varied formats, including SGML/TEI, upon
                                completion of suitable identification and login procedures.</item>
                        </list></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Further lines of development</head>
                    <p>
                        <list type="bulleted">
                            <item>Development of tools for online query of texts with metric markers
                                (corpus of medieval-Renaissance lyric poetry), as well as musical
                                texts (corpus of 17th century Italian poetry for music).</item>
                            <item>Enhancing the search system to allow consultation of
                                bibliographical databanks according to structured DBT
                                procedures.</item>
                            <item>Implementing a prototype able to natively process SGML/XML files,
                                particularly in TEI format (Text Encoding Initiative).</item>
                            <item>Testing procedures for interaction between, on the one hand,
                                library catalogues and other bibliographical databanks based on the
                                UNIMARC international standard and, on the other, digital libraries
                                using forthcoming standards for network delivery (meta-data,
                                particularly Dublin Core). Inter-communication and the greatest
                                possible integration between the two environments is in fact
                                essential to avoid a rift between the two major sources of publicly
                                available information.</item>
                            <item>Implementation of a terminological repository containing thesaurus
                                relationships and the relative procedures for conversion to and from
                                the UNIMARC and Dublin Core standards.</item>
                            <item>Testing procedures for importing and exporting standard UNIMARC
                                format data to and from the Biblioteca Italiana Telematica
                                catalogue. This, with the aim of storing the electronic resources of
                                the Biblioteca Italiana Telematica within various library OPACs,
                                starting with those of the universities co-operating in the
                                project.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
