<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Border Crossing: Engineers, Papyrologists, and the
                    Graphical Use Interface</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Melissa</forename>
                        <surname>Terras</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Oxford University</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Digital Resources</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The discovery of the writing and stylus tablets from Vindolanda, a Roman Fort
                    built in the late 80s AD near Hadrian's Wall at modern day Chesterholm, has
                    provided a unique resource regarding the Roman occupation of northern Britain
                    and the use and development of Latin around the turn of the first century AD.
                    However, although papyrologists have been able to transcribe and translate most
                    of the writing tablets, the meaning of the majority of the stylus tablets
                    remains obscure. These small wooden plaques with a hollow recess which was once
                    filled with wax and written on by means of a metal stylus are well preserved;
                    however, the wax has deteriorated leaving a wooden surface with small strokes
                    where the stylus pen has occasionally breached the wax covering. Making sense of
                    such minute indentations by eye alone has proved impossible for papyrologists,
                    and the problem is compounded by the fact that many tablets were reused again
                    and again leaving the remains of many texts on the damaged surfaces.</p>
                <p>An EPSRC funded project at the Department of Engineering Science, University of
                    Oxford, was initiated two years ago to analyse these tablets and develop new
                    image processing techniques to retrieve information from small incisions in
                    damaged surfaces (the techniques developed being applicable to a wide variety of
                    engineering problems). Some headway has been made using wavelet filtering to
                    remove woodgrain in images of the stylus tablets, and developing and
                    appropriating Phase Congruency and Shadow Stereo techniques to identify
                    candidate writing strokes. However, until some interface is put into place
                    between these engineering techniques and the papyrologist, the stylus tablets'
                    texts will not become decipherable because of the complex nature of the
                    papyrology process and the difficulties encountered in expecting a
                    non-mathematical user to utilise such algorithms.</p>
                <p>This paper gives a brief background to the project, before discussing the steps
                    taken and problems encountered whilst developing the computer application and
                    user interface for this system. Focussing on the interaction between historians,
                    papyrologists and the application developer, and the design of the graphical
                    user interface, the paper discusses the benefits and problems surrounding such a
                    multi-disciplinary project.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
