<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Austrian Academy Corpus - Doing literary markup by
                    means of XML</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Karlheinz</forename>
                        <surname>Moerth</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Austrian Academy of Sciences</name>, Austria <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Hanno</forename>
                        <surname>Biber</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Austrian Academy of Sciences</name>, Austria <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The poster we intend to present is supposed to give some details concerning the
                    pilot phase of the newly founded Austrian Academy Corpus (AAC). The AAC is a
                    project which has been started with the perspective of building up a digital
                    corpus tailored to the particular needs of scholars doing research in the field
                    of literary studies. The build-up of electronic text collections has been the
                    domain of linguists so far. Although literary texts are becoming available in
                    ever-increasing numbers, many of these products originated from linguistic
                    endeavours to gather data for lexicographic or learners' purposes. Literary
                    scholars have rather neglected the whole issue. Most of the existing digital
                    literary resources are poorly edited and serve for little more than simplistic
                    word searches. As the exigencies of work on literary texts differ considerably
                    from those of linguistic studies the AAC has been trying to work towards
                    solutions that meet the necessities of the literary domain. The AAC proceeds in
                    its work from the basis of digital data which have been collected at the
                    Austrian Academy of Sciences during the last few years. At that time the
                    department's focus was placed on literary sources which were classified as
                    functional literary text types, i.e. magazines, diaries, sermons, speeches,
                    letters, obituaries and the like. Thus the materials in the corpus display
                    considerable variety as to contents and structure. The data was accumulated
                    primarily for text-lexicographic purposes preparing a phraseological dictionary
                    which was published in 1999. This text-dictionary was based on a literary
                    satirical magazine which appeared for the first time in 1899 in fin-de-siecle
                    Vienna and was published until 1936. This magazine, 'Die Fackel', which was very
                    popular among intellectuals in its time, is still of utmost interest to scholars
                    of German literature trying to understand this crucial period of history. The
                    electronic text of 'Die Fackel' was generated in a first run by means of rather
                    unsophisticated OCR, a process which was completed several years ago. During the
                    compilation of the above-mentioned text-dictionary the quality of this
                    electronic text was improved in several runs of proofreading and adding basic
                    markup which was developed specifically for this purpose. Only very few tags
                    were applied, indicating for example the position of images or identifying
                    special characters, which were not supported by the standard code-pages of the
                    user interface. The texts being digitised at the moment (primarily historical
                    magazines) undergo several stages of processing, first being scanned and made
                    readable by means of OCR, then being corrected several times. The application of
                    markup is the last step in this process. Formatting information of the digitised
                    texts is in the first instance conserved in file formats such as RTF or
                    utilizing standardized style sheets which yield quite reasonable results. With
                    the increasing availability of more advanced text encoding techniques the
                    working group of the AAC started to think about a more general approach to cope
                    with the manifold problems of integrating text and text-related secondary data.
                    We had to look for a markup scheme which allowed for labelling different types
                    of data within one coherent markup system. In their endeavours to find
                    appropriate ways of describing the structure of texts, linking up data and
                    facilitating structured searches the working group of the AAC started doing
                    experiments applying XML (Extensible Markup Language) to their data. The issue
                    of XML, especially the question of XML versus SGML, has been touched upon
                    repeatedly in Humanities computing. XML, as the youngest descendant of the
                    SGML/HTML family, is a subset of SGML and can be viewed as the logic further
                    development of SGML. As a general rule one can assume that SGML-encoded data can
                    easily be transformed into XML-data, to a certain extent even the other way
                    round. The XML related experiments at our department started already in the
                    early stages of XML's appearance on the scene, i.e. in 1998. As yet only parts
                    of the corpora of the AAC have been provided with XML-conforming markup as we
                    are still trying to fathom out the potential benefits of XML for our work. Basic
                    markup (start and end of pages, line breaks), character encoding as well as
                    concatination of hyphenated words was carried out by means of a special
                    conversion engine. There are many different ways to perform such
                    transformations. Many would prefer to accomplish such a task making use of
                    scripting languages such as Perl which, of course, can be a quite practicable
                    and efficient way to do it. We tried to use graphical user interfaces from the
                    very beginning of our work in order to ensure the constant monitoring and
                    controlling of the transformation processes. Therefore we developed our tools
                    using the programming language Delphi, a RAD tool which helped to cut developing
                    time. The absence of any XML compliant browser software in the early phase
                    forced us to seek a solution of our own and consequently to develop a graphical
                    interface to bring our data on screen and display them in a readable form. These
                    experiments showed that the fundamentally strict structure of XML documents
                    makes parsing pretty straightforward. Even in the absence of a definitive set of
                    tags XML-files are still processible without parsing an attached DTD (Document
                    Type Definition). As the texts we are working on contain passages in various
                    languages and characters XML's compliance with the Unicode Standard proved to be
                    extremely helpful. Unicode has brought about the unification of a huge number of
                    diverging standards and will in the future ensure the exchangeability and
                    interoperability of all sorts of textual data. XML does not only allow generic,
                    highly specialised encoding, but also enables the flawless exchange of data
                    among different systems.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
