<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Automatic Text Aligning in a Parallel Text
                    Corpus</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Mikhail</forename>
                        <surname>Mikhailov</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Tampere</name>, Finland <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <p>Parallel text corpora supply researchers with very important data for
                        multilingual lexicography and translation studies as well as for language
                        typology. The crucial problem in compiling parallel corpora is aligning the
                        texts. Manual aligning is impossible for large corpora, so ways of automatic
                        aligning are to be found. The aim of the research project at the University
                        of Tampere is to compile a Russian-Finnish parallel corpus and to develop
                        the software for automatic aligning of the Russian and Finnish subcorpora.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>1. General</head>
                    <p>Since the 60s and 70s text corpora development has become much easier.
                        Electronic texts in a large variety of languages can be obtained on the
                        Internet; scanning and OCR technologies have been much improved during the
                        last ten years. Associations like TELRI and ELRA are helping linguists from
                        different countries to join their efforts in collecting language resources
                        in electronic form. The number of corpus-based projects is rapidly growing
                        while the number of scholars that are skeptical about this innovation is
                        reducing at the same speed. In most lexicographic projects text corpora are
                        being used. Applied linguistic research is another field where text corpora
                        are welcome as an inexhaustible source of empirical information, polygon for
                        testing various linguistic tools - spell-checkers, OCRs, machine translation
                        systems, NLP systems etc. At the same time, the corpora are quite useful for
                        theoretical, 'armchair linguistics' [Fillmore, 1992] as well. Nowadays text
                        corpora are quite widely used for compiling monolingual dictionaries.
                        Nevertheless it is still a problem to use text corpora in bilingual
                        lexicography. Of course it is possible to use two text corpora but it would
                        have been more useful to have parallel texts and tools for looking up words
                        and their translations as well as parallel contexts. Furthermore, the use of
                        bilingual and multilingual text corpora is by no means limited to
                        multilingual lexicography.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2. The Project</head>
                    <p>The aim of the research project running at the Department of Translation
                        Studies of the University of Tampere is to collect a bilingual corpus of
                        parallel texts (Russian and Finnish). The texts will be Russian classical or
                        fiction texts and their translations into Finnish. The corpus will not be
                        very big (4-5 million running words) but it will be equipped with efficient
                        search tools for analysis of parallel texts. At present we have a
                        substantial corpus of Russian prose (4.5 million words) and have started to
                        collect the translations of Russian texts into Finnish and to modify the
                        software for running the parallel text corpus. We have equipped the above
                        mentioned text corpus of Russian prose with certain tools for building word
                        lists and concordances. The present task is to collect Russian fiction texts
                        and their translations into Finnish. As a result we shall have authentic
                        Russian texts (normal Russian language) and Finnish texts influenced by the
                        Russian original. It is quite evident that the language of translations is
                        different from the original prose: the translator is under the influence of
                        the language from which he/she is translating (that is why when I was a
                        student our professors told us we should not use examples from translations
                        for our research). Grammar forms, syntactic patterns, word frequencies in
                        the Russian subcorpus will be more or less representative for the standard
                        Russian language. This will not be so for the Finnish subcorpus. Grammar,
                        sentence structure, and vocabulary of the translations are influenced by the
                        original text. This means that the Corpus will be 'asymmetrical', centered
                        on the Russian language.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3. Maintenance of the Corpus</head>
                    <p>The basic idea is to separate the texts from the tags. Usually the corpus
                        software is 'anti-intellectual' - all those programs can do is to find
                        strings of characters, show them or perform calculations on them. The
                        corpora developers therefore have to make explicit all relevant information,
                        i.e. to tag the texts. In our Corpus the texts are 'clean'. They are stored
                        as ordinary text files. All relevant information is registered in the
                        Microsoft Access database. The database is used for data processing as well.
                        The user can get concordances for specified word(s) or word combination(s).
                        He/she can also use the word list for query-making. It is quite easy to
                        specify context size (in sentences) and comparison for the main and second
                        search key (whole word / start of word / end of word / any part of word) as
                        well as the second search key position (same sentence / next word). The
                        approach for corpus compiling we use has many reserves - we are planning to
                        add to the program lemmatizing routines which will make it possible to build
                        another index - a grammatical one. This will make searching for grammar
                        forms also possible.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>4. Parallel Concordancing</head>
                    <p>However, the most difficult and most interesting part of the project will be
                        to find out whether automated parallel concordancing is possible. The
                        starting point was the idea that although the translator changes a lot in
                        the translation in comparison to the original text - he may join or split
                        the sentences, change clauses into phrases, omit or add certain words, use
                        broader or narrower equivalents - still he translates something literally.
                        Certain words cannot be skipped in the translation; otherwise we shall have
                        an entirely new text. The words that in most cases are translated literally
                        we shall call keywords. So, we presume that if equivalents for more than
                        half of keywords of extract A from the original were found in extract B of
                        the same size from the translation, extract B is likely to be the
                        translation of extract A. What word classes shall be keywords? Of course we
                        have to exclude prepositions, conjunctions, pronouns, etc. We also have to
                        exclude words with very broad meanings (e.g. idti - 'to go'). Some words are
                        parts of idioms and therefore unpredictable in translations (bog - 'god',
                        tchert - 'devil'). From what is left we also have to exclude words having
                        high-frequency homonyms. E.g. we cannot include the Russian word 'petchen' -
                        'liver' - in the Russian-Finnish glossary of keywords because the Finnish
                        equivalent for this word is 'maksa' which in many forms is homonymous with
                        the verb 'maksaa' - 'to pay'. Another criterion is word frequency.
                        Frequently used words may cause problems because they are everywhere. Words
                        that occur only once also have to be excluded. Most useful for our research
                        are words that have a frequency in the range of 2 to 6 occurrences. This is
                        about 35% of the words in the analyzed text (Dostoyevski, <title level="m"
                            >Notes from the cellar</title>). Most of these words and some of the
                        more frequently used words will be included in the list of keywords.
                        Together with Finnish dictionary equivalents they form the core of the
                        system.</p>
                    <p>The system works as follows: <list>
                            <item>1) Extract A from the original is split into words.</item>
                            <item>2) Keywords are selected; weight of the sample is
                                calculated.</item>
                            <item>3) Finnish equivalents B1, B2, ... Bn for the keywords are looked
                                up.</item>
                            <item>4) Contexts for every keyword are looked up and checked by other
                                keywords.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>For each context the weight is calculated. If the weight of the context Bx is
                        more than 60% of the weight of the extract A, Bx is considered a translation
                        of A and presented to the user. If our hypothesis is true, the program will
                        be able to find parallel places if a) the context is long enough (we cannot
                        say at present what 'long enough' means); b) enough keywords were found; c)
                        the translation is close enough to the original.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>5. Applications of the Parallel Text Corpus</head>
                    <p>The parallel text corpus would be very useful in the fields of comparative
                        studies, translation studies, and bilingual lexicography. It would make it
                        possible to find how the word is actually translated, which is sometimes
                        quite different from what is expected according to the dictionaries. It will
                        be easy to find translations of quotations. It would also be quite possible
                        to monitor usage of certain grammatical forms or constructions and ways of
                        translating them into another language.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Fillmore</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">'Corpus linguistics' vs. 'Computer-aided armchair
                                linguistics'</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Directions in Corpus Linguistics, Stockholm</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1992">1992</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">Parallel Corpora</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.ruf.rice.edu/~barlow/para.html"
                            />&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Rundell</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">The corpus of the future, and the future of the
                                corpus</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m"/>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.ruf.rice.edu/~barlow/futcrp.html"
                            />&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">j.</forename>
                                    <surname>Svartvik</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Corpus linguistics comes of age</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Directions in Corpus Linguistics, Stockholm</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1992">1992</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
