<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">A Case Study of an Evaluation Questionnaire Concerning
                    the Integration of a Hypermedia Project in University Courses</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Lilane</forename>
                        <surname>Gallet-Blanchard</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Université de Paris-Sorbonne</name>, Paris <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Marie-Madeleine</forename>
                        <surname>Martinet</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Université de Paris-Sorbonne</name>, Paris <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Summary</head>
                    <p>The presentation will develop the results of a questionnaire survey following
                        the introduction of hypermedia products in cultural history and humanities
                        computing courses. This experiment concerns the use of a hypermedia CD-ROM
                        on Georgian Cities (developed by the Research Centre 'Cultures Anglophones
                        et Technologies de l' Information' CATI at the Université de
                        Paris-Sorbonne), a prototype of which was demonstrated in a paper at
                        ACH-ALLC 1999; in the academic year 1999-2000 it is used in teaching in four
                        universities, Paris-Sorbonne, Nanterre, Lille and Mulhouse, both in classes
                        on eighteenth-century cultural history and on humanities computing.
                        Concurrently, a website was created, meant to serve as supporting material
                        for the courses, containing chapters presenting the CD-ROM, sections on
                        documentation methods and gateways to relevant websites on the 18th century
                        (in particular 'virtual cities' sites developed by the Universities of Bath
                        and Missouri), on literary resources, and on architectural history. This was
                        part of a strategy to develop the teaching of documentation methods and
                        electronic resources in humanities courses, with which the research centre
                        was entrusted.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Presentation</head>
                    <p>The presentation will consist of a demonstration of the products based on the
                        analysis of the questionnaires, highlighting the sections which were shown
                        by this survey to be significant in terms of learner use of media.
                        Illustrative material such as syllabus outlines, students' worksheets and
                        documents used concurrently will be available, as well as samples of website
                        pages.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The survey</head>
                    <p>It was based on four questionnaires, two for teachers and two for students,
                        in each case one pre-program and one post-program. The questionnaires were
                        worked out on the models recommended by the Oxford CTI (Porter) and by the
                        Open University's Programme on Learner Use of Media (PLUM). The CTI
                        questionnaire was used especially for its structure relating the general
                        background of humanities computing courses and the details of the current
                        experiment, and for its format. The PLUM recommendations which were
                        particularly relevant were those on alternative conditions of use in the
                        instructional context, and on the interaction between interface and
                        contents, assessing improvements both in approach and in knowledge. The
                        points emphasized in the present questionnaires focused on two main types of
                        questions: 1) the integration of IT resources in the syllabus (Deegan) -
                        apart from the present CD-ROM, and also including it 2) interface/navigation
                        procedures for the present CD-ROM, and their relation with the contents,
                        focusing on the potential of multimedia presentation for the development of
                        interdisciplinary approaches (Zuern). The survey also included monitoring
                        reports by the teachers, where they recorded the stages in the students' use
                        of the CD-ROM, and their methods for resorting to other materials used in
                        conjunction (for instance comparison with websites or paper documents,
                        note-taking).</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The results</head>
                    <list type="bulleted">
                        <item><emph rend="bold">areas selected by students:</emph> two main types of
                            navigation paths emerged.<list type="bulleted">
                                <item>A large number of students focused on general chapters on
                                    demography or education; they had a particular project as a
                                    purpose and were using this program as a resource in which to
                                    look for explanations on the topic. A graduate student doing
                                    research on townscape painting in the 18th century consulted the
                                    CD-ROM to find documents on the subject and new approaches to
                                    it, taking notes; she was also interested in finding methods of
                                    presentation for visual questions which could hardly be conveyed
                                    in other media (modelling of changing shadow effects for
                                    instance).</item>
                                <item>Others selected topographical navigation in one of the cities.
                                    They were seeking multidisciplinary contextualisation to their
                                    subject studies (for instance in literature - e.g. Smollett - or
                                    in social history). Their comments were that it brought to life
                                    subjects which so far they had not visualized so clearly.</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>
                            <emph rend="bold">renewal of approach</emph>
                            <list type="bulleted">
                                <item>IT / subject: This experiment was initially integrated into
                                    the current syllabus and tasks, to which it was meant to provide
                                    an extra dimension. Its more innovative benefits were that it
                                    opened vistas on new approaches to the subject, thus encouraging
                                    critical thinking about the relative interest of various
                                    methodologies (Talarico). It helped students to formulate such
                                    questions on the definition of subject approaches and make a
                                    more critical use of IT.</item>
                                <item>students' role: Their responses differed according to their
                                    previous experience of IT. The classes caused students' interest
                                    in the teachers' preparation work for the documents used in
                                    class (an attitude which is not so explicit for traditional
                                    methods of teaching). In the sections of the courses where the
                                    teachers (who do the authoring work) demonstrated how to
                                    construct a program like the one they had just seen as a
                                    finished product, they were interested in being taken behind the
                                    scenes, especially if they had previous experience of authoring
                                    programs themselves (for instance doing a personal website); it
                                    enabled them to compare their practice with the teacher's. In
                                    that case, having themselves experienced the difficulties of
                                    scripting, they were surprised to see that it worked first time
                                    (which seemed normal to those who have no experience of
                                    computers). It encourages students to relate their own
                                    extracurricular interests to their studies. Those who so far had
                                    used IT started realising that it was not beyond reach since
                                    they could see it done under their eyes. They were also asked to
                                    do follow-up work, finding relevant sites on the Internet, which
                                    helped them to practise navigation and to formulate queries (use
                                    of keywords, Boolean operators, interpretation of the results in
                                    terms of 'noise' and 'silence' where necessary). Generally
                                    speaking, students appreciated questions about possible
                                    improvements to the CD-ROM, and listed corrections they
                                    suggested, which gave them an active role.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <emph rend="italics">conclusions for the teaching methods</emph>
                            <list type="bulleted">
                                <item>It helps teachers identify issues in the pedagogical use of
                                    IT. The faculty members involved in the project took part in it
                                    because it enabled them to add a variety of approaches to the
                                    subject. They could compare the guided use of such resources -
                                    exploration according to a path selected by the teacher - and
                                    the individual use by students. In addition, other colleagues
                                    who taught courses on related subjects - e.g. a literature
                                    course on Smollett and Jane Austen - asked for a demonstration
                                    to be given to their class, both as background information on
                                    Georgian Bath and for the extracts of film adaptations of the
                                    novels. It was a means to introduce such material to faculty
                                    members who had not used it so far.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The analysis of the survey</head>
                    <p>A detailed analysis of the survey will show the results sorted according to
                        several criteria, e.g. level of studies, or subject. It will also correlate
                        the answers according to previous experience of IT in the curriculum.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Marilyn</forename>
                                    <surname>Deegan</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">From innovation to integration</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Villes visite virtuelle</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>PUP</publisher>
                                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">7-19</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">PLUM</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://iet.open.ac.uk/Plum/evaluation/contents.html"
                            />&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Sarah</forename>
                                    <surname>Porter</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Lisa</forename>
                                    <surname>McRory</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Digital Text in Humanities Teaching</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Lou</forename>
                                    <surname>Burnard</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Marilyn</forename>
                                    <surname>Deegan</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Harold</forename>
                                    <surname>Short</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">The Digital Demotic: A Selection of Papers from Digital
                                Ressources in the Humanities 1997</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>King's College, Office for Humanities
                                    Communication</publisher>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Kathryn</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                        >Marie</forename><surname>Talarico</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Cyberspace without Tears: Fundamental Approaches to the
                                Uses of Technology in the Classroom</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">14</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">199-210</biblScope>
                                <date when="1999">June 1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">John</forename>
                                    <surname>Zuern</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Timelines OnLine: Hypermedia and Information
                                Architecture in the Representation of Intellectual History</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">Paper at ACH-ALLC, University of Virginia, 12 June
                                1999</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
