<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">"Hyperlectures": Teaching Postmodern Culture on the
                    Web</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Licia</forename>
                        <surname>Calvi</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Trinity College Dublin</name>, Eire <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>One of the major didactic difficulties, regardless of the kind of knowledge that
                    must be learnt, seems to be that of ensuring a correct "transfer" of information
                    from the teacher to the learner. This "transfer", as Plato already illustrated,
                    may be problematic because of what happens in the "head" of the learner,
                    something which ultimately influences what the learner herself can understand -
                    see also (Ambroso 1999). In order to guarantee a successful information
                    transfer, it is therefore necessary that the teacher adopts a series of
                    strategies taking into account how information is processed by learners.
                    Cognitive science may help in this respect to shed a new light on how
                    information is received, processed, stored and ultimately retrieved when facing
                    real-life situations - see, for instance, (Dix et al. 1993). From these
                    characteristics, it is indeed possible to draw different learner profiles,
                    different learning models.</p>
                <p>Traditionally, according to van der Veer (1990), the individual characteristics
                    that HCI (Human-Computer Interaction) takes into account while conceiving
                    interfaces and user-friendly systems include:<list>
                        <item>1. learners' personality, mainly in terms of introvert or extrovert
                            behaviour;</item>
                        <item>2. the cognitive styles that students follow while learning, either a
                            verbal or a visual style;</item>
                        <item>3. the strategies they exploit for learning, namely a heuristic or
                            systemic procedure;</item>
                        <item>4. finally, the structures they use to represent the knowledge they
                            have acquired. These structures ultimately reflect the different
                            long-term memory modalities employed to process information, i.e.,
                            semantic or episodic structures.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Once this assumption is accepted, the teacher must satisfy all these requirements
                    in order to be able to support the learner in gaining the most efficient
                    learning possible. IT (Information Technologies) take part in this dialogue by
                    helping the teacher to assume perfectly her role of "learning facilitator
                    according to the learner's pace and modalities" (Ambroso 1999).</p>
                <p>It is with this intention in mind that we have started to develop a series of
                    hyperlectures on postmodern culture and philosophy which are completely taught
                    online. The term "hyperlectures" was originally coined by Frode Ulvund (1997) to
                    indicate "a multimedia lecture transferred on the internet" and later rephrased
                    by Rob van Craenenburg (forthcoming) in his series of online lectures on
                    culture. In the context of this presentation, it will be used to indicate a
                    courseware that has two characteristics: conceptually, it is adaptive, and
                    structurally, it is layered (see below). These hyperlectures originate from the
                    two separate courses on "Interactive Narrative" and on "Technology and Culture"
                    which were taught last year within the MSc in Multimedia Systems at TCD. As
                    such, they have a dual objective: on the one hand, they intend to show the
                    development of hyperfiction, i.e., of electronic fiction, from its early
                    attempts still in a paper-based medium to the current computer-based works.
                    According to some scholars (see, for instance Landow 1997), there is indeed a
                    strict relationship between the theory of literature and the theory of
                    hypertext: the former theorises the open work, that the latter ultimately
                    embodies and tests. In this respect, understanding hyperfiction implies a
                    definition of both the medium hypertext and the more theoretical narrative
                    principles implicit in any text: story formation, the notion of the plot, the
                    role of both author and reader, the mutual actions they are required to play. On
                    the other hand, since hyperfiction has emerged and imposed itself in recent
                    years, it becomes important to understand the dominant way of representing and
                    of thinking of reality, the present major philosophical discourse, what is
                    referred to as postmodernism.</p>
                <p>The hyperlectures on postmodern culture build on the expertise acquired through
                    two previous experiences at developing Internet-based courseware: they include
                    the development of an adaptive courseware to teach hypertext to MSc students in
                    Computer Science, which is still in use and has been used by several
                    universities in Europe, and an adaptive courseware to teach business Italian to
                    MA students in Romance Philology, which has only been developed for experimental
                    reasons. Whereas the former experience focused on the setting up of a
                    methodology for knowledge acquisition on the Web that progressively keeps into
                    account every student's learning proficiency within the field of a mainly
                    technology-oriented education (Calvi and De Bra 1997), the other project
                    examined the validity of this same framework in a more linguistic domain when
                    combining the "situated" teaching of Italian with the acquisition of a
                    domain-specific knowledge like the Italian present economic reality (Calvi in
                    press). What these Web-based courses have in common is the approach that was
                    used in designing and developing them, i.e., the need to adapt to users. User's
                    adaptivity and customisation is a sort of number 0 rule to make an efficient use
                    of the Web and to ensure that results will be significant in terms of learning.
                    This also means being able to cope with the problems raised by knowledge
                    globalisation and cultural differences. And still, preserving one's specific
                    characteristics in the view of the safeguard of minority languages and cultural
                    heritage that has become so prominent in EU policies. In the investigation of
                    the educational possibilities of hypertext for learning, these issues have
                    become relevant (see, for example, (Brusilovsky 1996):<list>
                        <item>1. the necessity to adapt information to users, i.e., to provide
                            information according to users' learning needs, level of competence
                            achieved thus far, goals, and preferences, in order to facilitate
                            learning (a user-tailored approach to information presentation);</item>
                        <item>2. the complementary requirement of fostering both textual and
                            conceptual coherence in structuring information;</item>
                        <item>3. the subsequent need to limit, if not to avoid completely, cognitive
                            overload while users process information by appropriately determining
                            the sequences of nodes and links to be consequently shown to
                            users.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>It is a sort of "guided pulling" (Perrin 1998), where it is up to the learner to
                    choose which further step to take in the acquisition process in an intimately
                    autonomous way because the system does not hinder in any way his/her exploratory
                    behaviour. The process of progressively unveiling links does not indeed
                    correspond to the common notion of "guided tours", although it is always the
                    teacher/designer who determines not only how the content material can be
                    presented to students, but also how it can be structured and how its concepts
                    can be interconnected to one another.</p>
                <p>The postmodern course is now being followed by two sorts of students: students
                    enrolled in a Master's programme in Multimedia Systems at TCD, who have a very
                    heterogeneous academic background (from engineering to biology, from
                    communication studies to sculpture and painting), although the master is taught
                    within the Computer Science department; and students enrolled in a Master
                    programme in Romance Philology at the University of Antwerp, who have therefore
                    a mainly humanistic background. By the end of the course (in a couple of months,
                    therefore well before the conference is scheduled) data about their interaction
                    modalities with be systems will become available for analysis. This will allow
                    us to verify if the design guidelines that have been chosen have matched onto
                    actual use.</p>
                <p>During the presentation we will describe in details the hyperlectures from the
                    point of view of both its design rationale and objectives and will relate it to
                    the previously acquired experiences mentioned above in order to outline the
                    methodological and pedagogical implications behind the use of hypertext in
                    education.</p>
                <p>The course can be found at the URL &lt;<ptr
                        target="http://wwwis.win.tue.nl/~calvi/pmw"/>&gt;.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Ambroso</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Nuovi orientamenti nella didattica dell'italiano come
                                L2</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Proceedings of the conference La didattica
                                dell'italiano lingua straniera oggi. Realtà e prospettive</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>VUB Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Brusilovsky</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Methods and Techniques of Adaptive Hypermedia</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">User Modeling and User-Adapted Interaction</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">6</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">2-3</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">87-129</biblScope>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Calvi</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Business Italian via a Proficiency-Adapted CALL
                                System</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor><name><forename type="first">D.</forename><forename
                                        type="middle"
                                    >P.</forename></name><surname>O'Baoill</surname></editor>
                            <title level="j">Special Issue of TEANGA</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">18</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp"/>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>(In press)</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Calvi</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">P.</forename><surname>De
                                        Bra</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">A Proficiency-Adapted Framework for Information
                                Browsing and Filtering in Educational Hypermedia Systems</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">International Journal of User Modelling and
                                User-Adapted Interactions</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">7</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">257-277</biblScope>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Dix</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Finlay</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Abowd</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Beale</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Human-Computer Interaction</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>Prentice Hall</publisher>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Landow</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Hypertext 2.0. The Convergence of Contemporary Critical
                                Theory and Technology</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Perrin</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">What Cognitive Science Tells us About the Use of New
                                Technologies</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">Paper presented at the Conference Languages for
                                Specific Purposes and Academic Purposes--Integrating Theory into
                                Practice, Dublin, 6-8 March 1998</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>van Craenenburg</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Teaching Culture in a multi-linear Environment</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>Intellect Books</publisher>
                                <date>(forthcoming)</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">C.</forename>
                                    <surname>van der Veer</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Human-Computer Interaction. Learning, Individual
                                Differences, and Design Recommendations</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Alblasserdam</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Offsetdrukkerij Haveka B.V.</publisher>
                                <date when="1990">1990</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">F.</forename>
                                    <surname>Ulvund</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Hyperlectures - Teaching on Demand</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">Paper originally presented at Cincinnati Symposium on
                                Computers and History, University of Cincinnati, Cincinnati, OH, May
                                2-3 1997 and at the XIIth International Conference of the AHC in
                                Glasgow, UK, June 30 - July 3 1997</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>online reference</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
