<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="panel">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Supporting Digital Scholarship: a Project Funded by the
                    Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">John</forename>
                        <surname>Unsworth</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Virginia</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Worthy</forename>
                        <surname>Martin</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Virginia</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Thornton</forename>
                        <surname>Staple</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Virginia</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Ken</forename>
                        <surname>Price</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Virginia</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Summary:</head>
                    <p>To date, digital library efforts have focused on library-based production of
                        digital primary resources. This project will, for the first time, address
                        second-generation digital library problems, where the focus is on scholarly
                        analysis, reprocessing, and the creation of digital primary resources. With
                        $1m in support from the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation over three years
                        (2000-2002), the University of Virginia's Institute for Advanced Technology
                        in the Humanities (IATH) and the University of Virginia Libraries' Digital
                        Library Research and Development Group will address three closely related
                        problems: <list>
                            <item>1. scholarly use of digital primary resources;</item>
                            <item>2. library adoption of "born-digital" scholarly research;
                                and</item>
                            <item>3. co-creation of digital resources by scholars, publishers, and
                                libraries.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>We predict that these problems will confront all research universities within
                        the next decade and - because both faculty-driven humanities research
                        computing and digital library activities have been underway at the
                        University of Virginia for most of the past decade - we believe we are
                        uniquely positioned to address these problems now. The outcome of this
                        project will be methods and guidelines for, and examples of, the management
                        of digital objects across the scholarly information continuum, from creation
                        (by libraries or scholars) to use in research, re-presentation in
                        scholarship, and re-integration into library collections as scholarly
                        publications and tools for research.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Institutional Background:</head>
                    <p>Since its inception in 1992, the Institute has focused intensive support and
                        advanced computer resources on long-term humanities research proposed by
                        faculty at the University of Virginia and elsewhere. To date, the Institute
                        has supported more than forty fellows in architecture, landscape
                        architecture, architectural history, art history, religious studies,
                        classics, anthropological linguistics, medieval and 19th-century British
                        literature, 19th-century American literature, American history, classical
                        history, history of science, archaeology, film, and music, among other
                        disciplines.</p>
                    <p>The majority of this research - indeed, most of the Institute's work -
                        involves intensive collaboration among groups of scholars, and between
                        scholars and the Institute's technical experts. The Pompeii Forum project,
                        for example, sends an interdisciplinary group of researchers to Pompeii each
                        summer, where a systematic survey of the Forum at Pompeii is being conducted
                        using an extremely accurate surveying device known as a laser Total station,
                        and feeding data from that device into a laptop in the field. These
                        measurements are then brought back to the Institute, where they are
                        processed into two-dimensional plans and three-dimensional CAD models.
                        Further field-research provides an extensive photographic survey of the
                        buildings at Pompeii, and these photographs are used in conjunction with
                        advanced photogrammetric software to create accurate, photo-realistic
                        surfaces for the three-dimensional CAD models. Finally, using modeling tools
                        custom-built at the Institute, the researchers are able to combine
                        individual building models into a model of the entire site and even render
                        the walls transparent, in order to see both sides at once, thus producing an
                        analysis of the Forum more detailed, more accurate, and more flexible than
                        any other to date.</p>
                    <p>The University of Virginia Libraries have established a number of electronic
                        data centers that work closely with the Institute's staff and fellows: the
                        Electronic Text Center, the Geospatial and Statistical Data Center, the
                        Digital Media Center, and the Special Collections Digital Center. Library
                        digital centers have provided support to many of the same faculty involved
                        in research with the Institute, and staff from these centers meet regularly
                        with IATH staff and others in a digital library interest group. Most
                        recently, the Libraries have established a Digital Library Research and
                        Development Group, charged with long-range planning of digital library
                        architectures, systems, and procedures. Having begun to assemble a broad
                        digital collection, they recognize that no library management system yet
                        exists to handle it and they have dedicated themselves to developing an
                        appropriate solution to the problem.</p>
                    <p>Further information about library digital centers is available on the Web at
                            &lt;<ptr target="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/ecenters.html"/>&gt;</p>
                    <p>Information about Digital Library Research and Development is available at
                            &lt;<ptr target="http://www.lib.virginia.edu/dl/intro/"/>&gt;.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Project Goals:</head>
                    <p>Much of what has taken place in digital library contexts to date has aimed at
                        producing large collections of digital data, often - in fact usually -
                        without the involvement of the intended audience for that data, scholars and
                        researchers. In this project, we aim to foreground the scholarly user -
                        something we believe we are uniquely positioned to do - and from this
                        perspective we will look at the issues of collections development, data
                        management, metadata, and digital library systems. We expect to complete a
                        number of trials in these areas, and although we do not believe the scope of
                        this project is sufficient to provide universal or definitive solutions, we
                        do expect to arrive at a better understanding of the problems that will be
                        involved in the next generation of digital library activities.</p>
                    <p>So much hyperbole attends the current phase of digital library development
                        that it may seem surprising to suggest there are things scholars need to do
                        that digital libraries cannot support. Three scenarios are presented here as
                        examples of some of those unsolved, second-generation digital library
                        problems:</p>
                    <div>
                        <head>Scenario 1: Scholarly use of digital primary resources</head>
                        <p><emph rend="italics">A literary scholar researching the history of a
                                particular poem knows that its author also painted the subject of
                                the poem. She can find information about the poem and the painting
                                in the digital library, and can even retrieve a digital image of the
                                painting. The scholar knows that other dual-media works were
                                produced by this author, and she suspects that the author's
                                arrangements of his paintings in exhibitions might well be
                                significant in understanding the related literary works: therefore,
                                the scholar would like to use the digital library to find out when
                                the painting in question was exhibited and, for a given exhibition
                                date, would like to know what painting was to its left and what
                                painting was to its right - and then see those paintings together in
                                a virtual reconstruction of the exhibit.</emph></p>
                        <p>In this example, we consider the possibility that the scholar of the very
                            near future will want to do something more than browse or perform
                            keyword searches in the digital library. The promise of the digital
                            library is that it will enable scholars to frame questions that would
                            have been inconceivable without this technology. And yet, in practice,
                            we find that digital libraries support only very narrowly defined
                            investigative activities. Partly this is because we tend to treat
                            objects in the digital library as though they had no other temporal or
                            spatial contexts - as though they had always and only existed, discrete
                            and timeless, in our information systems. Partly, too, these limitations
                            are a sign that the digital library is mainly concerned, at this point,
                            with providing simple access to the discrete digital object, rather than
                            with supporting context, comparison, or analysis - the building blocks
                            of scholarship.</p>
                        <p>We could begin to grapple with this problem by producing several
                            proof-of-concept example projects, in which data and metadata expressly
                            support more complex kinds of "behaviors" in the digital library, and
                            are associated with other objects in the digital library (e.g., Java
                            applets) that actualize those behaviors on the end-user's machine. This
                            follows the Fedora model that the library is already developing,
                            specifically that aspect of Fedora that permits "client access to
                            multiple views, or disseminations, of the object's data through the
                            transparent activation of external mechanisms that execute these content
                            type behaviors"</p>
                        <p>&lt;<ptr target="http://www2.cs.cornell.edu/NCSTRL/CDLRG/FEDORA.html"
                            />&gt;.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Scenario 2: Library adoption of "born-digital" scholarly
                            research</head>
                        <p><emph rend="italics">An archaeologist spends decades producing detailed
                                digital records of an important classical archaeological site. The
                                records include CAD reconstructions of individual buildings,
                                topographical maps, photographs, and maps locating particular
                                artifacts in areas and layers of excavation, and large-scale
                                computer models of the entire site. Upon retirement, the
                                archaeologist offers his entire collection of digital records to the
                                library (since no publisher has ever known what to do with them) -
                                but he offers them on the condition that the library treat these
                                records as a special collection, catalogue them, and make them
                                available through the web to other researchers and students of
                                archaeology.</emph></p>
                        <p>This example makes plain the problems that libraries will inevitably face
                            as they come to collect digital resources produced by scholars outside
                            of library (and quite possibly, publishing) frameworks. The problem is
                            likely to be especially acute in the areas of architecture and
                            archaeology, where data is likely to have been produced by researchers
                            in digital form, and where we have few (if any) established conventions
                            for collecting, normalizing, cataloguing, providing, or preserving such
                            data. A single map or CAD drawing could represent hundreds of hours of
                            research, data gathering, and expert analysis - as valuable, in
                            principle, as a monograph or a journal - and yet libraries might well be
                            unable to accept it, for lack of appropriate systems and procedures. </p>
                        <p>As a pilot project in this area, we can recruit large existing
                            collections of digital architectural and archaeological data (from The
                            Pompeii Forum, Victorian London, The Waters of the City of Rome,
                            Jefferson's Architecture, and other IATH projects), and use that data to
                            experiment with cataloging, collections, and preservation issues raised
                            in such contexts. At the end of three years, we would expect to have
                            brought several such collections into the library.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Scenario 3: Co-creation of digital resources by scholars, publishers,
                            and libraries</head>
                        <p><emph rend="italics">A historian, working together with technical experts
                                in the library's Geospatial and Statistical Data Center, uses census
                                data, eyewitness accounts, military records and contemporary GIS
                                information to generate a time-indexed, geo-referenced
                                reconstruction of troop movements in a famous civil-war battle. The
                                research is going to be published by a university press, and the
                                press has contributed original vector data for the underlying map.
                                At different points in this process, the press, the historian, the
                                historian's graduate research assistants, and library experts all
                                need to share editorial control of the evolving data set. At the end
                                of the process, the data set needs to be published by the press,
                                collected in the library, and connected to textual records of the
                                event.</emph></p>
                        <p>Increasingly, we believe, scholars and libraries and publishers will
                            enter into collaborative arrangements involving the production of
                            digital primary resources by the library, a scholarly treatment of those
                            resources, and electronic publication of the result. We have already
                            seen many instances of this pattern in IATH research projects. In
                            retrospect, it seems perfectly reasonable that the institution owning
                            the primary resources (a rare book, a painting, a statue, a map) would
                            want to produce its initial digital representation; once that digital
                            representation exists, it seems inevitable that scholars will want to do
                            what they have always done - edit, contextualize, re-present, and
                            analyze the (now digital) object. And, if not inevitable, it seems at
                            least likely that the result of this scholarly engagement with digital
                            primary resources will be the stuff of scholarly publishing. There are
                            many unanswered questions, though, behind these three reasonable
                            assumptions: should it be a goal to have a single authoritative version
                            of the digital object? If so, how might scholars and/or publishers
                            register corrections or revisions to the original, if the original is
                            produced (and presumably owned) by a library or museum? If several
                            scholars disagree on the verisimilitude of the digital representation,
                            how will their range of opinions be recorded and connected to that
                            representation? If electronic editions of the artifact become the norm,
                            instead of an authoritative version with apparatus, then how should
                            those editions be derived and denoted?</p>
                        <p>At IATH, we already have several projects that raise this sort of problem
                            - the Valley of the Shadow, the Walt Whitman Archive, the Victorian
                            London project, and others. We have a document management system
                            (Astoria) that will help to address some of the practical procedural
                            issues involved in managing multiple authorship; we will experiment with
                            integrating that system into the library's production strategies, to
                            address those situations in which a single authoritative version is
                            necessary or desirable, but we would also expect to experiment with
                            managing and coordinating multiple divergent editions of a single base
                            object, or multiple perspectives on an object.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <p>In order to address the many problems - some technical, some social, some
                            intellectual - raised in these three scenarios, we need to move beyond
                            the simple production and cataloguing of digital collections, and begin
                            to recognize that, in the library of the future as in libraries of the
                            past and present, most materials will be produced by many hands, not
                            few; most materials will incorporate many perspectives, not one; and
                            most materials will need to support specialized and pointed research as
                            well as general, blunt queries.</p>
                        <p>Recognizing these things, we will undertake a collaborative investigation
                            of advanced digital library problems, including library absorption of
                            scholar-produced digital resources, library/scholar co-creation of such
                            resources, and analytical use of digital humanities data. Within this
                            investigation, our emphasis will be on metadata practices, library
                            systems, and production protocols that support scholarly use. And though
                            we don't promise to solve all the problems that might be raised in this
                            area, we will establish guidelines that will be useful to others,
                            produce examples that others can imitate, and learn which problems are
                            easy to solve and which are difficult.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Content:</head>
                    <p>We will focus in particular on visual and spatial data, with an emphasis on
                        architecture and archaeology, but also considering visual arts, especially
                        in complex spatial and temporal contexts. There are a number of research
                        projects already underway in scholarly contexts that are producing and
                        freely distributing digital data in architecture and archaeology. The
                        problem these disciplines face is that there is no well-established
                        institutional mechanism for collecting, preserving, or publishing digital
                        objects of this sort (CAD drawings, digital topo-maps, 3D models, even
                        digitized photo or slide collections). Moreover, the strategies for
                        cataloguing and describing of art objects do not work very well with the
                        more hierarchical and complex information structures that characterize
                        architectural and archaeological data. With respect to visual arts, we are
                        particularly interested in developing and applying metadata structures that
                        would support comparison, contextualizing, and analysis of art works, and in
                        producing some sample applications that would demonstrate to other libraries
                        and scholars the value of spatial and temporal metadata.</p>
                    <p>Part of the budget for this project will go, in small one-year awards,
                        directly to ongoing faculty research. A library/IATH committee will
                        administer these funds, and they will be used to support experimentation, in
                        the context of faculty research, the results of which would generalize
                        readily to other contexts. Normalizing data, standardizing metadata,
                        capturing new data in accordance with recently specified best practices -
                        all of these are appropriate activities for this committee to fund.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Intellectual Property:</head>
                    <p>The University of Virginia will grant to The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation a
                        non-exclusive, royalty-free right to access, use, and distribute for
                        educational, social and/or charitable purposes, the software technologies,
                        tools, and related documents developed as a result of this project and to
                        incorporate such software technologies, tools, and related documents in
                        other projects supported by The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Systems, Procedures, and Standards:</head>
                    <p>This project raises technical challenges at the level of information systems
                        design and at the level of standards design and implementation, and it
                        requires a coordinated investigation of these issues by IATH and the
                        Library's Digital Library Research and Development Group. Fairly high-level
                        staff will be needed for this: at IATH, we need to support cutting-edge
                        technical work in architecture, archaeology, mapping, and other visual-data
                        fields. We also need to hire a second person at IATH, to concentrate on
                        database and document management systems, as the production end of a
                        continuum that delivers data to library systems. In the Library, we would
                        like to add a position to the Digital Library Research and Development Group
                        to implement systems and standards for producing, managing, and
                        disseminating visual and spatial data in library contexts, to ensure that
                        those library systems respond appropriately to the needs of research users,
                        and to work with IATH and others on the difficult issues of adoption and
                        co-creation, mentioned above.</p>
                    <p>Software tools and environments for producing, managing, and publishing large
                        image collections are of interest to IATH, and even more so to the Library,
                        inasmuch as many of our research projects involve the creation and use of
                        extensive image collections. IATH's principal interests in this area would
                        be workflow and data management: on the library side, Thornton Staples has
                        been working with the Cornell Digital Library Group (Carl Lagoze) on
                        technical issues involved in the creation of digital repositories, and on
                        the implementation of Lagoze's Flexible and Extensible Digital Object and
                        Repository Architecture.</p>
                    <p>Both IATH and the Library are very interested in applications of SGML, XML,
                        and HyTime to the problem of describing art, architecture, and
                        archaeological sites. In particular, we believe there is significant work
                        yet to be done in the description of art collections, the treatment of
                        three-dimensional objects as information structures, and capturing the
                        passage of time as an element of these collections and structures. Thornton
                        Staples has been working in this area, developing something he calls the
                        General Descriptive Modeling Scheme (GDMS), an Extensible Markup Language
                        (XML) document type definition (DTD) that is intended to be used to create
                        textual models describing real-world phenomena (such as creations, events,
                        places and people) and giving a context for describing the content of, and
                        relations among, digital objects.</p>
                    <p>All of these interests could have a direct relevance to Mellon's projected
                        work in the areas of art, architecture, and archaeology, in ARTSTOR. In
                        order for collections of two- and three-dimensional image data to be useful
                        for teaching and research, the ARTSTOR collections will need to be embedded
                        in data structures that can support annotation, multiple spatial and
                        temporal arrangements of works and sites, and the representation of change
                        over time.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Personnel:</head>
                    <p>Library and Institute staff directly involved in design aspects of this
                        project throughout the three years, as part of their regular duties, include
                        Worthy Martin, Technical Director, IATH and Associate Professor, Computer
                        Science; Daniel Pitti, Project Director, IATH; Thornton Staples, Director,
                        Digital Library Research and Development; John Unsworth, Director, IATH, and
                        Associate Professor, English.</p>
                    <p>Other Library personnel who would contribute some part of their time to
                        implementation, as part of their regular library employment, would include
                        Edward Gaynor (Special Collections); Rick Provine (Digital Media Center);
                        David Seaman (Electronic Text Center); Ross Wayland (Digital Library
                        Research and Development); Patrick Yott (GeoSpatial Information Center).</p>
                    <p>IATH fellows whose ongoing research will be directly involved in this project
                        include: Ed Ayers et al., <emph rend="italics">Valley of the Shadow</emph>;
                        David Blair, <emph rend="italics">WaxWeb</emph>; John Dobbins, Kirk Martini
                        et al., <emph rend="italics">The Pompeii Forum Project</emph>; Morris Eaves,
                        Robert Essick, Joseph Viscomi, <emph rend="italics">The Blake
                        Archive</emph>; Lavahn Hoh, <emph rend="italics">The Circus in Europe and
                            America</emph>; Jerome McGann, <emph rend="italics">The Rossetti
                            Archive</emph>; Michael Levenson et al., <emph rend="italics">Monuments
                            and Dust (Victorian London)</emph>; Kathy Poole, <emph rend="italics"
                            >Boston Back Bay Fens</emph>; Ken Price et al., <emph rend="italics"
                            >Walt Whitman Archive</emph>; Ben Ray, <emph rend="italics">The Salem
                            Witch Trials</emph>; Katherine Rinne, <emph rend="italics">Waters of the
                            City of Rome</emph>; Marion Roberts, <emph rend="italics">Salisbury
                            Cathedral</emph>; Ken Schwartz, <emph rend="italics">Charlottesville
                            Urban Design</emph>; Richard Guy Wilson, <emph rend="italics"
                            >Jefferson's Architecture</emph>.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Management Plan:</head>
                    <p>This project will be jointly managed by John Unsworth and Thornton Staples,
                        with close cooperation among IATH personnel, faculty fellows, and library
                        staff. Fellows will provide digital objects (maps, photographs, models,
                        etc.) and the metadata to accompany those objects, as well as some
                        functional specifications for scholarly use of those objects. The Digital
                        Library Research and Development Group will work with IATH and its fellows
                        to establish guidelines for the production of digital data and metadata to
                        be collected and disseminated by library systems, and they will advise IATH
                        and its fellows on the systems design and development issues that attend the
                        adoption of information produced by IATH fellows. IATH staff will support
                        data production to agreed-upon standards, will consult with fellows and
                        library staff on the specification of those standards, and will work with
                        library staff to prototype the functionality requested and specified by the
                        scholars who produce (and intend to use) the data.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Work Plan:</head>
                    <p><emph rend="bold">Year One:</emph> Primary objectives in the first half of
                        this year will be hiring, training, and information-gathering (which would
                        include external consultation as well as a thorough analysis of our own data
                        and systems). In the second half of the year, we will finalize a first
                        version of the General Descriptive Modeling Scheme, while working with
                        individual projects to establish and document standard procedures for
                        producing descriptive, structural, and administrative metadata.</p>
                    <p><emph rend="bold">Year Two:</emph> In the second year, we will attempt to
                        deposit information from the Waters of Rome, Boston Back Bay Fens, and the
                        Pompeii Forum projects into the Digital Library, and we will experiment with
                        Java applets provided via Fedora as disseminators for the comparison and
                        analysis of visual art objects based on metadata, probably using projects on
                        Blake, Rossetti, and Salisbury Cathedral.</p>
                    <p><emph rend="bold">Year Three:</emph> In the third year, we will focus on the
                        difficult issues involved in co-creation of scholarly resources, both
                        technical and social. We will experiment with multi-author/single version
                        solutions (in the Valley project, Jefferson's Architecture, and Victorian
                        London), and we will also look at multi-author/multiple edition solutions
                        (with some of the same projects, plus Whitman, Salem, and others).</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Dissemination:</head>
                    <p>Information about the problems encountered and lessons learned in the
                        experiments described here will be reported at the conferences that project
                        participants normally attend - annual meetings of the Association of
                        Research Libraries, the Research Libraries Group, the Digital Libraries
                        Federation, the American Association of University Presses, the Modern
                        Language Association, the Association for Computers in the Humanities, the
                        Association for Literary and Linguistic Computing, the annual XML/SGML
                        conference, the Markup Technologies conference; these results would be
                        appropriate to publish in the journals associated with some of these
                        professional associations as well. Our presentations at these and other
                        conferences would be supported in many cases by the travel portion of the
                        budget.</p>
                    <p>In addition to these venues, the Web itself is obviously an important medium
                        in which to publish project results and documentation - for example,
                        Document Type Definitions, production manuals, best practices, and reports
                        on our failures and successes. Reusable technical products of the research
                        such as DTDs or software will be freely distributed, updated, and documented
                        through the Web. Finally, the web-based content that is produced in the
                        different scholarly projects that participate in this research can provide
                        links to "how-to" information.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
