<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The Digital Performance Archive</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Rachael</forename>
                        <surname>Beach</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">The Nottingham Trent University</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>While digital performance events and experiments proliferate and new performance
                    genres are beginning to emerge, no central record or archive of these
                    developments is currently being collated. The Digital Performance Archive (DPA)
                    aims to fill that gap by archiving and critically analysing significant new
                    interdisciplinary developments in performance which draw upon (or exist within)
                    digital media in its varied forms. To this end, The Digital Performance Archive
                    will undertake a comprehensive study and recording of the development of
                    'digital performance' in the last decade of the Twentieth Century.</p>
                <p>The study will cover both digital resources used in performance and digital
                    resources on performance created in the two year period 1999 to 2000 (with
                    important precedents of the 90's also being catalogued). Digital resources in
                    performance include theatrical productions and live-art installations that
                    incorporate electronic media, to live-broadcast World Wide Web performances and
                    Internet based collaborations, to interactive drama and the new performative
                    'virtual environments' of MUDS, MOOs and IRC. Digital resources on performance
                    include those being used to document, analyse and critique performance: from
                    performing arts databases, websites and mailing lists, to academic CD-ROMS and
                    laser discs. The project aims to be of value to researchers across a wide range
                    of academic disciplines, from drama and performance to art and design, from the
                    social sciences to computer science and cybernetics.</p>
                <p>The Digital Performance Archive will have several outcomes. Firstly it will
                    collate an extensive searchable database on the World Wide Web, in order that
                    the public will be able to gain access to work held by the DPA, in particular to
                    the websites and digital files provided by practitioners. Secondly, as material
                    for a DVD, the DPA will document exemplars of digital performance on video. This
                    interactive DVD will also include other significant documents and examples of
                    digitally related performance, all of which will be critically examined. Lastly,
                    the DPA will produce an academic publication presenting a critical overview of
                    the field. As already stated there is currently no other archive that is devoted
                    specifically to this type of work. Perhaps the main reasons for this are that
                    these types of works are so current, so diverse and developing at such an
                    extraordinary rate that there is, as yet, no accepted methodology for dealing
                    with them. Whilst one of the DPA's objectives is to create this web-searchable
                    database archive of the works within the field, clearly it also has an important
                    role to play in beginning to create a structure for the study of the works in
                    its collection and of the field as a whole. It is these seemingly conflicting
                    roles of provider of raw information on the web and of interpreter in such a
                    fast moving 'discipline' that make the project so interesting and ambitious. </p>
                <p>In no part of the project is this paradox more evident than in the Web based
                    database of works. Here the archive benefits from a comparison with photographs
                    and photographic archives. Sekula writes that,<cit rend="block">
                        <quote>The photographic archives' components are not conventional lexical
                            units, but rather are subject to the circumstantial character of all
                            that is photographable. Thus it is absurd to imagine a dictionary of
                            photographs, unless one is willing to disregard the specificity of
                            individual images in favor of some model of typicality ... Clearly one
                            way of 'taming' photography is by means of this transformation of the
                            circumstantial and idiosyncratic into the typical and emblematic. This
                            is usually achieved by a stylistic or interpretive feat, or by a
                            sampling of the archive's offerings for a 'representative'
                            instance.</quote>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>Clearly, as in the above description, the DPA, whilst dealing with files and
                    information of similar types, will not be dealing with standard content within
                    these types, especially in such a broad and shifting field. However, an
                    interpretative ' taming' route will be taken with the material chosen by the DPA
                    for the DVD and publication. This approach however is not viable for the
                    searchable web database whose aim is to provide files to the researcher as the
                    practitioner meant them to be seen. If this is not wholly possible visually, the
                    files should at least be as free as possible from any interpretation that might
                    be placed on them by the DPA.</p>
                <p>Sekula continues:<cit rend="block">
                        <quote>Another way is to invent a machine, or rather a clerical apparatus, a
                            filing system, which allows the operator/researcher/editor to retrieve
                            the individual instance from the huge quantity of images contained
                            within the archive. Here the photograph is not regarded as necessarily
                            typical or emblematic of anything, but only as a particular image which
                            had been isolated for purposes of inspection.</quote>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>The creation of such a filing system is the ultimate aim of the DPA web database.
                    However, Sekula creates a picture of an ideal situation in which a user finds
                    exactly what they are looking for in the filing system. He does not consider
                    that there are inherent biases in the creation of such a system. When attaching
                    metadata to practitioners' files in order to allow database searches, the DPA
                    must respect the descriptions attached to them by practitioners themselves,
                    whilst also trying to create a system which is coherent and consistent (or
                    typical and emblematic) across all the works. In addition, there needs to be
                    some mediation between these two biases and the searches that the user brings to
                    the database. It is a challenging aspect of the project.</p>
                <p>This poster will provide delegates with the opportunity to see the breadth of
                    works that the DPA must archive and define. It will be a chance to see how far
                    the DPA has progressed with its acquisitions and with placing these acquisitions
                    within its web 'filing system'. The poster will give delegates the opportunity
                    to test this web searchable database and provide comment. The DPA will welcome
                    the opportunity to discuss with delegates any similar problems and solutions
                    they have encountered.</p>
                <p>The archive is a joint project between Digital Research Unit of the Department of
                    Visual and Performing Arts at The Nottingham Trent University, and the Media and
                    Performance Research Unit, Department of Media and Performance at the University
                    of Salford.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Sekula</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">The Body and the Archive</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Bolton</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">The Contest of Meaning: Critical Histories of
                                Photography</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>The MIT Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
