<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Chinese Collections in Museums on the Web: Current
                    Status, Problems, and Future</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Hsin-Liang</forename>
                        <surname>Chen</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Graduate School of Library and Information
                                Science</name>, <name type="org">UT-Austin</name>
                            <email>chen@gslis.uexas.edu</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2003">2003</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Georgia</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Athens, Georgia</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 2003</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Eric</forename>
                        <surname>Rochester</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">William</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Kretzschmar</surname>, Jr.</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>INTRODUCTION</head>
                    <p>With the development of computing technology, many Chinese museums and
                        museums with significant Chinese collections have digitized and provided
                        images of their collections on Web sites. These online resources offer users
                        around the world access to valuable treasures to learn about Chinese
                        culture. However, there are obstacles that must be overcome to achieve the
                        goals of promoting the Chinese heritage and educating new generations.</p>
                    <p>The purpose of this project is to study how museum practitioners use current
                        image indexing practices and services to retrieve the images of the Chinese
                        collections. Several issues, including image needs, information-seeking
                        strategies, information queries, search functions, display formats and
                        human-computer interaction are examined in this study.</p>
                    <p>This paper focuses specifically on the current practices of image management.
                        The following questions are addressed:<list type="bulleted">
                            <item>What kind of images do the museums index?</item>
                            <item>How do the museums index their image collections?</item>
                            <item>What kind of indexing tools do the museums use?</item>
                        </list></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>BACKGROUND OF THE PROBLEM</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>CURRENT IMAGE MANAGEMENT AT MUSEUMS AND ART LIBRARIES</head>
                        <p>Graham (1999) surveyed 60 art libraries in the U.K. The survey included
                            the important issues of image collections, cataloging and indexing
                            practices, content-based image retrieval (CBIR) systems, and the use of
                            images. Graham’s study reports on the current management of image
                            collections and techniques for image and video retrieval in the U.K.
                            Eakins and Graham (1999) study the current state of the art in CBIR
                            systems within the U.K. and submit several suggestions to U.K.
                            governmental agencies, users and managers of image collections, and CBIR
                            software developers. The Visual Image User Study (VIUS) project at Penn
                            State University is conducting an extensive and systematic assessment of
                            its needs for digital image delivery (Pisciotta, et al, 2001). The VIUS
                            project is working to develop digital picture libraries to serve new
                            uses of digital images for teaching and research.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>IMPORTANCE OF INFORMATION NEEDS AND INFORMATION-SEEKING BEHAVIOR TO
                            SYSTEM DESIGN</head>
                        <p>Stephenson (1999) examined several cultural heritage image databases and
                            identified key issues for future improvements. She pointed out that, in
                            addition to technological challenges, the areas of audience, user
                            behavior, and use should be addressed as well. According to Stephenson,
                            museums should examine:<list type="bulleted">
                                <item>For whom are museums building an image database?</item>
                                <item>What image databases are museums building?</item>
                                <item>What are those users’ purposes in using the image
                                    database?</item>
                                <item>What functionality do the users need to use the
                                    database?</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>These questions reflect a user-centered design philosophy which assists
                            database designers understand their users thoroughly.</p>
                        <div>
                            <head>
                                <emph rend="italics">Defining the primary user group</emph>
                            </head>
                            <p>One of the major goals of an online image database is to break the
                                barriers of time differences, geographical locations, and limited
                                physical access to materials. This brings up a critical question:
                                who is the user? The online database is likely to serve a diverse
                                group of users: local and remote users, experienced and naïve
                                users, and existing and new users. Different user services are
                                required for this diverse group of users. Museums should examine the
                                institutional goals and purposes of their online image databases to
                                determine the priority of their missions.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>
                                <emph rend="italics">Understanding anticipated users</emph>
                            </head>
                            <p>After determining their primary user group, the museums should study
                                their users. The following questions should be considered:<list
                                    type="bulleted">
                                    <item>Goals of designing an online image database</item>
                                    <item>Differences between existing access to the image
                                        collection and the use of the new online image
                                        database</item>
                                    <item>Anticipated users’ behavior in different locations</item>
                                    <item>Selection of surrogates for image indexing and
                                        retrieval</item>
                                    <item>Information architecture of the online image
                                        database</item>
                                </list></p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>
                                <emph rend="italics">Supporting discovery and retrieval</emph>
                            </head>
                            <p>To use the online image database successfully, the users should have
                                knowledge of information retrieval in general, subject areas, and
                                search systems. On the other hand, the museums should investigate
                                the following factors:<list type="bulleted">
                                    <item>Indexing standards such as metadata</item>
                                    <item>Query analysis</item>
                                    <item>Effectiveness and efficiency of indexing tools and
                                        methods</item>
                                    <item>Multi-dimensional indexing and retrieval methods</item>
                                    <item>Users’ capabilities</item>
                                    <item>User support and training</item>
                                </list></p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>
                                <emph rend="italics">Supporting functionality</emph>
                            </head>
                            <p>New functions may be created to facilitate users’ search strategies.
                                To achieve such goals, studies on interface design, human-computer
                                interaction, and users’ information-seeking behavior should be
                                conducted. Different tools may be required by special users and
                                environments.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>
                                <emph rend="italics">Other challenges</emph>
                            </head>
                            <p>In addition to the above key issues, the museums also face several
                                    challenges:<list type="bulleted">
                                    <item>lack of communication among museums;</item>
                                    <item>lack of indexing standards and tools; and</item>
                                    <item>lack of translation standards of Chinese into western
                                        languages.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>Chinese museums and museums with significant Chinese collections
                                should form a consortium to establish communication and to develop
                                collaboration. Many western museums have begun those efforts. The
                                Art Museum Image Consortium (AMICO) is one of those consortiums, but
                                its image collections only have about 6,000 works from Asian
                                cultures (AMICO, 2001). The lack of indexing standards and tools is
                                the same challenge for all museums. Most museums either develop
                                their own indexing standards and tools or do not have adequate
                                professional personnel to manage their image collections (CLIR,
                                1999; Graham, 1999). Regarding translation standards, although
                                American libraries started using Pinyin as the standard romanization
                                scheme for Chinese characters on October 1, 2000 (RLG, 2000), many
                                museums may not be aware of this change and may still use the
                                Wade-Giles system. These challenges are important to the development
                                of image collections.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>METHODOLOGY</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>PARTICIPANTS</head>
                        <p>Six museums were selected for this study based on the size and diversity
                            of their Chinese collections or their image management. The six
                            participating museums were in the states of California, Illinois,
                            Massachusetts, New York, Ohio, and Washington, D.C.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>PROCEDURE</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>
                                <emph rend="italics">Pre-visit questionnaire</emph>
                            </head>
                            <p>A set of self-administered questionnaires was used to collect
                                librarians’ views on cataloging/indexing practices, the functions of
                                new image management systems, and the use of images. The
                                questionnaires were distributed to librarians before an on-site
                                visit and were collected between January and April 2002.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>
                                <emph rend="italics">Follow-up phone interview</emph>
                            </head>
                            <p>After all respondents answered the questionnaires, the investigator
                                examined the questionnaires and conducted phone interviews with the
                                respondents for unclear answers and in-depth information. The
                                investigator identified several key people for observations and
                                interviews when visiting museums.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>
                                <emph rend="italics">On-site visit</emph>
                            </head>
                            <p>Based on the knowledge gained from the questionnaires and phone
                                interviews, on-site visits were conducted between June and August
                                2002. The investigator observed librarians and museum practitioners’
                                image seeking behavior and also interviewed those people for further
                                understanding of their search behavior. The investigator interviewed
                                museum administrators to obtain their expectations for digital image
                                management in the mission of the museum.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</head>
                    <p>According to the questionnaires, observations, and interviews, the
                        investigator reports on the current status, problems, and future of image management:<list>
                            <item><emph rend="italics">Current Status</emph>: all six museums have
                                been digitizing the Chinese collections. Photographic prints,
                                photographic negatives, and transparencies/slides (35 mm) are the
                                most popular formats. All the museums have used or purchased a
                                computer-based image management system to organize the digital
                                images and related information.</item>
                            <item><emph rend="italics">Problems</emph>: most museums did not have
                                comprehensive records in the past, so they have spent substantial
                                amounts of their budgets and people-power to establish basic records
                                or re-enter data for the digital images. Their conventional
                                cataloging and indexing practices are not suitable or transferable
                                for the new image management system. Image management systems used
                                by the six museums are not able to accommodate the features of the
                                Chinese collections and their records. Most image management systems
                                are not metadata/XML ready, which means that the expansion of the
                                systems onto the Web may be limited. Each museum has its unique
                                institutional structure, which hinders the workflow of image
                                management and a lack of communication and collaboration exists
                                among museums departments. </item>
                            <item><emph rend="italics">Future</emph>: the development of the
                                indexing schema is critical to the management of digital images and
                                to the museum practitioners and on-line users. Image management
                                systems should be enhanced with the standards of metadata/XML, etc.
                                for the Web-based environment. </item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Regarding the image-seeking behavior of museum practitioners, and the
                        administration's expectations of digital images, the investigator will
                        report the findings of these issues in the future.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>REFERENCES</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name type="org">Art Museum Image Consortium (AMICO)</name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="u"/>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note><ptr target="http://www.amico.org"/> (access September, 2001)</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name type="org">Council on Library and Information Resources</name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m"> Scholarship, instruction, and libraries at the turn of
                                the century: Results from five task forces of learned societies and
                                the Council on Library and Information Resources</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace>
                                <publisher> The Council</publisher>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Eakins</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Graham</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m"> Content-based image retrieval: A report to the JISC
                                Technology Application Programme</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>[Online]: <ptr
                                target="http://www.unn.ac.uk/iidr/research/cbir/report.html"
                            /></note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Graham</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">The description and indexing of images: Report of a
                                survey of ARLIS members, 1998/99</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>[Online]. Available: <ptr target="http://www.unn.ac.uk/iidr/ARLIS/"
                            /></note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Pisciotta</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Brisson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Ferrin</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Dooris</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Spink</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Penn State Visual Image User Study</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">D-Lib Magazine</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol"/>
                                <biblScope type="issue">July/August</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp"/>
                                <date when="2001">2001</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>URL: <ptr
                                target="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/july01/pisciotta/07pisciotta.html"
                            />(access September 2001).</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name type="org">Research Libraries Group (RLG)</name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="u">Library of Congress, other US libraries join
                                international community on use of Pinyin</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>URL: <ptr target="http://www.rlg.org/pr/pr20000-pinyin.html"/>(access
                            September, 2001)..</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Stephenson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">“Recent developments in cultural heritage image
                                databases: directions for user-centered design</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Library-Trends</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">48</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">410-437</biblScope>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
