<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Software for Humanities Computing: Image Annotation,
                    Unicode, and SGML packages from the Institute for Advanced Technology in the
                    Humanities</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">John</forename>
                        <surname>Unsworth</surname>
                        <affiliation>Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities, <name
                                type="org">University of Virginia</name>
                            <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Bergen</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bergen, Norway</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 1996</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Anne</forename>
                        <surname>Lindebjerg</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Espen</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                        <surname>Ore</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Øystein</forename>
                        <surname>Reigem</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities at the University of
                    Virginia supports computer-mediated research projects in all disciplines of the
                    humanities. In the service of these projects, we do some software development.
                    In this session, John Unsworth, Director of the Institute, will demonstrate some
                    of the software pack-ages publicly available or under development at the
                    Institute. Those packages include:</p>
                <p><emph rend="italics">
                        <emph rend="bold">Inote</emph>
                    </emph>: an image annotation program, written in Java. Inote allows a user to
                    superimpose multiple clear overlays on an image and, without altering the
                    underlying image, draw details (point, circle, rectangle) on those overlays and
                    attach annotations (text or image) to the detail. It can load images by http,
                    and it can be delivered, along with an annotated image, through the web. Inote
                    also has some special features including automatic overlay generation, in which
                    the software identifies lines of text in a page image and automatically creates
                    details for those lines. Inote will also save overlays as client-side ismap
                    instructions. Planned features include audio annotations and SGML awareness.</p>
                <p><emph rend="italics">
                        <emph rend="bold">MU</emph>
                    </emph>: a perl-based program that will build fill-out forms for SGML editing
                    through the web, using a simple template of SGML tags as the basis for the form.
                    MU supports file-locking (for collaborative work over the net), allows one to
                    save and reload files as they are being edited, provides space for notes and
                    remarks, and automatically builds a selectable list of SGML files in
                    progress.</p>
                <p><emph rend="italics">
                        <emph rend="bold">Babble</emph>
                    </emph>: a Unicode-based program that permits synoptic display of many texts in
                    many different character sets. Babble respects the directionality of different
                    languages in text-wrapping, allows text display columns to be vertical or
                    horizontal, permits selective scroll-locking of text columns, and performs
                    string and mark searches. This software, currently written in Motif and C++, is
                    being ported to Java, and we expect the Java version to be SGML-aware.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
