<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">CETH TEI Pilot Projects</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Wendell</forename>
                        <surname>Piez</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Center for Electronic Texts in the Humanities
                                (CETH)</name>
                            <email>piez@rci.rutgers.edu </email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Anthony</forename>
                        <surname>Lioi</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Center for Electronic Texts in the Humanities
                                (CETH)</name>
                            <email>lioi@rci.rutgers.edu </email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Julia</forename>
                        <surname>Lougovaya</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Center for Electronic Texts in the Humanities
                                (CETH)</name>
                            <email>lougovay@gandalf.rutgers.edu </email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Mary Jo</forename>
                        <surname>Watts</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Center for Electronic Texts in the Humanities
                                (CETH)</name>
                            <email>mwatts@rci.rutgers.edu </email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Bergen</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bergen, Norway</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 1996</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Anne</forename>
                        <surname>Lindebjerg</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Espen</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                        <surname>Ore</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Øystein</forename>
                        <surname>Reigem</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>SGML</item>
                        <item>publishing (electronic)</item>
                        <item>teaching</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The CETH TEI Pilot Projects are a group of demonstrations of high-quality
                    scholarly and educational resources created in conformance with the Guidelines
                    of the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) for the markup of Humanities texts in SGML
                    (Standard Generalized Markup Language). We are using off-the-shelf SGML creation
                    and browsing tools (SoftQuad Author/Editor; WordPerfect with SGML; SoftQuad
                    Panorama) to develop prototype electronic text resources which take advantage of
                    SGML and TEI functionalities (especially for cross-platform compatibility and
                    networked publication), which can be created and browsed via PC platforms, and
                    which further develop and extend the concept of a networked electronic edition
                    of a text. A central goal of the project is the production of documentation
                    which will help scholars and educators at other institutions to assess our work,
                    to design similar projects of their own, and to open discussion not only on the
                    means but on the purposes and potential uses of such editions.</p>
                <p>Please consult the project front page on the World-wide Web, presently at <ptr
                        target="http://www.rci.rutgers.edu/~piez/front.htm"/> (currently in
                    progress), for a more detailed overview.</p>
                <div>
                    <head><title level="m">"The Child in the House"</title>: An Electronic
                        Edition</head>
                    <p rend="presenter">Wendell Piez</p>
                    <p>An electronic edition with output in two forms: print (using WordPerfect with
                        SGML) and networked via the World-wide Web (using SoftQuad Panorama). The
                        project is intended to provide a prototype for a high-quality "fascicle"
                        edition of a text, suitable both for networked browsing and for
                        micro-publishing. The editor of this project also offers documentation
                        introducing Humanities scholars to the TEI, as well as supporting
                        documentation for using WordPerfect 6.1, SGML Edition, as a publishing
                        utility for TEI texts.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>"<title level="m">Their Eyes Were Watching God</title>, Chapter 1"</head>
                    <p rend="presenter">Anthony Lioi</p>
                    <p>An edition with critical commentary which demonstrates the uses of TEI
                        linking mechanisms in a hypertext rendition. The markup traces the
                        occurrence of thematically-related tropes in the text, linking them with
                        each other and with the commentary. This project offers a prototype of a
                        critical edition useful not only as a pedagogical tool (demonstrating the
                        function of thematic figuration in a literary text) but as a form of
                        disseminating research results.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>John Donne's Elegy "<title level="a">Love's Progress</title>"</head>
                    <p rend="presenter">Mary Jo Watts</p>
                    <p>This edition is a rendition of a Renaissance manuscript (extant in Rutgers
                        Special Collections and Archives) in facsimile and analytical transcription.
                        Alternate style sheets provide different views of the text. The
                        transcription is linked dynamically to a digital image of the manuscript,
                        which in some views is more legible than the original.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Virgil's <title level="m">Aeneid</title> Book I, with the Latin
                        Commentaries of Servius</head>
                    <p rend="presenter">Julia Lougovaya</p>
                    <p>An edition of the poem with line-by-line commentaries, interactively
                        accessible with hypertext functionality. A very useful tool for the student
                        of Virgil, the Latin language, and the history of literary criticism, this
                        project shows how electronic means not only can provide broad access to a
                        relatively obscure text (the fourth-century commentaries of Servius) but
                        also how hypertext linking between these commentaries and their subject,
                        Virgil's poem, can improve a reader's ability to navigate and interpret both
                        texts.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
