<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">"Grotefend", a tool for deciphering ancient syllabic
                    scripts</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Heikki</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                        <surname>Särkkä</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Joensuu</name>, School of Translation
                            Studies <email>SARKKA@cc.joensuu.fi</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Bergen</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bergen, Norway</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 1996</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Anne</forename>
                        <surname>Lindebjerg</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Espen</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                        <surname>Ore</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Øystein</forename>
                        <surname>Reigem</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>deciphering</item>
                        <item>syllabic scripts</item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The "Grotefend" program that will be introduced in this paper is intended to
                    facilitate the making of hypotheses concerning the decipherment of an unknown
                    syllabic script. In essence, the program consists of two modules, one that can
                    be used for assigning readings to the signs and the other for analysis of the
                    text. The two modules can be used independently of each other, that is, a text
                    can be analysed without making any assumptions about how any given sign should
                    be read. The program was written in Visual Basic at the Department of Computer
                    Science of the University of Joensuu by Tuomo Pusa and Kari Tanskanen.</p>
                <p>At the outset, the user establishes the range of signs used in a given text and
                    gives each sign a number. This converts the text into a sequence of numbers and,
                    as the case may be, gaps representing word separators. The use of numbers is a
                    purely practical device obviating the need for choosing a standard visual
                    representation for each sign. The strings of numbers and any word separators
                    where these can be recognized are then inputted as the data to the program. Once
                    this has been done, tentative readings can be given to the individual signs by
                    using an input table. Any time a reading is assigned to a given sign, the same
                    reading is automatically given to all the occurrences of that sign in the text.
                    Any reading can be changed afterwards without affecting the readings of other
                    signs.</p>
                <p>The following reports can be generated by the program: <list>
                        <item>1. Total frequency of basic signs</item>
                        <item>2. Total frequency of basic signs that may occur word-initially</item>
                        <item>3. Total frequency of basic signs that may occur word-finally</item>
                        <item>4. Basic signs only occurring word-initially and their absolute
                            frequency</item>
                        <item>5. Basic signs only occurring word-finally and their absolute
                            frequency </item>
                        <item>6. Repeated strings. This is a list of strings of 2-5 basic signs
                            occurring more than once in the text with their line numbers.</item>
                        <item>7. Repeated strings found on the assumption that the text runs
                            boustrophedon. If repeated strings are found on lines X and Y (X and Y
                            being line numbers), there is a probability that the text was written
                            left to right and right to left on alternative lines if the difference
                            X-Y is an odd number. The higher the occurrence of repeated strings
                            under the said conditions and the longer they are, the higher the
                            probability that the text in fact does run boustrophedon.</item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>Apart from the above, the data generated can be used as a basis for generating
                    further, perhaps more interesting data such as the relative frequencies of
                    different signs, which, in turn, should be helpful for formulating hypotheses
                    about the genetic or structural kinship of the language concerned with languages
                    of known structural characteristics.</p>
                <p>A fundamental problem that has to be addressed in calculating relative sign
                    frequencies is the nature of the unknown system, that is, whether we are dealing
                    with a syllabary consisting of vowels and open syllables only like the system of
                    Linear B or the two kana syllabaries of Japanese as opposed to, say, the system
                    of Akkadian cuneiform which uses closed syllables as well in a seemingly
                    unsystematic way that allows the same word to be written in numerous different
                    ways. Given a long enough text, the number of different signs is likely to give
                    us a clue to the nature of the system used. Strings of signs regularly repeating
                    in the text would be indicative of a stable graphemic system while few
                    repetitions would lead one to expect a "variable key" system comparable to
                    cuneifroms that would be correspondingly more difficult to break in a way that
                    commands confidence.</p>
                <p>Worth studying is the question of how long a text should be in order for us to be
                    able to draw valid inferences about the language. Not unnaturally, that depends
                    on the type of inferences we would like to make. At the most basic level, the
                    decipherer has to make sure that the textual material s/he is looking at
                    consists of samples of the language. If we manage to determine the minimal
                    length of text that is needed for the identification of a given text as
                    representing a given language with a given degree of probability, we are in a
                    better position to collect a corpus of texts that are indeed written in the same
                    language. Any advance made in the decipherment on the basis of one text could
                    then be checked against other texts in the same language.</p>
                <p>Problems of decipherment are further compounded by the fact that the script tells
                    us very little about the phonology of the language unless we know the degree of
                    fidelity with which phonemic contrasts are reflected by the it. A case in point
                    here would be the differences between the older and the younger futhark in
                    Scandinavia.</p>
                <p>Even in the face of the above uncertainties concerning the fit between the
                    graphology and phonology of a language, there are certain features that are a
                    priori likely to prove more fertile than others. If it is a question of a
                    syllabic script, word-initial vowels are an obvious starting point. Even if the
                    vowel 'a' is the most frequent vowel across a range of languages, absolute
                    frequencies will vary depending on the historical phonology of the language
                    concerned.</p>
                <p>Depending on the language, identification of proper nouns may occasionally be
                    possible because of their greater length. The following regularity is suggested:
                    in a text consisting of otherwise shorter reoccurring units, a reoccurring unit
                    considerably longer than average is indicative of a proper noun. The rationale
                    behind this may be either that sentential strings like 'Marduk will help him'
                    are used as names or the fact that a longish repeated element consists of a noun
                    plus one or more epithets. On comparison with known languages from the same
                    area, identification of proper nouns in turn will give valuable clues to the
                    surrounding textual material both in terms of its semantic content and syntactic
                    function.</p>
                <p>The reports given by the program are only an aid to researchers that takes away
                    some of the tedious spadework necessary for successful decipherment. As such,
                    however, the program is a tool that should speed up the process by allowing
                    scholars to direct their creative efforts towards more demanding tasks.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Yves</forename>
                                    <surname>Duhoux</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Thomas</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Palaima</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">John</forename>
                                    <surname>Bennet</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Problems in Decipherment</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Louvain-la-Neuve</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Peeters</publisher>
                                <date when="1989">1989</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
