<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Using Collaborative Hypermedia to Replace Lectures in
                    University Teaching.</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">David</forename>
                        <surname>Skillicorn</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Queen's University</name>
                            <email>skill@qucis.queensu.ca </email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>courseware</item>
                        <item>hypermedia</item>
                        <item>Hyperware</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>Web-based hypermedia and related technologies have attracted great attention,
                        because they have obvious potential to improve the quality of teaching and
                        learning at universities. The potential benefits include:<list
                            type="bulleted">
                            <item>Increased access for non-traditional students, for whom the
                                traditional university format is impractical;</item>
                            <item>Availability of material at all times and in all places;</item>
                            <item>Responsiveness to students' learning styles by providing material
                                in different ways and at different levels;</item>
                            <item>Incentive to `ratchet up' by capturing the best presentations, the
                                best interactions, the best questions, and preserving them;</item>
                            <item>Student-directed learning rather than professor-directed
                                teaching;</item>
                            <item>Community and interaction based on ideas rather than physical
                                presence.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Many courses have been developed using web pages as the presentation tool,
                        and electronic mail and chat systems as the community-building tool. There
                        are several deficiencies to this approach:<list type="bulleted">
                            <item>The on-line course material is very often 'extra' material,
                                increasing the demands on students;</item>
                            <item>On-line courseware typically costs more, both to develop and to
                                deliver to students;</item>
                            <item>Material is not access-protected, causing loss of revenue for
                                institutions and copyright problems for developers;</item>
                            <item>The use of multiple tools requires students to learn many
                                different interfaces, increasingly the cognitive overhead of the
                                material that they want to learn.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>We have developed several courses using the Hyperwave hypermedia system,
                        developed at the Technical University of Graz in Austria. This system
                        provides a seamless environment in which students can interact with
                        hypermedia material, create their own additions, and communicate with one
                        another and with the instructor. These courses are offered without any
                        lectures, relying solely on interactions within the hypermedia system to
                        convey content and create a learning community. Experience so far has shown
                        that this approach works, and may even produce better learning outcomes than
                        conventional lecture presentations.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>An Introductory Computing Course</head>
                    <p>We illustrate the use of the system using CISC104, an introductory
                        programming and computing science background course, taken by students in
                        all years, and from all departments of the Faculty of Arts and Science. The
                        approach has also been used in 3rd and 4th year courses in Computing
                        Science.</p>
                    <p>Students interact with the course material using an ordinary web browser,
                        such as Netscape. Pages delivered by the Hyperwave server are enhanced with
                        a standard set of buttons that allow users to identify themselves to the
                        system, to create new documents, or to annotate existing documents.</p>
                    <p>Hyperwave hypermedia is organised in two ways: the standard link paradigm is
                        supplemented by a hierarchical collection paradigm. This provides extra
                        context which helps users to avoid the feeling of not knowing where they
                        are. The top level of the course material consists of the following
                            collections:<list type="bulleted">
                            <item>Introductory material about the course,</item>
                            <item>Course home page,</item>
                            <item>Core course material,</item>
                            <item>Announcements,</item>
                            <item>Questions and Answers,</item>
                            <item>Assignments,</item>
                            <item>Exercises,</item>
                            <item>Social Area.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>The core course material was organised into three streams, each partitioned
                        by week. This meant that students could always tell how far they were
                        supposed to have progressed. Each `lecture' consists of textual material,
                        enriched with images, and with regular questions added to make it harder to
                        interact passively with the material.</p>
                    <p>The question and answer area allowed students to ask questions publicly and
                        get them answered, usually within a few hours. Because everyone can see the
                        answers, many students have their questions answered before they were asked.
                        The assignments collection was used to `hand out' the programming
                        assignments, and also to provide solutions after the due date. The exercises
                        collection contained a weekly set of programming exercises and their
                        solutions, to provide suggestions for reinforcing material. The social area
                        allowed students to communicate on non-academic matters.</p>
                    <p>Other aspects of the course were traditional. The instructors had office
                        hours, and teaching assistants were available at scheduled times in their
                        offices and in one of the computing laboratories. Assessment was based on
                        programming assignments, a midterm examination, and a final examination. </p>
                    <p>Student feedback fell into two categories. Some students, probably the
                        majority, found no difficulty with the approach and appreciated the
                        flexibility of delivery. A smaller group felt the absence of lectures
                        keenly, at least at the beginning of the course. Discussions with some of
                        them indicated that they believed, at some level, that lectures caused
                        learning to happen without their active participation. It is easy to see, in
                        retrospect, how such beliefs tend to be fostered by universities, and
                        dispelling them may be the major contribution of technology to learning.
                        Most found it possible to adapt their model of learning and to succeed in
                        the course. Our experiences have been positive, and several more course are
                        migrating to the Hyperwave system.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Why Hyperwave?</head>
                    <p>In the introduction, we indicated several deficiencies of the majority of
                        hypermedia courseware approaches. We summarize how the Hyperwave system, and
                        our incremental approach to development, avoid them.</p>
                    <p>There are three essential aspects to making hypermedia courseware development
                            cost-effective:<list type="bulleted">
                            <item>Courseware must save money somewhere else. It is therefore
                                critical that such courseware <emph rend="italics">replace</emph>
                                other teaching, rather than supplement it.</item>
                            <item>Courseware must be developed incrementally, allowing savings from
                                the very first delivery to be used to fund the next round of
                                development. This makes it possible to start from modest amounts of
                                seed money. Our initial offering of CISC104 required about four
                                months of full-time work by a hypermedia development staff member.
                                Upper-year and seminar courses are much cheaper to develop, since
                                courseware provides perspective rather than content.</item>
                            <item>Courseware does not have to be up to Hollywood standards to be
                                effective, and does not all have to be developed by instructors.
                                Students can make their own contributions to courseware, and such
                                contributions are arguably more useful and impressive to other
                                students. Seminar courses, in particular, can start from a list of
                                the issues, the content being created by the discussions of the
                                participants (which can then be preserved as starting points for
                                subsequent offerings).</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>The problems of controlling access are handled extremely well by the
                        Hyperwave system, which allocates <emph rend="italics">read</emph>,<emph
                            rend="italics"> </emph>, and <emph rend="italics">delete</emph>
                        privileges on a per-collection basis. Thus students can create documents,
                        but not anywhere; and can control whether they are visible to the whole
                        world, the class, a small group within the class, or are entirely
                        private.</p>
                    <p>The Hyperwave system provides a seamless interface with the functionality of
                        a hypermedia browser, chat group, and electronic mail system. Once students
                        have absorbed the basic paradigm, they can do everything related to a course
                        within one environment.</p>
                    <p>The Hyperwave courseware is available for demonstration purposes using the
                        url <ptr target="http://hyperg.queensu.ca"/>. A guest userid and password
                        will be available during the poster sessions.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
