<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="panel">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Root, trunk, and branch: institutional and
                    infrastructural models for humanities computing in the U.K.</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Willard</forename>
                        <surname>McCarty</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">King's College London</name>
                            <email>Willard.McCarty@kcl.ac.uk</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Lou</forename>
                        <surname>Burnard</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Oxford University</name>
                            <email>lou@vax.oxford.ac.uk</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Marilyn</forename>
                        <surname>Deegan</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">De Monfort University</name>
                            <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Glasgow</name>
                            <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Harold</forename>
                        <surname>Short</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">King's College London</name>
                            <email>Harold.Short@kcl.ac.uk</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>institutional humanities computing</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <div>
                        <head>The question</head>
                        <p>In the half-century since humanities computing began, with the work of
                            Roberto Busa, the activities grouped under this rubric have grown in
                            number, sophistication, and institutional importance. They have
                            developed from a loose collection of techniques, often applied as "mere
                            tools" in the pursuit of seemingly unrelated research questions, to what
                            at least some argue is a coherent academic field with its own role to
                            play in research and training of students. Although full- and part-time
                            academic posts are as yet very rare, and dedicated support units in the
                            field are still by no means the norm, academic institutions throughout
                            the world are beginning in a serious way to identify humanities
                            computing as part of their basic mission and institutional profile.
                            Humanities computing plays a major role in the planning of professional
                            associations and international academic bodies such as the British
                            Academy and the American Council of Learned Societies. At this stage it
                            is not entirely clear, however, how the field should best be organised,
                            or indeed how it should be defined and related to the other disciplines
                            and to the support activities with which it is associated.</p>
                        <p>How institutions within the U.K. are dealing with these issues is the
                            broad question this panel seeks to address. It is an important question
                            because good models, which we are in process of discovering, are an
                            invaluable aid to others who wish to bring the benefits of computing,
                            intelligently applied, into their departments and disciplines.
                            Institutions are under considerable pressure to get whatever they do
                            right the first time; this is, as always, truer for the application of
                            technology in the resource-poor humanities than in other disciplines.
                            Proven models are therefore badly needed.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Scope</head>
                        <p>The scope of the panel is limited to the U.K. for practical reasons, but
                            the intention is very much to contribute to an international discussion.
                            Its aim -- ambitious enough -- is a coherent view of what may be
                            possible for humanities computing within one country. The U.K. in fact
                            makes a good case in point, since it is sufficiently small and
                            centralised yet institutionally diverse to form the basis of a
                            manageable study.</p>
                        <p>From within the U.K., three universities with long history of activity in
                            humanities computing are represented -- Glasgow, King's College London,
                            and Oxford -- together with national initiatives, such as the Office for
                            Humanities Communication (OHC), the Computers in Teaching Initiative
                            (CTI), and the Arts and Humanities Data Service (AHDS).</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>History</head>
                        <p>Attention to the institutional issues surrounding humanities computing is
                            possibly as old as the field itself; such issues were, for example, the
                            basis for the creation of Humanist in 1987 and have continued to be
                            among the revisited topics. Panels devoted to the subject have become a
                            regular feature of ACH/ALLC conferences. This panel follows directly,
                            however, from a Colloquium on Humanities Computing, convened in
                            September 1996 by the STELLA Project (Glasgow), King's College London,
                            and De Montfort University to discuss the nature and purpose of the
                            field. Position statements and notes from the Colloquium were put on the
                            Web shortly after the event, and there are immediate plans to use these
                            as stimulus for discussion on Humanist, and thence in further
                            publications. This panel is intended as one means among these others of
                            advancing the discussion.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Structure of the panel</head>
                        <p>Based on the outcome of discussions preceding the Conference, panel
                            members Burnard, Anderson, and Short will be asked first to address the
                            fundamental question of what humanities computing is, then to describe
                            its form at their home institutions and how they see it evolving, with
                            particular attention to the problems and opportunities of their
                            particular model. Deegan will then describe the supra-institutional
                            means in the U.K. for coordinating activities among institutions and
                            representing these both to national agencies and to the international
                            community. McCarty, as chair, will introduce the issues and discussants
                            and following their presentations, sum up and lead a discussion with
                            members of the audience.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Individual statements (in the order of presentation)</head>
                    <div>
                        <p rend="presenter">Lou Burnard</p>
                        <p>Computing support for the arts and humanities at Oxford is provided
                            centrally by the Humanities Computing Unit (HCU) within Oxford
                            University Computing Services (OUCS), whose facilities it complements.
                            The HCU embraces several types of activity and forms of support. It
                            includes a Centre for Humanities Computing (CHC); a nationally-funded
                            CTI Centre for Textual Studies; the Oxford Text Archive, and a number of
                            externally funded research projects, including the British National
                            Corpus (BNC). The objective of the HCU is to serve the students,
                            post-graduates, and staff of the humanities disciplines by providing
                            expertise, training, and consultancy in the uses of information
                            technology; by facilitating and promoting their access to a variety of
                            high-quality scholarly electronic resources for use in research and
                            teaching; and by carrying out research and development in computing as
                            it is applied to the humanities disciplines.</p>
                        <p>The CHC, as the primary centre of local expertise, encourages visits from
                            post-graduates and staff; it also sends its staff to the humanities
                            faculties. It provides these faculties with a range of training, from
                            general introductory sessions to special purpose colloquia and workshops
                            and one-day topical overviews that can be integrated into existing or
                            new lecture series and courses. The national activities, such as the CTI
                            Centre, contribute to the overall strength of the CHC by bringing in
                            wide-ranging knowledge and experience.</p>
                        <p>For the future, the HCU needs to secure funding to establish new and
                            currently temporary posts in IT support, research support, and
                            publications, and to put the infrastructural services on a firm basis.
                            Especially promising is the new position shared between the CHC and the
                            English Faculty.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <p rend="presenter">Jean Anderson</p>
                        <p>My paper will describe the form that computing has taken in the Arts
                            Faculty at the University of Glasgow, what has been achieved, and why we
                            are currently changing our model.</p>
                        <p>While computing in the humanities has a history several decades long at
                            the University of Glasgow, <emph rend="italics">humanities
                                computing</emph> as such is a comparatively new endeavour for us. At
                            Glasgow, computing has been centred in the departments serving specific
                            disciplines. The paper describes the several units which are attached to
                            departments, how the disciplines served by them use computing in their
                            teaching and research, and how these units have expanded to create new
                            opportunities for collaboration between them.</p>
                        <p>This department-centred model is now undergoing a change. Humanities
                            computing methods and techniques have become more sophisticated and
                            inter-disciplinary co-operation is easier and more common. At Glasgow we
                            have developed a trans-disciplinary capacity which is allowing us to
                            pull together these previously disparate groups into one centre. The
                            paper describes our new humanities computing centre, how it continues to
                            support our existing units and why it provides greater opportunity to
                            share and disseminate our expertise and create new projects.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <p rend="presenter">Harold Short</p>
                        <p>The Centre for Computing in the Humanities (CCH), King's College London,
                            is a department in the School of Humanities, with both academic and
                            support responsibilities. It runs a three-year undergraduate minor
                            programme - "Humanities with Applied Computing" - and offers training to
                            post-graduates through workshops and co-supervision of research. (An
                            M.A. programme in humanities computing is currently being designed.) The
                            CCH provides collegial support, in the form of consulting or direct
                            participation, to teaching and research projects within the School, as
                            well as applications and desk-top support to staff, complementing the
                            less discipline-specific services of the Computing Centre.</p>
                        <p>The staffing structure of the CCH has been designed to provide close
                            integration of the academic and support activities, and includes a
                            full-time Director, a Senior Lecturer, a Lecturer, and 3 applications
                            and 3 operational support staff. The department's academic focus is the
                            responsibility of the lecturers, who are expected to contribute to the
                            research profile of the College as well as to teach in the undergraduate
                            programme and participate in collaborative projects.</p>
                        <p>King's College London has a long history of innovation in humanities
                            computing. The CCH represents, however, a new stage in its evolution. It
                            reflects a long-term institutional commitment to the idea that this
                            field is not only an essential part of teaching and learning in the
                            humanities, but that humanities computing also has its own scholarly and
                            intellectual integrity, and that all the disciplines are best served by
                            a model which encompasses both the academic and support elements and
                            embeds them in the academic structure of the institution.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <p rend="presenter">Marilyn Deegan</p>
                        <p>My topic is the national infrastructure for humanities computing and its
                            effects on institutional models such as those described by the other
                            participants.</p>
                        <p>It is important to understand that the UK Higher Education community is a
                            relatively cohesive body compared with other countries like the U.S.
                            Most institutions of higher education in the U.K. receive funding from
                            central government sources and are mandated to operate in a highly
                            controlled fashion. While such centralisation can cause problems, it
                            also offers opportunities for national funding of initiatives that
                            address issues in various subjects throughout all the institutions.
                            Other national funding bodies in the U.K. can also be approached for
                            funds, e.g. the Research and Innovation Centre of the British Library.
                            Two such initiatives have proven especially beneficial in spreading the
                            growth of humanities computing in the U.K. over the last ten years: the
                            CTI, which now funds subject-based centres in many subjects, several in
                            the humanities; and the OHC, now based at King's College London. New,
                            more recent national initiatives in electronic library research and
                            digitization programmes will also have a huge impact on the provision of
                            resources to the humanities community. There are also projects which
                            have been taking advantage of funding provided by the European
                            Union.</p>
                        <p>As a result of these supra-institutional bodies and the projects they
                            have funded, humanities computing fits within a broader national context
                            alongside other fields concerned with providing digital resources, for
                            example. The creation of this national context means that humanities
                            computing has moved from a specialized area, the concern of only a few
                            researchers, to the mainstream of humanistic practice and discourse.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
