<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Multi-Authorship of the <title level="m">Scriptores
                        Historiae Augustae</title>: How the Use of Subsets Can Win or Lose the
                    Case.</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Penelope</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Gurney</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Ottawa</name>
                            <email>pgurney@uottawa.ca</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Lyman</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">W.</forename>
                        <surname>Gurney</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Themis Research Corporation</name>
                            <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>stylometry</item>
                        <item>statistical analysis</item>
                        <item>computer methods</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <p>This paper describes recent research that we have carried out on the
                        arbitration of disputed authorship attribution. In an earlier study, we
                        lemmatized and disambiguated fully the thirty biographies of the <title
                            level="m">Scriptores Historiae Augustae</title>, and the results of the
                        analysis of that work have provided us with a benchmark and control group
                        for further analysis of two major related questions:<list>
                            <item>* Can statistical analysis be based successfully upon the argument
                                that "... stylometric theory posits the existence of homogeneity
                                within a single work by a single author." (Ledger &amp; Merriam,
                                1994).</item>
                            <item>* Does such homogeneity imply that stylometric analysis of a
                                subset can be equivalent to the analysis of the whole?</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>This paper thus extends the reach of our previous research on the analysis of
                        fully lemmatized and disambiguated texts, and describes general problems
                        that occur when subsets of the main text are to be compared in place of the
                        entire text. It thus attempts to lay out ground rules for application of our
                        techniques to texts of lengths that are too extensive for complete manual
                        disambiguation.</p>
                    <p>The importance of the SHA to historians derives from the simple fact that it
                        is a critically important "source" of historical information for much of the
                        tumultuous period leading up to the reign of Constantine the Great, the
                        first Christian emperor of the Roman Empire. The need for stylometric
                        analyses of the texts is based upon the understanding that the usefulness of
                        this set of imperial biographies would be increased greatly if it could be
                        demonstrated that there was but a single mind, and hence but a single human
                        frame of reference for the historical information included; and therefore
                        that the multitude of fabrications and apparently deliberately false
                        statements that infect this irreplaceable work can be treated and allowed
                        for as the creations of but one individual mind. A demonstration of multiple
                        authorship, on the contrary, would imply a disjointed effort of authorship
                        which would be immeasurably more difficult to integrate into a coherent
                        history of those turbulent times.</p>
                    <p>Extensive historical analysis carried out over the past century has resulted
                        in near complete acceptance of the concept of single authorship of the SHA.
                        Our recent research, however, described in an earlier paper (Gurney
                        &amp; Gurney, 1996), and based entirely on internal stylometric methods,
                        shows, to a rather high degree of statistical confidence, that the
                        attribution in the manuscripts to the six otherwise unknown authors is
                        probably based upon historical fact.</p>
                    <p>The initial lemmatization and disambiguation of the SHA was taken to
                        completion, since we could find no proof that subsets are equivalent to the
                        full texts in stylometric analysis. The concept of homogeneity had usually
                        been stated explicitly or implicitly (Ledger &amp; Merriam, 1994), but
                        has apparently not actually been put to the test (Kenny, 1986), although the
                        size of the subsets has been a matter for discussion (Ellegård, 1962;
                        Burrows &amp; Craig, 1994). Hence we completed this highly
                        labour-intensive task of full disambiguation of the more than 100,000 words
                        of text, using techniques described in an earlier conference on the analysis
                        of frequency of use of vocabulary of different kinds, including function
                        words, conjunctions, the most frequently used vocabulary, and the rate of
                        introduction of new lemmas for each 100 words (Gurney &amp; Gurney,
                        1994).</p>
                    <p>The importance of the <title level="m">Scriptores Historiae Augustae</title>
                        for an attempted understanding of the critical years leading to the era of
                        Constantine and his successors has justified the expenditure of the time and
                        effort involved in the complete lemmatization and manual disambiguation of
                        the text. Such effort is impracticable, however, in texts that run to many
                        hundreds of thousands of words; and for that reason, we have recently
                        developed a new line of research. In this system, our avenue of approach is
                        to make repeated random and non-random choices of subsets of target texts,
                        and to attempt to determine if the results of statistical analyses based
                        upon these chosen subsets are essentially statistically equivalent to those
                        produced by the entire texts.</p>
                    <p>The question of the alternative use of subsets became much more urgent when
                        we embarked upon the course of TEI-compatible tagging of all parts of speech
                        in the SHA, and upon the disambiguation and tagging of its earlier model,
                        the <title level="m">Lives of the Twelve Caesars</title> of Gaius Suetonius
                        Tranquillus, a work of just under 100,000 words that comprises the
                        biographies of the first twelve emperors of Rome. This work of Suetonius is
                        intended to act as a control work to the SHA in our further study of
                        authorship of imperial biographies.</p>
                    <p>We therefore began analyses of various subsets of the works, in comparison
                        with comparable analyses of the entire text, in an attempt to determine if
                        it is accurate to state that a given text by a given author will be
                        internally homogeneous to the point that subsets of itself can be
                        demonstrated to be congruent to it, in the face of stylometric comparison
                        with other works of the same author, or of other authors, or even with each
                        other, and with the full text.</p>
                    <p>The new analysis required production of a new series of subset texts. First
                        came the reduction of each text to a single sentence per disk record. Each
                        of these files was created in three different forms, each with a different
                        combination of sentence-delimiters to determine sentence-length: full stop,
                        full-stop plus semi-colon, and that pair plus full-colon. In this way, we
                        attempted to circumvent the problems of the differences of definition of
                        sentence-length between classical times and the modern, and also between
                        interpretations of editors from differing modern language groups, such as
                        the difference in usage of the semi-colon between German and
                        English-speaking editors (Janson, 1964). Initial analyses demonstrated that
                        the use of the set of three delimiters gives acceptable results, and hence
                        all further research was conducted on sentences that were determined by
                        those three delimiters.</p>
                    <p>From these files, three new groups of files were created for comparison with
                        the original 30. First, 120 files consisting of the four quarters of each
                        text were compiled, in addition to 60 files containing each half. Second, a
                        set of 30 files containing exactly the first 500 words of text was
                        developed. And finally, two sets of 30 files were created, each file
                        containing one-quarter of all sentences of a specific biography of the SHA,
                        chosen randomly from that text (by the linear congruence method of the ICON
                        language): in one set, the file consists of sentences selected from the
                        entire text; and in the other, with sentences chosen in equal numbers from
                        each individual quarter of the text. These randomly-selected files were
                        generated as controls for several reasons, one obtaining from the fact that
                        it is apparent that sentence-length, in general, decreases slightly in each
                        successive quarter of the biographies.</p>
                    <p>The 270 new subset biographies, in their logical groups of 30, were then
                        passed to an application system that generates a large number of matrices of
                        data in a form suitable for transmission to SAS and SPSS.</p>
                    <p>The original techniques that had given striking results in analysis of the 30
                        complete biographies were next applied to the various matrices that had been
                        created from the subsets.</p>
                    <p>We also applied the techniques to an analysis of sentence-length
                        distributions in the SHA, as some previous researchers have attempted to do.
                        We found, however, that, even in the entire text, there is so little
                        stylometric information encoded in apparent sentence-length, that scarcely
                        more than random distribution can be found.</p>
                    <p>One new type of analysis was also applied, to good effect: that of treating
                        the 4 one-quarter biographies of each original biography as if they were
                        fragments of different works of the same attributed author. By this device,
                        it appears to be possible to ascertain if certain fractions of a work are
                        functionally equivalent to the whole, and if the whole work is cohesive,
                        coherent, uniform and stylometrically homogeneous.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Results</head>
                    <p>The first results demonstrated that the structure of a work, something which
                        a reader recognizes subjectively, appears to be reflected in the stylometric
                        analysis: for the various subsets of a work are not necessarily homogeneous;
                        and the various quarters appear to be incompatible, to various degrees, one
                        with another. For example, the seven works by Spartianus, studied as
                        quarter-works, became twenty-eight works, which can be analyzed in the same
                        manner as the original thirty. The only measure, however, which gives
                        results even remotely comparable to those of the original text, is the
                        analysis of the usage of conjunctions, in which the set of final quarters of
                        the seven texts stands off very clearly from the others. This demonstrates a
                        major drawback to the use of the subsets, however, since it is clear that
                        the only means by which the results of the final quarter can be seen to be
                        relevant and important, is by use of the fully-disambiguated original text
                        as control: the subsets cannot be used as controls for themselves.</p>
                    <p>In the half-text analyses, one test, that of the 15 most frequently used
                        lemmas which appear in each of the 30 segments, gave almost complete
                        differentiation; but most of the other tests gave very indifferent
                        results.</p>
                    <p>In the analysis of function words in the 500-word segments, there was good
                        differentiation of only three authors: Capitolinus, Spartianus, and
                        Lampridius.</p>
                    <p>The various quarter-texts provided mixed results: on one test, quarter #1
                        provided some differentiation of specific authors; whereas on a different
                        test, and different quarter, other authors were separated. Hence, it is
                        clear that no one test on subsets can provide clear discrimination of
                        authorship, although many do appear to demonstrate a degree of multiple
                        authorship.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Discussion of Results</head>
                    <p>As the various analyses were carried out, several points became clear:<list>
                            <item>* The larger the size of the subset in relation to the full text,
                                the better the result;</item>
                            <item>* Any increases above the minimum possible number of key words
                                used to generate full differentiation of authorship in the full
                                texts produced only slight increases in the degree of
                                differentiation. Such increases, when applied to the subsets,
                                however, generated large increases in differentiating power, but
                                without reaching anything near the degree of resolution of the full
                                texts; and in no case was the discrimination clear-cut.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>It is very clear from the analysis that, had only small segments of the texts
                        been chosen for analysis, then a hypothesis of multiple authorship could not
                        have been confirmed; it is only the full lemmatization and disambiguation of
                        the entire text which has permitted such a conclusion.</p>
                    <p>It is further evident from this study that the two questions raised for study
                        have both been answered in the negative, namely:<list>
                            <item>* There appears to be no homogeneity within any specific work of
                                an individual author; rather, each work is suffused with sufficient
                                variety internally as to maintain the interest of the reader. This
                                variety may be the fundamental cause for analysis of small subsets
                                not to be equivalent to analysis of the whole.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>A fundamental conclusion of this experiment is, therefore, that, although it
                        is not permitted to extrapolate, in general, from one experiment on one set
                        of texts, to the stylometrics of other authors and languages, it
                        nevertheless appears clearly necessary, for any research project that
                        intends to use subsets of a text, to ensure that those subsets are
                        stylometrically homogeneous with the full text - a probability, given the
                        results of this experiment, which does not appear to be high.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">F.</forename>
                                    <surname>Burrows</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Craig</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Lyrical Drama and the "Turbid Mountebanks": Styles of
                                Dialogue in Romantic and Renaissance Tragedy</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">28</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">63-86</biblScope>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Ellegård</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">A Statistical Method for Determining Authorship. The
                                "Junius" Letters, 1769-1772</title>
                            <title level="s">Acta Universitatis Gothoburgensis</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Göteborg</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1962">1962</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Gurney</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Gurney</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Enhanced Content-Analysis of Inflected Languages
                                Through a System of Computer Assisted Lemmatization</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">Presented at 'Consensus ex Machina?'. ALLC/ACH, Paris,
                                19-23 April</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Gurney</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Gurney</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Disputed Authorship: 30 Biographies and Six Reputed
                                Authors. A New Analysis by Full-Text Lemmatization of the <title
                                    level="m">Historia Augusta</title></title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">Presented at ALLC/ACH '96. Bergen, June 25-29</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <surname>Janson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">The Problems of Measuring Sentence-Length in Classical
                                Texts</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Studia Linguistica </title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">18</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">26-36</biblScope>
                                <date when="1964">1964</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Kenney</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">A Stylometric Study of the New Testament</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1986">1986</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Ledger</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">V.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">N.</forename>
                                    <surname>Merriam</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Shakespeare, Fletcher, and the Two Noble
                                Kinsmen</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">9</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">235-248</biblScope>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
