<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="panel">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The State of Authorship Attribution Studies: (1) The
                    History and the Scope; (2) The Problems -- Towards Credibility and Validity. </title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Joe</forename>
                        <surname>Rudman</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Carnegie Mellon University</name>
                            <email>rudman@cmphys.phys.cmu.edu </email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">David</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">I.</forename>
                        <surname>Holmes</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of the West of England</name>
                            <email>david.holmes@csm.uwe.ac.uk</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Fiona</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Tweedie</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Glasgow, United Kingdom</name>
                            <email>fiona@stats.gla.ac.uk</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">Harald</forename>
                        <surname>Baayen</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Max Planck Institute for Psycholinguistics</name>
                            <email>baayen@mpi.nl</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>authorship attribution</item>
                        <item>stylistics</item>
                        <item>statistics</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Session Abstract</head>
                    <p>There are many serious problems with the science of authorship attribution
                        studies. This session proposes to look at the history of the field, identify
                        many of the more major problems, and offer some solutions that will go a
                        long way towards giving the field credibility and validity.</p>
                    <p>Willard McCarty's recent posting on "Humanist" (Vol. 10, No. 137)
                        "Communication and Memory" points out one of these problems, "...scholarship
                        in the field is significantly inhibited, I would argue, by the low degree to
                        which previous work in humanities computing and current work in related
                        fields is known and recognized."</p>
                    <p>A major indication that there are problems in a field is when there is no
                        consensus as to correct methodology or technique. Every area of authorship
                        attribution studies has this problem -- research, experimental set-up,
                        linguistic methods, statistical methods....</p>
                    <p>It seems that for every paper announcing an authorship attribution method
                        that "works" or a variation of one of these methods, there is a counter
                        paper pointing out crucial flaws:<list type="bulleted">
                            <item>Donald McNeil points out that scientists disagree as to Zipf's
                                law;</item>
                            <item>Christian Delcourt raises objections against current practice in
                                co-occurrence analysis;</item>
                            <item>Portnoy and Petersen show errors in Radday and Wickmann's use of
                                the correlation coefficient, chi-squared test, and t-test;</item>
                            <item>Hilton and Holmes showed problems in Morton's QSUM
                                techniques;</item>
                            <item>Smith raised many objections against Morton's early
                                methods;</item>
                            <item>There is Merriam vs Smith;</item>
                            <item>There is Foster vs Elliott and Valenza.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>This widespread disagreement has not only kept authorship attribution studies
                        out of most United States court proceedings, but it also threatens to
                        undermine even the legitimate studies in the court of public and
                        professional opinion.</p>
                    <p>The time has come to sit back, review, digest, and then present a theoretical
                        framework to guide future authorship attribution studies.</p>
                    <p>The first paper, by David Holmes, will give the necessary history, scope, and
                        present direction of authorship attribution studies with particular emphasis
                        on recent trends.</p>
                    <p>The second paper, by Harald Baayen and Fiona Tweedie, will focus on one
                        problem: the use of so-called constants in authorship attribution
                        questions.</p>
                    <p>The third paper, by Joseph Rudman, will point out some of the problems that
                        are keeping authorship attribution studies from being universally accepted
                        and will offer suggestions on how these problems can be overcome.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>Stylometry: Its Origins, Development and Aspirations.</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">David I. Holmes</p>
                        <div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Introduction</head>
                                <p>This paper is the opening paper in the session on stylometry and
                                    aims to review the historical development of stylometry up to
                                    and including its current standing as a statistical tool within
                                    the humanities.</p>
                                <p>Stylometry - the statistical analysis of literary style -
                                    complements traditional literary scholarship since it offers a
                                    means of capturing the often elusive character of an author's
                                    style by quantifying some of its features. Most stylometric
                                    studies employ items of language and most of these items are
                                    lexically based. A sound exposition of the rationale behind such
                                    studies has been provided by Laan (1995).</p>
                                <p> The main assumption underlying stylometric studies is that
                                    authors have an unconscious as well as a conscious aspect to
                                    their style. Every author's style is thought to have certain
                                    features that are independent of the author's will, and since
                                    these features cannot be consciously manipulated by the author,
                                    they are considerd to provide the most reliable data for a
                                    stylometric study. The two primary applications are
                                    attributional studies and chronological problems, yet a
                                    difference in date or author is not the only possible
                                    explanation for stylistic peculiarities. Variation in style can
                                    be caused by differences of genre or content, and similarity by
                                    literary processes such as imitation.</p>
                                <p>By measuring and counting stylistic traits, we hope to discover
                                    the 'characteristics' of a particular author. This paper looks
                                    at criteria which may serve as a basis of measurement within the
                                    context of stylometry's origins and historical development.</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Word-length and sentence-length</head>
                                <p>The origins of stylometry may be traced back to the work of
                                    Mendenhall (1887) on word-lengths and the idea of counting
                                    features of a text was extended by Yule (1938) to include
                                    sentence-lengths. Morton (1965) used sentence-lengths for tests
                                    of authorship of Greek prose, but we now know that neither of
                                    these measures are wholly reliable indicators of authorship.</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Function words</head>
                                <p>Word-usage offers a great many opportunities for discrimination.
                                    Some words vary considerably in their rate of use from one work
                                    to another by the same author, others show remarkable stability
                                    within an author. For discrimination purposes we need
                                    context-free or 'function' words and this paper reviews the
                                    seminal work of Mosteller and Wallace (1964) on function word
                                    frequencies. Morton (1978) developed techniques of studying the
                                    position and immediate context of individual word-occurrences
                                    but his method has, however, come under much criticism and Smith
                                    (1985) has demonstrated that it cannot reliably distinguish
                                    between the works of Elizabethan and Jacobean playwrights.</p>
                                <p> The idea of using sets (at least 50 strong) of common
                                    high-frequency words and conducting what is essentially a
                                    principal components analysis on the data has been developed by
                                    Burrows (1987) and represents a landmark in the development of
                                    stylometry. The technique is very much in vogue now as a
                                    reliable stylometric procedure and Holmes and Forsyth (1995)
                                    have successfully applied it to the classic 'Federalist Papers'
                                    problem. Examples of the technique will be displayed.</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Vocabulary distributions</head>
                                <p>One of the fundamental notions in stylometry is the measurement
                                    of what is termed the 'richness' or 'diversity' of an author's
                                    vocabulary. If we sample a text produced by a writer we might
                                    expect the extent of his/her vocabulary to be reflected in the
                                    frequency profile of word-usage. This paper reviews measures
                                    which may be thought of as 'indices of diversity'.</p>
                                <p>Mathematical models for the frequency distributions of the number
                                    of vocabulary items appearing exactly r times (r=1,2,3....) have
                                    aroused the interest of statisticians ever since the work of
                                    Zipf (1932). The best fitting model appears to be that
                                    attributed to Sichel (1975) and this paper will cover the Sichel
                                    model in addition to looking at the behaviour of the
                                    once-occurring words (hapax legomena) and twice-occurring words
                                    (hapax dislegomena) as useful stylometric tools.</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Content analysis</head>
                                <p>Content analysis refers to tabulating the frequency of types of
                                    words in a text, the aim being to reach the denotative or
                                    connotative meaning of the text. Although content analysis
                                    should be useful in stylometry it has seldom been employed, but
                                    this paper will review the successful application of content
                                    analysis to the 'Federalist' problem by Martindale and McKenzie
                                    (1995).</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Neural networks</head>
                                <p>Stylometry is essentially a case of pattern recognition. Neural
                                    networks have the ability to recognise the underlying
                                    organisation of data which is of vital importance for any
                                    pattern recognition problem, so their application in stylometry
                                    is both inevitable and welcome. The results achieved by Merriam
                                    and Matthews (1994) and by Lowe and Matthews (1995) will be
                                    discussed.</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>The future</head>
                                <p>As the amount of available computer-readable literary texts
                                    continues to increase, we can expect expansion in the use of
                                    automated pattern recognition techniques, such as neural
                                    networks, to act as 'assistants' to help in the resolution of
                                    outstanding authorship disputes. Automated feature finders will
                                    be developed (Forsyth and Holmes, 1996) to let the computer take
                                    over the task of finding the features that best discriminate
                                    between two candidate authors for a disputed text. There will be
                                    theoretical advances too, as in the change from lexically based
                                    techniques to syntactic annotation proposed by Baayen, Van
                                    Halteren and Tweedie (1996).</p>
                                <p>Stylometry, though, presents no threat to traditional
                                    scholarship. In the context of authorship attribution,
                                    stylometric evidence must be weighed in the balance along with
                                    that provided by more conventional studies made by literary
                                    scholars.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="bibliography">
                        <head>References</head>
                        <listBibl>
                            <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="middle">H.</forename>
                                            <surname>Baayen</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">H.</forename>
                                            <surname>Van Halteren</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">F.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                            <surname>Tweedie</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">Outside the Cave of Shadows: Using Syntactic
                                        Annotation to Enhance Authorship Attribution</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <biblScope type="vol">11</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">121-131</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">F.</forename>
                                            <surname>Burrows</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">Word Patterns and Story Shapes: The Statistical
                                        Analysis of Narrative Style</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <biblScope type="vol">2</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">61-70</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1987">1987</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                                            <surname>Forsyth</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">I.</forename>
                                            <surname>Holmes</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">Feature-Finding for Text Classification</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <biblScope type="vol">11</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="issue">4</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="pp"/>
                                        <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">I.</forename>
                                            <surname>Holmes</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                                            <surname>Forsyth</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">The 'Federalist' Revisited: New Directions in
                                        Authorship Attribution</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <biblScope type="vol">10</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">111-127</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1995">1995</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">N.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">M.</forename>
                                            <surname>Laan</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">Stylometry and Method. The Case of
                                        Euripides</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <biblScope type="vol">10</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">271-278</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1995">1995</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                            <surname>Lowe</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                            <surname>Matthews</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">Shakespeare vs. Fletcher: A Stylometric
                                        Analysis by Radial Basis Functions</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <biblScope type="vol">29</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">449-461</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1995">1995</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                            <surname>Martindale</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                            <surname>McKenzie</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">On the Utility of Content Analysis in Author
                                        Attribution: The 'Federalist'</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <title level="j">Computers in the Humanities</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <biblScope type="vol">29</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">259-270</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1995">1995</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">C.</forename>
                                            <surname>Mendenhall</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">The Characteristic Curves of
                                        Composition</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <title level="j">Science</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <biblScope type="vol">IX</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">237-249</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1887">1887</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                            <surname>Merriam</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                            <surname>Matthews</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">Neural Computation in Stylometry II: An
                                        Application to the Works of Shakespeare and Marlowe</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <biblScope type="vol">9</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">1-6</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1994">1994</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">Q.</forename>
                                            <surname>Morton</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">The Authorship of Greek Prose</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <title level="j">Journal of the Royal Statistical Society
                                        (A)</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <biblScope type="vol">128</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">169-233</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1965">1965</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="book">
                                <monogr>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">Q.</forename>
                                            <surname>Morton</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="m">Literary Detection</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Scribners</publisher>
                                        <date when="1978">1978</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="book">
                                <monogr>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">F.</forename>
                                            <surname>Mosteller</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
                                            <surname>Wallace</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="m">Inference and Disputed Authorship: The
                                        Federalist</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <pubPlace>Reading</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher>
                                        <date when="1964">1964</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">H.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                                            <surname>Sichel</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">On a Distribution Law for Word
                                        Frequencies</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <title level="j">Journal of the American Statistical
                                        Association</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <biblScope type="vol">70</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">542-547</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1975">1975</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">W.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                                            <surname>Smith</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">An Investigation of Morton's Method to
                                        Distinguish Elizabethan Playwrights</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <biblScope type="vol">19</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">3-21</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1985">1985</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">U.</forename>
                                            <surname>Yule</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">On Sentence Length as a Statistical
                                        Characteristic of Style in Prose with Application to Two
                                        Cases of Disputed Authorship</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <title level="j">Biometrika</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <biblScope type="vol">30</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">363-390</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1938">1938</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="book">
                                <monogr>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">K.</forename>
                                            <surname>Zipf</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="m">Selected Studies of the Principle of Relative
                                        Frequency in Language</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <pubPlace/>
                                        <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                                        <date when="1932">1932</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                        </listBibl>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>Lexical `constants' in stylometry and authorship studies </head>
                        <p rend="presenter">Fiona J. Tweedie</p>
                        <p rend="presenter">R. Harald Baayen</p>
                        <div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Introduction</head>
                                <p>Various measures of lexical richness have been employed in
                                    stylometry and authorship attribution (see, e.g., Holmes, 1994,
                                    for a review). These measures have been advanced as
                                    characteristic constants whose value is not influenced by the
                                    text size. This study investigates in detail to what extent
                                    these measures are truly constant, how well they are suited for
                                    discriminating authors, and to what extent the values assumed by
                                    these measures are influenced by discourse structure (see
                                    Baayen, 1996).</p>
                                <p>Text constants have been developed because the simplest measure
                                    of lexical richness, the vocabulary size V(N), varies with the
                                    number of tokens in the text, N. In order to remove this
                                    dependency, constants have been proposed that are supposed to be
                                    independent of N. These range from the simple type-token ratio
                                    to more complex measures such as Orlov's Zipf size (Orlov,
                                    1983).</p>
                                <p>Combinations of these constants have been used to investigate
                                    problems of authorship (see for example Holmes, 1992 and Baayen
                                    et al, 1996). The latter discriminated two authors at lexical
                                    and syntactic levels using analyses of function words and
                                    lexical richness. They found that function words performed
                                    better than the constants at both levels, and that the inclusion
                                    of syntactic information improved the discrimination. Baayen et
                                    al. (1996) concluded that considering the text at a more
                                    abstract level, using the reduced variability of the syntactic
                                    vocabulary, increases the efficacy of the techniques.
                                    Nevertheless, the constants also tap into stylistic properties
                                    of texts at a fairly abstract level. In order to properly
                                    evaluate the discriminatory potential of the text constants, we
                                    must clarify whether and how effectively they capture
                                    similarities and differences between authors, and to what extent
                                    they are truly constant.</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Validity - Are the Constants Constant?</head>
                                <p>Figure 1 shows plots of 4 constants for Carroll's <title
                                        level="m">Alice in Wonderland</title> that illustrate the
                                    main patterns in our survey of 15 measures of lexical richness.
                                    Measurements have been taken at 20 equally-spaced points in the
                                    text. The first panel shows Brunet's W to be an increasing
                                    function of the text size. The second plot, that of Honore's H,
                                    initially appears unstable, but less variable above N=13,000.
                                    The lower plots show Sichel's S and Yule's K; S is quite
                                    variable while K descends sharply from its initial value, then
                                    rises with N.</p>
                                <figure>
                                    <head>Figure 1</head>
                                </figure>
                                <p>To evaluate the extent to which violation of the randomness
                                    assumption is responsible for the observed variability in the
                                    values of the `constants', the order of words in the texts was
                                    completely randomised and the measurements retaken. One hundred
                                    such randomisations were carried out.. The means of the
                                    randomisations are shown as points, the maxima and minima by +
                                    and - respectively. Crucially, only the mean values for K
                                    indicate that its value is theoretically truly constant for
                                    randomised text; those for W and H increase and decrease with
                                    text size, while S rises then decreases. It is clear from these
                                    graphs, both of the actual and randomised texts, that far from
                                    being stable, the constants are as variable as V, the variable
                                    that they were intended to replace.</p>
                                <p>In sum, with the exception of K and possibly the Zipf size,
                                    constants are not constant in theory, and, without exception,
                                    none are constant in practice. The empirical values of the
                                    constants are co-determined by the way in which the randomness
                                    assumption is violated in running text, namely by coherence in
                                    lexical use at the discourse level (see Baayen, 1996).</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Developmental Profiles</head>
                                <p>Thus far we have considered a single text. It is possible that
                                    the variability we have observed is very small when compared to
                                    other texts and that discrimination is still possible between
                                    authors. In order to investigate this we analysed a total of
                                    fifteen texts, detailed in Table 1.</p>
                                <p>The resulting graphs for W, H, S and K are shown in Figure 2.
                                    Examining the first plot, it can be seen that, while the value
                                    of W varies with N, texts by the same author vary in the same
                                    way; the Carroll texts are coincident, as are the James texts
                                    and two of the Conan Doyle texts. It is also clear that this is
                                    not necessarily the case; the Baum texts are widely separated,
                                    as is the third Conan Doyle text from the other pair. A similar
                                    structure is found in the graph of H, with slightly different
                                    orderings. Turning to S, however, we find that the constant is
                                    so variable that it is impossible to separate authors, even at
                                    larger text sizes. The plot of K again yields a pattern in which
                                    texts are fairly well separated. The different ordering of the
                                    texts in this graph indicates that K is measuring a different
                                    facet of the lexical structure of these texts. The Conan Doyle
                                    texts now group together, as do the Baum texts, but now the
                                    Carroll texts diverge.</p>
                                <figure>
                                    <head>Figure 2</head>
                                </figure>
                                <p>We have calculated the values for fifteen lexical richness
                                    constants and found that the resulting profiles could be
                                    classified into four families, exemplified in the graphs above.
                                    The largest family of constants is that to which W belongs.
                                    Honore's H represents a much smaller family. S comprises the
                                    family of constants that are of no discriminatory value. K makes
                                    up a family with D, variables that are theoretically constant
                                    given the urn model of word distribution within text. Some texts
                                    that are separated in the other families are coincident in this
                                    family, others are more divergent.</p>
                                <p>It is clear from the above that several constants measure the
                                    same facet of the vocabulary structure. Thus, only those
                                    constants with the greatest discriminatory sensitivity within a
                                    given family need to be considered. The developmental profiles
                                    of the constants show sensitivity to authorship, although this
                                    is not absolute in that texts written by the same author may
                                    diverge. We have also developed techniques for evaluating the
                                    statistical significance of patterns of similarity and
                                    dissimilarity in the developmental curves. While the variance of
                                    most constants is not known, so that comparisons on the basis of
                                    constants for full texts remain impressionistic, we can now
                                    evaluate in a more precise way whether or not the developmental
                                    profile of a constant differentiates between texts.</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Conclusions</head>
                                <p>Almost all textual constants in our survey are highly variable,
                                    and assume values that change systematically as the text size is
                                    increased. Some constants are inherently variable, others are
                                    truly constant in theory. All constants are substantially
                                    influenced by the non-random way in which word usage is governed
                                    by discourse cohesion. This variability indicates that the
                                    constants cannot be relied on to compare texts of different
                                    lengths. Crucially, however, the developmental profiles of the
                                    majority of constants have an interesting discriminatory
                                    potential, in that they reveal consistent and interpretable
                                    patterns that pick up author-specific aspects of word use.</p>
                                <p>For authorship attribution studies, we strongly recommend the use
                                    of the developmental profiles of selected constants, rather than
                                    the isolated values of the constants for complete texts. Our
                                    data shows, however, that authors are not `prisoners' of their
                                    own developmental profile. The discourse structure of texts by
                                    the same author can be quite different, and the same holds for
                                    the kind of vocabulary an author exploits for a given text.
                                    Compared to the use of syntax, word use is more easily
                                    influenced by choices which are under the conscious control of
                                    authors. Consequently, the developmental profiles of constants
                                    are less reliable than syntax-based measures for the purpose of
                                    authorship attribution. At the same time, the developmental
                                    profiles capture essential differences in word use and discourse
                                    structure. From this perspective, we would like to defend their
                                    usefulness in the domain of quantitative stylistics.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="bibliography">
                        <head>References</head>
                        <listBibl>
                            <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">H.</forename>
                                            <surname>Baayen</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">The Randomness Assumption in Word Frequency
                                        Statistics</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <editor>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                            <surname>Perissinotto</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </editor>
                                    <title level="m">Research in Humanities Computing</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <biblScope type="vol">5</biblScope>
                                        <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
                                        <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">17-31</biblScope>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">H.</forename>
                                            <surname>Baayen</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">H.</forename>
                                            <surname>van Halteren</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">F.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                            <surname>Tweedie</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">Outside the Cave of Shadows: Using syntactic
                                        annotation to enhance authorship attribution</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <biblScope type="vol">11</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">121-131</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">I.</forename>
                                            <surname>Holmes</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">A Stylometric Analysis of Mormon Scripture and
                                        Related Texts</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <title level="j">Journal of the Royal Statistical Society Series
                                        A</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <biblScope type="vol">155</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">91-120</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1992">1992</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">I.</forename>
                                            <surname>Holmes</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">Authorship Attribution</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <biblScope type="vol">28</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">87-106</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1994">1994</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">K.</forename>
                                            <surname>Orlov</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">Ein Model der hufigskeitstruktur des
                                        Vokabulars</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <editor>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">H.</forename>
                                            <surname>Guiter</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </editor>
                                    <editor>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                            <surname>Arapov</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </editor>
                                    <title level="m">Studies in Zipf's Law</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <pubPlace>Bochum</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Brockmeyer</publisher>
                                        <date when="1983">1983</date>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">154-233</biblScope>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                        </listBibl>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <table cols="3" rows="16">
                            <head>
                                <emph rend="bold">Table 1: Texts used in this study</emph>
                            </head>
                            <row>
                                <cell role="label">Author</cell>
                                <cell role="label">Title</cell>
                                <cell role="label">Key</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Baum, L. F.</cell>
                                <cell>The Wonderful Wizard of Oz</cell>
                                <cell>b1</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Tip Manufactures a Pumpkinhead</cell>
                                <cell>b2</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Carroll, L.</cell>
                                <cell>Alice's Adventures in Wonderland</cell>
                                <cell>a1</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Through the Looking-glass and<lb/>what Alice found
                                    there</cell>
                                <cell>a2</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Conan Doyle, A.</cell>
                                <cell>The Hound of the Baskervilles</cell>
                                <cell>c1</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>The Valley of Fear</cell>
                                <cell>c2</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>The Sign of Four</cell>
                                <cell>c3</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>James,</cell>
                                <cell>Confidence</cell>
                                <cell>j1</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>The Europeans</cell>
                                <cell>j2</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>St Luke</cell>
                                <cell>Gospel according to St Luke (KJV)</cell>
                                <cell>L1</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>Acts of the Apostles (KJV)</cell>
                                <cell>L2</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>London, J.</cell>
                                <cell>The Sea Wolf</cell>
                                <cell>l1</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>The Call of the Wild</cell>
                                <cell>l2</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell>Wells, H. G.</cell>
                                <cell>The War of the Worlds</cell>
                                <cell>w1</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>The Invisible Man</cell>
                                <cell>w2</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>The State of Authorship Attribution Studies: Problems and
                            Solutions.</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">Joseph Rudman</p>
                        <div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Introduction:</head>
                                <p>There are major problems in the science of "non-traditional"
                                    authorship attribution studies (those using statistics and the
                                    computer). This paper will show that the problems exist, will
                                    list and explain some of the more major problems, and will offer
                                    some suggestions on how these problems can be resolved.</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Problems exist:</head>
                                <p>Non-traditional authorship attribution research has had enough
                                    time and effort -- well over 300 studies and 30 years -- to pass
                                    through the "shake-down" phase and enter one marked by steady,
                                    solid, and scientific studies that force a consensus among its
                                    practitioners.</p>
                                <p>A major indication that there are problems in a field is when
                                    there is no consensus as to correct methodology or technique.
                                    Every area of authorship attribution studies has this problem --
                                    e.g. research, experimental set-up, linguistic methods,
                                    statistical methods.</p>
                                <p>It seems that for every paper announcing an authorship
                                    attribution method that "works" or a variation of one of these
                                    methods, there is a counter paper pointing out crucial flaws,
                                        e.g.:<list type="bulleted">
                                        <item>Donald McNeil points out that scientists disagree as
                                            to Zipf's law;</item>
                                        <item>Christian Delcourt raises objections against current
                                            practice in co-occurrence analysis;</item>
                                        <item>Portnoy and Petersen show errors in Radday and
                                            Wickmann's use of the correlation coefficient,
                                            chi-squared test, and t-test;</item>
                                        <item>Hilton and Holmes showed problems in Morton's QSUM
                                            techniques;</item>
                                        <item>Smith raised many objections against Morton's early
                                            methods;</item>
                                        <item>There is Merriam vs Smith;</item>
                                        <item>There is Foster vs Elliott and Valenza.</item>
                                    </list></p>
                                <p>This widespread disagreement has not only kept authorship
                                    attribution studies out of most United States court proceedings,
                                    but it also threatens to undermine even the legitimate studies
                                    in the court of public and professional opinion.</p>
                                <p>Most authorship attribution studies have been governed by
                                    expediency, e.g.:<list type="bulleted">
                                        <item>The text is not what should be used but it was
                                            available. </item>
                                        <item>This is not how the data should have been treated but
                                            the packaged program didn't do exactly what was
                                            needed.</item>
                                        <item>The control data isn't complete but it would have
                                            taken too long to input the correct data.</item>
                                    </list></p>
                                <p>There is a lack of experimental memory. Researchers working in
                                    the same "area" of authorship attribution fail to cite and make
                                    use of pertinent previous efforts. Willard McCarty's recent
                                    posting on "Humanist" (Vol. 10, No. 137) "Communication and
                                    Memory" points this out, "...scholarship in the field is
                                    significantly inhibited, I would argue, by the low degree to
                                    which previous work in humanities computing and current work in
                                    related fields is known and recognized."</p>
                                <p>The problems with the use of statistics by many authorship
                                    attribution are many and varied. Too many researchers are led
                                    into the swampy quicksand of statistical studies by the ignis
                                    fatuus of a "more sophisticated statistical technique".</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Problems and suggested solutions:</head>
                                <p>The "umbrella" problem is that most non-traditional authorship
                                    attribution researchers do not understand what constitutes a
                                    valid study. They do not understand that it is a scientific
                                    experiment and must be approached and carried out as such.</p>
                                <p>The corrections for many of the specific problems become apparent
                                    once the problem is pointed out and there is a consensus that
                                    there is a problem. This paper will expand upon, expound, and
                                    give examples from published studies of the following problems.
                                    The paper will also give the detailed solutions for these
                                    problems. One of the "solutions" will be the dissemination of a
                                    bibliography of over 500 entries.</p>
                                <p>Problem 1:</p>
                                <p>Not really knowing the field of the questioned work (e.g. does
                                    someone trained in physics know enough about Plato and all that
                                    is involved with the study of the classics to do a valid
                                    authorship attribution study of a questioned Plato work).</p>
                                <p> Not knowing the sub-disciplines of authorship attribution
                                    studies (e.g. linguistics, statistics, stylistics, computer
                                    science).</p>
                                <p>Problem 2:</p>
                                <p>Not doing the necessary research for each step of the study. (The
                                    steps will be shown.)</p>
                                <p>Not doing a traditional authorship attribution study.</p>
                                <p>Problem 3:</p>
                                <p>Not knowing when the flaws in the experimental set-up are fatal.
                                    And, therefore, not realizing that the study should not be
                                    done.</p>
                                <p>Problem 4:</p>
                                <p>Taking shortcuts and making unverified assumptions with the
                                    experimental set-up, the data, and the statistical tests (e.g.
                                    poor or wrong controls,"cherry picking").</p>
                                <p>Problem 5:</p>
                                <p>Ad hominem attacks and self-serving critiques.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
