<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main"><figure/>Electrifying Wordsworth</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Ronald</forename>
                        <surname>Tetreault</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Dalhousie University</name>
                            <email>tetro@is.dal.ca</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Wordsworth</item>
                        <item>e-text</item>
                        <item>hypertext</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Though his claim that "poetry is the spontaneous overflow of powerful feelings"
                    might tempt us to favour texts closest to the original sources of inspiration,
                    Wordsworth is equally famous for the inveterate revision of his poems over the
                    remaining half-century of his life. Recollection in tranquillity cannot help but
                    overlay spontaneity with deliberation, but if perfection is the work of time
                    then we may be justified in preferring the final authorized texts. Then there
                    are the versions in between, where a poem finely polished may be marred by
                    subsequent over-refinement. Which to choose has always been the editor's
                    dilemma; establishing a text has always meant that we must privilege one version
                    over others, and settle for a static representation of what might be better
                    understood as a dynamic process.</p>
                <p>De Selincourt's landmark edition confirmed the authority of Wordsworth's final
                    texts. "No poet ever paid more meticulous or prolonged attention to his text
                    than Wordsworth," wrote De Selincourt<note n="1">"Preface" to <title level="m"
                            >The Poetical Works of William Wordsworth</title>, ed. E. de Selincourt
                        (5 vols.; Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1940), I, v.</note> in justification of
                    choosing the last lifetime edition of 1849-50 as his copy-text, though he was
                    careful to indicate evidence of development by citing early manuscripts in an
                    apparatus criticus at the bottom of the page. Unease with this portrait of the
                    poet in old age has become more acute among his recent editors, who have
                    attempted a snapshot of a Wordsworth closer to the moment of inspiration by
                    printing the earliest completed version of the poems. A leader of this movement
                    is Stephen Gill, whose Oxford Authors edition aims to restore the "original
                    identity" of the poems.<note n="2"><title level="m">William Wordsworth</title>
                        (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1984), back cover.</note></p>
                <p>But the idea of a poem's "identity", like that of the poet's, is destabilized
                    when we begin to regard it as a work in progress. In his recent book, <title
                        level="m">Revision and Romantic Authorship</title> (Oxford University Press,
                    1996), Zachary Leader argues that the protean Romantic self cannot be captured
                    in the earliest versions of poems. All writers revise their texts, and perhaps
                    none more so than Wordsworth. In a review of this book, Frank Kermode writes
                    that Leader <cit rend="block">
                        <quote>wants to know what notions of identity underlie the assumption that a
                            poet in his twenties could be identical with the poet who, in his
                            seventies, was still tinkering with his early writings, as if they were
                            essential to the expression of the singleness of a life or a life-work,
                            rather than leaving them alone as virtually the work of a different
                            person, or at any rate of a person in no need of being assimilated to a
                            later one.</quote>
                        <bibl>
                            <note n="3">"Floating Hair v. Blue Pencil", <title level="j">London
                                    Review of Books</title>, 6 June 1996, pp.15-16.</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>Revision for Leader is a vital part of the creative process, and reveals a
                    complexity in acts of composition that are at odds with comfortable notions of a
                    unitary self. It is dubious not only to think that age is best which is the
                    first, another instance of that bias Jerome McGann warned against, stemming from
                    our "uncritical absorption in Romanticism's own self-representations".<note
                        n="4"><title level="m">The Romantic Ideology: A Critical
                            Investigation</title> (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1983),
                        p.1</note> Besides the merits of mature reflection, more than one hand might
                    be involved in the making of changes (as is clearly evident in many Wordsworth
                    manuscripts), further undermining the notion that the Romantic poet was a
                    solitary genius who sings as artlessly as a bird. But the print medium is not
                    well-equipped to show change over time except by the cumbersome apparatus of
                    footnotes, cannot possibly for reasons of space present all versions as they
                    evolved, and can only with difficulty make evident the extent to which
                    composition and revision can be a social activity. Wryly, Kermode observes that
                    these early, late, and intermediate versions "may one day be represented by
                    hypertext, ....[although] these plural texts are not likely to be of much use to
                    people who simply want to read Wordsworth and leave it to the experts to give
                    them a text."</p>
                <p>True, an electronic Wordsworth may not be eagerly sought out by the general
                    reader; I've met very few lovers of reading who prefer a screen-image over an
                    affordable book you don't even have to plug in to use. Indeed, such a Wordsworth
                    edition may not in fact be meant to be "read" at all, at least not in the sense
                    in which we still use the term today.<note n="5">Sven Birkerts points to this
                        distinction quite clearly in <title level="m">The Gutenburg Elegies: The
                            Fate of Reading in an Electronic Age</title> (Boston: Faber and Faber,
                        1994), p.15: <quote>"It is precisely where reading leaves off, where it is
                            supplanted by other modes of processing and transmitting experience,
                            that the new dispensation can be said to begin."</quote></note>Instead,
                    a hypertext Wordsworth would be meant to be explored, studied closely in a
                    fashion that the linear structure of print makes difficult, and used at a
                    distance by scholars who don't enjoy the privilege of proximity to a major
                    research library. Even more important, Wordsworth in hypertext may be the most
                    effective way yet to represent Wordsworth in development. This medium
                    reinscribes textual stability as a series of moments in a lengthy creative
                    process, for, by adding motion to comparative views, hypertext enables us to
                    represent change. His transformation from Romantic rebel to Victorian sage makes
                    Wordsworth an ideal choice for exploring the potential of this fluid means of
                    representation. Such a rendition of his text would be a key example of the way
                    digital media are "contributing to a general reconsideration of traditional,
                    unitary notions of identity", as Sherry Turkle, a student of the self in the
                    computer age, has written.<note n="6"><title level="m">Life on the Screen:
                            Identity in the Age of the Internet</title> (New York: Simon &amp;
                        Schuster, 1995), p. 260.</note>Thus, when Bruce Graver and I announce here
                    that Cambridge University Press has agreed to publish our electronic edition of
                        <title level="m">Lyrical Ballads</title> on CD-ROM, we do so conscious of
                    the enormous value of previous print editions and the scholarship that has
                    produced them, but also confident that an edition in this form will do what
                    print never quite could to show Wordsworth as an evolving self.</p>
                <p>There have been several other pioneers on this particular frontier of cyberspace,
                    but none so far have conceived their project as we have. Chadwyck-Healey's <ref
                        target="http://www.chadwyck.co.uk/products/p001.html">English Poetry
                        Full-Text Database</ref> is perhaps the best-known of the CD-based products,
                    but it by no means focuses on Wordsworth nor does it print more than one version
                    of any poem, and that usually from an out-of-copyright late edition. Their
                    student version, <ref target="http://www.chadwyck.co.uk/products/p002.html"
                        >English Poetry Plus</ref> on CD- ROM, contains just 39 Wordsworth titles,
                    and never acknowledges the source of any of these texts. Using software designed
                    by Electronic Book Technologies of Providence RI, it does have a pleasing user
                    interface, an effective search function, and links to brief biographical
                    sketches. A more scholarly work is promised by David Miall of the University of
                    Alberta; his <ref target="http://www.ualberta.ca/%7Eenglishd/rom-cd.htm"
                        >Romanticism: CD-ROM</ref> forthcoming from Blackwell's is an electronic
                    anthology offering a "generous selection" of poems by Wordsworth, but how these
                    are to be chosen and what texts they are to be based on is not specified.</p>
                <p>A networked environment promises much wider dissemination than a single-user CD,
                    so it is gratifying to see Wordsworth already prominent on the World Wide Web.
                    The best guide to Wordsworth on-line is to be found in Alan Liu's gloriously
                    encyclopedic <ref
                        target="http://humanitas.ucsb.edu/shuttle/eng-rom.html#authors">Voice of the
                        Shuttle Web Page for Humanities Research</ref> , a resource to which we are
                    all indebted. At least a couple of what can best be described as "fan pages"
                    have been posted: Thomas C. Gannon's <ref
                        target="http://www.usd.edu/%7Etgannon/words.html">Wordsworth Page</ref>
                    (which features a thoughtful quote for the day) and Richard Darsie's <ref
                        target="http://www.ece.ucdavis.edu/%7Edarsie/wordsworth.html">Selected
                        Poetry of William Wordsworth</ref>, an eclectic gathering of a dozen poems.
                    More systematic collections have been made available by academic institutions.
                    Columbia University's <ref
                        target="http://www.columbia.edu/acis/bartleby/wordsworth/index.html">Project
                        Bartleby</ref> reproduces all the poems in the 1888 edition of Wordsworth's
                        <title level="m">Complete Poetical Works</title>, indexing them
                    chronologically and by first line. The <ref
                        target="http://library.utoronto.ca/www/utel/rp/authors/wordswor.html"
                        >Representative Poetry Archive</ref> at the University of Toronto offers a
                    selection of 44 poems from a wide range of textual sources, all documented.
                    Individual scholars have also begun to experiment with posting electronic texts
                    for study purposes. Michael Gamer's collection of the <ref
                        target="http://www.english.upenn.edu/%7Emgamer/Romantic/lbprose.html">prose
                        associated with <title level="m">Lyrical Ballads</title></ref> is a good
                    case in point, while Richard Bear (a Ph.D. candidate in electronic book design
                    at the University of Oregon) has attempted to recreate the text of the rare <ref
                        target="http://darkwing.uoregon.edu/%7Erbear/ballads.html">1798
                        Bristol</ref> first edition, first issue of <title level="m">Lyrical
                        Ballads</title>, probably based on a copy of the 1926 Noel Douglas
                    replica.</p>
                <p>Our project differs from these in several significant respects. First, the poems
                    we will present have not been arbitrarily chosen, but are a reasonably coherent
                    group stemming from a single collection first published jointly but which came
                    to be dominated by Wordsworth's poems in subsequent editions. Second, we will
                    offer not just one version of each poem but all the versions of poems by
                    Wordsworth and Coleridge appearing in the four lifetime editions of <title
                        level="m">Lyrical Ballads</title>, together with later important versions of
                    poems revised by Wordsworth in his lifetime, and these will be linked
                    hypertextually. Third, our copy-texts will be taken from the original editions
                    themselves as held in libraries around the world, though of course our
                    procedures will be informed by the findings of previous scholars, especially the
                    editors of the Cornell Wordsworth series. Fourth, our e-texts will be
                    "marked-up" or tagged using SGML (Standard Generalized Markup Language) in
                    conformity with the principles of the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI). Fifth, we
                    plan to link our transcribed e-texts to scanned images of the original printed
                    editions in order to give the reader some sense of the look of the poems upon
                    the page. Finally, this scholarly hypertext edition will be issued on CD-ROM in
                    the first instance, with the intention of proceeding to network distribution as
                    soon as it becomes practical.</p>
                <p>Cambridge University Press's <ref
                        target="http://www.cup.cam.ac.uk/pubgroups/reference/cdromstop.html">CD-ROM
                        series</ref> currently consists of four offerings: Peter Robinson's edition
                    of <title level="m">The Wife of Bath's Prologue</title>, a <title level="m"
                        >World Shakespeare Bibliography 1990-1993</title>, Samuel Johnson's <title
                        level="m">Dictionary</title>, and the <title level="m">Works</title> of John
                    Ruskin. The first of these (the one with which I am most familiar) assembles all
                    58 of the pre-1500 manuscripts and printed editions of the prologue, using
                    Robinson's <title level="m">Collate</title> program to compare the different
                    versions and to generate an apparatus of variants. The 58 versions, together
                    with the apparatus and digitized images of 1200 manuscript pages, are linked
                    together using Electronic Book Technologies' <ref
                        target="http://www.ebt.com/docs/prodinfo.html#DynaText">DynaText</ref>
                    software to create a hypertext "book". Typically, a DynaText book is <figure/>
                    presented on the screen in two windows (click on the image for a clearer view),
                    one a narrow column on the left containing a table of contents and the other a
                    wider data-window on the right containing the text or texts compiled from top to
                    bottom in one large file document. Rather than accessing the contents of that
                    file document linearly, a simple mouse-click on one element of the table of
                    contents takes the user directly to the designated section of the text. Each
                    such section may be opened as an independent window, and the windows so
                    generated can be scaled and moved about the screen to permit the comparison of
                    texts.</p>
                <p>Although DynaText is powerful software that can handle a huge mass of complex
                    material, I find myself as the member of the editorial team responsible for
                    hypertext design chafing at some of its limitations. DynaText was initially
                    conceived as a commercial product designed to provide rapid indexed access to
                    large prose documents such as catalogues and manuals; its table of contents
                    window gives effective access to works with section titles and sub-headings, but
                    is a blunt instrument when it comes to the presentation of poetry, where the
                    user quite rightly demands access line by line. Short of embedding every line of
                    each poem into the table of contents, there seems to be no easy way of
                    navigating through the variant texts. The <title level="m"
                    >Collate</title>-generated apparatus helps if opened into an independent window,
                    but then other windows have to be opened and manipulated on the screen in order
                    to compare lines once interesting variants are found. But the cluster of
                    multiple windows thus generated can be awkward to scale and arrange on the
                    screen, nor is it easy to keep track of which window holds which portion of the
                    immense file document. With a multiplicity of texts such as the <title level="m"
                        >Lyrical Ballads</title> offers, it is all too easy for the reader to get
                    lost in cyberspace. The navigational tool so far proposed, the inclusion of a
                    "base text for collation" at the top of the long file document in the
                    data-window, is as much a relic of print culture as the model of the
                    single-document "book" divided into subsections. In addition to the multiple
                    versions of each poem, the editor is obliged either to construct a further ideal
                    version of the of the poem to serve as the "base text" or, worse (because it
                    violates the principle that this new medium should not merely reproduce the book
                    but transcend it), to choose one of the existing variant texts, say from the
                    first edition or the last lifetime edition, as the "base text". I had thought to
                    address this difficulty by including texts of all the poems from all four
                    lifetime editions of <title level="m">Lyrical Ballads</title> as potential base
                    texts, and then asking the reader at the beginning of each session to choose
                    which of the editions he or she wished to use as the base text against which all
                    the others would be collated. But this was not interactivity so much as an
                    offloading of editorial responsibility, and furthermore resulted in an
                    unnecessarily vast proliferation of alternative texts within the DynaText
                    file.</p>
                <p>Instead, to address these navigational problems, I have begun to experiment with
                    functionalities associated with Internet delivery of documents over the World
                    Wide Web. An array of windows is essential to the display of the Wordsworth
                    project, for as Sherry Turkle observes "windows have become a powerful metaphor
                    for thinking about the self as a multiple, distributed system."<note n="7"
                            ><title level="m">Life on the Screen</title>, p.14. Turkle follows
                        George Landow, <title level="m">Hypertext</title> (Baltimore: Johns Hopkins
                        University Press, 1992) and Richard Lanham, <title level="m">The Electronic
                            Word</title> (Chicago : University of Chicago Press, 1993) in writing of
                        the way identity is understood as fragmented and discontinuous in the
                        digital age.</note>What seems most attractive about HTML (Hypertext Markup
                    Language) standards at the present stage of development is that they enable the
                    use of frames, a system of layout in which windows are generated on the screen
                    according to a pre-determined pattern. Though this pattern can be easily altered
                    by the user, its grid provides an intelligible starting point for the display of
                    multiple texts of the same poem on the screen at the same time. My prototype
                    pages for the <ref target="http://is.dal.ca/%7Etetro/ww2/welcome.html"><title
                            level="m">Lyrical Ballads</title> Hypertext Project</ref> (click to see
                    it in full interactivity) take "Simon Lee" as a test-case, and consist
                    <figure/>of two successive contents pages which lead to a galaxy of pages each
                    composed of five frames: one narrow vertical column on the left plays the
                    customary table of contents role, while a grid of four squares on the right
                    allows the reader to compare four different versions of the poem on the screen
                    at once. The text in each window may be scrolled through manually, but by the
                    use of internal anchors a simple click on a live hyperlink in the left-hand
                    window causes all four texts in the squares to scroll simultaneously to the same
                    line (click on the image for a clearer, though static, view). In this way, a
                    balance is struck between exploration and direction in the reader's examination
                    of textual complexity.</p>
                <p>There is a second feature of this scheme meant to help readers find their
                    bearings. The left-hand column contains no mere list of contents but what I call
                    a "variant map" of the poem being studied. The variant map is a guide to
                    revisions that were made at various stages in the poem's development. It is
                    based on the poem to the extent that it reproduces the text of the poem wherever
                    changes were not made, but whenever a change in any of the versions under
                    consideration is encountered it substitutes a descriptive hyperlink for the
                    variants themselves. The reader is thus alerted that an alteration has been
                    made, and by clicking on the "hotspot" can summon up the parallel passages.
                    Replacing the base or reading text with a variant map turns the annotation
                    process inside out in a way that seems appropriate to the dynamism of this
                    medium, for the hiatus in reading caused by running across a link cues the
                    reader to click on the spot and look to the right (in the direction of the
                    normal flow of reading) to learn the word or character elided and to compare
                    texts. Rather than footnotes which distract attention from a definitive text,
                    the variant map is an abstraction of the poem which does not privilege one
                    version of the text over another and that piques the reader's curiosity by means
                    of gaps in the text to pursue the significance of revisions made in successive
                    versions.</p>
                <p>Without doubt, there are numerous disadvantages to this proposed scheme of
                    display. Currently available bandwidth is simply too slow to deliver the amount
                    and complexity of digitized texts and images we envision. Besides, not everyone
                    is yet using a frames-capable browser, such as Netscape 2.0 or better (and some
                    users are still restricted to the text-only Lynx system). Furthermore, the
                    14-inch monitors commonly in use today do not have enough screen real-estate to
                    display more than four versions of the text at a time, and even this minimum
                    array for our purposes appears somewhat cramped. While these drawbacks may soon
                    disappear given the rapid advances in computer technology we are experiencing, a
                    more lasting objection is raised when we consider that HTML is a much simplified
                    subset of SGML and therefore inadequate to represent the complexity of the texts
                    in question. However, in the case of the variant map element, it should be
                    recognized that it can function quite irrespective of the markup scheme used.
                    The way its links interact with the frames is another matter, though, since
                    DynaText will not process frames the way a web-browser can. Help is on the way
                    from Electronic Book Technologies, as I have been informed by company
                    representatives that their <ref
                        target="http://www.ebt.com/docs/prodinfo.html#DynaWeb">DynaWeb</ref>
                    software is capable of browsing DynaText books tagged in SGML, conveying them
                    across a network, and in the process reproducing frames. Perhaps the solution to
                    the apparent incompatibility of Netscape extensions and SGML structures is to
                    project the DynaText <title level="m">Lyrical Ballads</title> through a DynaWeb
                    browser.</p>
                <p>In whatever ways this project may develop, its goal is not to supplant books nor
                    to discredit the achievements of earlier editors, but to attempt to do things
                    through this medium that print cannot, and in the process to discover what
                    unique capabilities it has, if any. The fixity of print has been able to give us
                    one Wordsworth or the other, but is not capable of fully representing his
                    evolving consciousness. The poet was well aware that each of us passes through a
                    succession of selves, not completely fragmentary and unrelated to one another
                    but sufficiently discontinuous for him to wish for our "days to be/Bound each to
                    each" by some means or other. Even if no more successful than natural piety,
                    digital media can at least enable us to give attention to the various stages of
                    composition and revision and to give each of them the respect they deserve. In
                    the end, we may find that we have done no more than translate the contents of
                    one medium into another, but that will not be without value, as textual critic
                    James Thorpe reminds us: <cit rend="block">
                        <quote>All editions carry the taint of time. They are for the here and now,
                            whether that is a decade, a generation, or a century. Ultimately they
                            must all be replaced for most purposes.</quote>
                        <bibl>
                            <note n="8"><title level="m">Principles of Textual Criticism</title>
                                (San Marino: The Huntington Library, 1972), p. 179.</note>
                        </bibl>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>To the extent that computers can help us to embody postmodern concepts like the
                    decentered self and show them at work in specific instances, they are the tools
                    of the time and will certainly have an impact on the study of literature. At the
                    least, digital hypertext editions can spark a renewal of interest in editing and
                    textual scholarship, analytical and descriptive bibliography, and even assist in
                    the realignment of literary studies from the theory and practice of critical
                    interpretation to the new cultural history's focus on the literary marketplace
                    and the material production and representation of "literature".<note n="9">A
                        sign of this latter trend is Alan D. Boehm's recent article on "The 1798
                            <title level="m">Lyrical Ballads</title> and the Poetics of Late
                        Eighteenth-Century Book Production", in <title level="j">ELH</title>,
                        63(1996), 453-87, which alerts us to "a set of rhetorical as well as
                        technical and commercial practices" involved in the creation of <title
                            level="m">Lyrical Ballads</title> as an artifact of print
                        culture.</note>What consequences they will have we cannot know until we
                    try.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
