<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Creatures of Habit? What collocation can tell us about
                    translation</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Dorothy</forename>
                        <surname>Kenny</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Dublin City University</name>
                            <email>Dorothy.Kenny@dcu.ie</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>collocation</item>
                        <item>translation</item>
                        <item>conventionalization</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Corpora in Translation Studies</head>
                    <p>Baker (1995) describes various types of electronic corpora that are of
                        specific interest to translation scholars. In Baker's terminology, a <emph
                            rend="bold">parallel corpus</emph> consists of texts originally written
                        in a language A alongside their translations into a language B. Parallel
                        corpora exist for several language pairs including English-French (Salkie
                        1995; and see also Church and Gale's work (1991) using the Canadian
                        Hansard), English-Italian (Marinai et al. 1992), and English- Norwegian
                        (Johansson and Hofland 1994; Johansson, et al. 1996). Parallel corpora can
                        be used to provide information on language-pair specific translational
                        behaviour, or to posit certain equivalence relationships between lexical
                        items or structures in source and target languages (Marinai et al.
                        1992).Typical applications of parallel corpora include translator training,
                        bilingual lexicography and machine translation.</p>
                    <p>Baker (1995) uses the term <emph rend="bold">comparable corpus</emph> to
                        describe a collection of texts originally written in a language, say
                        English, alongside a collection of texts translated (from one or more
                        languages) into English, and suggests that comparable corpora have the
                        potential to reveal most about features specific to translated text, i.e.,
                        those features that occur exclusively, or with unusually low or high
                        frequency, in translated text as opposed to other types of text production,
                        and that cannot be traced back to the influence of any one particular source
                        text or language. Translation theorists such as Shlesinger (1991), Toury
                        (1980), Vanderauwera (1985) and Baker (1993) have posited the following as
                        features of translated text: translated texts tend to be more explicit, less
                        ambiguous, and grammatically and lexically more conventional than source
                        texts or other texts produced in the target language.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Using collocation as an indicator of conservatism</head>
                    <p>The idea that translations are more conventional than their source texts or
                        other target language texts can also be tested by investigating
                        collocational patterns. Should familiar collocational patterns be somehow
                        flouted in a source text, then the point at which this happens will also
                        have special textemic status in that source text. This could occur, for
                        example, at points where the preference of a word under investigation for
                        collocates of a particular semantic set is not respected in a text, or, more
                        specifically, where there are "departures ... from the expected profiles of
                        semantic prosodies" (Louw 1993: 157). Corpus linguistics provides
                        interesting techniques for spotting recurring and, by contrast,
                        unconventional patterns of co-occurrence in vast quantities of text (Clear
                        1993; Louw 1993) and such techniques are being extended to bilingual corpora
                        (Peters and Picchi 1996; Smadja et al. 1996). If translators really are
                        under pressure to conform to target-language norms, one could expect
                        unconventional co-occurrences in source texts to be replaced by more
                        conventional collocations in the target text.</p>
                    <p>The current doctoral research represents an attempt to use collocation as an
                        indicator of conservative tendencies amongst translators. It involves the
                        building of a parallel corpus of contemporary German fiction translated into
                        English. Unconventional lexical co-occurrences are to be identified in the
                        German source texts, by comparing the source texts with a large reference
                        corpus of German, and using the tools of collocation analysis (Clear 1993;
                        Barnbrook 1996). The translation into English of such unusual lexical
                        combinations will then be investigated to see whether these are
                        conventionalized in any way. Such conventionalization can, of course, only
                        be established with reference to a large corpus of fiction originally
                        written in English, in other words, using a comparable corpus.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>A pilot investigation</head>
                    <p>This poster sets out specifically to report on a pilot test designed to
                        investigate collocational patterns in a small number of German source and
                        English target texts. The principle issues at stake are: how to choose node
                        words worth investigating in the original German texts; and how to identify
                        statistically significant collocations and, by contrast, unusual
                        co-occurrences in the source and target texts. Various approaches are taken
                        in the literature: Stubbs (1996), for example, investigates the collocates
                        of culturally significant nodes; other researchers (Clear 1993; Smadja 1993)
                        report on approaches that compute collocation patterns for every word form
                        in a corpus from the outset, only to later jettison those combinations that
                        fall below an arbitrary threshold of significance. It is also well known
                        that different measures of statistical significance yield different results
                        in automatic collocation recognition (Clear 1993; Smadja 1993). By comparing
                        approaches, it is hoped that this pilot test will indicate how the research
                        should proceed when it is scaled up to include the full set of German source
                        texts. It is also intended to reveal problems that may be specific to the
                        identification of collocations in two different languages, and specifically,
                        whether unconventional (free) lexical combinations can be fruitfully used as
                        a springboard for investigating conservative linguistics tendencies among
                        literary translators.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Baker</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Corpus Linguistics and Translation Studies:
                                Implications and Applications</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Baker</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Francis</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Tognini-Bonelli</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Text and Technology: In Honour of John Sinclair</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Amsterdam/Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>John Benjamins</publisher>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">223-250</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Baker</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Corpora in Translation Studies: An Overview and Some
                                Suggestions for Future Research</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Target</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">7</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">223-243</biblScope>
                                <date when="1995">1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Baker</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Francis</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Tognini-Bonelli</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Text and Technology: In Honour of John Sinclair</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Amsterdam/Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>John Benjamins</publisher>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Barnbrook</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Language and Computers</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Edinburgh University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>Church</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Gale</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Concordances for Parallel Text</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Using Corpora: Proceedings of the Seventh Annual
                                Conference of the UW Centre for the New OED &amp; Text
                                Research</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>St. Catherine's</publisher>
                                <date when="1991">1991</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Clear</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">From Firth Principles: Computational Tools for the
                                Study of Collocation</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Baker</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Francis</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Tognini- Bonelli</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Text and Technology: In Honour of John Sinclair</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Amsterdam/Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>John Benjamins</publisher>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">271-292</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Johansson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>Hofland</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Towards an English-Norwegian parallel corpus</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">U.</forename>
                                    <surname>Fries</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Tottie</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Schneider</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Creating and using English language corpora, Papers
                                from the Fourteenth International Conference on English Language
                                Research on Computerized Corpora, Zürich 1993</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Zürich</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Johansson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Ebeling</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>Hofland</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Coding and Aligning the English-Norwegian Parallel
                                Corpus</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Languages in Contrast Papers from a Symposium on
                                Text-based Cross-linguistic Studies, Lund 4-5 March 1994</title>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>Aijmer</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">B.</forename>
                                    <surname>Altenberg</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Johansson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Lund</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Lund University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">87-112</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">B.</forename>
                                    <surname>Louw</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Irony in the Text or Insincerity in the Writer? The
                                Diagnostic Potential of Semantic Prosodies</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Baker</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Francis</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Tognini- Bonelli</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Text and Technology: In Honour of John Sinclair</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Amsterdam/Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>John Benjamins</publisher>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">157-176</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Marinai</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Peters</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Picchi</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Bilingual Reference Corpora: Creation, Querying,
                                Applications</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">F.</forename>
                                    <surname>Kiefer</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Kiss</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Pajzs</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Papers in Computational Lexicography Complex
                                '92</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Budapest</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Linguistics Institute, Hungarian Academy of
                                    Sciences</publisher>
                                <date when="1992">1992</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Peters</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Picchi</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Bilingual reference corpora for translators and
                                translation studies</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">Paper presented at Unity in Diversity, International
                                Translation Studies Conference, Dublin City University, 9-11 May
                                1996</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1996">May 1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Salkie</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Intersect: a Parallel Corpus Project at Brighton
                                University</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Computers and Texts</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">9</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">4-5</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp"/>
                                <date when="1995">May 1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Shlesinger</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Interpreter Latitude vs. Due Process. Simultaneous and
                                Consecutive Interpretation in Multilingual Trials</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Tirkkonen-Condit</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Empirical Research in Translation and Intercultural
                                Studies</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Tübingen</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Gunter Narr.</publisher>
                                <date when="1991">1991</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">F.</forename>
                                    <surname>Smadja</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Retrieving Collocations from Text: Xtract</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Computational Linguistics</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">19</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">143-177</biblScope>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">F.</forename>
                                    <surname>Smadja</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>McKeown</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">V.</forename>
                                    <surname>Hatzivassiloglou</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Translating Collocations for Bilingual Lexicons: A
                                Statistical Approach</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Computational Linguistics</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">22</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">1-38</biblScope>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Stubbs</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Text and Corpus Analysis</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Blackwell</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Toury</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">In Search of a Theory of Translation</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Tel Aviv</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>The Porter Institute for Poetics and
                                    Semiotics</publisher>
                                <date when="1980">1980</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Vanderauwera</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Dutch Novels Translated into English: The
                                Transformation of a "Minority" Literature</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Rodopi</publisher>
                                <date when="1985">1985</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
