<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="panel">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The Epistemology of the Electronic Text: Scholarly and
                    Pedagogical Considerations</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Julia</forename>
                        <surname>Flanders</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Brown University</name>
                            <email>Julia_Flanders@brown.edu</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">John</forename>
                        <surname>Lavagnino</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Brown University</name>
                            <email>John_Lavagnino@brown.edu</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Carol</forename>
                        <surname>Barash</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Seton Hall University</name>
                            <email>barashca@pirate.shu.edu</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>edition</item>
                        <item>image</item>
                        <item>pedagogy</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <p>In invoking "the epistemology of the electronic text" this session means to
                        open up a set of questions which have to do with how we conceptualize
                        electronic texts as vehicles for information, and how we imagine their
                        particular kinds of authority. These issues have important implications for
                        how we use electronic texts in teaching and research, since they lie at the
                        heart of the cultural position of the electronic text, both within the
                        culture of the academy and outside it. We would like to ask not simply what
                        people want electronic texts to do, or what they want them to provide, but
                        what drives these desires and how they affect the actual use of the data and
                        function offered by electronic resources.</p>
                    <p>The papers in the session approach these questions from several angles, but
                        also speak to each other's concerns. John Lavagnino's paper on the place of
                        images in the electronic scholarly edition inquires into the role of the
                        image as guarantor of textual integrity, and the special emphasis that
                        images receive in discussions of electronic editions. His argument that
                        images loom disproportionately large in the imaginations of both creators
                        and users of electronic texts engages with Carol Barash's paper on the
                        pedagogical use of electronic texts, based on her work with the Women
                        Writers Project's textbase and other electronic resources. She investigates
                        both the actual use of images in teaching early women's writing, and the
                        methodological context that supports and motivates that use, arguing that
                        images enable different kinds of textual study and also have significant
                        pedagogical effects on students' use of the electronic materials. Julia
                        Flanders' paper addresses the question of the use of images in the context
                        of attitudes towards the edition: both as a product of human judgement and
                        taste, and as an accurate point of access to other, epistemologically prior
                        documents. Her paper undertakes to explicate the function of the electronic
                        edition in terms of the sociology of the academy, and its ascription of
                        different kinds of authority to different kinds of textual and physical
                        evidence: evidence which the electronic edition must offer in unfamiliar or
                        defamiliarizing ways.</p>
                    <p>Together, the papers will encourage a more self-conscious discussion of how
                        we imagine electronic text resources, and their claims to sufficiency and
                        authority.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>Trusting the Electronic Text</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">Julia Flanders</p>
                        <div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Introduction</head>
                                <p>The trustworthiness or untrustworthiness of electronic texts and
                                    electronic editions is a topic of acute concern to those who see
                                    conventional libraries supplemented by new electronic resources,
                                    many of which offer unparalleled access to rare materials if
                                    they can only be relied upon for accuracy and scholarly
                                    integrity. The public media also finds accuracy and integrity of
                                    great interest as a way of approaching the issue of electronic
                                    texts generally. Caveats about lack of depth, shoddiness, and
                                    unscholarliness have a more than factual force: they express as
                                    well the intangible concerns about the effects of electronic
                                    materials on the cultural status of texts, or their intimation
                                    of some underlying paradigm shift with unforeseeable
                                    consequences. The trustworthiness of the electronic text thus
                                    becomes the focus for deeper questions about its cultural
                                    authority.</p>
                                <p>As the electronic text, and particularly the electronic edition,
                                    receives increasing attention and use, expectations about what
                                    it should look like and do become more specific, ambitious, and
                                    realistic. We not only have diverse examples before us of
                                    successful electronic edition projects (the Canterbury Tales
                                    Project, the electronic edition of Samuel Johnson's Dictionary,
                                    the Rossetti Archive, the Blake Archive) but we also begin to
                                    have feedback from users--themselves increasingly
                                    knowledgeable--about what they expect and desire from the
                                    electronic edition; we have, in short, the growth of a set of
                                    common expectations which are even on the verge of becoming
                                    dogmatically entrenched. The electronic edition, it seems,
                                    should include some or all of the following: transcriptions of
                                    most or all of the important witnesses; an edited text which
                                    represents some sort of "best text" derived by the editor from
                                    the witnesses; digital images of illustrations, manuscripts, or
                                    even whole printed texts; annotations and textual notes;
                                    secondary criticism; facilities for collation of variants; and
                                    text encoding which identifies the salient components of
                                    structure and content upon which scholarly study is based.</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Evaluation Criteria</head>
                                <p>The criteria by which we judge and value these various possible
                                    components of the electronic edition vary considerably. For
                                    transcriptions and other textual material, we apply at least the
                                    notion of transcriptional accuracy, which is familiar enough
                                    from the realm of the printed text but takes on additional
                                    complexity when the text is transcribed using something like
                                    SGML. Secondary sources and annotations are additionally judged
                                    for their factuality--the degree to which the statements they
                                    make are true--and for their scholarly merit, credibility, and
                                    relevance. Likewise, the edited version of the text will be
                                    judged by the respectability and credibility of the scholarship
                                    that produces it. Facilities for textual analysis, which in
                                    projects like the Canterbury Tales may form a significant part
                                    of the editedness of the edition, can be judged according to a
                                    standard of computational accuracy: the capacity of the software
                                    and encoding to produce correct, usable results to queries and
                                    collations. Similarly, the encoding of the text may transform
                                    aspects of the content into a more readily processable form (for
                                    instance, by encoding punctuation or delimiters as attribute
                                    values rather than as content) which again would be judged by
                                    its ability to reconstruct the text accurately and usefully.
                                    Finally, images are judged by their quantity and quality of data
                                    (resolution and accuracy) but also by the air of tangible,
                                    attestable reality which they bring with them.</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Reality and Models</head>
                                <p>In the last two cases given above--images and what we might call
                                    computational features--we see an encapsulation of the
                                    polarities of the electronic edition. In the case of the image,
                                    data is provided which is only processable by the human eye, and
                                    which is nearly impervious (at least at present) to any kind of
                                    computerized retrieval or analysis. Almost in direct proportion
                                    to its intractability, the image is seen as substantiating the
                                    real-world existence of the text which the electronic
                                    transcription reproduces: without the visual evidence of the
                                    image, as John Lavagnino has argued, the electronic edition
                                    seems perversely ungrounded and untrustworthy. In the case of
                                    computational features, the original text is rendered far more
                                    accessible, in analytic terms, by the added encoding and the
                                    tools provided; we might even say that its textuality has been
                                    enhanced to the degree that the original sprawling data has been
                                    ordered and preprocessed by the work of encoding. This
                                    processing or functional modelling of the text, though, has a
                                    troubled status in relation to the edition's perceived
                                    authority, where that authority is construed along the axes of
                                    value which apply to the more familiar aspects of the edition
                                    derived from the realm of print. For one thing, the introduction
                                    of computational work into the process of editing the text (as
                                    for instance in the case of the collational features provided in
                                    the Canterbury Tales Project) seems to supplant what turns out
                                    to be a very important--though hard to quantify--component of
                                    the trustworthiness of the edition as a whole, namely the role
                                    of the scholarly editor. For another, the replacement of
                                    recognizable content by a computational model of it draws the
                                    text away from the realm of the tangibly real that things like
                                    images or sounds work to substantiate, with their irreducibility
                                    and untranslatability. These poles define in some sense the
                                    current parameters of the electronic edition--from unprocessable
                                    data as a facsimile of reality on the one hand, to highly
                                    processed data as a functional model of reality on the other.
                                    They also ask us to think about trustworthiness in the context
                                    of other criteria such as usefulness.</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Conclusion</head>
                                <p>Scholarly and pedagogical use of electronic editions relies on
                                    the criterion of trustworthiness not simply as a kind of paltry
                                    intellectual crutch, but at a deeper level as a crucial
                                    component of the architecture of academic study. To the extent
                                    that the electronic edition is being assimilated into the
                                    general work of the academy, it is being naturalized there in a
                                    form which corresponds most closely to the systems of value
                                    already operative in that sphere. This paper concludes that
                                    these systems of value, while not irrelevant, may lead scholars
                                    away from the more functional analytical aspects of the edition,
                                    towards those which--though they feel familiar--ultimately have
                                    very little to do with the electronic medium.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="bibliography">
                        <head>Bibliography</head>
                        <listBibl>
                            <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">John</forename>
                                            <surname>Lavagnino</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">Completeness and Adequacy in Text
                                        Encoding</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <editor>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">Richard</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                            <surname>Finneran</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </editor>
                                    <title level="m">The Literary Text in the Digital Age</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <pubPlace>Ann Arbor</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>University of Michigan Press</publisher>
                                        <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">Peter</forename>
                                            <surname>Robinson</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">Is there a text in these variants?</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <editor>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">Richard</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                            <surname>Finneran</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </editor>
                                    <title level="m">The Literary Text in the Digital Age</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <pubPlace>Ann Arbor</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>University of Michigan</publisher>
                                        <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">Kathryn</forename>
                                            <surname>Sutherland</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">Looking and Knowing: Textual Encounters of a
                                        Postponed Kind</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <editor>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">Warren</forename>
                                            <surname>Chernaik</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </editor>
                                    <editor>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">Marilyn</forename>
                                            <surname>Deegan</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </editor>
                                    <editor>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">Andrew</forename>
                                            <surname>Gibson</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </editor>
                                    <title level="m">Beyond the Book: Theory, Culture, and the
                                        Politics of Cyberspace</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Office for Humanities Communication
                                            Publications</publisher>
                                        <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                        </listBibl>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>The Place of Images in the Electronic Edition</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">John Lavagnino</p>
                        <div>
                            <p>Many of us are currently working on creating scholarly editions in
                                electronic form, and a few of us have even managed to complete
                                projects of this sort and make them publicly available. At this
                                early stage, with so little experience of such
                                editions---particularly experience with their use by scholars---it
                                would seem unlikely that we'd be in a good position to issue any
                                general rules about what an electronic edition should be, apart from
                                those rules that can be carried over from the long tradition of
                                scholarly editing for print publication (such as concern for
                                accuracy of transcription and completeness of documentation).</p>
                            <p>Yet there is actually one principle that has gained widespread
                                agreement---a principle which is peculiar for the nearly complete
                                absence of argument that has been presented in its support. This is
                                the principle that states that an electronic edition must always
                                include facsimiles of the sources on which it is based. The fullest
                                statement of this position that I know is from G. Thomas Tanselle:
                                    <cit rend="block">
                                    <quote>the advantages of hypertext as apparatus will not be
                                        fully exploited unless its capabilities for visual
                                        reproduction are used. Digitized images of the original
                                        manuscripts and printed pages should always be provided,
                                        along with the more manipulable electronic texts (that is,
                                        keyboarded transcriptions of manuscripts and rekeyboarded or
                                        optically converted texts of printed pages). Just as a
                                        scholarly edition in codex form is considered deficient if
                                        it does not provide a record of variant readings, a
                                        hypertext edition (or ``archive'') should be regarded as
                                        inadequate if it does not offer images of the original
                                        documents, both manuscript and printed. Important physical
                                        evidence will obviously still be unreproduced, but at least
                                        the range of paleographical and typographical evidence made
                                        available will be far greater than has been customary in
                                        editions of the past---even in ``facsimile'' editions, which
                                        have usually been limited to single documents.</quote>
                                    <bibl>[Tanselle 1995, 591]</bibl>
                                </cit></p>
                            <p>It is easy to observe in this statement the problem that afflicts
                                many discussions on this subject: what starts out as a potential
                                    <emph rend="italics">advantage</emph> of the electronic edition
                                somehow turns into an absolute <emph rend="italics"
                                    >requirement</emph>, without any argument to support this
                                transformation. And yet it seems perfectly clear that all we are
                                really talking about is a technical possibility whose exploitation
                                is valuable for many sorts of materials, but is by no means
                                essential to every scholarly edition. If reproductions of the
                                sources are really so necessary, then there is no reason apparent
                                here why the rule applies only to electronic editions: it is
                                perfectly possible for print editions to contain such information as
                                well, and if it's really necessary it's necessary for those editions
                                too. (See also Litz (1996) for another instance of this
                                position.)</p>
                            <p>But although no reasons are given for this curious position, it is
                                possible to infer some. One reason is no doubt the submerged idea
                                that an electronic edition is somehow not as real as one on paper
                                (McKenzie 1991 is one publication that actually advances a form of
                                this argument directly rather than assuming it without discussion).
                                A variant of this view, and one that does have some reasonable
                                grounding, is the idea that transcriptions in some kinds of
                                electronic editions are not terribly reliable because they were
                                produced by scanning or offshore typists rather than scholars, and
                                that we therefore need the images to check the transcriptions;
                                Womersley (1996) seems to have this in the back of his mind, in
                                reviewing such a production, though he doesn't fully articulate it.
                                This is a point that only applies to editions created in this
                                particular way, though, and not to electronic editions in
                                general.</p>
                            <p>A larger reason is the lingering strain of positivism that afflicts
                                both humanities computing and textual editing: in both disciplines
                                the idea still persists that it could be possible simply to
                                establish the facts without any element of interpretation, and that
                                indeed it would be best if we could eliminate all interpretation
                                from our work. Yet any informed understanding of digital images
                                involves an awareness of the large number of choices that go into
                                decisions on just how to do it---on the resolution, color spectrum,
                                and lighting, for example (see Robinson 1993 for a survey, and
                                Tanselle 1989 for a general account of the pitfalls of image
                                reproduction). And, for works produced in the era of print, it is in
                                general impossible to collect and digitize the entire range of
                                extant sources: since each copy of a book can be different, a truly
                                definitive collection of data requires the imaging of every last
                                copy. The images that go into an electronic edition are necessarily
                                the product of scholarly selection from a wide range of materials
                                and ways to reproduce them; such processes of selection are
                                inescapable in editing, and they are among the ways in which an
                                edition creates a new representation of the text, rather than simply
                                transmitting information about it.</p>
                            <p>A more reliable basis for thought on just what an electronic edition
                                needs would focus on the particular nature of the texts in question,
                                and on the representation of them that the edition seeks to create,
                                rather than on an attempt to raise up general rules applicable to
                                every edition. For some texts, the importance of reproductions of
                                original sources has been well argued; their significance for the
                                study of manuscripts has been made particularly clear in several
                                cases. For other texts, an editor may well judge that different
                                kinds of materials are more important than images of sources, such
                                as annotations or the texts of related works and adaptations. There
                                are choices involved in doing this, choices with which other
                                scholars might disagree. But the avoidance of choice is not an
                                alternative, because it's not possible.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Works Cited</head>
                        <listBibl>
                            <biblStruct>
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">Walton</forename>
                                            <surname>Litz</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">Afterword</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">Richard</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                            <surname>Finneran</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="m">The Literary Text in the Digital Age</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <pubPlace>Ann Arbor</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>University of Michigan Press</publisher>
                                        <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">245-248</biblScope>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct>
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">F.</forename>
                                            <surname>McKenzie</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">Computers and the Humanities: a Personal
                                        Synthesis of Conference Issues</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <editor>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">May</forename>
                                            <surname>Katzen</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </editor>
                                    <title level="m">Scholarship and Technology in the Humanities:
                                        Proceedings of a Conference held at Elvetham Hall,
                                        Hampshire, U.K., 9th-12th May 1990</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Bowker</publisher>
                                        <date when="1991">1991</date>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">157-169</biblScope>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="book">
                                <monogr>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">Peter</forename>
                                            <surname>Robinson</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="m">The Digitization of Primary Textual
                                        Sources</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                                        <publisher>Office for the Humanities Communications
                                            Publications</publisher>
                                        <date when="1993">1993</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">Thomas</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">G.</forename>
                                            <surname>Tanselle</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">Critical Editions, Hypertexts, and Genetic
                                        Criticism</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <title level="j">The Romanic Review</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <biblScope type="vol">86</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">581-593</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1995">May 1995</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">Thomas</forename>
                                            <forename type="middle">G.</forename>
                                            <surname>Tanselle</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">Reproductions and Scholarship</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <title level="j">Studies in Bibliography</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <biblScope type="vol">42</biblScope>
                                        <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">25-54</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1989">1989</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                            <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                                <analytic>
                                    <author>
                                        <name>
                                            <forename type="first">David</forename>
                                            <surname>Womersley</surname>
                                        </name>
                                    </author>
                                    <title level="a">Delightful ways to cheat learning</title>
                                </analytic>
                                <monogr>
                                    <title level="j">Times Higher Education Supplement</title>
                                    <imprint>
                                        <biblScope type="vol"/>
                                        <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                        <biblScope type="pp">vii</biblScope>
                                        <date when="1996">14 June 1996</date>
                                    </imprint>
                                </monogr>
                            </biblStruct>
                        </listBibl>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>Textual Studies, Cultural Studies: Text, Image and the Production of
                            Knowledge in the Interdisciplinary Literature Classroom</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">Carol Barash</p>
                        <div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Introduction</head>
                                <p>This paper is based on pilot courses using the Brown University
                                    Women Writers Project (WWP) textbase in basic literature courses
                                    at Seton Hall University. I will discuss the relationship
                                    between texts and images in the use of a full-text database to
                                    teach several aspects of literary study: close reading and
                                    analysis of the text's language and structure (textual studies),
                                    the relationship between the text and its historical contexts
                                    (cultural studies) and literary history, and writing about
                                    literature. Students are clearly attracted to the visual aspects
                                    of electronic culture. Do the visual images lead students to a
                                    better understanding of cultural differences? Can pictures and
                                    sound, because they seem comfortable and knowable, enable
                                    students to learn what is different about other cultures and
                                    other historical periods, and learn to read and understand the
                                    cultural referents in a literary text? Those questions lead one
                                    to a complex matrix of assumptions about knowledge, reading, and
                                    culture, which this paper will develop in relation to teaching
                                    literary and cultural studies via the electronic medium.</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Textual Studies</head>
                                <p>By "textual studies" I mean work with the language and structure
                                    of a text. The electronic medium greatly enhances close reading
                                    of the literary text. From easy access to "virtual reference
                                    room" sources (dictionary, bible, myth, time lines) to textual
                                    analysis (word counts, collocates, structural analysis),
                                    electronic texts allow students to work closely with the
                                    language and structure of a literary text, to analyze local
                                    structures and meanings, and to study how linguistic patterns
                                    play out in a longer work. SGML enables students to work
                                    structurally and formally, and particularly to study the
                                    relationship between language and structure in a literary work.
                                    Students are encouraged to test out their own ideas about the
                                    text, and to see whether and how those ideas are manifest in the
                                    text's language. It would seem that one does not need images to
                                    perform strictly "textual" studies in this sense.</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Writing about Literature</head>
                                <p>It would also seem that one does not need anything more than
                                    words to teach students how to write about the language of a
                                    literary text: take the data they have from close work with the
                                    text's language and structure and teach them how to translate
                                    that data into an argument about the text. One can even teach
                                    them to perform textual analysis on their own work (which words
                                    and phrases appear repeatedly? what are they close to? what are
                                    they code for? do key words appear in the key sections of the
                                    text?), and to think about their own writing as linguistic and
                                    rhetorical structure. One might imagine that student's writing
                                    is enhanced by close work with the language of a literary text,
                                    particularly in the absence of all the hypertext capabilities
                                    they like so much, but tend to use like a video game. </p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Cultural Studies, Literary History, and Electronic
                                    Texts</head>
                                <p>In order to understand why one needs the images--even to teach
                                    students to perform linguistic and textual analysis--we need to
                                    think about the electronic text in relationship to other
                                    historical and cultural variants of the literary text. I take
                                    cultural studies and literary history to be necessarily
                                    overlapping domains. By "cultural studies" I mean the
                                    relationship between the text and its own history, and also its
                                    relationship with other literary and cultural texts.</p>
                                <p>Here one begins with the materiality of the text: what it looked
                                    like, which texts it was responding to, how it was produced (by
                                    the author, the publisher, the audiences who first read it),
                                    what other texts (either words or images) appeared close to it
                                    in its original form, how it changed over time (how the words
                                    were arranged or packaged differently, what other texts appeared
                                    near it in new contexts). The cultural history of a literary
                                    text quickly leads the scholar or teacher to the text as a
                                    material object, and its relationship to other texts as material
                                    objects (a bible that fits inside a lady's purse is very
                                    different from a folio produced for reference in a library; one
                                    gets a much clearer sense of what Katherine Phillips's poems are
                                    trying to do when one sees the early 17th-century emblem books
                                    she was imitating; the allusions in Jane Barker's manuscript
                                    poems come from anti-Catholic broadsides of the 1680s; etc.).
                                    Some of this information could be conveyed (and in some cases,
                                    conveyed better) by verbal description, and some things will
                                    never be knowable without access to the original text. However,
                                    images of material included with the published versions of a
                                    literary text--title page, front matter, engravings--allow the
                                    student to feel that much closer to the original "text," the
                                    book that people held in their hands, read to one another, and
                                    experienced--in some sense--as a physical object. The feeling of
                                    comfort and proximity associated with printed books, and with
                                    the way knowledge is conveyed through books, extends to the
                                    pedagogical situation.</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Conclusions</head>
                                <p>We are clearly in a transitional moment, and many of our students
                                    learn better in the electronic medium than they do by
                                    traditional means. Images (visual and aural) are crucial to
                                    teaching what is actually different about literature from
                                    different historical moments. I do not mean to be offering a
                                    simple paean to hypertext, or to multimedia, or to electronic
                                    dazzle of any kind; rather, I wish to suggest that we and our
                                    students already think about--and inevitably study--literary
                                    texts as cultural, material, and visual artifacts. We study (and
                                    teach and produce) layers of textual meaning that work back and
                                    forth between text as reproducible verbal structure and text as
                                    multiple, ambiguous and conflicting instances. While much
                                    crucial cultural information about a text resides outside
                                    it--and is thus the responsibility of the teacher or scholar,
                                    but not the textbase editor--those aspects of the text that were
                                    originally visual ought to be included as part of a textbase
                                    that is intended as a pedagogical resource. Rather than recreate
                                    formalism in the electronic medium, I want to argue that we
                                    should think of this new textual domain as part of cultural and
                                    interdisciplinary history, and therefore a place in which the
                                    words of a text always exist in relationship to other verbal and
                                    visual texts, which ideally one ought to be able to have access
                                    to for teaching and scholarship.</p>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
