<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The Model Editions Partnership--Towards a National
                    Database</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">David</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">R.</forename>
                        <surname>Chesnutt</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of South Carolina</name>
                            <email>David.Chesnutt@sc.edu</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>SGML</item>
                        <item>editing</item>
                        <item>database</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>1. Introduction to Model Editions Partnership</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>1.1. Purpose and Goals</head>
                        <p>The Model Editions Partnership is developing a series of sample editions
                            for delivering historical documents on the World-Wide Web. The
                            Partnership includes the editors of seven on-going documentary editions
                            as well as leaders from the Text Encoding Initiative and the Center for
                            Electronic Text in the Humanities. The project began in July 1995 with
                            major funding from the National Historical Publications and Records
                            Commission (U.S.) and the University of South Carolina. The first six
                            phases will be completed in June 1998. The goals for that three-year
                            period are:<list type="bulleted">
                                <item>To help define the scholarly frameworks for tomorrow's
                                    historical editions.</item>
                                <item>To develop practical solutions for creating and delivering
                                    those editions.</item>
                                <item>To establish sample editions which demonstrate a variety of
                                    solutions to the first two goals.</item>
                                <item>To move the editorial community into the mainstream of
                                    electronic text.</item>
                                <item>To help lay the foundation for a national database to enhance
                                    the use of historical editions.</item>
                            </list></p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>1.2. SGML Markup</head>
                        <p>The Partnership is predicated on the view that SGML markup can be used to
                            create the scholarly frameworks required and that SGML markup offers a
                            practical method for preparing and delivering documentary editions. A
                            close study of the scholarly issues involved in preparing documentary
                            editions led to the publication of "A Prospectus for Electronic
                            Historical Editions" in May 1996 (<ptr
                                target="http://mep.cla.sc.edu/prostoc.htm"/>). The Prospectus set
                            forth a series of design principles; a typology of the kind of editions
                            which might be expected to develop; and a discussion of importance of
                            markup. (A report on the Prospectus was given at the ALLC/ACH conference
                            in Bergen.)</p>
                        <p>The Bergen report also noted the Partnership's development of two
                            Document Type Definitions based on a subset of the TEI Guidelines. The
                            data-capture DTD<list type="bulleted">
                                <item>Defines a new MEP header for each historical document.</item>
                                <item>Redefines &lt;docGroup&gt; and other elements to
                                    accommodate the way in which scholarly editors typically
                                    organize material in the editions.</item>
                                <item>Eliminates many of the TEI prose elements like
                                    &lt;opener&gt; used to group elements at the beginning
                                    and end of documents.</item>
                                <item>Substitutes explicit elements in place of the
                                    &lt;hi&gt; (highlight) element and its
                                    attributes.</item>
                                <item>Defines new elements as appropriate.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The archival DTD retains the MEP header and the redefinition of
                            &lt;docGroup&gt; and the other elements required for the
                            structure of historical editions. However, divisional units like
                            &gt;opener&lt; are restored as is the more familiar highlight
                            element with its attributes. This transformation is done mechanically.
                            The premise here is that future migration of the data will be more
                            easily accomplished if the archival markup of the data conforms more
                            closely to current TEI markup.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2. Progress Report on Implementation</head>
                    <p>As this abstract is being written, the staff is marking up the text of the
                        sample editions and plans are being made for delivering the sample editions
                        on the Web in June 1997. One of the major facets of the presentation at
                        ACHALLC97 will be a progress report on encoding and delivering the samples,
                        which will take place between November 1996 and the end of May 1997.
                        Although it is impossible to predict with certainty the details of our
                        progress at this time, certain aspects of the development of the sample
                        editions in that period are predictable.</p>
                    <div>
                        <head>2.1 Evolution of Markup</head>
                        <p>Despite the intensive review of documents which provided the basis for
                            the development of the data-capture DTD, experience shows that markup
                            systems evolve over time. Some changes may be made for the convenience
                            of data entry; others, because new textual features are identified; and
                            still others, because textual features previously ignored assume
                            importance in the eyes of the scholar. The presentation will review our
                            experience in these areas with explicit examples of where we chose to
                            expand the DTD as well as other cases where we chose <emph rend="bold"
                                >not</emph> to expand the DTD. Beyond the markup questions which
                            arise from the texts are those which will undoubtedly arise as we move
                            the data into the delivery environments.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>2.2 Implementation of Delivery Software</head>
                        <p>We expect to deliver the sample editions using both SoftQuad's Panorama
                            and Electronic Book Techology's DynaWeb. At this point, we have created
                            small mockups with Panorama, but we have no experience with DynaWeb. (We
                            have been accepted in EBT's Higher Education Grant program and our full
                            application is currently pending.) Markup issues associated with
                            implementing the samples in each software package are important and the
                            ACHALLC97 presentation will summarize our findings in this area. To put
                            it another way, we will look at the following questions. Which markup is
                            easier to implement in each of the delivery systems? Are there
                            adjustments in either DTD which would make it easier? What are the
                            trade-offs if DTDs are modified to facilitate delivery? Modification of
                            the DTDs can, of course, be avoided by transforming the existing data to
                            meet the required formats for the delivery software. This can be
                            accomplished with macros or filters and is a common practice used in
                            print publishing. At the same time, we have sometimes found that the
                            markup we were using could have been modified with no loss of
                            information and with significant gains in processing--thus reducing
                            costs.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3. Towards a National Database</head>
                    <p>The idea of establishing a national database for American documentary
                        editions has been implicit from the beginning of the Model Editions
                        Partnership. A database of American materials which cuts across the
                        humanities and sciences offers many advantages which cannot be accomplished
                        easily by piece-meal publication. We have often noted that scholarly
                        editions are printed on paper designed to last 300 years. If we are to
                        achieve similar longevity in our electronic editions, we must have the kind
                        of infrastructure that supports itself and the migration of the editions. A
                        subscription database can meet those requirements. Further, the gathering of
                        editions in a digital archives will facilitate cross-edition searching and
                        cross-edition indexing. And we can expect such a depository to provide the
                        metadata required by librarians as well as version control. The ACHALLC97
                        presentation will expand on these themes and describe some of the projects
                        which are being planned as stepping stones toward the establishment of an
                        American Documentary Heritage database.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
