<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Adapting Web Electronic Libraries to English
                    Studies</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Ian</forename>
                        <surname>Lancashire</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Toronto</name>
                            <email>ian@chass.utoronto.ca </email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christopher</forename>
                        <surname>Douglas</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Toronto</name>
                            <email>cdouglas@chass.utoronto.ca</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Dennis</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">G.</forename>
                        <surname>Jerz</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Toronto</name>
                            <email>d.jerz@utoronto.ca</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>web</item>
                        <item>electronic-library</item>
                        <item>English</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>The UTEL Project</head>
                    <p>We are developing a Web-based University of Toronto English library (named
                        UTEL) under a development grant from the Provost's office. UTEL aims to
                        integrate electronic materials into both teaching and research activities of
                        English faculty and students. Our basic materials come from the CD-ROM
                        published by the Modern Language Association of America with <title
                            level="m">Using TACT with Electronic Texts</title> (New York, 1996):
                        over 3,000 texts from <title level="m">Beowulf</title> to World-War-I
                        poetry. Many of these texts are donated by Dr. Jeffery Triggs, director of
                        the North America Reading Program for the Oxford English Dictionary. Many
                        come from new editions of major English works--based on original editions
                        and manuscripts--by the project director, Ian Lancashire. Other materials
                        are contributed by members of the English department especially for UTEL. It
                        is already partly on the Web in <title level="m">Representative Poetry
                            On-line</title>, a collection of 1,340 poems by over 215 poets.
                        Inevitably, current UTEL development emphasizes texts from other genres:
                        drama, novels, and non-fiction prose.</p>
                    <p>A full-time faculty member, who works on the project without release time,
                        directs two graduate assistants from the Department of English Ph.D.
                        program, who have year-long contracts. Both do research in 20th-century
                        literature. One is a C++ programmer and Web-site designer for a Faculty of
                        Engineering Writing Facility. The other has no prior programming experience.
                        UTEL has very sound infrastructural support from the Faculty of Arts and
                        Science through its CHASS (Computers in the Humanities and Social Sciences)
                        facility, the heir to the Centre for Computing in the Humanities (CCH), and
                        from the University Library through its Information Commons and Web Design
                        Group.</p>
                    <p>UTEL project members routinely segment, encode in HTML, document, and index
                        these texts with <emph rend="italics">TACTweb</emph> and <emph
                            rend="italics">patterweb</emph>, both local search engines. Users will
                        be able to read the texts or print them out as well as search them. We use
                        java, perl, sed, emacs, and other well-known UNIX utilities to design the
                        Web pages.</p>
                    <p>We routinely discuss our work with departmental members of differing
                        professional persuasions. They include postmodernists, deconstructionists,
                        new historicists, philologists, feminists, diehard new critics,
                        psychological critics, language teachers, and computer-based and cultural
                        theorists. Although the university provides all faculty and students with
                        e-mail addresses and Web access, workstations are at a premium still. Many
                        find logging on difficult in practice. Most faculty offices are not yet
                        connected to the university backbone.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The Limits of the Virtual Library</head>
                    <p>The construction of UTEL-like sites is likely to become common in the near
                        future because of the availability of good Web browsers and of the resources
                        of many university e-text sites, including the texts on the MLA CD-ROM.
                        However, we believe that Web-based virtual libraries need to be
                        reconceptualized to function well within post-secondary education.</p>
                    <p>UTEL-like virtual educational sites sometimes depart from discipline
                        standards. The lack of peer-reviewed material, the instability of sites, and
                        usability problems with on-line materials for reading, note-taking, and
                        in-class reference can be swept away by improving technology. Yet inevitably
                        UTEL-like sites aid a kind of text-based discourse analysis more than
                        literary studies emphasizing biography, history, and cultural context.
                        On-line libraries like UTEL match the professional needs of English studies
                        differently from one type of theoretical approach to another. This
                        privileging exists partly because on-line UTEL-like sites are
                        computer-based, partly because they have been modelled by computational
                        researchers.</p>
                    <p>UTEL-like sites, if conceived of as information banks, do not yet meet the
                        needs of the whole profession of English studies. They tend to supply the
                        needs of librarians, computer scientists, and English researchers at work in
                        computational text analysis and editing. Current electronic libraries favour
                        teaching and research methods of those who analyze or edit texts and those
                        who use a scientific method in doing so. There is nothing inappropriate
                        about this approach (quite the contrary), but no general-purpose medium for
                        education, such as the Web, should treat one type of theoretical and
                        practical work differently from another.</p>
                    <p>For this reason, a local discipline-based Web site should be re-conceived as
                        a collection of individual faculty and departmental offices, each occupied
                        by an on-line double of a faculty member, each drawing on a UTEL-like
                        library. Sites of this kind would resemble a network of artificial
                        intelligences that correspond to current faculty members and that can serve
                        students and indeed the public with their expertise and learning around the
                        clock.</p>
                    <p>The pressing issue in on-line educational computing is not etexts or encoding
                        methods, not computerized classrooms or search engines. The issue is how to
                        organize UTEL-like sites to enhance the usability of a discipline's
                        researchers and teachers within the university and within the community.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Artificial Intelligences and the Web</head>
                    <p>In 1988 Hans Moravec, a computer scientist at Carnegie- Mellon, forecast that
                        in 2018 the technology will exist to capture directly in digital form an
                        individual's thoughts on-line. He wrote only four years after sf- writer
                        William Gibson's <title level="m">Neuromancer</title>, set at about this
                        future time, depicted the virtual lives of Henry Case and Dixie Flatline on
                        a net eventually governed by a joint artificial intelligence code-named
                        Wintermute and Neuromancer. Ten years later another Nebula-award winner,
                        Canadian Robert Sawyer, portrayed in <title level="m">The Terminal
                            Experiment</title> (1995) a psychological case study of immortality
                        obtained by a Toronto doctor who made three virtual copies of his mind,
                        released into the Internet.</p>
                    <p>This speculative fiction is far from today's crude software agents, the
                        go-bots that conduct intelligent on- line searches for clients and report
                        back results meeting very selective criteria. Yet the direction of the
                        marketplace itself is clear enough. Information banks are not sufficient.
                        Intelligent advice on how to harness them must be in place. Just as
                        universities place information in libraries and situate the intelligence to
                        negotiate that knowledge base in faculty members and librarians, so on-line
                        universities must supplement their Web sites with on-line intelligences. </p>
                    <p>A faculty member's Web page is potentially his professional double. It can
                        echo almost the scholar's entire productivity: course descriptions,
                        bibliographies, schedules, texts, and notes; self-administerable student
                        tests; lecture notes; curriculum vitae; faq sheets; and interactive
                        question-answering programs. Most of this technology exists today, but
                        UTEL-like Web sites in this context must be re-conceptualized as feeding the
                        needs of on-line simacula of individual teacher-researchers as well as
                        departmental sites that represent the faculty as a group.</p>
                    <p>We will discuss how teacher-researchers, no matter what their theoretical
                        perspective may be, can be linked with UTEL-like sites; and how that step
                        will both ease the university's transformation by information technology and
                        re-establish the primacy of faculty in an on-line academe.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Ian</forename>
                                    <surname>Lancashire</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>in collaboration with</resp>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">John</forename>
                                    <surname>Bradley</surname>
                                </name>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Willard</forename>
                                    <surname>McCarty</surname>
                                </name>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Michael</forename>
                                    <surname>Stairs</surname>
                                </name>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Wooldridge</surname>
                                </name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title level="m">Using TACT with Electronic Texts: Text Analysis
                                Computing Tools Version 2.1</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>MLA</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>With CD-ROM.</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Ian</forename>
                                    <surname>Lancashire</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Representative Poetry On-Line: Updating A Historical
                                English Teaching Anthology</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Siemens</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">William</forename>
                                    <surname>Winder</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Scholarly Discourse and Computing Technology:
                                Perspectives on Pedagogy, Research, and Dissemination in the
                                Humanities</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>Printed in <title level="j">Text Technology</title> and on-line in
                                <title level="j">Computing in the Humanities Working
                            Papers</title>.</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Hans</forename>
                                    <surname>Moravec</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Mind Children: The Future of Robot and Human
                                Intelligence</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1988">1988</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">
                                <ref
                                    target="http://www.library.utoronto.ca/utel/rp/rp.html"
                                    >Representative Poetry On-line</ref>
                            </title>
                            <edition>Version 2.0</edition>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Toronto</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>University of Toronto Library</publisher>
                                <date when="1994">1994-</date>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
