<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Eighteenth-Century Cities in an Interdisciplinary
                    Curriculum: Creating a CD-ROM -- Hyperlink Structure and Interpretive
                    Approaches</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Liliane</forename>
                        <surname>Gallet-Blanchard</surname>
                        <affiliation>Department of English <name type="org">Université Paris
                                IV-SORBONNE</name>
                            <email>Liliane.Gallet@wanadoo.fr</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Marie-Madeleine</forename>
                        <surname>Martinet</surname>
                        <affiliation>Department of English <name type="org">Université Paris
                                IV-SORBONNE</name>
                            <email>marie-madeleine.martinet@paris4.sorbonne.fr</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Virginia</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, VA</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/AlLC 1999</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <forename type="middle"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <p>The presentation shows how hypertextual modelling gives multiple contexts to
                        documents in urban studies, representing an interdisciplinary approach. It
                        starts from the example of a hypermedia program on eighteenth-century cities
                        developed with Director authoring software by the Research Centre "Cultures
                        Anglophones et Technologies de l'Information" (CATI) - Université de
                        Paris-Sorbonne.</p>
                    <p>Such a program focuses on the documents' integration in a contextualized
                        setting (Carter). The pathway structure (McAleese) allows the types of
                        hyperlinks to represent distinct approaches to the subject (Deegan).
                        Integrating electronic documents into humanities studies (Seaman) introduces
                        alternative methods, in accordance with the capacity of hypermedia programs
                        to develop sequentially for literary texts or to follow hypertext links in
                        cultural studies (Madsen). This procedure exploits the aesthetics of
                        cyberspace and its own structures, making full use of the meanings which are
                        encoded in the medium (Murray).</p>
                    <p>The range of documents aims to reconstruct the total experience of the urban
                        world. It complements interactive maps with photographs, pictures and
                        animations, and with literary descriptions or audio files -views of music
                        rooms with extracts of works performed there-; it adds interpretive
                        documents, encouraging reflexive interactivity.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Data and structure</head>
                    <p>The program is designed so that the data should always be seen as part of the
                        structure in which they are embedded (Delany and Landow). It places each
                        document in a series of choices between views in different scales (an
                        overview of a topic, or a map of a city, leading to subchapters or to
                        buildings indicated by hot spots, with return buttons to the overall view),
                        and in several contexts--for instance a topographical setting and thematic
                        references, as a multidetermined hub of links (Vauxhall linked to a map, but
                        also part of chapters on gardens, music and literature). The semantic
                        structure can change, recentring the thematic nodes: while the navigation
                        bar remains identical, new sets of buttons appear according to the
                        contexts.</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>a)users can at any moment alternate between the information delivery
                            level and that of organization, accessing the site map with its
                            hierarchy of subject headings, where the title of the section containing
                            the current frame is highlighted; for example they may start from a city
                            then move to its section on religion and from there to a general chapter
                            on religion: switching to the site map at that point will highlight
                            'Topics/Religion' emphasizing that the user has moved from topographical
                            to thematic navigation.</item>
                        <item>b)section and screen: sections are arranged so that a constant element
                            (eg. a map or a view of a building) is retained through several screens
                            while another part of the screen displays additional details in
                            sequence; a button 'return to top screen of section' allows the user to
                            replace a frame in the overall structure.</item>
                        <item>c)screen and document: anchors open on context-sensitive
                            hyperlinks.</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Software concepts and interpretive research</head>
                    <p>The conditional links incite the students to make a selection between buttons
                        to move to the next screen, increasing their awareness of the spatial
                        dimensions and temporal structures in literature (Dawson) or in art.</p>
                    <p>Software concepts can be incorporated into issues-based approaches (Bass), so
                        that the variety of interactive effects emphasizes methodological
                        differences in interdisciplinary subjects. Hypermedia integrates the
                        specific software applications developed by several disciplines, imaging
                        their respective methods and goals. Modelling of theories draws attention to
                        methodology (McCarty). Interactivity enriches the interpretation, for
                        instance supplementing architectural morphology with the analysis of society
                        and showing the building in use (Scott), or experiencing the visual axes
                        from many locations of the plan (Thomas). These effects are obtained using
                        the 'perspective' facility in a CAD software, in a simulation of
                        architectural draughtsmanship: having to choose between viewing a building
                        in elevation or in oblique perspective differentiates between these options
                        in architectural drawing (Hiley).</p>
                    <p>The options of hyperlinks on complex documents correspond to distinct
                        interpretive methods, keeping the other options as a background. Some are
                        branching buttons, leading to several types of contextualization, such as
                        that of social and economic life (the museum of eighteenth-century life at
                        'No 1 The Crescent' or Covent Garden as a market), or literary and artistic
                        representations (Fielding's descriptions and Hogarth's paintings). Others
                        start problem-solving sections in activity spaces, for instance integrating
                        the history of mathematical methods into social history: in a simulation of
                        cartographic methods, interactive objects representing surveyors and their
                        instruments can be activated by the user to reconstruct the phases of
                        map-making; the two options underline the differences between surveying,
                        where the user has to move a figure of a surveyor associated with
                        conditional scripts, and using trigonometry, where the user has to enter
                        calculations in an editable field.</p>
                    <p>Mediating documents through electronic presentation emphasizes the
                        interaction of content and method.</p>
                    <figure/>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Randall</forename>
                                    <surname>Bass</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Integrating Research and Pedagogy through an Electronic
                                Archive Project in an American Studies Curriculum</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">ACH / ALLC Conference 1994</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Bryan</forename>
                                    <surname>Carter</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">From Imagination to Reality: Using Immersion Technology
                                in a Literary Setting</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">DRH 98</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">John</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Dawson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">A Dimensional Analysis of Narrative and
                                Dialogue</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">ACH / ALLC Conference 1994</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Marilyn</forename>
                                    <surname>Deegan</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">"Transgressing the Boundaries of Texts</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Gestion électronique de données et nouvelles
                                technologies en sciences humaines</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Presses de l'Université de Paris-Sorbonne</publisher>
                                <date when="1995">1995</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">33-42</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Paul</forename>
                                    <surname>Delany</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <forename type="first">George</forename>
                                <forename type="middle">P.</forename>
                                <surname>Landow</surname>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Hypermedia and Literary Studies</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Cambridge, Mass.</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>MIT</publisher>
                                <date when="1991">1991</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Mike</forename>
                                    <surname>Hiley</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Presenting Heritage on the Web</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">DRH 98</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.BoughtonHouse.org.uk"/>&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Ray</forename>
                                    <surname>McAleese</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Catherine</forename>
                                    <surname>Green</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Hypertext: State of the Art</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Intellect</publisher>
                                <date when="1990">1990</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Willard</forename>
                                    <surname>McCarty</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">What is Humanities Computing</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m"/>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr
                                target="http://ilex.cc.kcl.ac.uk/wlm/essays/what/what_is.html"
                            />&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Deborah</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Madsen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Hypertext and Critical/Cultural Theory</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Computers and Texts</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">11</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">4-6</biblScope>
                                <date when="1996">March 1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Janet</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Murray</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Hamlet on the Holodeck or Towards an Aesthetics of
                                Cyberspace</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">ACH / ALLC Conference 1994</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Sarah</forename>
                                    <surname>Scott</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Simon</forename>
                                    <surname>Fitzpatrick</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Ellen</forename>
                                    <surname>Pawley</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Helen</forename>
                                    <surname>Pownall</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Architecture and Society : Interactive Approaches to
                                Architectural Design and Use</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Craft</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">18</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">7-9</biblScope>
                                <date when="1998">Summer 1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">David</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Seaman</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">From Margin to Mainstream</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">ACH / ALLC Conference 1994</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Judith</forename>
                                    <surname>Thomas</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Creating Places: The Virtual Tour and the Media
                                Archive</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m"/>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr
                                target="ftp://ftp.virginia.edu/public_access/dic/thomas/rainey1.jpg"
                            />&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
