<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The "Preposterous Muddle" Revisited: An XML Thematic
                    Catalog DTD</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Perry</forename>
                        <surname>Roland</surname>
                        <affiliation>Technology Services Alderman Library <name type="org"
                                >University of Virginia</name>
                            <email>pdr4h@virginia.edu</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Virginia</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, VA</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1999</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <forename type="middle"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>Thematic catalogs of music have been produced for centuries. Yet, little
                        attention has been paid to the study of this class of documents due to its
                        specialized and complex nature. This paper describes the thematic catalog,
                        its value in the field of music bibliography, and proposes an XML Document
                        Type Definition that, it is hoped, will stimulate debate on the value of
                        standardization of this document class.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>What is a Thematic Catalog?</head>
                    <p>A thematic catalog systematically arranges a body of music. Its general
                        functions are the same as other bibliographical tools: identification,
                        location, and collocation. The thematic catalog, however, derives special
                        power from the use of brief citations of music, called incipits, which
                        provide more certain identification of musical works than any single element
                        or combination of elements used for other materials, such as creator, title,
                        publisher, or date. (Brook, p. vii) Such precise identification is necessary
                        because a single musical work can exist in multiple printed and recorded
                        editions, because portions of musical works are frequently published or
                        performed separately (sometimes with a different title) with no reference to
                        the parent work, and because entire musical works, or selected portions, are
                        often arranged or transcribed to create "new" entities. (Nagy, p. 15)</p>
                    <p>Brook identifies several applications for thematic catalogs -- mnemonic aid,
                        table of contents, guide to a composer's own output, inventory of library
                        holdings, advertisement for a copying or publishing firm, legal document,
                        compilation of "true" themes, musicological documentation, and thematic
                        locator for incipits without an existing catalog. (Brook, p. x-xv) This list
                        of functions demonstrates the same continuum of activity from simple
                        list-making to complex analytical endeavor observed in general
                        bibliographies. (Krummel 1984, p. 4)</p>
                    <p>The Value of Thematic Catalogs Thematic catalogs have long been recognized as
                        a solution to the special problems of accessing and describing music. The
                        earliest examples of thematic catalogs were produced in the 9th to 11th
                        centuries (Brook, p. x). The fact that production of printed thematic
                        catalogs has increased every year since 1850 (Basart, p.7) also demonstrates
                        their value. Vincent Duckles wrote "the thematic catalog is one of the most
                        useful of all reference tools in the field of music bibliography." (Duckles,
                        p. 552) While Duckles was primarily concerned with the value of thematic
                        catalogs to scholars, librarians, and catalogers, Brook's list clearly
                        demonstrates their usefulness to many segments of the music community.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>How is a Thematic Catalog Organized?</head>
                    <p>Despite Cowley's statement that "the compiler of a bibliography ... is bound
                        by no conventional rules of arrangement" (Cowley, p. 179), several
                        organizational methods can be identified for thematic catalogs. When dealing
                        with the work of a single composer, catalog entries are usually arranged
                        chronologically or in some classified manner, e.g., by genre. (Basart, p. 6)
                        Alphabetical arrangement is usually preferred when addressing a single genre
                        or a body of works by many composers. It is not uncommon, however, to
                        encounter complex hierarchical arrangements, e.g., alphabetical geographical
                        entries containing alphabetical composer entries containing works listed by
                        date.</p>
                    <p>Responding to the rise in production of thematic catalogs, Hyatt King was the
                        first to set down the data requirements for a thematic catalog. (King, p.
                        45-46) His list of suggestions was later expanded based on examination of
                        catalogs created after the publication of King's guidelines. (Basart, p.
                        8-10) While not appropriate in every situation, the data requirements given
                        by King and Basart demonstrate the wide range of information that may be
                        included in a thematic catalog.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Why Do We Need a Standard?</head>
                    <p>The benefits to creators and users of an encoding and interchange standard
                        for thematic catalogs are many. The major benefit of a structured markup
                        language like XML is that syntax and semantics are treated separately. Once
                        the precise identification of the role of the information in a document is
                        accomplished, the data is almost infinitely malleable and can be distributed
                        in both print and electronic forms. This is a considerable advantage given
                        the difficulty of creating a thematic catalog and the wide-ranging needs of
                        its potential users.</p>
                    <p>Possible applications of the standard include: (1) encoding and interchange
                        of data in existing catalogs; (2) improvement of the quality of information
                        contained in future catalogs by providing a template for creators; (3)
                        realization of "music in print" or "recordings in print" publications,
                        highly desirable by the music community, comparable to the cumulative trade
                        catalogs the book world enjoys (Krummel 1987, p. 47); 4) creation of
                        databases necessary for identifying anonymi, eradicating past errors of
                        attribution, resolving multiple-parent riddles, and providing data for
                        future research, e.g., stylistic analysis (LaRue, p. 1181).</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Why Not Use an Existing DTD?</head>
                    <p>The DTDs that exhibit potential for markup of thematic catalogs (TEI and
                        MARC) are unsatisfactory. TEI is designed primarily for representing texts,
                        not data, while MARC uses a flat database approach that doesn't accommodate
                        markup of existing catalogs. In addition, neither DTD allows markup of
                        musical data using recognized musical terminology, such as "clef" or "pitch
                        range". Consequently, markup of this group of documents is more likely to be
                        successful if a new DTD, under the control of the music community, is
                        created.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The MusiCat DTD</head>
                    <p>The MusiCat DTD is intended to meet the specialized needs of thematic catalog
                        creators and users. It provides traditional access points like title,
                        creator, and imprint as well as music-specific data elements, such as tempo,
                        meter, and key.</p>
                    <p>The DTD allows for the many bibliographic arrangements encountered by using
                        (descriptive unit) elements. Data elements within the are optional and
                        repeatable, including additional descriptive units. This approach is
                        structured enough to be usable for database-oriented applications, but loose
                        enough to accommodate presentation-oriented existing catalogs. It is also
                        applicable to other kinds of catalogs and bibliographies where extensibility
                        is a concern.</p>
                    <p>The use of header information at each descriptive level allows for the
                        inclusion of management data necessary for collaborative projects and data
                        access restriction, very important concerns to the music community.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>MusiCat Examples</head>
                    <p>While space does not permit inclusion of the entire DTD, short examples of
                        compliant markup are provided below.</p>
                    <div><head>Example 1</head>
                        <eg>           &lt;musicat&gt; 
                            &lt;catalog id="18thItalianInstr"&gt;
                            
                            &lt;descunit class="composer" id="besozzi"&gt;
                            
                            &lt;creator&gt;Besozzi, Alessandro, 
                            &lt;daterange&gt;&lt;date&gt;1702&lt;/date&gt;&lt;date&gt;1775&lt;/date&gt;&lt;/daterange&gt; 
                            &lt;biography&gt;
                            
                            &lt;p&gt;Oboe virtuoso active in the royal court of Turin ...&lt;/p&gt; 
                            &lt;p&gt;There are nineteen trio sonatas by Alessandro Besozzi ...&lt;/p&gt; 
                            
                            &lt;/biography&gt; 
                            
                            &lt;/creator&gt; 
                            &lt;descunit class="entry" id="It67"&gt;
                            
                            &lt;md&gt;&lt;key class="sig"&gt;A major&lt;/key&gt;&lt;/md&gt; 
                            &lt;titlepage label="1."&gt;
                            
                            &lt;title&gt;Sonata a tre&lt;/title&gt; / Del Sigr. Allessandro Besozzi/ Basso/ 
                            
                            &lt;/titlepage&gt; 
                            &lt;physdesc&gt;
                            
                            &lt;extent&gt;v 1 &amp; 2, bass.&lt;/extent&gt; 
                            &lt;dimensions&gt;22x30.5 cm&lt;/dimensions&gt; 
                            &lt;otherphysdetail&gt;Hand A. Brown&lt;/otherphysdetail&gt; 
                            
                            &lt;/physdesc&gt; 
                            &lt;inciplist&gt;
                            
                            &lt;incip&gt;
                            
                            &lt;notation&gt;&lt;!-- musical notation --&gt;&lt;/notation&gt; 
                            &lt;md&gt;
                            
                            &lt;duration units="measures"&gt;:11:+:14:&lt;/duration&gt; 
                            &lt;tempo class="term"&gt;Andante&lt;/tempo&gt; 
                            
                            &lt;/md&gt; 
                            
                            &lt;/incip&gt; 
                            &lt;incip&gt;
                            
                            &lt;notation&gt;&lt;!-- musical notation --&gt;&lt;/notation&gt; 
                            &lt;md&gt;
                            
                            &lt;duration units="measures"&gt;:34:+:38:&lt;/duration&gt; 
                            &lt;tempo class="term"&gt;Allegro&lt;/tempo&gt; 
                            
                            &lt;/md&gt; 
                            
                            &lt;/incip&gt; 
                            &lt;incip&gt;
                            
                            &lt;notation&gt;&lt;!-- musical notation --&gt;&lt;/notation&gt; 
                            &lt;md&gt;
                            
                            &lt;duration units="measures"&gt;:21:+:29:&lt;/duration&gt; 
                            &lt;tempo class="term"&gt;Allegro&lt;/tempo&gt; 
                            
                            &lt;/md&gt; 
                            
                            &lt;/incip&gt; 
                            
                            &lt;/inciplist&gt; 
                            &lt;bibref&gt; 
                            Published as no. 6 of 
                            &lt;title&gt;XII Sonates ... par Mrs. Bezzossi. Oevre IIe&lt;/title&gt;. 
                            &lt;imprint&gt;&lt;place&gt;Paris&lt;/place&gt;, 
                            &lt;publisher&gt;Le Clerc&lt;/publisher&gt;, 
                            &lt;date&gt;ca. 1740&lt;/date&gt;&lt;/imprint&gt; 
                            
                            &lt;/bibref&gt; 
                            
                            &lt;/descunit&gt; 
                            &lt;!-- additional descunits of class "entry" --&gt; 
                            
                            &lt;/descunit&gt; 
                            &lt;!-- additional descunits of class "composer" --&gt; 
                            &lt;/catalog&gt; 
                            &lt;/musicat&gt;</eg></div>
                   <div><head>Example 2</head> 
                       <eg>&lt;musicat&gt; 
                           &lt;catalog id="DaviesP"&gt;
                           
                           &lt;descunit class="dramatic works"&gt;
                           
                           &lt;descunit class="entry" id="d4"&gt;
                           
                           &lt;title&gt;The Lighthouse&lt;/title&gt; 
                           &lt;imprint&gt;&lt;date&gt;1979&lt;/date&gt;&lt;/imprint&gt; 
                           &lt;md&gt;&lt;duration units="time"&gt;75 mins&lt;/duration&gt;&lt;/md&gt; 
                           &lt;imprint&gt;&lt;publisher&gt;Chester Music&lt;/publisher&gt;&lt;/imprint&gt; 
                           &lt;md&gt;
                           
                           &lt;formgenre&gt;Chamber opera in one act with prologue&lt;/formgenre&gt; 
                           &lt;scoring&gt;for tenor, baritone, bass and instrumental ensemble&lt;/scoring&gt; 
                           
                           &lt;/md&gt; 
                           &lt;odd&gt;Libretto by the composer&lt;/odd&gt; 
                           &lt;performed&gt;
                           
                           &lt;performerlist label="Characters:&gt; 
                           &lt;performer&gt;
                           
                           &lt;dramatispersona&gt;Sandy, Officer 1&lt;/dramatispersona&gt;Tenor 
                           
                           &lt;/performer&gt; 
                           &lt;performer&gt;
                           
                           &lt;dramatispersona&gt;Blazes, Officer 2 
                           &lt;/dramatispersona&gt;Baritone 
                           
                           &lt;/performer&gt; 
                           &lt;performer&gt;
                           
                           &lt;dramatispersona&gt;Arthur, Voice of the Cards, Officer 3 &lt;/dramatispersona&gt;Tenor 
                           
                           &lt;/performer&gt; 
                           
                           &lt;/performerlist&gt; 
                           
                           &lt;/performed&gt; 
                           &lt;scoring&gt;flute (doubling piccolo and alto flute), clarinet in A ...&lt;/scoring&gt; 
                           &lt;scoring&gt;*percussion: marimba, 4 timpani, ...&lt;/scoring&gt; 
                           &lt;performed&gt;First performance &lt;date&gt;September 2, 1980&lt;/date&gt; at the
                           
                           &lt;corpname&gt;Edinburgh International Festival&lt;/corpname&gt; by &lt;performer&gt;Neil Mackie&lt;/performer&gt;, &lt;performer&gt;Michael Rippon&lt;/performer&gt;, &lt;performer&gt;David Wilson-Johnson&lt;/performer&gt; and &lt;performer class="group"&gt;The Fires of London&lt;/performer&gt; conducted by &lt;performer role="conductor"&gt;Richard Dufallo&lt;/performer&gt; 
                           &lt;/performed&gt; 
                           &lt;composed&gt;Commissioned by the &lt;corpname role="commissioner"&gt; Edinburgh International Festival&lt;/corpname&gt;. Winner of the first Tennent Caledonian Award. 
                           &lt;/composed&gt; 
                           &lt;imprint&gt;
                           
                           &lt;availability&gt;Full score, vocal score and parts for hire. Publication of full score and vocal score for sale 1981/2. Libretto on sale. 
                           &lt;/availability&gt; 
                           
                           &lt;/imprint&gt; 
                           
                           &lt;/descunit&gt; 
                           &lt;!-- additional descunits of class "entry" --&gt; &lt;/descunit&gt; 
                           
                           &lt;!-- additional genre descunits --&gt; 
                           
                           &lt;/catalog&gt; </eg></div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Ann</forename>
                                    <surname>Basart</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Bringing Order into Preposterous Muddle: Recent Trends
                                in Thematic Catalogs</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Cum notis variorum</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">67</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">5-17</biblScope>
                                <date when="1982">Nov. 1982</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Barry</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Brook</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Viano</forename>
                                    <surname>Richard</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Thematic Catalogues in Music: An Annotated
                                Bibliography</title>
                            <edition>2nd ed.</edition>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Pendragon Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">D.</forename>
                                    <surname>Cowley</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Bibliographical Description and Cataloguing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Grafton &amp; Co.</publisher>
                                <date when="1939">1939</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Vincent</forename>
                                    <surname>Duckles</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">A Checklist of Thematic Catalogues</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Notes</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">11</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">552</biblScope>
                                <date when="1954">Sept. 1954</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Charles</forename>
                                    <surname>Goldfarb</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Paul</forename>
                                    <surname>Prescod</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">The XML Handbook</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Upper Saddle River, N.J.</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Prentice-Hall PTR</publisher>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Alec</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">Hyatt</forename>
                                    <surname>King</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">The Past, Present and Future of the Thematic
                                Catalogue</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Monthly Music Record </title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">LXXXIV</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">953, 954</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">10-13, 39-46</biblScope>
                                <date when="1954">1954</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Krummel</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Bibliographical Handbook of American Music</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Urbana</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>University of Illinois Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1987">1987</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Krummel</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Bibliographies: Their Aims and Methods</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Mansell Publishing</publisher>
                                <date when="1984">1984</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Jan</forename>
                                    <surname>LaRue</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">George</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Logemann</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">EDP for Thematic Catalogues</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Notes</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">22</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">1179-86</biblScope>
                                <date when="1965">1965-66</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Kären</forename>
                                    <surname>Nagy</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Music Authority Control: A Public Service
                                Perspective</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Ruth</forename>
                                    <surname>Tucker</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Authority Control in Music Libraries</title>
                            <title level="s">MLA Technical Report No. 16</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Canton, MA</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Music Library Association</publisher>
                                <date when="1989">1989</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
