<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Timelines Online: Hypermedia and Information
                    Architecture in the Representation of Intellectual History</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">John</forename>
                        <surname>Zuern</surname>
                        <affiliation>Department of English, <name type="org">University of
                                Hawai'I</name>
                            <email>zuern@hawaii.edu</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Virginia</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Charlottesville, VA</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1999</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <forename type="middle"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>My presentation will address the potential--and some of the problems--of applying
                    the principles of information architecture and graphic design elaborated in the
                    work of Nielsen [13], Rosenfeld and Morville [15], Tufte [17], and Wurman [19]
                    to the creation of web-based educational resources that represent the history of
                    ideas. While my own work is focused on developing instructional materials in the
                    history of literary theory and criticism, my presentation discusses general
                    problems in the graphic design of timelines that are relevant to a number of
                    humanities disciplines.</p>
                <p>Although careful attention to historical issues is commonplace in courses on
                    literature, educators who confront the daunting task of teaching literary theory
                    often find that time constraints and the perceived difficulty of individual
                    texts preclude sufficient consideration of the historical and institutional
                    contexts which have shaped the formation of concepts, approaches, and
                    assumptions. Such consideration is, however, crucial for an understanding of any
                    theory's contribution. Carefully designed hypermedia systems have the potential
                    to represent intellectual history as a dynamic, networked process driven by
                    dialogue and contest, providing students a means of exploring the complexity of
                    that history and of entering into the conversation that sustains it.</p>
                <p>In an effort to move beyond an instrumental application of electronic media as a
                    storage-and-delivery system for learning materials, my project seeks to develop
                    design strategies that take into account developments in the theory of
                    historiography (e.g. Foucault [7], White [18], and Ginzburg [8]) that have
                    important implications for the representation of history in any format. With
                    reference to recent work in knowledge representation [12] and a series of
                    concrete examples, my paper will demonstrate some of the theoretical and
                    methodological challenges that arise when we turn to relatively static spatial
                    relationships as a means of conveying the dynamic temporal and conceptual
                    interconnections that characterize intellectual history. Developing solutions
                    for problems of design is a hermeneutic procedure that engages the designer in a
                    "dialogue with the design situation" [4] and demands a critical examination of
                    received frameworks for organizing historical knowledge. In the case of
                    graphical timelines, the dominant metaphor of the "line" itself tends to
                    privilege chronology, which presents history as a sequence of events, over
                    models that emphasize, for example, networks of discourses [7].</p>
                <p>The scope of my own project in its present form is restricted to the years
                    1965-1975, a decade in which a number of influential positions articulated
                    within philosophy, linguistics, and the social sciences began to inform
                    literary-critical study. In pursuing this project, I have attempted to meet the
                    following desiderata for resources of this kind:<list type="bulleted">
                        <item>to make available clear, accurate historical data, such as
                            biographical dates of important figures, publication dates, and the
                            dates and rosters of significant seminars and conferences, as well as
                            references to major historical, social, and cultural events that have an
                            impact on the development of ideas;</item>
                        <item>to augment the above data with the kinds of anecdotal material
                            valorized by the New Historicism in literary criticism as well as
                            relations of quotidian events, personal habits, and chance occurrences
                            of which records exists and out of which "microhistories" might be
                            assembled [8];</item>
                        <item>to ensure that the system encourages both browsing and known-item
                            searching;</item>
                        <item>to allow users to specify the types of information they wish to access
                            (for example, a chronological bibliography of an individual theorist's
                            publications or the genealogy of a particular critical term);</item>
                        <item>to allow users to control the level of granularity (for example,
                            choosing to access a chronological bibliography of an single theorist's
                            or of representative texts of an entire school of thought);</item>
                        <item>to permit multiple forms of access and interpretation (enlisting the
                            poetics of hypertext fiction to allow users to construct a range of
                            narratives that tell the multiple stories of the development of
                            contemporary literary theory).</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>These goals entail a number of conceptual and technical challenges. All
                    timelines, regardless of their form, write history in the course of displaying
                    it. As much as the historian, the courseware developer has to interpret the
                    materials at hand "in order to construct the moving pattern of images in which
                    the form of the historical process is to be mirrored" [18]. The relative
                    openness of hypermedia in relation to print documents does little to mitigate
                    the risk of imposing interpretations upon users; Aarseth [1] has argued that
                    predetermined paths in hypertext can restrict readers to a greater extent than
                    the eminently browsable formats of traditional print materials. Developers of
                    instructional media in all fields, especially those whose subject matter is as
                    complex and overdetermined as that of intellectual history, must be attuned to
                    the expressive and interpretative functions of content selection and navigation
                    design, concerns which cannot be extricated from the resource's overall
                    architecture and operability. One concern in particular is that of correlation:
                    how can the system encourage users to correlate historical data without
                    sacrificing the chronological or otherwise rational organizational structures of
                    the data?</p>
                <p>I will illustrate my remarks with demonstrations from my own project as well as
                    examples of print timelines (Kitts [9], Mann [11], and Davis [5]); interactive
                    timelines designed for educational kiosks (Skydeck [15]); web-based timelines
                    that employ HTML (Eckman [6] and Landow [10]), PDF (Bauer et al. [2]) and CGI
                    programming (Benjamin and Slaughter [3]). I conclude my discussion with
                    suggestions of how three-dimensional data-management and mapping systems such as
                    Dynamic Diagrams' MAPA system, Plumb Design's ThinkMap, and can further serve to
                    accomplish some of the goals outlined in my paper.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="book" n="1">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Aarseth</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Cybertext: Perspectives on Ergodic Literature</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="2">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Bauer</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">B.</forename>
                                    <surname>Carlson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Burgess</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Miller</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="u">Timeline of Computing History</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.computer.org/computer/timeline/"/>&gt;.
                            October 18, 1998.</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="3">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">B.</forename>
                                    <surname>Benjamin</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Slaughter</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="u">Literary Contests and Contexts Timelines</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr
                                target="http://www.cwrl.utexas.edu/~contests/critical_tools/e314l_fall_1998/archives/timelines/"
                            />&gt;. October 18, 1998.</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="4">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Coyne</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Snodgrass</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>

                            <title level="a">Is designing mysterious? challenging the dual knowledge
                                thesis</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Design Studies</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">2</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">124-131</biblScope>
                                <date when="1991">1991</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book" n="5">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Davis</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>West</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Women writers in the United States: a timeline of
                                literary, cultural, and social history</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="6">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Eckman</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="u">Modernism Timeline, 1890-1940</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr
                                target="http://weber.u.washington.edu/~eckman/frames/ftimeline.html"
                            />&gt;. November 25, 1998.</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book" n="7">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Michel</forename>
                                    <surname>Foucault</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">The Archeology of Knowledge and The Discourse on
                                Language</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <persName>
                                    <name>
                                        <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                        <forename type="middle">M.</forename>
                                        <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                                        <surname>Smith</surname>
                                    </name>
                                </persName>
                                <resp>(trans).</resp>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Pantheon</publisher>
                                <date when="1972">1972</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="8">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Carlo</forename>
                                    <surname>Ginzburg</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Microhistory: Two or Three Things That I Know about
                                It</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Critical Inquiry</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">20</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">10-35</biblScope>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="9">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">B.</forename>
                                    <surname>Kitts</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Printed Time</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Octavo: An International Journal of Typography</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">6</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">6-11</biblScope>
                                <date when="1988">1988</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="10">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Landow</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="u">The Victorian Web</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr
                                target="http://www.stg.brown.edu/projects/hypertext/landow/victorian/victov.html"
                            />&gt;. November 25, 1998.</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book" n="11">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Mann</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Landscape Architecture: An Illustrated History in
                                Timelines, Site Plans, and Biography</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>John Wiley and Sons</publisher>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book" n="12">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">B.</forename>
                                    <surname>Markman</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Knowledge Representation</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Mahwah, N.J.</pubPlace>
                                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum</publisher>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book" n="13">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Nielsen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Designing Web Sites with Authority: Secrets of an
                                Information Architect</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Indianapolis</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>New Riders</publisher>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="14">
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">Skydeck @ Embarcadero Center</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">19998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.sfskydeck.com/edu_hist.html"/>&gt;.
                            November 25, 1998.</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book" n="15">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Rosenfeld</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Morville</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Information Architecture for the World Wide Web:
                                Designing Large-Scale Web Sites</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>O'Reilly</publisher>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="16">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >F.</forename><surname>Roth</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >C.</forename><surname>Mei</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Kerpedijiev</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                        >A.</forename><surname>Kolojejchick</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Toward an Information Visualization Workspace:
                                Combining Multiple Means of Expression</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Human-Computer Interaction</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">12</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">131-185</biblScope>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>

                    <biblStruct type="book" n="17">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Tufte</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Visual Explanations: Images and Quantities, Evidence
                                and Narrative</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Cheshire, CT</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Graphics Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book" n="18">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Hayden</forename>
                                    <surname>White</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Tropics of Discourse: Essays in Cultural
                                Criticism</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1978"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book" n="19">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Wurman</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Information Architects</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Zurich</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Graphis Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
