<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The FALMER Project: Toward an Electronic Critical
                    Edition</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Michel</forename>
                        <surname>Bernard</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Université de la Sorbonne-Nouvelle (Paris III)</name>,
                            France <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Digital Resources</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>What will be the critical editions in the electronic era? Hubert de Phalèse, a
                    research center in La Sorbonne-Nouvelle University (Paris III), in accordance
                    with its pragmatic approach to literary computing problems, decided to launch
                    this debate by putting on line a critical edition of the complete works of
                    Lautréamont / Isidore Ducasse (<ptr
                        target="http://www.cavi.univ-paris3.fr/phalese/hubert1.htm"/>). This edition
                    is an integral hypertext (in which nearly every word of the text is linked with
                    a comment), which gathers all that one usually finds in the critical editions,
                    but on a scale which does not have equivalents on paper: variants, philological,
                    literary and encyclopedic comments, biography, bibliography, iconography, index,
                    etc.</p>
                <p>This prototype poses, concretely, a certain number of problems, on several levels:<list>
                        <item><emph rend="bold">Technical:</emph> Which interface is to be used? The
                            purely automatic search engines (including the uses of Java and other
                            script languages) appeared unsuited and a new device of
                            computer-assisted indexing was developed. It makes it possible to
                            provide to the user a lemmatized index and, especially, lexical cards
                            which can be enriched at will. The current solution of setting on line
                            presents some inconveniences but it has the advantage of proposing to
                            the greatest number of users the consultation of the edition and of
                            inviting them to take part in it.</item>
                        <item><emph rend="bold">Contents:</emph> The new support is, virtually,
                            infinite. What is a critical edition to contain now that we are not
                            concerned any more with its volume? All the versions of the text, for
                            example, can now be proposed with the reading. But does one have to
                            publish the intertexts, contemporary works, criticism, etc? How can the
                            interconnection, in network, of several resources enrich a critical
                            edition? Under which scientific and legal conditions?</item>
                        <item><emph rend="bold">Validation:</emph> Can this type of edition be
                            regarded as more reliable than the paper editions? According to which
                            protocols will such editions be judged? One of the risks is the
                            apparition of a great quantity of work without scientific guarantee. How
                            will the possibilities of collective work and permanent updating will
                            modify our design of what a philological work should be?</item>
                        <item><emph rend="bold">Publication:</emph> Who will deal with the building
                            and the diffusion expenses of such electronic products? Will the
                            redistribution of the budget headings in this type of edition lead the
                            academics to transform themselves into diffusers or will the traditional
                            editors change their practice? In addition, new prospects open with the
                            critical edition, which it will be necessary to evaluate and explore to
                            know the real potentialities of them.</item>
                        <item><emph rend="bold">Work in group:</emph> Data processing and the
                            Internet support the participation of a growing number of speakers
                            around an intellectual work. Which will be the roles of each one
                            (project director, data processing specialists, humanists, students,
                            active readers, etc.)? The concepts even of authors and readers will not
                            have any more the same direction.</item>
                        <item><emph rend="bold">Real time:</emph> The possibility of permanent
                            update offered by an Internet site makes it possible to revalue the
                            traditional concepts. It is not indeed essential any more to put on line
                            a completely completed work, and the noted errors can be immediately
                            corrected. In addition, this type of edition makes it possible to
                            account for the topicality of research in the field, which connects it
                            with a review (of which the periodicity is much higher besides than for
                            any scientific review).</item>
                        <item><emph rend="bold">Interactivity:</emph> The possibility of putting in
                            contact creators and users of electronic publishing, by means of the
                            electronic mail, also connects this type of edition to a permanent
                            conference. It is possible, in the long term, that scientific
                            communities (specialists in an author, for example) gather around great
                            electronic projects, that they would make live by publishing the results
                            of their work there.</item>
                        <item><emph rend="bold">Cost:</emph> The very low cost of setting on line
                            such an edition (I except the working time of researcher)s makes it
                            possible at the same time to consider some undertakings in the face of
                            of which the traditional editors move back (very large corpus, work of
                            interest only for few specialists) but also to allow researchers to
                            publish under some good working conditions works of weak size or that
                            don't fit in the framework of current university editions.</item>
                        <item><emph rend="bold">Multi-media:</emph> What can be the contribution of
                            multi-media to a scientific work like a critical edition? All in this
                            field remains to be invented, because the traditional edition accustomed
                            us to purely textual tools, primarily for reasons of cost. The sound and
                            visual illustrations will bring to the literary text a very interesting
                            dimension (publication of manuscripts, interpretations, iconographic
                            documents, contemporary pieces of music, etc), from the teaching point
                            of view as in the research field, but it is necessary to be wary of the
                            easy effects which accustomed us, the general public, to electronic
                            publishing. It is all the more urgent to answer these questions that the
                            share of electronic documentation in literary studies would have, as in
                            the other documentary fields, to increase until gradually replacing the
                            traditional supports. Consequently, the survival of the texts and their
                            formal characteristics will be closely related to the devices which will
                            ensure their transmission, their conservation and their reading.</item>
                    </list></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
