<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">A Corpus-Based Methodology for Identifying Non-nominal
                    "It": Rule-Based and Machine Learning Approaches</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Richard</forename>
                        <surname>Evans</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Wolverhampton</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Computational / Corpus Linguistics</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>In this paper, seven uses of "it" are identified in English. These uses involve
                    noun phrase anaphora (eg. "Do not sweep the dust when dry, you will only
                    recirculate IT."), verb phrase anaphora (eg. "Raising money for your favourite
                    charity can be fun. You can do IT on your own..."), reference to clauses (eg.
                    "Not every city would be suited to this approach, IT must be admitted."),
                    reference to entire discourse segments, (eg. "Always use a tool for the job it
                    was intended to do. Always use tools correctly. If IT feels very awkward,
                    stop."), cataphoric reference to entities (eg. "When IT fell, the glass
                    broke."), pleonastic uses in which the pronoun has no reference and is used only
                    due to a requirement of the grammar (eg. "IT was {raining, 4 o'clock, All
                    Saints' day, etc.}", "IT's recommended that...", "IT's easier to..."), and uses
                    in idiomatic constructions (eg. "I take IT you're going now."). Due to the
                    absence of a suitable term in the literature, the term "non-nominal it" is used
                    to identify all the cases in which "it" is not in an anaphoric relationship with
                    a noun phrase in the text. Numerous researchers have so far proposed
                    hand-crafted rule-based pattern matching techniques to identify pleonastic "it".
                    These methods have the drawback that they require recognition of potentially
                    large and open-ended lists of trigger words and complex expressions in order to
                    succeed. The goal here was to compare a rule-based method with a method devised
                    to use machine learning to make the identification. It was hoped that
                    information such as the position of the pronoun and its complex relation to the
                    surrounding syntactic context would contribute to the accuracy of the
                    identification. We implemented both methods. Corpora were constructed, annotated
                    and used to classify and evaluate the accuracy of these programs. A comparison
                    was made between them.</p>
                <p>The literature makes it easy to infer the importance of recognising non-nominal
                    uses of "it" in the fields of anaphora resolution, information retrieval,
                    machine translation and text summarisation. The task is especially crucial when
                    it is considered that almost one third of the uses of "it" in our corpus of
                    randomly selected texts were non-nominal.</p>
                <p>In the full paper, the treatment of pleonastic "it" in surveys of English usage
                    is reviewed, as is work by Paice &amp; Husk (1987), Lappin &amp; Leass (1994)
                    and Denber (1998) on methods for automatic recognition of pleonastic "it". The
                    application of machine learning to a different problem in linguistics is
                    described in the review of Litman (1996) on the automatic classification of cue
                    phrases. One of the methods in the present paper applies machine learning to the
                    automatic identification of non-nominal "it".</p>
                <p>A novel resource was required for this corpus-based research. A corpus was
                    therefore constructed using 77 randomly selected texts from the BNC and stripped
                    down versions of the Susanne corpus. We implemented a software tool that
                    facilitates SGML mark up of instances of "it" that appear in the corpus by a
                    human annotator. Non-Nominal uses of "it" are marked &lt;PLEO
                    ID="XX"&gt;it&lt;/PLEO&gt; whereas other instances are left unmarked by the
                    annotator. On completion, the corpus contained 368830 words, 3171 occurrences of
                    "it" and 1025 non-nominal uses. A DTD was defined for the annotated corpus and
                    the SGML aware LT-Chunker (Mikheev 1996) was used to tokenise the corpus while
                    preserving the prior mark up. The tokenised file was then processed by a Perl
                    program written to report the paragraph, sentence and word positions of the
                    non-nominal instances of "it". This information was written to a data file and
                    used to evaluate the methods implemented and described later.</p>
                <p>We implemented a program based on Paice &amp; Husk's (1987) method for
                    recognition of pleonastic "it". In the first step, a plain text version of the
                    corpus was tagged using Tapanainen &amp; Jarvinen's (1997) SGML-blind
                    FDG-Parser. The output from the tagger was converted to an SGML format by our
                    software and then processed by our program based on Paice &amp; Husk's pattern
                    recognition method. In this way a classification was assigned to each instance
                    of "it". Evaluation was performed by comparing the output of the program with
                    the contents of the data file produced earlier.</p>
                <p>A machine learning approach was also implemented. It exploits Daelemans' (1999)
                    TiMBL memory based learning method. TiMBL works by using a training file of
                    feature-value vectors that have been given a classification: non-nominal; or
                    not. The construction of the training file was made by processing a plain text
                    version of the annotated corpus with the FDG-Parser and the SGML conversion
                    program. The SGML file was input to a program that described each instance of
                    "it" as a vector of feature values. The features used in our approach were
                    designed to describe the position of non-nominal instances, the lemmas of
                    significant "following" words such as verbs and adjectives, as well as the
                    relation of "it" to other structures in the text, such as prepositions and noun
                    phrases. A thorough description appears in the full paper. The vectors
                    associated with the instances were classified by comparison with the data file
                    constructed earlier. The set of classified vectors made this way was then used
                    as the training file. TiMBL classifies query vectors according to their
                    similarity to the examples in the training file. The method of ten-fold
                    cross-validation was used to obtain an evaluation of the average accuracy of the
                    technique over our corpus.</p>
                <p>The results of our automatic evaluation showed no major differences in the level
                    of accuracy between the two methods. However, it was noted that the method based
                    on work by Paice &amp; Husk was slightly more accurate over this text (78.81%
                    vs. 78.68%) but had a stronger tendency to misclassify instances as non-nominal
                    (false positives: 265 vs. 243). If false positives are undesirable to the user,
                    then the machine learning approach is better.</p>
                <p>Further experiments in which the classification of instances in the training set
                    was extended using a 7-ary system, in accordance with the uses given in the
                    introduction, showed some improvement in making the binary distinction between
                    nominal and non-nominal uses. The classification accuracy rose to 78.74% and the
                    number of false positive classifications fell to 209. Predictably, the detection
                    rate for each of the different types of usage was low (50.35% on average).</p>
                <p>Given that TiMBL is reliant on a training file, it will also be beneficial to
                    extend our resource in terms of size as well as information content. The present
                    file, with 3171 instances, cannot be considered to be of sufficient size. The
                    availability of a suitable resource for evaluation is also important for the
                    application of optimisation techniques. Of course, non-nominal pronouns appear
                    in languages other than English, and it would be valuable to generate resources
                    in order to explore machine learning based methods to identify non-nominal
                    pronouns for them.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Burnard</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Users Reference Guide British National Corpus Version
                                1.0</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>Oxford University Computing Services, UK</publisher>
                                <date when="1995">1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Daelemans</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">TiMBL: Tilburg Memory Based Learner version 2 Reference
                                Guide,</title>
                            <title level="s">ILK Technical Report - ILK 99-01</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>The Netherlands</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Tilburg University</publisher>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Denber</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Automatic Resolution of Anaphora in English</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>Eastman Kodak Co., Imaging Science Division</publisher>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Lappin</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">H.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >J.</forename><surname>Leass</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">An Algorithm for Pronominal Anaphora Resolution</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Computational Linguistics</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">20</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">4</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp"/>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >J.</forename><surname>Litman</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Cue Phrase Classification Using Machine
                                Learning</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Journal of Artificial Intelligence Research</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">5</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">53-94</biblScope>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Mikheev</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">LT_CHUNK V 2.1</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>Language Technology Group, University of Edinburgh,
                                    UK</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >D.</forename><surname>Paice</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >D.</forename><surname>Husk</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Towards the Automatic Recognition of Anaphoric Features
                                in English Text: The Impersonal Pronoun 'It'</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Computer Speech and Language</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Academic Press</publisher>
                                <biblScope type="vol">2</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">109-32</biblScope>
                                <date when="1987">1987</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Sampson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">English for the Computer: The SUSANNE Corpus and
                                Analytic Scheme</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1995">1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Tapanainen</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <surname>Jarvinen</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">A Non-Projective Dependency Parser</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">The Proceedings of The 5th Conference of Applied
                                Natural Language Processing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>ACL</publisher>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">64-71</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
