<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Computing in the School of English and Scottish
                    Language And Literature (SESLL) at the University of Glasgow</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">G.</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Glasgow</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <p>The STELLA project (Software for Teaching English and Scottish Language and
                        Literature) has served the School of English and Scottish Language and
                        Literature at the University of Glasgow since 1987. We have produced
                        teaching packages and brought research databases into use in teaching. All
                        our programs have been thoroughly tested in the classroom, and have been
                        subjected to comment and detailed criticism by thousands of students, and
                        their teachers, since their first appearance.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Teaching Packages</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>English Grammar: an Introduction </head>
                        <p>This revised program takes the university student of English from
                            identifying parts of speech in context through the more complex
                            processes involved in parsing phrases and clauses. The central feature
                            of the teaching package is the exercise. There are five types, from
                            naming parts of speech in context through to parsing phrases and
                            clauses. The grammatical model is Hallidayan, but the primary reference
                            is to the online coursebook. (Professor CJ Kay &amp; Dr J.B.
                            Corbett) </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>The Basics of English Metre:</head>
                        <p>This package uses a traditional approach to introduce students to the
                            main conventional metres used in English verse, especially iambic
                            pentameter. It can be used both with students who require a
                            straightforward grounding in the subject and with those who study it in
                            greater depth. (Professor CJ Kay)</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>ARIES Assisted Revision in English Style:</head>
                        <p>ARIES is designed to help the user achieve competence in written style.
                            It consists of interactive exercises, each focusing on problem areas in
                            punctuation, grammar and spelling, with explanations and examples.
                            (Professor CJ Kay)</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>The Essentials of Old English:</head>
                        <p>These courses teach the rudiments of Old English from scratch. The
                            courses consist of graded sessions, each a combination of different
                            kinds of materials, including gap-filling, parsing, word lists and
                            comprehension exercises. There is substantial help and texts with
                            translations and notes. The current set of programs falls into two
                            parts: Basics - a single series of short exercises designed for
                            beginners in the subject; Plus - a suite of five distinct sets of
                            exercises, designed to support a structured learning-programme whereby
                            students of Old English develop a thorough grounding in the principles
                            of Old English grammar. (Dr JJ Smith)</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>A Guide to Scottish Literature:</head>
                        <p>Essays on Scottish Literature, covering the period from 1350 to 1920. The
                            essays are followed by notes, questions and topics for discussion, and
                            are suitable for use in courses from sixth-year studies upwards. The
                            material is divided into three sections: Medieval and Renaissance
                            Literature 1375-1700; Poetry and Fiction 1700-1900; Poetry, Fiction and
                            Drama Since 1920. (Professor DG Gifford)</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>A Guide to Older Scots:</head>
                        <p>This package consists of a reference book for students of the Older Scots
                            language. It contains an introduction, an historical outline, a summary
                            of the chronology, information on spelling, pronunciation, vocabulary,
                            grammar and style, and comprehensive reading lists. (Dr JJ Smith)</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>An Anthology of 16th and Early 17th Century Scots Poetry:</head>
                        <p>The anthology contains works of twenty of the major Scottish poets of the
                            period. It is linked to online teaching materials for a course in
                            medieval and renaissance Scottish Literature. (T. Van Heijnsbergen)</p>
                        <p>STELLA also maintains a web site for Scots texts: STARN the Scots
                            Teaching and Research Network &lt;<ptr
                                target="http://www2.arts.gla.ac.uk/COMET/level2.htm"/>&gt; and
                            email discussion lists for Scottish Literature and Language &lt;<ptr
                                target="http://www.mailbase.ac.uk/lists/scotlanglit-all/sub.html"
                            />&gt;. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>A Guide to Piers Plowman:</head>
                        <p>This is a full hypertext edition of the B- text, complete with notes and
                            supplementary materials. It is intended for a spectrum of undergraduate
                            users and provides assistance in areas such as glossing and explanatory
                            notes. (DM O.Brien)</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>The Historical Thesaurus of English:</head>
                        <p>This is a major research database project which is creating the first
                            historical thesaurus to be compiled for any of the world's languages,
                            and will include almost the entire recorded vocabulary of English from
                            Old English to the modern period. It will resemble works like Roget's
                            Thesaurus in that words will be arranged according to their meanings
                            rather than listed alphabetically. It will, however, differ from any
                            other thesaurus so far produced by listing obsolete words and obsolete
                            meanings of current words as well as treating contemporary English
                            comprehensively.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
