<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Digital Images for Online Distance Education in the
                    Humanities</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sue</forename>
                        <surname>Tickner</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Glasgow</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Richard</forename>
                        <surname>Hooker</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Glasgow</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Francis</forename>
                        <surname>Halsall</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Glasgow</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Digital Resources</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>This paper will describe the design and development of a web-based distance
                    education course in Art History at the University of Glasgow. In planning such
                    courses the interplay between new media, distance education and the existing
                    systems in a campus-based institution raises numerous issues which need to be
                    resolved before such a course is feasible. Not least of these are the obstacles
                    still inherent in accessing and delivering online images: in terms of locating
                    the desired resources, copyright and costing implications, institutional
                    agreements with other bodies such as the CLA and its digitising licence and
                    dual-mode delivery both on and off-campus. We suggest that, two years on from
                    Dan Greenstein's call for "new and creative ways to manage relations between
                    those who 'own' rights in image resources and those who have an interest in
                    acquiring access to them" <note>(1) Greenstein, Daniel (1997). <title level="a"
                            >Digital Images and Virtual Scholarly Collections</title>. Abstract,
                        Joint International Conference of the Association for Computers and the
                        Humanities and the Association for Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing,
                        Queen's University, Kingston, Ontario, CANADA, June 3 - 7, 1997 &lt;<ptr
                            target="http://www.qucis.queensu.ca/achallc97/papers/s008.html"
                        />&gt;</note> no simple methodology, clear guidelines for use or
                    satisfactory search interface yet exists.</p>
                <p>In common with other distance education developments in recent years, the work
                    has been carried out in close partnership between the academic department
                    concerned and GUIDE (Glasgow University Initiative in Distance Education).
                    Following successful small-scale, campus-based attempts to implement new
                    educational methods in teaching Art History, and in response to encouragement
                    within the department, the Level 2 class convenor approached GUIDE for advice on
                    potential distance options. Accordingly, in keeping with institutional policies
                    and national pressures to widen participation (in particular flexible, distance
                    and part-time provision), a 'flagship' course is to be offered at level 2 of a
                    undergraduate degree course from January 2001.</p>
                <p>The course will consist of two 30 credit modules (a total of 600 notional
                    learning hours). One module will be on Scottish Art and the other on Art,
                    Culture and the Avant-Garde. On the understanding that development work is never
                    right first time, the initial module will be run once, closely evaluated,
                    analysed and amended where appropriate. If this proves to meet our goals in the
                    second presentation it will serve as a template, or model, for the design of the
                    second module. A record of the history of the production of the course is being
                    kept, to show how and why decisions to use particular methods of delivery and/or
                    technology are made. It is intended that such a record will contribute to
                    decision-making in the design of similar online distance education courses.</p>
                <p>This development work constitutes a new departure, raising research issues in
                    several areas. One aspect of this is in the innovative nature of these plans,
                    and their place within the existing setting. For GUIDE, and indeed the
                    University as a whole, this will be one of the first ventures into part-time
                    distance provision at undergraduate level.</p>
                <p>If the course proves a success in pedagogical terms and there is sufficient
                    demand, we envisage the development of future courses, with the long-term aim of
                    offering a distance education route through access to postgraduate provision.
                    Achieving this aim requires a long-term commitment to developing other part-time
                    distance courses that articulate with these modules in a cross-disciplinary
                    degree structure within the Humanities. Ultimately, it requires the existence of
                    sufficient comparable courses to enable a broad range of studies on the basis of
                    part-time distance learning, in any subject, and at any level across the
                    institution. As a flagship undergraduate distance course, it must also meet
                    University requirements to an exemplary degree, and specifically those Quality
                    Assurance guidelines being developed by GUIDE for distance education. The
                    template we produce must therefore be of the highest possible quality, whilst
                    remaining reasonably adaptable to future requirements. The development
                    experience must inform and enable GUIDE to better assist future projects
                    employing digital resources.</p>
                <p>GUIDE has been working with a lecturer in the History of Art department to
                    develop the first module on which the template will be based. In the first year,
                    the module will run parallel to the face-to-face one, although it will cover
                    different themes and use very different methods. It is not simply a distance
                    version of the existing campus-based module. The process of designing a new
                    distance learning course is very different from that involved in attempts to
                    translate existing teaching materials into distance learning format. Existing
                    Level-2 provision is heavily reliant on lectures. It is partly in order to
                    investigate more exploratory, active learning approaches that this course has
                    been conceived. It will be largely, though not entirely, web-based, and make use
                    of group and peer-learning methods. We see the medium of online distance
                    learning as enabling the transformation of the relationship between student,
                    lecturer and the sources of learning materials - a transformation which,
                    according to constructivist advocates of networked learning, will be necessary
                    for the success of these methods.</p>
                <p>In the development of this course, therefore, we have sought to identify the main
                    features of this transformation with particular reference to art history. We
                    have designed the course with a view to minimising the negative effects of
                    losing face-to-face contact and maximising the benefits of technology-assisted
                    distance education. We do this with the understanding that this constitutes not
                    merely a compromise, but a fundamental change in what it means to teach, learn
                    and communicate.</p>
                <p>The fit with existing provision is only one of the issues raised. Another results
                    from these different aims for the distance modules. The teaching of the
                    discipline of art history and indeed the discipline itself - would have been
                    unthinkable without the photographic transparency. Although it is exponentially
                    more portable than a work of art, the transparency is also exponentially less
                    portable than its digital equivalent. The new methods and web-based delivery
                    will only be adding value to lecture-based provision if the technology is
                    harnessed to provide easy, 'on-demand' access to source materials, especially
                    digital resources. Ironically, the emergence of the technology for high quality
                    digitisation of images promises a utopia of accessibility whilst simultaneously
                    aggravating the problem of copyright. It has sometimes seemed as though the
                    complexity of copyright law has resulted in a situation where the ability to
                    access and use images is more restrictive now than before digitisation.</p>
                <p>Other complex issues in the course design include the need to retain and extend
                    successful features of the on-campus provision in Art History without competing
                    too heavily for recruitment from the full-time student population (especially in
                    the early stages when the options for continuation by these methods will be
                    severely limited), and generic issues in online teaching and learning,
                    especially those affecting developments in the Humanities. The effects of these
                    considerations will be demonstrated in the design and evaluation of the course
                    which will, by July 2000, be preparing for delivery.</p>
                <p>Some suggestions which might facilitate the use of visual resources in teaching,
                    drawn from our experience, will be offered to digital image service providers.
                    Specific complications we encountered will be explored and those solutions we
                    have found described. We hope these will help to ease the path for future users
                    of these exciting resources in Humanities teaching.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
