<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Hyperfiction Reading Research: An Experiment in
                    Method</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Colin</forename>
                        <surname>Gardner</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Sheffield</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>[1] Introduction</head>
                    <p>Hyperfiction reading experiments have been carried out as part of the
                        author's PhD research. The experiment complements and, in significant ways,
                        extends methods for critical metadiscursive commentary on non-linear
                        literary texts, and can be considered a preliminary and partial response to
                        a question posed in the title of an article by G. P. Landow: "What's a
                        Critic to Do" (Landow, 1994). Screen recording software has been used to log
                        readers' navigation of hyperfiction and to generate data amenable to
                        informal qualitative and quantitative analysis. Although this is an
                        exploratory study, it is expected that the data will provide a basis for
                        testing the hypothesis that analysis of navigational choices made within a
                        well-defined context can be used to suggest how a reader may have
                        interpreted the text. The data will be integrated within the various models
                        of reading hyperfiction and contribute to the growing methodological corpus
                        of research on this topic. Whilst the value of results deriving from this
                        meta-interpretational analysis may be questioned, it should nevertheless
                        provide a point of departure for a very urgent and timely debate into the
                        paths that technocriticism might take with regard to hypertext fictional
                        narrative.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <div>
                        <head>[2a] Analysis</head>
                        <p>Focusing on readings of a well-known hyperfiction, Michael Joyce's
                            'Afternoon: a Story', the experiment makes use of the fact that reading
                            online allows the movement of a reader through a text to be monitored
                            discretely, such as where the reader has visited and for how long.
                            Readers sometimes 'hover' around the screen using a mouse, and the
                            screen recording software captures this activity for use by the
                            analyst/critic. In Readingspace (the viewing application for Storyspace
                            texts) words selected by the reader are highlighted with a red outline.
                            This is important to the success of the meta-interpretation because the
                            words actually chosen by the reader, even where they do not activate a
                            specific link, are significant in themselves as indicators of an
                            intention on the reader's part. In this way, directions that readers
                            take in fictional narratives may act as a kind of interpretative index
                            for that reading. To this end, the experimental procedure requires
                            analysis of each space visited to assess the relation between its
                            semantic elements; this is referred to as "immediate context analysis".
                            Not relevant to meta-interpretation of the reader, but nevertheless
                            useful to the analyst/critic, is an analysis of the relation between
                            link elements and their destination spaces: this is the "narratological
                            context analysis". Finally, analysis of the connection of pathways along
                            which the reader can negotiate the structure reveals what may be
                            referred to as vortices, since recursal (returns to the same screen in
                            the same reading) is subject to probability factors set up by the
                            arrangement of links. This is referred to as "probability analysis" and
                            its corresponding factors are centrifugal/centripetal.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>[2b] Experimental factors</head>
                        <p>Two objections have to be contended with in this research: randomness and
                            conformity. Between the two extremes of random selection of links by a
                            reader, and a single predetermined reading sequence, this study aims to
                            use reading research to find out what relationship exists, if any,
                            between the content of the narrative and the choices made by the reader.
                            These factors might be deemed to involve an unacceptable indeterminacy
                            of variables, or to lack the rigour and exactitude of more "scientific"
                            analyses, much less to contribute positively to the problem of
                            hyperfiction criticism. Whilst it is acknowledged that no research can
                            give a reliable or purely objective indication of the state of a
                            reader's mind, the fact that engaged readers make conscious choices
                            suggests that their decisions are amenable to objective analysis.
                            Therefore, what this research cannot, and does not, aim to recreate is
                            what is in the reader's mind in the course of navigation; it attempts to
                            augment, using the data available, the range of critical tools necessary
                            for critique of the hyperfictional literary text. Since decisions made
                            by writers in their choice of words are open to stylistic analysis, it
                            would seem reasonable to suppose that the choices made by readers can be
                            considered in the same way. Some choices will be more considered than
                            others and, as a result, measures to guard against undue interpretations
                            are implemented. For example, the reader profile between some screens
                            might suggest a skimming mode. However, in others, the strategy may
                            change to one of close reading and more considered responses. Decisions
                            occurring within a skimming mode would lead to a lower level of
                            confidence in meta-interpretational analysis than in an intensive mode.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>[3] Theoretical Perspectives</head>
                    <p>Although a strong argument can be made against anachronistic theoretical
                        recontextualisations (Aarseth, 1997: 82ff) in a return to the parlance of
                        such theories in the notion, for example, of "form and content" (Ryan,
                        1997:690), the powerful resonance of these ideas with issues prevalent in
                        our own time often can be too irresistible. Such revisitations might also
                        suggest an almost inevitable reconsideration of the material conditions of
                        literature observed by Aarseth to be "invisible" to most literary theory
                        (1997: 164). In the analyses outlined above (2a), terminology and ideas from
                        existing models have been used. Complementing a standard grammatical
                        analysis of the spaces (for example, that found in the later chapters of
                        Greenbaum and Quirk, 1990: 394ff), and Gèrard Genette's 'Narrative
                        Discourse: An Essay in Method' (1980), is Aarseth's (1997) "textonomy" and
                        discussion of 'Afternoon', as well as J. Yellowlees Douglas' (1994) analysis
                        and interpretation of her own readings of the work. There are perhaps models
                        better suited to, or more concomitant with, the aspirations of the research
                        and it is anticipated that interested participants will be forthcoming with
                        suggestions.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>[4] Content of poster</head>
                    <p><list>
                            <item>1. Title and brief explanation of aims of experiment</item>
                            <item>2. Diagrams showing structure relevant to analysis</item>
                            <item>3. Charts plotting reading data</item>
                            <item>4. Separate key to diagrams and charts linked to
                                interpretations</item>
                            <item>5. Interpretations linked to diagrams (handout)</item>
                            <item>6. Analysis of the results in bullet point format</item>
                        </list></p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>[5] Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Espen</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Aarseth</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Cybertext: Perspectives on Ergodic Literature</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Johns Hopkins UP</publisher>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Perrti</forename>
                                    <surname>Alasuutari</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Researching Culture: Qualitative Method and Cultural
                                Studies</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Sage</publisher>
                                <date when="1995">1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">Yellowlees</forename>
                                    <surname>Douglas</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">'How do I stop this thing?': Closure and Indeterminacy
                                in Interactive Narratives</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">George</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Landow</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Hyper/Text/Theory</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Johns Hopkins UP</publisher>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">159-88</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Gèrard</forename>
                                    <surname>Genette</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Narrative Discourse: An Essay in Method</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>Trans.</resp>
                                <name><forename type="first">Jane</forename><forename type="middle"
                                        >E.</forename><surname>Lewin</surname></name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Ithaca</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Cornell University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1980">1980</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Sydney</forename>
                                    <surname>Greenbaum</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Randolph</forename>
                                    <surname>Quirk</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">A Student's Grammar of the English Language</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Harlow</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Longman</publisher>
                                <date when="1990">1990</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">George</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Landow</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Hyper/Text/Theory</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Johns Hopkins UP</publisher>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">George</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >P.</forename><surname>Landow</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">What's a Critic to Do? Critical Theory in the Age of
                                Hypertext</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">George</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Landow</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Hyper/Text/Theory</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Johns Hopkins UP</publisher>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">1-48</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Colin</forename>
                                    <surname>Robson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Real World Research: A Resource for Social Scientists
                                and Practitioner-Researchers</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Blackwell</publisher>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Marie-Laure</forename>
                                    <surname>Ryan</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Interactive Drama: Narrativity in a Highly Interactive
                                Environment</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Modern Fiction Studies</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">43</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">677-707</biblScope>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
