<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Textual Variation, Electronic Editions and
                    Hypertext</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Edward</forename>
                        <surname>Vanhoutte</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Office for Scholarly Editing and Document Studies
                                (BEB/OSEDS)</name>, Belgium <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Digital Resources</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The advent of the electronic paradigm to the field of scholarly editing and
                    textual criticism opens up new possibilities for both the production process and
                    the delivery of products which may herald a new era in scholarly editing. A new
                    practice including text encoding, automated tagging, automatic collation, the
                    use of scripting languages, etc. creates new kinds of editions in which the
                    record of textual variation becomes a central point of attention, both on the
                    markup- and on the delivery-side. In this paper I will address both sides
                    through a problematization of the apparatus criticus or variorum as an essential
                    part of an electronic edition.</p>
                <p>The new reality of scholarly editing in which for instance archives become
                    editions and editions include archives (McGann 1996 and Robinson 1996), and
                    hybrid editions come into being as a combination of critical, diplomatic,
                    facsimile and reading editions (De Smedt &amp; Vanhoutte 2000), calls for a new
                    theoretical framework and a thorough critique of the theory and practice of
                    paper-based critical philology. The existing rationales of textual criticism
                    cannot simply be transposed from the hard-copy to the electronic paradigm. This
                    would for instance mean a transposition of the unpracticality and illegibility
                    of the apparatus criticus or variorum to a medium which is essentially
                    structured differently. The editor of a paper-based edition tries to design the
                    apparatus as an economic and compact model in which to store textual variety,
                    often through a combination of variants. This more than once results in an
                    unsuperable density and thus a malfunctioning of a tool which should above all
                    be transparent and consultable. The apparatus criticus or apparatus variorum of
                    a printed critical edition fails, through its form and formality, in what it
                    intends to do, that is to provide a substitute and a documentation of each
                    complex source in such a physical form that it is usable for the interested
                    scholar (Vanhoutte 1998). The possibility to include digital facsimiles in an
                    electronic edition discharges the apparatus from the theoretical imperative of
                    being a substitute. The need for documentation of textual variety, however,
                    remains, but in electronic editions, compactness is being overruled by
                    explicitness. On the markup-side, this means the use of a system which can tag
                    every reading as well as genetic commentary, meta-data variation and variation
                    over structural boundaries (Smith 1999). On the delivery-side, this means the
                    use of a system which can supply the user with the possibility to consult every
                    witness on its own and - facultatively - in combination with a suggested
                    orientation text to an acceptable level of granularity.</p>
                <p>Over the past couple of years, several gentle solutions have been put into
                    practice, which either function on the markup- or on the delivery-side
                    (corresponding roughly with what Vanhoutte 1999 respectively calls the Archive-
                    and Museum-function), but none of which provides a full answer to this
                    documentation-maxim. Taking the three fundamental requirements of electronic
                    scholarly editions - accessibility, longevity and intellectual integrity
                    (Sperberg-McQueen 1994) - as parameters for an evaluation of possible designs of
                    electronic editions, I will argue that there are at least three sorts of
                    editions in the electronic paradigm: electronic editions, electronic editions
                    with hypertext functionality and hypertext editions which do not meet the
                    requirements of electronic editions. Further, this paper will (re)formulate
                    additions to these requirements, focussing on modern literature.</p>
                <p>Because hypertext is the visualization of linking which DeRose &amp; Van Dam
                    (1999) define as "the ability to express relationships between places in a
                    universe of information" and which are explicitly marked or can be generated
                    automatically by making use of some sort of markup, the syntax of this markup
                    and the markup-language become essential in designing a hypertext and/or an
                    electronic edition.</p>
                <p>On the basis of the three fundamental requirements for electronic editions, the
                    syntax of the markup (language) and the orientation towards a markup- or a
                    delivery-side, I distinguish three sorts of editions in the electronic paradigm:<list>
                        <item>
                            <emph rend="bold">A. hypertext editions:</emph>
                            <list type="bulleted">
                                <item>Are only concerned with accessibility: they explicitly link
                                    apparatus to base text, digital facsimile to base text, several
                                    versions to orientation text.</item>
                                <item>Make use of (a combination of) HTML, JavaScript (for pop-up
                                    boxes), frames.</item>
                                <item>Are being designed from a display point of view and are useful
                                    for didactic purposes and on-sight consulting. Hypertext
                                    editions of this sort are acceptable as a formatted output with
                                    a specific purpose for a specific audience, but are for visual
                                    purposes only.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <emph rend="bold">B. electronic editions:</emph>
                            <list type="bulleted">
                                <item>Are concerned with accessibility, longevity and intellectual
                                    integrity by making use of generic markup schemes in their
                                    design, such as those provided by the TEI (cf. chapter 19 of the
                                    P3 Guidelines), the MASTER scheme (Robinson, Burnard, Proffitt
                                    &amp; Driscoll 1999), or a project specific SGML DTD.</item>
                                <item>Can be concerned with linking external or internal apparatus
                                    to a base or an orientation text.</item>
                                <item>Can be concerned with providing alternative views of the same
                                    document.</item>
                                <item>Are being designed from a markup point of view and are useful
                                    to the scholarly community.</item>
                                <item>Can be used to generate several spin-off products (including
                                    editions of category A).</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <emph rend="bold">C. electronic editions with hypertext
                                functionality:</emph>
                            <list type="bulleted">
                                <item>Same as B, but make extensive use of Pointer and Reference
                                    syntax to explicitly express relationships which can also be
                                    viewed in a browser, or make use of the present markup to
                                    programmatically generate linking.</item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>From B and C it follows that the explicit documentation of textual variation in
                    an apparatus criticus or variorum linked to a base text is no prerequisite
                    anymore for an electronic edition. Textual variation can be documented
                    implicitly by the textual description of each witness or document source. The
                    extraction of alternative views of the witnesses, facultatively projected
                    together with one version which functions as an orientation text, can be a
                    possible solution to the problems concerning the instability of a (base) text.
                    This paper will conclude with some notes on the use of XML and XSL in a
                    construct which both caters for the markup- and the display-side.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Steven</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >J.</forename><surname>DeRose</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">A.</forename><surname>Van
                                        Dam</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Document Structure and markup in the FRESS hypertext
                                system</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Markup Languages: Theory &amp; Practice</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">7-23</biblScope>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor><name><forename type="first">Marcel</forename><surname>De
                                        Smedt</surname></name></editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Vanhoutte</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Stijn Streuvels. De teleurgang van den Waterhoek.
                                Elektronisch-kritische editie</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Gent/Amsterdam</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>KANTL/Amsterdam University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                        >M.</forename><surname>Sperberg-McQueen</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Textual Criticism and the Text Encoding
                                Initiative</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">Paper presented at MLA '94, San Diego, 1994</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.uic.edu:80/orgs/tei/talks/mla94.htm"
                            />&gt;.</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Sperberg-McQueen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Burnard</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                                Interchange. (P3)</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Chicago and Oxford</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Text Encoding Initiative</publisher>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Jerome</forename>
                                    <surname>McGann</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">The Rationale of HyperText</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">TEXT</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">9</biblScope>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">11-32</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Robinson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Geoffrey Chaucer. The Wife of Bath's Prologue.</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Robinson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Burnard</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Proffitt</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Driscoll</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Initiatives Towards a Standard Encoding for Manuscript
                                Descriptions</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>

                            <title level="u">Session at DRH99, London, 1999</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <surname>Smith</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Textual Variation and Version Control in the
                                TEI</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">33</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">1-2</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">103-112</biblScope>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>

                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Vanhoutte</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Where is the editor? Resistance in the creation of an
                                electronic critical edition</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">Paper presented at DRH98, Glasgow, 1998</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
