<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">A Pilot Study in the Use of E-Books for
                    Learning</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Norshuhada</forename>
                        <surname>Shiratuddin</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Universiti Utara Malaysia</name>, Malaysia <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Monica</forename>
                        <surname>Landoni</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Strathclyde</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <p>There are quite a number of educational electronic learning devices for
                        children aged between 3 to 12 years old. These portable laptop look-alike
                        devices are designed to make drill and practice exercises painless and more
                        fun with elements of text, audio and animation. This paper describes a study
                        on how children use and feel about learning with such a device. Preliminary
                        findings suggest that the readability of the machine is poor and kids prefer
                        a richer display of information, and for this reason producers of learning
                        devices should look very carefully at representation issues.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>1. Introduction</head>
                    <p>Paper books have been used as extremely useful aids for the support of many
                        activities including teaching and learning for many years. However, another
                        type of book, known as the electronic book, has emerged, with many companies
                        engaging in manufacturing electronic reading devices used for displaying,
                        reading and storing electronic information. Nuvomedia Inc.[14], SoftBook
                        Press Inc. [16] and EveryBook Inc. [12] are examples of manufacturers of
                        hand-held reading devices who are currently targeting only professionals
                        that require access to lots of reference materials [6]. In contrast, Oregon
                        Scientific [15], VTECH [17],and IQ Builders [13], are producing fun,
                        friendly computer-based learning machines for children aged between 3 to 12
                        years old.</p>
                    <p>Paper books have been used as extremely useful aids for the support of many
                        activities including teaching and learning for many years. However, another
                        type of book, known as the electronic book, has emerged, with many companies
                        engaging in manufacturing electronic reading devices used for displaying,
                        reading and storing electronic information. Nuvomedia Inc.[14], SoftBook
                        Press Inc. [16] and EveryBook Inc. [12] are examples of manufacturers of
                        hand-held reading devices who are currently targeting only professionals
                        that require access to lots of reference materials [6]. In contrast, Oregon
                        Scientific [15], VTECH [17],and IQ Builders [13], are producing fun,
                        friendly computer-based learning machines for children aged between 3 to 12
                        years old.</p>
                    <div>
                        <head>1.1 Definition of an electronic book</head>
                        <p>An electronic book (e-book) is essentially a computer-based information
                            storage/dissemination artefact that embeds a book metaphor [4]. More
                            precisely, an electronic book is usually considered to be composed of a
                            collection of reactive (screen based) pages of electronic information
                            that are (usually) organised in a thematic way and that exhibit many of
                            the characteristic features and properties of a conventional book [3]. </p>
                        <p>There have been various attempts to categorise e-books according to their
                            main features [2,3,7]. We thought that there was a need for a more
                            flexible philosophy in order to accommodate the wide range of new
                            objects produced nowadays, as they are all labelled e-books. We propose
                            that e-books be classified according to what aspect of the book they
                            emphasise (purpose, content, functionalities, appearance) and by taking
                            into account the kind of audience they target. According to this
                            bi-dimensional categorisation the pilot study described in this paper
                            considers e-books whose purpose is mainly educational and whose audience
                            is made up of children in primary school.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2. The Learning Machine</head>
                    <p>The machine considered in this pilot study is called 'Zip, the Robot Learning
                        PC'. It is designed for 4-7 year olds and has 50 activities covering
                        vocabulary, spelling, grammar, maths, music and games. It can be expanded
                        with add-in smart cards. Like a real laptop, it has a QWERTY keyboard and a
                        mouse to also introduce essential computer user skills. The machine is
                        powered either by 4AA size batteries or a 9V AC adapter. </p>
                    <p>Game activities and questions come in groups of 10. Users are given 3
                        attempts to answer each question. Points are awarded according to the number
                        of attempts taken to answer each question correctly. Each attempt to answer
                        a question is timed 1 minute for levels 1-5 and 30 seconds for level 6. If
                        users are unable to answer in time, it is counted as an incorrect attempt.
                        The user is praised for each correct answer and prompted for action if the
                        given time is exceeded.</p>
                    <p>The score is displayed at the end of each activity and users scoring 85
                        points or higher after a group of 10 questions can proceed to the next
                        higher level of difficulty. Scores of 60 points or below go to the next
                        lower level.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3. Observed qualitative study</head>
                    <p>Six 5-8 year old children were given the opportunity to play with the
                        learning machine. All participants are considered as "moderate technology
                        users" for their age as all have had many experiences playing with CD
                        titles, video games and personal computers. Moderate technology experience
                        is essential as this study assumed the children are used to computer
                        interface metaphor and handling of input devices.</p>
                    <p>While using the machine, the kids were observed for reactions and at the end
                        of the playing time, each kid was asked to answer some questions regarding
                        selected parameters.</p>
                    <p>This initial study attempts to observe the children's preferences toward the
                        learning device, thus, a study of display preferences by Wearden [11] is
                        partially adopted. Navigability, physical format and overall preference were
                        selected and used as observation parameters. However, instead of observing
                        wait time, we measured the overall time each child takes to play with the
                        machine. A major challenge for flat panel display technology is to reproduce
                        the viewability or readability of ink on paper [5]. Realising the importance
                        of the readability concept, this parameter is also observed in this study. </p>
                    <p>The observed parameters were further broken down into the following
                            questions:<list type="bulleted">
                            <item><emph rend="bold">Navigability:</emph> (1) How easy is it to make
                                game choices? (2) Are the input devices easy to use and
                                handle?</item>
                            <item><emph rend="bold">Physical format:</emph> (1) How heavy is the
                                machine? (2) Do you like the design of the casing, screen and
                                keyboard?</item>
                            <item><emph rend="bold">Readability:</emph> (1) Are the texts clearly
                                displayed? (2) Are the texts and graphics smoothly outlined or are
                                they too jagged? (3) Do you like the black and grey display? (3) Is
                                the audio clearly understandable?</item>
                            <item><emph rend="bold">Overall preference:</emph> (1) Do you prefer
                                learning with CD-ROM, paper or the electronic learning
                                machine?</item>
                        </list></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>4. Results and Conclusions</head>
                    <p>Although this study was done on a small controlled scale, the opinions of
                        these young children should not entirely be ignored and there are still a
                        few points to be taken into account when designing future products.</p>
                    <p>Some of this study's observed results are in agreement with other studies'
                        findings. Take for example: <list>
                            <item>1. Doane stated that an important parameter of the e-book is its
                                necessary weight limitation. It cannot be heavier than we normally
                                expect a book to be [5]. When asked about the weight, the children
                                agreed that the machine weight is ideal and they prefer collections
                                of books in electronic form compared to paper books.</item>
                            <item>2. Jaggies' in LCD are found to be liked least [1] in a study by
                                Gujar et al. The six kids in this observation study also complained
                                about the too-jagged texts and graphics.</item>
                            <item>3. The readability of this machine is observed to be low in the
                                eyes of the kids. Reasons are low resolution black and grey displays
                                (Nielsen design guidelines state that low resolution monitors have
                                poor readability [9] ), small display screens, dull grey display
                                panels, and too many jagged texts and graphics.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>These children prefer richer <emph rend="bold">colourful</emph> multimedia
                        displays, as opposed to the findings by Wearden who did a survey of 276
                        university students and found that the least important potential features of
                        an e-book are animated graphics, audio and video [10]. It is possible to
                        conclude that the age factor has some effects on this parameter, but further
                        studies have to be performed to validate it.</p>
                    <p>One other issue that needs to be discussed is the average time each of the
                        children took to play with the machine. Liu's study showed that multimedia
                        technology with its use of video, audio and graphics could engage children
                        for a longer period of time [8]. However, this is not the case in this case
                        study. All of the six children seemed to manage to get excited and
                        interested for not more than 20 minutes only - as opposed to an average time
                        of about 50 minutes they spent on educational games or CD titles. This
                        detected time suggests that there is not enough fun for the kids in the
                        contents, displays and activities. Thus more attention has to be paid by the
                        producers of such devices to the way they present information in order to
                        make their overall appearance more appealing to the right audience.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct n="1.">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Gujar</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">B.</forename>
                                    <surname>Harrison</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >A.</forename><surname>Fishkin</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">comparative evaluation of display technologies for
                                reading</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Proceedings of HFES' 1998</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">527-531</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="2.">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >G.</forename><surname>Barker</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">An Object Oriented Approach to Hypermedia
                                Authoring</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Interactive Multimedia Learning Environments: Human
                                Factors and Technical Considerations on Design Issues</title>
                            <title level="s">NATO ASI Series</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">132-152</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="3">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >G.</forename><surname>Barker</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Electronic Libraries of the Future</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Encyclopedia of Microcomputers</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">Volume 23, Supplement 2</biblScope>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>Marcel Dekker, Inc.</publisher>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">121-152</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="4.">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >G.</forename><surname>Barker</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">The role of digital libraries in future educational
                                systems</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Online Information 98 Proceedings</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">301-310</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="5.">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >W.</forename><surname>Doane</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">A comparison of display technologies suitable for
                                e-book</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m"/>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr
                                target="http://www.jmc.kent.edu/futureprint/1998fall/christie.htm"
                            />&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="6.">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >C.</forename><surname>Judge</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">E-books : A library on your lap</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">BusinessWeek</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol"/>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp"/>
                                <date when="1998">Nov 5, 1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.businessweek.com/1998/46/b3604010.html"
                            />&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="7.">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first"
                                        >M.</forename><surname>Landoni</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">The Visual Book System: A Study of the Use of Visual
                                Rhetoric in the Design of Electronic Books</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <edition>PhD Thesis</edition>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Department of Information Science of the University of
                                    Strathclyde, Glasgow</publisher>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="8.">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Min</forename>
                                    <surname>Liu</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">An Exploratory Study of How Pre-Kindergarten Children
                                Use the Interactive Multimedia Technology: Applications for
                                Multimedia Software Design</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Journal of Computing in Childhood Education</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">7</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">1/2</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp"/>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="9.">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Nielsen</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Electronic books - A bad idea</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m"/>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">July 26, 1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.useit.com/papers/webwriting"/>&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="10.">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Wearden</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Electronic Books : A Study of Potential Features and
                                Their Perceived Value</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m"/>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr
                                target="http://www.jmc.kent.edu/futureprint/1998fall/Weadren.htm"
                            />&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="11.">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Wearden</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Lanscape vs. Portrait Formats : Assessing Consumer
                                Preferences</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m"/>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr
                                target="http://www.jmc.kent.edu/futureprint/1998summer/Wearden.htm"
                            />&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="12.">
                        <monogr>
                            <author/>
                            <title level="m"/>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.iqbuilders.co.uk/"/>&gt; (Nov.
                            1999).</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="13.">
                        <monogr>
                            <author/>
                            <title level="m"/>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.everybook.net"/>&gt; (Oct, 1999).</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="14.">
                        <monogr>
                            <author/>
                            <title level="m"/>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.nuvomedia.com"/>&gt; (Oct, 1999).</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="15.">
                        <monogr>
                            <author/>
                            <title level="m"/>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.oregonscientific.co.uk"/>&gt; (Oct,
                            1999).</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="16.">
                        <monogr>
                            <author/>
                            <title level="m"/>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.softbook.com"/>&gt; (Oct, 1999). </note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="17.">
                        <monogr>
                            <author/>
                            <title level="m"/>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.vtech.com/"/>&gt; (Nov, 1999). </note>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
