<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-185">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Violence and the Digital Humanities Text as Pharmakon</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Bradley, Adam James</name>
                    <affiliation>The University of Waterloo, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>adam.bradley@uwaterloo.ca</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
            <p>There has long been a tendency of
                    tools in the digital humanities to be objects through which literary scholars
                    are intended to perform meta-analyses of texts. One of the inconsistencies with
                    this act is that in the process of displaying a data visualization we destroy
                    the actual text that is being studied. This act is a type of pharmakon, creative
                    because it shifts the aesthetic of the text for re-interpretation and
                    destructive because the original artifact is lost in this process of creation.
                    By appropriating Rene Girard’s definition of violence – namely that the attempt
                    to represent texts visually and digitally is a form of mimetic rivalry that
                    leads to violence in terms of the text itself, and using Denis Diderot’s three
                    fold vision of creation (‘enthousiasme’), I will show that the mimetic nature of
                    digital humanities tools creates an allowing condition for a type of violence
                    that is both destructive (Girard’s ‘violence’) and creative (Diderot’s
                    ‘enthousiasme’). By juxtaposing the work of Girard and Diderot in this way it
                    becomes possible to see digital humanities projects (specifically data
                    visualization projects) as acts of violence. It was this line of reasoning that
                    brought me to my primary research question: Is it possible to develop a
                    visualization technique that does not destroy the original text in the process,
                    one in which the digital humanist can be a creator in terms of Diderot’s
                    enthusiasme?</p>
            <p>My paper will suggest a new method for
                    visualizing texts that specifically addresses this question. The proposed method
                    uses rigorous mathematics – developed with the aid of an interdisciplinary team
                    of mathematicians and computer scientists at the University of Waterloo – that
                    addresses this problem of violence and suggests that through interdisciplinary
                    study and mathematical precision we can produce digital humanities tools that
                    encode the original texts in their entirety without any violence towards the
                    text. This project is an attempt to ‘form a new kind of literary study
                    absolutely comfortable with scientific methods yet completely suffused with the
                    values of the humanities’ as suggested by R. G. Potter in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Literary Computing and Literary Criticism: Theoretical and Practical Essays
                        on Theme and Rhetoric.</hi></p>
            
                <p>Using the resources of the University of Waterloo’s Digital Media
                    Lab, I created a data visualization technique that was originally intended to
                    study form in poetry but has proven to have wide reaching applications. What
                    differentiates this project from other similar work, such as the TextArc
                    project, is that the algorithm created to model the visualization creates a
                    one-to-one relationship between the visualization and the original text. What
                    this means specifically is that unlike a meta-analysis tool, this project
                    encodes the original layout and punctuation of a text within the algorithm that
                    produces the visualization making it both a tool for meta-analysis and a keeper
                    of the original text. This removes the need for an analyst that intimately
                    understands the visualization and allows for a transition between the two states
                    (aesthetic visualization and original text) without any hindrances. This
                    effectively solves the problem of losing the text in the analysis, or more
                    specifically, of traditional literary scholars complaints that they do not know
                    how to interpret the visualization created by the digital humanities model. By
                    including a one-to-one correspondence between the text and the visualization,
                    the intuition that is being engaged in the criticism spawned by the
                    visualization can take on a second dimension between the original text and the
                    literary critic. </p>
            <p>The actual program was written in python
                    and uses an aesthetic inspired by avant-garde art, namely the shifting of
                    perspectives to try to gain insight into the original text. This is accomplished
                    by creating 3D graphs in an infinitely countable box that represents all of the
                    possible words from a null string to an infinitely long word using the alphabet.
                    Each word of the original text is then encoded with an algorithm that uses a
                    combination of mathematics, developed by Georg Cantor, and a method of my own
                    devising to create a unique set of co-ordinates for each word in the English
                    language and graph them in 3d space. This creates a unique 3d object for every
                    poem and engages a shifted aesthetic to try to find new insights into the
                    arrangement of the original words. In terms of the actual aesthetics of the
                    visualization the program claims nothing new, but the focus of this study was to
                    try to devise a method for maintaining the text within the mathematics of data
                    visualization and that is what I have done.  I envision this project as
                    axiomatic in nature and call in my paper for all data visualizations to live up
                    to the standard of non-violence towards texts. I believe this exercise in
                    mathematical rigor will inspire the digital humanist to consider the use of data
                    visualization in a new way that will ultimately lead to better and more
                    thoughtful tools for use in literary study.</p>
            </div>
                
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>