<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-168">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Investigating the genealogical relatedness of the endagered Dagon languages</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Moran, Steven</name>
                    <affiliation>Research Unit: Quantitative Language Comparison, LMU, Munich, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>steve.moran@lmu.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Prokic, Jelena</name>
                    <affiliation>Research Unit: Quantitative Language Comparison, LMU, Munich, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>j.prokic@lmu.de</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>Dogon languages are spoken predominately in eastern Mali in West Africa. The
                Dogon were made famous by Marcel Griaule, a French anthropologist who pioneered
                Ethnography in France, and worked with the Dogon between 1931-1956. He reported that
                the Dogon had advanced astronomical knowledge of the Sirius binary star system,
                knowledge that is not possible without telescope. Since then, the Dogon have been
                shrouded in controversy and mystery.</p>
            <p>As late as 1989, Dogon appeared in
                reference books as if it were a single language, e.g. Bendor-Samuel 1989 (as found
                in Blench 2005). The standard encyclopedic reference on the world’s languages, the
                Ethnologue,<note><ref target="http://www.ethnologue.com/" type="external">http://www.ethnologue.com/</ref></note> now lists 14 Dogon languages (Lewis 2009),
                but this figure is too low. In 2004, an extensive sociolinguistic survey by
                Hochstetler et al. (2004) estimated no less than 17 distinct languages and described
                the language family as highly internally divided. Since 2004, much initial survey
                work on Dogon has been undertaken by Roger Blench, Denis Douyon and Jeffrey Heath’s
                Dogon languages project,<note><ref target="http://dogonlanguages.org/" type="external">http://dogonlanguages.org/</ref></note> which has lead to the ‘discovery’
                of a web of divergent dialects, some of which have been raised to the status of
                distinct languages based on standard linguistic criteria. Thus, the current Dogon
                linguistic situation is not at all transparent. Dogon languages are very
                under-described, many are highly endangered, and all are genealogically not well
                established (Blench 2005; Heath 2008).</p>
            <p>The Dogon languages project provides
                a tentative detailed inventory of known Dogon languages. There are currently 20
                distinct languages grouped (crudely) into eight geographical regions, with no
                implications for genealogical subgrouping. The internal structure of the Dogon
                language family is unknown, as is the number of mutually unintelligible languages it
                contains. In fact, the Ethnologue gives a flat genealogical tree. The position of
                the Dogon languages relative to other African language families is also unclear
                because of Dogon’s unique typological characteristics. Its lineage has long been
                disputed, as summarized in Table 1.<note>See Hochstetler et al. (2004) and Hantgan’s Dogon bibliography for references at: <ref target="http://dogonlanguages.org/bibliography.cfm" type="external">http://dogonlanguages.org/bibliography.cfm</ref>.</note></p>
            
            <table>
                <head>Table 1: Historical classification of Dogon</head>
                <row>
                    <cell><hi rend="bold">Year</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="bold">Classification (language family)</hi></cell>
                    <cell><hi rend="bold">Author</hi></cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1924</cell>
                    <cell>Nigéro-Sénégalais</cell>
                    <cell>Delafosse</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1941</cell>
                    <cell>Voltaic (Eng. Gur)</cell>
                    <cell>Homburger</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1948</cell>
                    <cell>Voltaic; Gurunsi</cell>
                    <cell>Baumann &amp; Westermann</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1951</cell>
                    <cell>Mandé</cell>
                    <cell>Holas</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1952</cell>
                    <cell>Mandé</cell>
                    <cell>Delafosse</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1952</cell>
                    <cell>Gur (Fr. Voltaic)</cell>
                    <cell>Westermann &amp; Bryan</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1953</cell>
                    <cell>Voltaic</cell>
                    <cell>Bertho</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1953</cell>
                    <cell>Non-classified</cell>
                    <cell>de Tressan</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1950/60</cell>
                    <cell>Gur</cell>
                    <cell>Calame-Griaule</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1963</cell>
                    <cell>Gur</cell>
                    <cell>Greenberg</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1971</cell>
                    <cell>Gur</cell>
                    <cell>Bender-Samuel</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> 1981</cell>
                    <cell>Voltaic</cell>
                    <cell>Manessy</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1981</cell>
                    <cell>Volta-Congo</cell>
                    <cell>Bendor-Samuel</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1993</cell>
                    <cell>Unresolved; non-classified</cell>
                    <cell>Galtier</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>1994</cell>
                    <cell>Unresolved; non-classified</cell>
                    <cell>Plungian and Tembiné</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>2000</cell>
                    <cell>Ijo-Congo</cell>
                    <cell>Williamson and Blench</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>2009</cell>
                    <cell>Volta-Congo</cell>
                    <cell>Lewis</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            
            <p>In this paper, we use a marriage of digital methods
                successfully applied in bioinformatics to decode DNA and determine the genetic
                relatedness of humans, and we apply these methods to language data in an attempt to
                shed light on the prehistory of the Dogon languages and determine their genealogical
                subgroupings. The comparative method employed in historical and comparative
                linguistics (the study of language change to reconstruct the genealogical
                relatedness of languages) is a very laborious and time-consuming task that involves
                identifying cognates (words that share a common etymological origin) through their
                shared meanings and common sound change correspondences (e.g. English ‘is’, German
                ‘ist’, Latin ‘est’, Indo-European ‘esti’).</p>
            <p>We show how recent advances in
                the use of quantitative methods in the study of language comparison can be applied
                to digital data of (endangered) languages to automate the discovery of regular sound
                correspondences and cognate forms. Next, powerful statistical techniques allow for
                new insights into the origin and evolution of human languages. We use distance-based
                methods like Levenshtein (Levenshtein 1965) and character-based methods like
                Bayesian Markov Chain Monte Carlo methods (Page &amp; Holmes 2006) to induce
                language family trees from lexical data. We present the first subgrouping hypothesis
                for the Dogon language family and we will discuss the limits of current quantitative
                approaches, where the state-of-the-art in computational historical linguistics is
                heading, and what we can hope to glean from their application to linguistic
                diversity.</p>
        
        </body>
        <back>
            <div><head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Bendor-Samuel, J., E. J. Olsen, and A. R. White</hi> (1989). <hi
                        rend="italic">The Niger-congo languages – a classification and description
                        of Africa’s largest language family</hi>, chapter Dogon. Langham: UP of
                    America, pp. 169-177.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Blench, R.</hi> (2005). A survey
                    of Dogon languages in Mali: overview. <hi rend="italic">Ogmios</hi> 26:
                    14-15.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Heath, J.</hi> (2008). <hi rend="italic">A
                        grammar of Jamsay</hi>. Berlin: Mouton de Gruyter.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Hochstetler, J. L., J. Durieux, and E. Durieux-Boon</hi> (2004).
                        <hi rend="italic">Sociolinguistic survey of the Dogon language area</hi>.
                    SIL International.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Levenshtein, V.</hi> (1965). Binary codes capable of correcting
                    deletions, insertions and reversals. <hi rend="italic">Doklady Akademii Nauk
                        SSSR</hi> 163: 845-848.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Lewis, M. P.</hi> (2009). <hi rend="italic">Ethnologue: languages
                        of the world</hi>, Sixteenth edition. SIL International.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Page, R. D. M., and E. C. Holmes</hi> (2006). <hi rend="italic"
                        >Molecular evolution: a phylogenetic approach</hi>. Malden: Blackwell.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>