<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-176">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Geo-Temporal Interpretation of Archival Collections Using Neatline</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Nowviskie, Bethany</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Virginia, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>bethany@virginia.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Graham, Wayne</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Virginia, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>waynegraham@virginia.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>McClure, David</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Virginia, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>dm4fn@virginia.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Boggs, Jeremy</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Virginia, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>jkb2b@virginia.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Rochester, Eric</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Virginia, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>err8n@virginia.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>In late 2009, with funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities, the
                Scholars’ Lab at the University of Virginia Library began development of Neatline, a
                tool with which students, scholars, and archivists can express the geo-temporal
                dimensions of literary or historical collections: <ref target="http://neatline.org/" type="external">http://neatline.org/</ref>.  These
                expressions take the form of customizable, highly interpretive, interlinked, and
                interactive web-based timelines and maps. They are built using open-source software
                and standards-based approaches to geospatial data, and they permit scholars to draw
                heavily on digitized archival content and standardized metadata created by cultural
                heritage institutions. That said, each use of Neatline is imagined as a
                carefully-designed narrative or exhibit – a subjective story told in time and space
                through small-scale interpretive decision-making, rather than (as is more commonly
                pursued in our era of ‘big data’) an algorithmically-derived or data-driven
                geotemporal information visualization. In the broadest terms, Neatline is conceived
                as a contribution – in the visual vernacular – to multidisciplinary, place-based
                scholarship using primary sources. </p>
            <p>This paper describes: 1) the theoretical goals of Neatline, including a role for
                iterative sketching (or graphesis) and hand-craftedness in digital interpretive
                toolbuilding; 2) the decision-making process which led us to architect Neatline not
                as a stand-alone tool, but as a set of mix-and-match plugins for Omeka, an
                open-source platform for online collections and exhibits; and 3) preliminary
                assessment of ongoing work on the project, undertaken since 2010 as a partnership
                between the Scholars’ Lab at UVa Library and the Roy Rosenzweig Center for History
                and New Media at George Mason University.  </p>
            <p>As an NEH-funded prototyping project, Neatline made three claims to innovation or to
                a shifting of the landscape of geo-temporal visualization in the humanities.  First,
                by building on primary resources expressed in EAD (Encoded Archival Description)
                metadata – among other standards, such as VRA Core – Neatline creates a pragmatic
                path for collaboration among metadata providers and scholars. Although EAD has long
                been employed by academics working in concert with archivists, as in the Walt
                Whitman Archive, its use has typically been straightforwardly bibliographical, as a
                finding aid or for the production of catalogs of manuscripts and letters. EAD has
                rarely been used as a stepping-stone to rich, interpretive or theory-based
                expression (much less visualization) of the <hi rend="italic">content</hi> of those
                primary resources. The Neatline project aims to demonstrate the value of archival
                metadata to interpretive scholarship, and thereby strengthen connections among
                scholars and collections stewards.</p>
            <p>Next, Neatline aims for ease of use by scholars new to the digital humanities. This
                was a major argument in our bid for NEH funding, and our rationale for shifting from
                development of a stand-alone, downloadable tool (installable as a single,
                server-side application), to a functionally atomized array of interchangeable
                plugins for Omeka (<ref target="http://omeka.org" type="external">http://omeka.org</ref>) is arguably the most important contribution of
                the project to the current scene of humanities computing software development.
                Neatline was imagined as a self-contained, self-service, single-function tool that
                nonetheless allowed expert users easy access ‘under the hood’ to customize and
                contribute to its open source code. For a stand-alone tool, this would have been the
                right approach; but we quickly realized that we had the opportunity to model a more
                productive and collaborative set of open source software practices. The Scholars’
                Lab has now shared source code for 9 completed or in-progress Neatline-related
                plugins with the Omeka developers’ community, and Omeka forms the backbone for basic
                content management functionality in our project. We feel strongly that our shift to
                Omeka plugin production retains or enhances all of the desired qualities of our
                originally-proposed system, while adding two great benefits. First, Neatline has
                become mix-and match. In other words, no longer must users assent to the entire,
                ideal Neatline workflow in order to make use of our work – and in fact we are seeing
                great interest in and use of individual plugins in Omeka user communities and
                scholarly and archival contexts far removed from those interested in geo-temporal
                interpretation. Secondly, our close collaboration with the Omeka team and open
                source developers’ community is leading to advancements in the core code of Omeka
                itself, again benefiting a far wider audience than we anticipated. Not only were we
                able to leverage Omeka as a technical and social framework for Neatline, but our
                work has made the system a more attractive option for research and special
                collections libraries – even those with sophisticated technical and repository
                infrastructure of their own.</p>
            <p>Finally, Neatline makes a theoretical contribution to the digital humanities by
                emphasizing hand-crafted visualization as a mode of praxis and scholarly inquiry.
                (This is a practice we have, after the experimentation of the UVa’s former ‘SpecLab’
                thinktank and the scholarship of Johanna Drucker, called <hi rend="italic"
                    >graphesis</hi>.) Low-tech sketching and storyboarding is regularly taught as
                part of the earliest design processes for digital projects in the Scholars’ Lab. A
                side effect of our work is to demonstrate the value of iterative interpretation and
                knowledge-production manifested in visual form – particularly within fields like
                history and literary studies, in which interpretation of visual artifacts is rarely
                taught and drawing is infrequently modeled as (in William J. Turkel’s formulation)
                ‘a way of knowing.’ We have emphasized this by designing drawing and editing
                interfaces that are relatively simple to use and nearly identical to a finished,
                end-user’s view. In Neatline, scholars are always sketching, erasing, and sketching
                again their arguments on the screen.</p>
            <p>Subjectivity in space and time is a matter of interest in Neatline. Our map and
                timeline-related plugins (in progress) are designed to offer users the ability to
                model multiple backgrounds or alternatives independently from the foreground of
                their critical attention, and express all of these fields and their interrelation
                visually. The spatial and temporal foreground stands as a place for scholarly
                commentary, including textual annotation as well as intervention in the visual field
                by means of the freehand drawing of lines and shapes. Meanwhile user-specified
                Neatline backgrounds can be empirical or unabashedly subjective – precisely
                geo-referenced or wholly speculative.  For example, one local test case, which we
                will demonstrate, uses the maps and letters of U.S. Civil War cartographer Jedediah
                Hotchkiss.  GIS (Geographic Information Systems) layers are brought into Neatline
                from modern satellite imagery, from scans of Hotchkiss’s own surveyed-and-drawn
                battlefield maps, and from the historical atlases that served as the surveyor’s
                mental ‘base layer.’  Against these, we have georectified an informal, child’s-eye
                map Hotchkiss drew in a letter, to allay his young daughter’s concerns about his
                welfare.  Neatline allows all of these documents to be plotted and annotated in
                space and time.</p>
            <p>We will describe not only the theoretical basis of the project, but its concrete
                products, including improvements to the Omeka codebase and the creation of a suite
                of open-source plugins. Most of these plugins are usable independently but gain
                value in combination, comprising the Neatline system.</p>
            <p>1. <hi rend="italic">EAD Importer</hi>: allows for the easy and easily-adjusted
                import of Encoded Archival Description metadata into an Omeka exhibit.</p>
            <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Neatline Maps</hi>: provides map display through one or more
                GeoServer instances or through any specification-compliant WMS service.</p>
            <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Neatline Features</hi>: allows users to draw on map layers,
                encoding and edit geospatial shape information.</p>
            <p>4. <hi rend="italic">Neatline Time</hi>: incorporates the well-known Simile Timeline
                Javascript framework into Omeka to provide chronological visualization of Omeka
                items.</p>
            <p>5. <hi rend="italic">Neatline Theme</hi>: provides facilities for combining Neatline
                and Omeka information into unified interactive presentations.</p>
            <p>In addition, our work on Neatline led us to develop five further plugins which users
                may employ as part of their Omeka exhibits. These plugins greatly extend the
                capacity of Omeka and make it a more attractive option not only for end-users, but
                for better-resourced libraries, digital humanities centers, and cultural heritage
                institutions – the constituency best positioned to contribute further development
                time to the open source code of Neatline and Omeka alike.</p>
            <p>1. <hi rend="italic">FedoraConnector</hi>: makes it possible to display, comment on,
                annotate, and otherwise employ objects inheriting behaviors from a Fedora Commons
                repository.</p>
            <p>2. <hi rend="italic">GenericXmlImporter</hi>: permits users to import any arbitrary,
                flat XML data into Omeka.</p>
            <p>3. <hi rend="italic">SolrSearch</hi>: allows use of the Solr search engine with
                Omeka, facilitating improved search and implementing faceted browsing.</p>
            <p>4. <hi rend="italic">TeiDisplay</hi>: allows users to render TEI files in HTML format
                and attach them to Omeka items. This plugin integrates with SolrSearch for indexing. </p>
            <p>5. <hi rend="italic">VRACoreElementSet</hi>: allows users to bring the VRA Core
                Element Set (designed for description of visual resources) into Omeka.</p>
            <p>The project continues under the rubric of an ‘Omeka + Neatline’ partnership with the
                Center for History and New Media, funded through 2013 by the United States Library
                of Congress, with a next major code release planned for January 2012. DH 2012 in
                Hamburg will coincide with the release of Neatline demonstration projects and
                end-user documentation at <ref target="http://neatline.org/" type="external">http://omeka.org</ref>.</p>
            <p>Neatline operates on archival metadata – itself already an interpretation of a
                literary or historical collection – to allow scholars to illustrate connections
                among documents and the spatial and temporal dimensions that arise through their
                reading.  In this, it embodies a theme of much work in the Scholars’ Lab: that
                method is a path to argument, and that interpretive digital humanities scholarship
                may be best enacted in iterative, visual modes. </p>
            <p><figure><graphic url="img176-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
            <p/>
            <p><figure><graphic url="img176-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
            <p/>
            <p><figure><graphic url="img176-3.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
            <p/>
            <p><figure><graphic url="img176-4.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
            <p/><p><figure><graphic url="img176-5.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
            <p/>
            <p><figure><graphic url="img176-6.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Catapano, T., K. M. Price, and K. Walter</hi> (2005). The Walt
                    Whitman Archive: Archivist-Scholar Collaboration in Description and
                    Representation. <hi rend="italic">Joint International Conference of the
                        Association for Literary and Linguistic Computing and the Association for
                        Computers and the Humanities</hi>, Victoria, British Columbia, 2005.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Drucker, J., and B. Nowviskie</hi> (2004). Speculative Computing:
                    Temporal Modelling. <hi rend="italic">A Companion to Digital Humanities.</hi>
                    Oxford: Blackwell.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Drucker, J. (2009).</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">SpecLab: digital aesthetics and projects in speculative
                        computing. </hi>U of Chicago P.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Kramer-Smyth, J., M. Nishigaki, and T. Anglade</hi>. <hi
                        rend="italic">ArchiveZ: Visualizing Archival Collections</hi>. Available:
                        <ref target="http://www.archivesz.com/" type="external"
                        >http://www.archivesz.com/</ref></p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Neatline: Plot Your Archive in Space and Time</hi>. University of
                    Virginia Library Scholars’ Lab. Available: http://neatline.scholarslab.org/</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Papers of Jedediah Hotchkiss</hi>, Accession #2822 and #2907,
                    Special <hi rend="italic">Collections</hi>, <hi rend="italic">University of
                        Virginia</hi> Library, Charlottesville, Va.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Scholars’ Lab Omeka Plugins.</hi> University of Virginia Library
                    Scholars’ Lab. Available: <ref
                        target="http://www.scholarslab.org/projects/omeka-plugins" type="external"
                        >http://www.scholarslab.org/projects/omeka-plugins/</ref></p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Turkel, W., and D. Elliott (2010).</hi> Rapid Prototyping to
                    Support Experimental History. <hi rend="italic">Playing with Technology in
                        History</hi> Symposium. 30 April 2010. Available: <ref
                        target="http://www.playingwithhistory.com/" type="external"
                        >http://www.playingwithhistory.com/</ref>
                </p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>