<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-123">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>‘All Rights Worth Recombination’: Post-Hacker Culture and ASCII Literature
                    (1983-1993)</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Katelnikoff, Joel</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Alberta, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>katelnikoff@ualberta.ca</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
            <head>ASCII Literature</head>
            <p>This presentation will focus on a literary and cultural movement of the computer
                underground that featured texts written in ASCII code and distributed by means of
                the Bulletin Board Systems (BBSes) that flourished from the early-1980s until the
                mid-1990s. Independently-produced ASCII publications (also known as textfiles,
                t-files, g-files, philes, etc.) offered computer users a means by which to share
                information and opinions with one another. This movement, at its height, also gave
                rise to an innovative literature that was shaped by the technological environment in
                which it was produced and by the digital culture that it was connected to.</p>
            <p>This presentation will focus primarily on two of the earliest serial ASCII
                publications: <hi rend="italic">PHRACK and</hi><hi rend="italic">Cult of the Dead Cow</hi>. These publications were founded in 1985
                (shortly after the film <hi rend="italic">WarGames</hi> and the book <hi rend="italic">Hackers: Heroes of the Computer Revolution</hi>). These publications share several things in common: they are
                collaborative projects, written and edited by pseudonymous computer users in their
                late teens / early twenties, they contain illicit information about hacking,
                phreaking, and mischief, and they are uncensored and boundary-pushing. They both
                refuse to copyright their material, with the hope and expectation that their
                publications will be freely uploaded and downloaded throughout the computer
                underground. And most importantly, both of these publications feature literary
                writings that innovate new forms and styles that are strongly influenced by the
                techniques and tenets of hacker culture, particularly in its connection to
                copyright.</p></div>
           <div>
            <head>Rhizomatic transfer</head>
            <p>When the earliest ASCII zines emerged, the computer underground consisted of
                    innumerable hubs of digital culture, primarily in the form of
                    independently-operated, predominantly non-profit bulletin board systems. BBSes
                    functioned much like answering services, routing incoming calls into an
                    interface that would allow callers to send messages, upload and download files,
                    and play door games. Most BBSes were very small and had one telephone line,
                    meaning that only one user could access the system at any given time. These
                    small BBSes were not directly linked to one another (unlike hypertext models),
                    but instead were connected through their users, most of whom would frequent
                    several other BBSes, downloading and uploading files from board to board.</p>
            <p>Because BBS
                culture had no hierarchy of organization and because most BBSes were non-profit,
                there was no major presence of corporate media organization (e.g. newspapers, book
                publishers) within BBS culture. The literati of the BBS world would instead emerge
                from a new chorus of voices: namely, those who were willing to publish their works
                without any remuneration and were willing to allow their works to be copied and
                distributed freely throughout the computer underground. In exchange for this, the
                writers would have the potential to proliferate from BBS to BBS, city to city,
                allowing for the distant (but actual) possibility of becoming major contributors to
                the shape of computer underground culture. As an acknowledgement of their
                willingness to allow users to do what they will with the text, most of these files
                either exclude any statement of copyright (<hi rend="italic">Phrack</hi>), or
                compose puns such as ‘all rights worth shit’ (<hi rend="italic">Cult of the Dead
                    Cow</hi>). The publishers implicitly acknowledge that, in order for their work
                to proliferate, they must allow the work to be freely downloaded from BBSes and
                freely uploaded to other BBSes.</p></div>
            <div>
            <head>Open source</head>
            <p>If information wants to be free, what does this freedom entail? ASCII publishers
                allow their works to be shared, transferred, and read without cost to the reader or
                creator. The files can be limitlessly replicated with minimal concern for material
                costs. But beyond the ability to distribute and use these files freely, <hi
                    rend="italic">Cult of the Dead Cow</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Phrack</hi> themselves take liberties that extend beyond use and distribution. These
                publications demonstrate a willingness to modify the work of others in order to
                produce new works of their own, in the way that we might envision software
                programmers using open-source code. What follows are three successive stages of open
                source literature: reprinting, modification, and recombination.</p></div>
            <div>
            <head>Reprinting</head>
            <p>‘The Conscience of a Hacker’ (also known as ‘The Hacker Manifesto’) is probably the
                most well-known essay of the ASCII era. It was originally printed in <hi
                    rend="italic">Phrack</hi> 1:3, Phile 7 (1986). It was later republished in <hi
                    rend="italic">Cult of the Dead Cow</hi> 12, without any acknowledgement that the
                essay had previously been published in <hi rend="italic">Phrack</hi>, and without
                the knowledge of the author. Moreover, <hi rend="italic">cDc</hi> used ‘The
                Conscience of a Hacker’ to overwrite the original content of issue 12 (the
                transcribed lyrics of Metallica’s <hi rend="italic">Master of Puppets</hi> album).
                For <hi rend="italic">Cult of the Dead Cow</hi>, it was not only their own copyright
                that was ‘worth shit,’ but also the copyright claims of other publishers and
                writers, both digital and mainstream. In 1988, they republished a rant entitled
                ‘Fuck the World,’ which strongly influenced the next ten years of ASCII literature.
                The article, ironically, was a reprint from a print publication entitled <hi
                    rend="italic">Forced Exposure</hi>. Although the editor of <hi rend="italic"
                    >cDc</hi> (Swamp Rat) does give credit to the author and original publisher in
                the issue, the header of the issue clearly reads ‘FUCK THE WORLD / by  Swamp Rat,’
                leaving generations of readers confused as to who truly authored the article, and to
                what extent the text is ‘by’ Swamp Rat. Here, unauthorized reprinting seems to take
                its place alongside hacking and explosives manuals as yet another form of illicit
                information.</p></div>
            
            <div>
            <head>Modification</head>
            <p>In <hi rend="italic">Cult of the Dead Cow</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Phrack</hi>,
                freedom of information also extends to the modification of text. In academia,
                scholars frequently build upon the work of their colleagues, citing the findings of
                other scholars as part of the process of developing their own work. In ASCII
                publications this is also common, but without the same insistence of formality. The
                most parasitic example of this was the practice of tagging, where BBS sysops would
                obtain published text files, modify them by adding advertisements for their BBSes to
                the header or footer of the file, and continue to distribute the file by means of
                their BBS. The modified versions would proliferate, often under the same file name,
                which would limit the circulation of (and possibly overwrite) copies of the original
                version.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Phrack</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Cult of the Dead Cow</hi> also
                modified texts, but for different reasons and in different ways. Instead of
                inserting their own text into other peoples’ publications, they would bring other
                people’s writing into their publications. This was often done without the knowledge
                or consent of the writer. In some instances, they would replicate a substantial
                portion of another text (or an entire text), and then add to or subtract from that
                text at will. One of <hi rend="italic">Phrack</hi>’s regular features, ‘Phrack World
                News,’ would republish articles from corporate media outlets, occasionally
                interjecting their own undercutting commentary in square brackets. The inversion is
                clear: this is what the mainstream is saying about us, and this is what we are
                saying about what them.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Phrack</hi>’s most documented exploit in modification is their publication of a
                scaled-back version of a document that had been illegally downloaded from a ‘secure’
                BellSouth computer, describing some of the workings of their Enhanced 9-11 system.
                Even though the contents of the file were lightweight and contained no indication of
                being proprietary or sensitive information, its republication demonstrated that the
                systems at BellSouth could be hacked, by affiliates of <hi rend="italic"
                >Phrack</hi>. The editor was indicted on charges of wire fraud, interstate
                transportation of stolen property, and computer fraud and abuse.</p></div>
            <div>
            <head>Recombination</head>
                <p>The central concept of hacking is to generate a flexible and adaptable mastery of
                codes, and to develop a mastery that transcends a system. This is central to the
                hack and to the hacker ethos. Like any other codes, legal codes are equally
                susceptible to disruption and modification, as demonstrated in these four
                publications, which demonstrate a libertarian attitude in their handling of illicit
                information (in terms both content and copyright). Like any other codes, literary
                and linguistic codes are likewise susceptible. Even in these early publications,
                there is a tendency toward the recombinant (that is, writing that borrows liberally
                from multiple sources). From the inception of ASCII literature, writers tend to
                transform, and recontextualize language, style, and form from other ASCII
                publications and from BBS culture. Writers blur the boundaries between information
                and narrative, purpose and play, text and intertext.</p>
            <p>The most prominent example of recombination that took place in this era is probably
                    ‘The <hi rend="italic">cDc</hi> #200
                    Higgledy-Piggeledy-Big-Fat-Henacious-Mega-Mackadocious-You-Can’t-Even-Come-Close-So-Jump-Back-K-BOOMIDY-BOOMIDY-BOOM
                    File.’ This file, designed to simulate the scrolling display of an early-1990s
                    BBS, follows the narrative arc of a BBS experience, with every message board and
                    file area transforming into narrative, each narrative venturing into the most
                    iconic tropes and mythemes of the computer underground, corporate culture, and
                    ASCII literature: Internet Relay Chat, <hi rend="italic">Teen Beat</hi>,
                    Encyclopedia Brown, K-Rad slang, <hi rend="italic">Phrack</hi> magazine, ‘The
                    Real Pirate’s Guide,’ George Bush, Malcolm X, and old school 40-column all-caps
                    ASCII. This issue begins to demonstrate what can be done with the structures and
                    contents made familiar by other publications. It demonstrates a writing that
                    takes freely and gives freely, which is never proprietary, and for whom all
                    rights remain shit. Most importantly, it leads into the next generation of ASCII
                    literature, where writers continue to borrow from one another, to build cultural
                    mythologies collectively, and to follow the hacking tenets set out by Steven
                    Levy: ‘All information should be free. Mistrust authority – promote
                    decentralization. You can create art and beauty on a computer.’</p></div>
       </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>