<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-186">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Patchworks and Field-Boundaries: Visualizing the History of English</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Alexander, Marc</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Glasgow, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>marc.alexander@glasgow.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>This paper uses the database of the <hi rend="italic">Historical Thesaurus of
                        English</hi> (Kay et al. 2009; hereafter abbreviated to <hi rend="italic"
                        >HT</hi>) to visualize change in the history of English, and in particular
                    in the English lexicon. The <hi rend="italic">HT</hi>, published in 2009,<hi
                        rend="italic"> </hi>is the world’s largest thesaurus and the most complete
                    thesaurus of English, arranging into hierarchical semantic categories all the
                    recorded meanings expressed in the language from Anglo-Saxon times to the
                    present. The underlying <hi rend="italic">HT </hi>database (see Kay &amp; Chase
                    1987; Wotherspoon 1992), held at the University of Glasgow, is a massive
                    computational resource for analyzing the recorded words of English with regards
                    to both their meaning and dates of use.</p>
            <p>The present paper describes a methodology of visualizing English using data from the
                    <hi rend="italic">HT</hi>, developed from an earlier pilot project (Alexander
                2010). By combining visualization techniques with the high-quality humanities data
                provided in the <hi rend="italic">HT</hi>, it is possible to give scholars a
                long-range view of change in the history, culture and experiences of the
                English-speaking peoples as seen through their language.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>The Data</head>
            <p>The data stored within the <hi rend="italic">HT</hi> is a fine-grained conceptual
                hierarchy containing almost all of the recorded words in English, arranged
                semantically. Each category of words is nested within other, wider categories, so
                that, for example, the verb category <hi rend="italic">Live dissolutely </hi>is
                within <hi rend="italic">Licentiousness</hi>, itself adjacent to <hi rend="italic"
                    >Guilt </hi>and <hi rend="italic">Rascalry</hi> and within the wider category
                    <hi rend="italic">Morality</hi>. This hierarchical structure differs from the
                organization of many other thesauri; <hi rend="italic">HT </hi>categories relate to
                others not just linearly, but can operate either horizontally (on the same
                hierarchical level) or vertically (on a higher or lower level, either containing or
                being contained by another category). In addition, each concept is able to contain a
                series of subcategories within itself, separate from the main sequence. It is this
                complex hierarchical structure which helps make the <hi rend="italic">HT</hi>
                database so useful for visualization: each individual point in the hierarchy can
                contain both word entries for the concept represented by that point, and also all
                the conceptual descendants which follow it, each surrounded by siblings of similar
                meaning.</p>
            <p>The size of the <hi rend="italic">HT</hi> also makes it amenable to computational
                    analysis. The current version of the database (as of mid 2011) contains 793,747
                    entries, compared to <hi rend="italic">OED2</hi>’s 616,500 (Algeo 1990: 137),
                    all within 236,346 categories, each representing a distinct concept. Taking into
                    account each field stored within it, the database itself contains approximately
                    22.7 million pieces of data.</p></div>
            
            <div>
                <head>Visualization</head>
            <p>The normal metaphor for visualizing hierarchy is a tree-like system, like that often
                used in organisation charts. <hi rend="italic">HT</hi> data is, however, far too
                large to be used in such a way – even a spider-like tree or hypertree could not
                represent the thesaurus, whose largest category alone (the adverb <hi rend="italic"
                    >Immediately</hi>) contains over 250 synonyms.</p>
            <p>Instead, the present paper will describe an alternative way of displaying the <hi
                        rend="italic">HT </hi>hierarchy, representing each category as a nested
                    rectangle on a plane. This technique produces a ‘treemap’ (see Shneiderman
                    2009), wherein each entry in a hierarchy is represented by a rectangle which is
                    large enough to contain smaller rectangles representing its descendants while
                    simultaneously being itself small enough to nest within further rectangles
                    representing its parent categories. In short, a treemap structure takes the
                    organisational chart metaphor of <hi rend="italic">senior is up </hi>and
                    replaces it with <hi rend="italic">senior is big</hi>.</p>
            <p>Doing this for the full hierarchy of the <hi rend="italic">HT</hi> lets us view the
                semantic structure of the English language as a whole. Figure 1 is therefore a
                treemap showing all of present-day English in the <hi rend="italic">HT</hi>, with
                every word represented by a small dot of ink. Those black dots are present-day words
                which originated in Old English, and white dots represent those which entered the
                language much more recently. The map is arranged by semantic field, so words in
                close semantic proximity are also physically close to one another on the diagram. An
                interactive display of this visualization allows an analyst to see which areas
                correspond to which categories and lexemes.</p>
            </div>
            
                
            <div>
                <head>Patchworks and Field-Boundaries</head>
            <p>One effect which is visible from Figure 1 is that modern English has a ‘patchwork’
                    effect in the visualization. Areas such as <hi rend="italic">Physics</hi> and
                        <hi rend="italic">Chemistry</hi> are quite light, as are parts of <hi
                        rend="italic">Number</hi> (which includes <hi rend="italic"
                    >Mathematics</hi>) and <hi rend="italic">Language</hi>. This phenomenon makes it
                    possible to visually view the areas where the English language has ‘stretched’
                    in order to accommodate new vocabulary. These light patches within the greater
                    patchwork are areas of recent lexical innovation, made up of clusters of words
                    first cited in the <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> and recorded in the <hi
                        rend="italic">HT </hi>from recent years. Therefore, we would expect this
                    patchwork effect in areas affected by rapid social, technological or academic
                    growth, such as <hi rend="italic">Computing</hi> (inside <hi rend="italic"
                        >Number</hi>, adjacent to <hi rend="italic">Mathematics</hi>), <hi
                        rend="italic">Physics, Chemistry, Linguistics, Communication, Travel</hi>,
                    and so on. Conversely, darker and therefore older patches cover existence in <hi
                        rend="italic">Time and Space, Creation, Causation, Faith, Emotion</hi>, and
                    the parts of <hi rend="italic">Number</hi> which refer to <hi rend="italic"
                        >Arithmetic</hi> or <hi rend="italic">Enumeration</hi>.</p>
                
            <p>This effect is pronounced in present-day English, but if other selections of the data
                are taken, it reduces somewhat. If the present-day data is thought of as a ‘slice’
                of the <hi rend="italic">HT</hi>, then other such slices can be taken between the
                Old English period and the present day. Other slices reveal that this patchwork
                effect, with its pronounced edges between new and old semantic fields, do not occur
                throughout the rest of the history of the language. Proceeding backwards from the
                present day through the Late Modern, Early Modern and Middle English periods, there
                is a visible reduction in the patchwork effect observed above, so that by Middle
                English almost no delineated rectangular patches of innovation can be found. The
                paper compares these slices and offers an interpretation of various areas of
                patchwork and patchwork-like effects across time, which, as a result of rapid
                growth, generally indicates fundamental and rapid progress in the context of the
                language.</p></div>
            
            <div>  
                <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>In the ways outlined above, such visual displays of <hi rend="italic">HT</hi> data
                    can provide useful entry points to a large, complex lexicographical and
                    lexicological dataset. Firstly, in a pedagogical sense, these displays can give
                    students and the public a new way of looking at humanities data, and of
                    exploring them interactively. Secondly, as computer displays and online
                    dictionary interfaces become more polished, new ways of encouraging exploration
                    of lexical data online are needed to replace the lost experience of browsing a
                    printed dictionary, rather than only providing users with a blank search
                    interface. And finally, such visualizations can point analysts towards areas of
                    possible semantic, lexical or cultural interest, whether areas of trauma in the
                    history of the language, areas of rapid growth, or areas of relative stability.
                    The paper will conclude by demonstrating some of these, including ‘slices’ of
                    the data giving visualisations of various points in the history of English (eg
                    in the time of Chaucer or Shakespeare), and in illustrating lacuna in our
                    knowledge of earlier periods of the language, and will outline areas of future
                    development of this approach.</p>
            
            <p><figure>
                        <graphic url="img186-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>Figure 1: Present-day English from the HT, shaded by first cited
                            date</head>
                    </figure></p>
            </div>    
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <head>References</head>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Alexander, M.</hi> (2010). ‘The Various Forms of Civilization
                    Arranged in Chronological Strata’: Manipulating the <hi rend="italic">Historical
                        Thesaurus of the OED.</hi> In M. Adams (ed.), <hi rend="italic">‘Cunning
                        passages, contrived corridors’: Unexpected Essays in the History of
                        Lexicography.</hi> Monza: Polimetrica.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Algeo, J.</hi> (1990). The Emperor’s New Clothes: The second edition
                    of the society’s dictionary. <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the
                        Philological Society</hi> 88(2): 131-150.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Kay, C., and T. J. P. Chase</hi> (1987). Constructing a Thesaurus
                    Database. <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi> 2(3):
                    161–163.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Kay, C., J. Roberts, M. Samuels, and I. Wotherspoon</hi> (2009). <hi
                    rend="italic">Historical Thesaurus of the OED</hi>. Oxford: Oxford UP.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Shneiderman, B</hi>. (2009). Treemaps for space-constrained
                visualization of hierarchies. <ref target="http://www.cs.umd.edu/hcil/treemap-history/index.shtml" type="external">http://www.cs.umd.edu/hcil/treemap-history/index.shtml</ref>
                (accessed 26 October 2011).</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Simpson, J., and E. Weiner, eds</hi>. (1989). <hi rend="italic">The
                        Oxford</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">English Dictionary</hi>, 2nd. ed. Oxford: Oxford UP.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Wotherspoon, I</hi>. (1992). Historical Thesaurus Database Using Ingres. <hi rend="italic">Literary and
                    Linguistic Computing</hi> 7(4): 218-225.</p></div>
                
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>