<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-283">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Enriching Digital Libraries Contents with SemLib Semantic Annotation System</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Nucci, Michele</name>
                    <affiliation>Università Politecnica delle Marche, Italy</affiliation>
                    <email>mik.nucci@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Grassi, Marco</name>
                    <affiliation>Università Politecnica delle Marche, Italy</affiliation>
                    <email>margra75@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Morbidoni, Christian</name>
                    <affiliation>Università Politecnica delle Marche, Italy</affiliation>
                    <email>christian.morbidoni@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Piazza, Francesco</name>
                    <affiliation>Università Politecnica delle Marche, Italy</affiliation>
                    <email>f.piazza@univpm.it</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>The advent of revolutionary communication
                    tools, like social media and image/video sharing, have transformed the Web into
                    a giant collection of resources created by millions of people around the planet,
                    representative of their different cultures and ideas. In this context, the
                    Digital Humanities community have understood that Digital Libraries (DL) should
                    no longer be simple ‘expositions’ of digital objects but rather provide
                    interaction with users, enabling them to contribute with new knowledge, e.g. by
                    annotating and tagging digital artefacts (Arko et al. 2006). This provides a
                    more engaging user experience, enabling scholars to benefit from the digital
                    world in their everyday work and researchers to work collaboratively (David et
                    al. 2008). The crowdsourcing paradigm has been experimented, as in (Holley
                    2010), by leveraging users annotations to enrich the DL, helping in curating
                    contents (correcting or signalling typos, etc.) or upload new digital
                    material<note>BBC WW2 People’s War: <ref target="http://www.bbc.co.uk/ww2peopleswar/" type="external">http://www.bbc.co.uk/ww2peopleswar/</ref></note>.</p>
                <p>Existing annotations tools,
                    however, are often limited to context and tags, which provide poor semantics,
                    and, when they offer more expressive annotations, use proprietary or
                    non-interoperable formats to represent semantics. In other words, the knowledge
                    created by advanced users carefully annotating contents with valuable
                    information is often lost, since it is not directly reusable by
                    applications.</p>
                <p>In this paper we present the prototypal annotation system
                    developed within the SemLib EU project. The SemLib Annotation System (AS) can be
                    easily integrated into existing DL or used through a bookmarklet to annotate
                    generic Web pages, addressing annotations at different level of complexity and
                    expressivity. In the prototype, users can write simple comments, augment them
                    with links to Linked Data<note>Linked Data: <ref target="http://linkeddata.org/" type="external">http://linkeddata.org/</ref></note> (LOD) and semantic tags. But
                    if they are scholars and need more expressivity they can create complex
                    structured relations among digital objects, connecting text within different
                    documents and relating to specific vocabulary terms.</p>
                <p>Annotations are
                    structured as RDF data, which is stored to a remote annotation server and can be
                    consumed by third party applications as ‘slices’ of a single collaborative RDF
                    graph.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>The Role of Semantic Annotations</head>
                <p>Data
                    interoperability and reuse are the main achievements that the DL research
                    community is trying to address by looking at Semantic Web (SW) and LOD
                    technologies. As argued in previous researches (Kahan et al. 2001; Haslhofer
                    2010; Gerber et al. 2010) and witnessed by the Europeana initiative, which is
                    adopting a RDF based data model (EDM), great expectations come for the semantic
                    technologies. Semantically structured data is expected to provide the ability to
                    mash-up heterogeneous information and establish connections among digital
                    objects independently provided by different institutions.</p>
                <p>Data
                    interoperability and flexibility of aggregation foster reuse and enable
                    serendipity: unexpected reuse of data by different persons and in different
                    contexts from the one data was produced in. Users annotations, when properly
                    represented as semantic data, can play an important role in this context, as
                    they link documents to data.</p>
                <p>On the one hand, semantic annotations
                    represent precise relations and metadata and they are reusable with relatively
                    low effort to augment the DL’s data. Here, it is very important to expose easily
                    accessible APIs to ‘slice’ the RDF data produced. On the other hand, LOD
                    annotations contain links to open datasets or ontologies that can be
                    contextualized. This allows applications to merge annotations and augment their
                    metadata with other semantic. As an example, if documents are connected to a
                    world wide linked data graph, composed by big datasets, vocabularies and user
                    annotations, software applications can let users explore such a graph and
                    possibly discover unexpected and interesting connections among them.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>Simple Use-Case</head>
                
                <p>Let us shortly describe a simple
                    use case that illustrates the kind of scenario that AS should
                    address.</p>
                <p>Alice is a researcher in politics and annotates a transcription
                    of an election rally. She writes a comment to a passage and then clicks the
                    ‘extract tags’ button. AS uses DBPedia Spotlight<note>DBPedia Spotlight: <ref target="http://dbpedia.org/spotlight" type="external">http://dbpedia.org/spotlight</ref></note> (or
                    possibly other multi language entity extraction tools) to propose a set of
                    entity tags, using remote metadata to build a preview with pictures,
                    descriptions, etc. Alice chooses a number of tags including the politician ‘X’
                    who is mentioned in the transcription and then she loads an ‘emotions
                    vocabulary’ that allows her to express a precise relation (e.g. ‘is a
                    manifestation of’) between the annotated sentence and the term ‘rage’ from the
                    vocabulary. Alices annotations are collected, among others by a virtual
                    community of users, into a Web site exposing a RDF based faceted browser, where
                    they are merged with further metadata about the DBPedia entities cited in
                    annotations and ontologies.</p>
                <p>A second user, Bob, made a similar annotation,
                    semantically linking to the politician ‘Y’ from DBPedia. Since in DBpedia the
                    two politicians are connected by their metadata (e.g. they are from the same
                    party or they are born in the same city, etc.), the two entities can have one or
                    more paths that connect them in the graph. Bob can explore such paths and
                    discover a relation among his annotation and the one from Alice. In addition,
                    when Bob search for the keyword ‘anger’, to find objects related to that
                    emotion, he will be able to find the transcription annotated by Alice, since an
                    emotion ontology is available and it defines ‘rage’ as a narrower term of
                    ‘anger’. At this point, Bob could also decide to create a new semantic
                    annotation expressing a similarity between the two transcriptions, for example,
                    using a simple ‘is similar to’ relation.</p>
                <p>Using the AS, DL administrators
                    or DL owners/maintainers can make their own annotations but they can also select
                    relevant end-user contributions, aggregate them and then publish back as
                    trusted/official annotations, importing them to enrich the DL.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Annotations Data Model</head>
                
                <p>Annotations represent a
                    peculiar type of resources, specifically conceived to add information to other
                    existing resources. Annotations acquire therefore full significance in relation
                    with the target resource and other contextual information, such as its author,
                    its creation date and the vocabulary terms used. Properly structuring an
                    annotation using SW technologies is therefore necessary at twofold level to
                    clearly separate contextual metadata from its content. The AS data model reuses
                    and extends OAC ontology (Sanderson et al. 2011) to encode contextual metadata
                    and to attach annotations to involved Web resources. Since OAC specification
                    makes no assumption on the kind of body an annotation can have, one of the first
                    issues that have been tackled in SemLib project is how to represent annotations
                    that have an RDF graph as body. In AS data model, annotation body is a named
                    graph containing a set of RDF statements. This allows to represent semantically
                    structured annotation content basing on the standard support for named graphs
                    provided by RDF triplestores and SPARQL in addition to query and access only
                    little slices of the entire collaborative knowledge base (KB).</p>
                <p>The
                    annotation storage is agnostic with respect to the ontologies used to represent
                    the informative content of annotations. Pluggable ontologies and SKOS taxonomies
                    can be used to encode annotations content according to standardized domain
                    vocabularies to foster data interoperability between different communities and
                    DL.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                
                <head>Annotations Sharing Model</head>
                <p>In AS users
                    collect their annotations in notebooks to organize their work, aggregating
                    annotations by topic or task, and to easily make available to others subsets of
                    their annotations enabling collaborative scenarios. Notebooks are identified by
                    dereferenciable URLs that applications can use to retrieve RDF-encoded
                    annotations and relative metadata in different formats. </p>
                <p>Sharing a
                    notebook is as easy as sharing its URL on the Web, similarly to what happens for
                    popular file sharing platforms and common mechanisms like e-mails, wikis or
                    social networks can be used. For each notebook, the owner can easily set
                    fine-grained rights access, also making it public or sharing it only with
                    selected users.</p>
                <p>Before creating and sharing annotations each user must
                    signing into the annotation system. To make as easy as possible the integration
                    of the annotation system in existing DL, single sign-on systems like OpenID and
                    OAuth have been used. Different authentication systems can be supported
                    developing dedicated plugins.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>Prototype</head>
                <p>At the
                    time of writing, a fully working AS prototype<note>For for a working demo see <ref target="http://metasound.dibet.univpm.it/release_bot/release/semlib-client_0.61-demo_page/examples/demo.html" type="external">http://metasound.dibet.univpm.it/release_bot/release/semlib-client_0.61-demo_page/examples/demo.html</ref></note> has been
                    developed and will be further enhanced in the continuation of the project. The
                    prototype can be used in any existing Websites through a dedicated bookmarklet,
                    which will injects the needed Javascript code into the Web pages.</p>
                
                <p>System architecture, shown in Fig. 1, is typically client-server. The
                    client-side component, which comprises a set of modules implementing the
                    graphical user interface to create and browse annotations, is developed in
                    Javascript. The server-side component is a RESTful Web service which implements
                    the main application logic and the storage for the annotations based on a native
                    Sesame triplestore with the support for semantic inference.</p>
                
                <p><figure><graphic url="img283-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 1: Simplified architecture of the Annotation System</head></figure></p>
                <p>The AS prototype allows users to compose RDF
                    statements using an on purpose GUI (Fig. 2), connecting selected items with
                    properties coming from pluggable ontologies.</p>
                <p><figure><graphic url="img283-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 2: An example of the annotations editor</head></figure></p>
                <p>Selected items can be DL resources, named entities coming from custom SKOS
                    vocabularies or Web reconciliation services like Freebase<note>Freebase: <ref target="http://www.freebase.com/" type="external">http://www.freebase.com/</ref></note> Web pages or fragments of these.
                        For example, users can create structured annotations in Dante Alighieri’s DL
                        page to reference other pages of the DL about Italian writers that have been
                        influential for him, to provide additional information about his place of
                        birth referring to Florence entity in Freebase or to link text-excerpts of
                        the Divine Comedy coming from the Gutenberg Project<note>Gutenberg Project: <ref target="http://www.gutenberg.org/" type="external">Gutenberg Project: http://www.gutenberg.org/</ref></note>.</p>
                <p>The AS prototype includes a module for comments and tags. At the moment, it provides basic
                        functionalities including entity extraction from user comments (based on
                        DBPedia Spotlight) and semantic tagging.</p>
                <p>To demonstrate how annotation can be consumed basing on simple REST API, the AS
                        prototype provides also an example faceted browsing facility, implemented
                        using Simile Exhibit<note>Exhibit: <ref target="http://www.simile-widgets.org/exhibit/" type="external">http://www.simile-widgets.org/exhibit/</ref></note>.</p>
                     
            </div>
            
            <div>
                 <head>Conclusions</head>
                
                <p>In this work, SemLib annotation system have been introduced,
                        discussing its data and annotation model and presenting a working annotation
                        system prototype, discussing how this is expected not only to foster
                        annotation sharing between DL and user engagement but also to allow the
                        application of crowdsourcing paradigm in the creation of added value for the
                        DL.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Fundings</hi></p>
                <p>The research leading to
                    these results has received funding from the European Union’s Seventh Framework
                    Programme managed by REA-Research Executive Agency [SEMLIB -
                        262301 - FP7/2007-2013 - FP7/2007-2011 -
                        SME-2010-1].</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <head>References</head>
                
          
            <p><hi rend="bold">Arko, R. A., K. M. Ginger, K. A. Kastens, and J. Weatherley</hi>
                (2006). <hi rend="italic">Using annotations to add value to a digital library for
                    education</hi> Online: <ref target="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/may06/arko/05arko.html"
                type="external">http://www.dlib.org/dlib/may06/arko/05arko.html</ref> (accessed on 7th March 2012).</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">David, S., M. Nucci, and F. Piazza </hi>(2008). Talia: a Research and
                Publishing Environment for Philosophy Scholars. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the
                    Digital Humanities 2008 Conference</hi>, Oulu, Finland, 25th-29th June,
                2008.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Gerber, A., and J. Hunter</hi> (2010). Authoring, Editing and
                Visualizing Compound Objects for Literary Scholarship. <hi rend="italic">Journal of
                    Digital Information</hi> 11.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Haslhofer, B., E. Momeni, M. Gay, and R. Simon</hi> (2010).
                Augmenting Europeana Content with Linked Data Resources. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Proceedings of the 6th International Conference on Semantic Systems
                    (I-Semantics)</hi>, September 2010.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Holley, R</hi>. (2010). Crowdsourcing: How and Why Should Libraries
                Do It? <hi rend="italic">D-Lib Magazine, The Magazine of Digital Library
                    Research</hi>, March/April 2010.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Kahan, J., and M. R. Koivunen</hi> (2001). Annotea: An Open RDF
                Infrastructure for Shared Web Annotations. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 10th
                    international conference on World Wide Web</hi>, pp. 623-632.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Morbidoni, C., M. Grassi, and M. Nucci</hi> (2011). Introducing
                SemLib Project: Semantic Web Tools for Digital Libraries. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Proceedings of the International Workshop on Semantic Digital Archives –
                    sustainable long-term curation perspectives of Cultural Heritage held as part of
                    the 15th International Conference on Theory and Practice of Digital Libraries
                    (TPDL)</hi>, Berlin, 29<hi rend="sup">th</hi> September 2011.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Sanderson, R., and H. van de Sompel</hi> (2011). <hi rend="italic">Open Annotation: Beta Data Model Guide</hi>, Online: <ref target="http://www.openannotation.org/spec/beta/"
                type="external">http://www.openannotation.org/spec/beta/</ref> (accessed on 7th March 2012).</p>
        </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>