<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-237">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>VariaLog: how to locate words in a French Renaissance Virtual Library</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Lay, Marie Hélène</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Poitiers, France</affiliation>
                    <email>marie-helene.lay@univ-poitiers.fr</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>The efficiency of search engines is based on the principle that the information
                    sought can be retrieved by ‘looking for words’ conveying the information and
                    that these words can be identified thanks to the string of characters they are
                    comprised of.  This view takes for granted that the words are always spelt in
                    the same way and that they comply with orthographic rules.</p>
                <p>Such is not the situation which prevails for the texts produced during the French
                    Renaissance period. Therefore the availability of older texts for purposes of
                    archiving and disseminating the cultural heritage tradition raises a particular
                    problem. In texts edited in French before the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, spellings are not
                    consistent, as proper spelling has not been ‘invented’ yet. One and the same
                    word may therefore be spelt in a variety of forms. This is not only a
                    time-related variation, as would be expected from the evolution of the language
                    between the 15<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century. In one and the same book many different
                    spellings may be identified for the one and the same word:<hi rend="italic"
                    > </hi>for the word <hi rend="italic">côté</hi>, either <hi rend="italic">coté,
                        cotté, cote, costé, </hi>or<hi rend="italic"> couste </hi>could be used, the
                    verb <hi rend="italic">savoir</hi> may be spelt either <hi rend="italic"
                        >scavoir</hi> or <hi rend="italic">sçavoir</hi>, ‘<hi rend="italic">je
                        sais</hi><hi rend="italic">’</hi> may be spelt ‘<hi rend="italic">ie
                        sçay</hi><hi rend="italic">’</hi>, and its past participle ‘<hi
                        rend="italic">su</hi><hi rend="italic">’</hi> may appear as ‘<hi
                        rend="italic">sceu</hi><hi rend="italic">’</hi>.</p>
                <p>It is therefore necessary to adapt search engines based on word form
                    identification if they are to render the service expected. Several strategies
                    can be envisaged and the purpose of this paper is to focus on those which resort
                    to linguistic expertise, either included in the documents themselves (by
                    annotation) or into the search engine (by query extension). The solutions
                    considered are produced in the context of the Virtual Humanistic Library Project
                    and its evolution (<ref target="http://www.bvh.univ-tours.fr/" type="external"
                    >www.bvh.univ-tours.fr</ref> ). This part of the project called <hi rend="bold"
                        >VARIALOG</hi>, is financed by a Google Digital Humanities Research
                    Award.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Methodological alternatives</head>
                <p>The BVH/VHL context, considered here, is that of a highly expert environment of a
                    relatively moderate size aiming at a complete editorial treatment and the
                    dissemination of annotated and validated resources. Within this context, two
                    solutions have been designed:</p><xmt:oList rend="arabic">
                <item>Texts annotation with linguistic information gained from lemmatization. The
                    forms retrieved, whatever their spelling, are lemmatized under a canonic form
                    which then becomes the pivot of further requests: for example the lemma for <hi
                        rend="italic">nuit</hi> groups together forms like <hi rend="italic"
                        >nuits</hi> (which is ‘regular french’) or <hi rend="italic">nuyctz
                    </hi>(old written form). A first solution, <hi rend="bold">HUMANISTICA</hi> (Lay
                    2000) was based on the adaptation of a probabilistic tagger/lemmatizer. The
                    results achieved were satisfactory but the adaptation of the analyzer had to be
                    started all over again to take into account specific features of this high
                    heterogeneous corpus. Another solution, <hi rend="bold">ANALOG</hi> (Lay 2010a,
                    2010b) was therefore developed. It provides an annotation computer assisted
                    environment, and is currently being used in the BVH project. But the enrichment
                    of text through linguistic annotation is a slow and costly process. Though this
                    solution is very useful to go on producing a reference environment, it is
                    nonetheless desirable to provide efficient query tools on texts already
                    available but not yet annotated.</item>
                <item>Query extension, without requiring the lemmatization process. The aim is not
                    to produce exactly the right forms (like in EEBO -VosPos-, Impact, ToTrTaLe,
                    LGeRM, or for old czech, or old German projects). We will do so, in order to
                    help in an editorial process (<hi rend="bold">DISSIMILOG</hi>), but here, we
                    just want to spot all the written forms which could correspond to a query, being
                    insensitive to variation.</item></xmt:oList>
                </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>VariaLog : Principles</head>
                        
                    <p>To solve the problem of spelling variation, one has to go back to
                        observational evidence. Two directions may be taken in this respect: either
                        observe the texts or observe the variants attested for a given form. </p>
                        <xmt:oList rend="arabic">
                    <item>Concerning text observation, the aim is to evaluate the number of forms
                        for a given text which do not correspond to the norm. Moreover, one must
                        take into consideration the extent to which the texts can be compared. We
                        intend to illustrate this with two short extracts from Montaigne and
                        Rabelais, two authors of paramount significance. </item>
                    <item>Concerning the observation of variants attested for one word, the idea is
                        to formulate the rules which govern the production of abnormal forms. We
                        will then build rules to extend queries, turning the search of a word into
                        the search of all the forms assumed by this word, and match the results with
                        forms in texts. 
                    <p>Comparing the searched forms and their spelling in text, a
                        typology of the situations occurring may be offered. The form being searched
                        is the same one (<hi rend="italic">raisons/raisons</hi>) or the link can be
                        very weak (<hi rend="italic">impératrice/empériere</hi>). Between these two
                        types, a whole gradation of situations can be organised on a linguistic
                        basis: relations between sounds and different ways of spelling in modern
                        french (<hi rend="italic">c=ss; n=nn; r=rr; s=z; t=th; ai=ei,ai,ey,ay,oi,oy;
                            [uv]=u,v; u=eu)</hi>, flexionnal history (<hi rend="italic"
                            >serais</hi>/<hi rend="italic">seray/serois) </hi>and morphological
                        history (<hi rend="italic">hôpital/hospitalier</hi>; <hi rend="italic"
                            >forêt/forestier; advis/avis). </hi>Due to the structural instability of
                        this linguistic data, equivalences between character strings are difficult
                        to track statistically and no model-based approach can be developed. But
                        linguistic knowledge helps recognize regular replacement patterns, which can
                        be turned into rules.</p></item>
                    <item>The next point which needs to be taken into account is the relevance of
                        the rules: they have to help find all the forms concerned (low silence, good
                        recall), and to avoid generating too much noise (good precision). </item></xmt:oList>
                    <p>To test the first results, a small corpus of  7 words (<hi rend="italic"
                            >vices/une/face/fesse/lu/vu/souverain</hi>) has been transformed by the
                        substitution rules mentionned above.<hi rend="italic"> </hi>The results do
                        contain all the relevant forms, but the 7 words have been extended to 118445
                        forms. There is obviously some correlation between the length of the word
                        and the number of generated words due to the combinatory process. </p>
                    <p>The solution chosen to fix that problem is to describe, for each rule, the
                        context in which the substitution is allowed. This aims at constraining
                        their application strongly, and limits their productivity. This
                        contextualisation is based on a good knowledge of the linguistic process
                        involved. In the example given below, 8 simple rules are transformed into 9
                        more complex rules. Most of the time, one simple rule will be derived into 5
                        to 15 contextualised rules. </p><table>
                        <row>
                            <cell> (?&lt;\=[bdflmnprstv])u=eu </cell>
                            <cell> ain=ein,ain,eyn,ayn </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> (?&lt;\=[aeiouy])c(?\=[eiy])=ss </cell>
                            <cell> ^s(?\=[eiy]) = c </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> (?&lt;\=[aeiouy])ss(?\=[eiy])=c </cell>
                            <cell> (?!^.+)v = u </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> (?!^.+)n(?&lt;!.+$)=nn </cell>
                            <cell> ^u = v </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> (?!^.+)r(?&lt;!.+$)=rr </cell>
                            <cell> s$ = z </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table><p>The results achieved are satisfactory: the rules produce all the
                        linguistically permissible variants, and the number of variants is much
                        lower. The 7 words generate 37 forms.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                    <head>VariaLog : Tool description</head>
                    <p> The tool itself is thought to be really user-friendly especially for the
                    tuning of rules and the evaluation of their consequences (efficiency and non
                    regression tests). It is a free available java program which first transforms a
                    list of words into an extended list of forms, using that for a rules set. Having
                    done this, the need is to localise the different forms attested in the old
                    spelling in a text, according to the requested form. The output file of this
                    last part of the process is an html file with a graphical highlighting (or bold
                    character) of the identified variant. Moreover, each form is connected to a
                    bubble showing the rules used to derive the variant. A table containing the
                    summary of the used rules for the text is also available: the human validation
                    process is quite friendly. This tool is being put forward to be integrated to an
                    XTF platform. </p>
                </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>Using a rule-based approach, VariaLog is designed to identify all the written
                    forms that are likely to correspond to a query, since it is insensitive to
                    variations in spelling. The recall rate (tested on 5000 forms) provides evidence
                    that all the linguistically permissible variants in French are produced by the
                    rules, so long as the problem is simply one of spelling (<hi rend="italic"
                        >nuit/nuyct</hi>)and not a morphological one (e.g. <hi rend="italic"
                        >impératrice/empérière</hi>).  As far as precision is concerned, the rules
                    may sometimes generate more ambiguity than anticipated. If  ‘o’ becomes ‘ou’,
                    then, <hi rend="italic">école</hi> becomes <hi rend="italic">écoule</hi>, which
                    is not an acceptable variation, but <hi rend="italic">volant</hi> becomes <hi
                        rend="italic">voulant</hi>, which is an acceptable variation; as a result,
                        <hi rend="italic">volant</hi> will correspond to <hi rend="italic"
                        >vouloir</hi> (‘want’), thus increasing the ambiguity of this form which
                    means  already ‘flying, robbing, wheel, flounce, shuttlecock’. The generated
                    ambiguity is no different from standard ambiguities, even in an orthographic
                    environment.</p>
                <p> Already used to search several French dialects, VariaLog can be used to process
                    any form of spelling variation, in any language. One just needs to adjust one’s
                    own specific spelling rules or dictionary. Our aim is to help locate spelling
                    variation efficiently. User feedback is most welcome.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div><head>References</head>
                
                <p><hi rend="bold">Baron, A., and Rayson, P.</hi> (2009). <ref
                        target="http://ucrel.lancs.ac.uk/publications/cl2009/314_FullPaper.pdf"
                        type="external">Automatic standardization of texts containing spelling
                        variation, how much training data do you need?</ref>In M. Mahlberg, V.
                    González-Díaz, and C. Smith (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Corpus
                        Linguistics Conference, CL2009</hi>. University of Liverpool, UK, pp.
                    20-23.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Burnard, L.</hi> (1995). <ref
                            target="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/Customization/Lite/teiu5_en.xml"
                            type="external">Text Encoding for Information Interchange – An Introduction to the Text
                        Encoding Initiative.</ref><hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Second Language
                            Engineering Conference</hi>, 1995.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Craig, H., and
                            R. Whipp</hi> (2010). <ref
                                target="http://llc.oxfordjournals.org/content/25/1/37.short" type="external">Old
                        spellings, new methods: automated procedures for indeterminate linguistic
                        data.</ref><hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi> 25(1):
                        37-52.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Demonet, M.-L., and M. H. Lay</hi> (2011). Digitizing European
                    Renaissance prints: a 3-year experiment on image-and-text retrieval. <hi
                        rend="italic">International Workshop on Digital Preservation of
                        Heritage</hi> (IWDPH07). Kolkata, 2007. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Erjavec, T.</hi> (2011). <ref
                                target="http://www.aclweb.org/anthology/W/W11/W11-1505.pdf" type="external">Automatic
                        linguistic annotation of historical language: ToTrTaLe and XIX century
                        Slovene.</ref><hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 5th ACL-HLT Workshop on
                            Language Technology for Cultural Heritage, Social Sciences, and
                            Humanities</hi>, 2011, Portland, pp. 33-38.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Hana,
                            J., A. Feldman, and K. Aharodnik</hi> (2011). <ref
                                target="http://www.aclweb.org/anthology-new/W/W11/W11-1502.pdf" type="external">A
                        Low-budget Tagger for Old Czech.</ref><hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 5th
                            ACL-HLT Workshop on Language Technology for Cultural Heritage, Social
                            Sciences, and Humanities</hi>, 2011, Portland, pp. 10-18.</p><p><hi
                            rend="bold">Lay-Antoni, M.-H. et  al.</hi> (2000),  <ref
                            target="http://lexicometrica.univ-paris3.fr/jadt/jadt2000/pdf/89/89.pdf"
                            type="external">Adaptation d’un lemmatiseur au corpus rabelaisien: naissance
                        d’Humanistica.</ref><hi rend="italic">jadt 2000,</hi> Lausanne.</p><p><hi
                            rend="bold">Lay, M.-H., et al.</hi> (2010). <ref
                            target="http://lexicometrica.univ-paris3.fr/jadt/jadt2010/allegati/JADT-2010-1045-1056_106-Lay.pdf"
                            type="external">Pour une exploration humaniste des textes: AnaLog.</ref><hi rend="italic">jadt
                            2010, </hi>Rome<hi rend="italic">.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Sánchez
                            Marco, C., G. Boleda, and L. Padró</hi>  (2011). <ref
                            target="http://ilk.uvt.nl/LaTeCH2011/slides/01_Sanchez-Marco_etal.pdf"
                            type="external">Extending the tool, or how to annotate historical language varieties.</ref><hi
                            rend="italic">ACL-HLT Workshop</hi>, 2011, Portland, pp. 1-9. </p><p><hi
                            rend="bold">Scheible, S., R. J. Whitt,M.  Durrell, and B. Bennett</hi>
                        (2011). Evaluating an ‘off-the-shelf’ POS-tagger on Early Modern German
                        text. <hi rend="italic">ACL-HLT Workshop</hi>, 2011, Portland, pp.
                        10-18.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Souvay, G. and J.M. Pierrel</hi> (2009). <ref
                        target="http://www.doaj.org/doaj?func=abstract&amp;id=812845"
                        type="external">LgeRM: Lemmatisation des mots en moyen français.</ref>
                    <hi rend="italic">TAL</hi> 50(2): 149-172.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Thaisen, J</hi>. (2011). <ref
                            target="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-346.xml;query=;brand=default"
                            type="external">Probabilistic Analysis of Middle English Orthography: the Auchinleck
                        Manuscript.</ref><hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities Conference Abstracts, 2011,
                        </hi>Stanford.</p>
                <p><ref target="http://www.bvh.univ-tours.fr/"
                            type="external">www.bvh.univ-tours.fr/</ref></p>
                <p><ref target="http://www.c-tei.org/"
                                type="external">http://www.c-tei.org</ref></p>
                <p><ref target="http://www.bvh.univ-tours.fr/XML-TEI/index.asp" type="external">http://www.bvh.univ-tours.fr/XML-TEI/index.asp</ref></p><p><ref
                            target="http://www.bvh.univ-tours.fr/Epistemon/philologic.asp"
                            type="external">http://www.bvh.univ-tours.fr/Epistemon/philologic.asp</ref></p><p><ref
                            target="http://xtf.cdlib.org/documentation/programming"
                            type="external">http://xtf.cdlib.org/documentation/programming</ref></p><p><ref
                            target="http://www.monkproject.org/"
                            type="external">http://www.monkproject.org/</ref></p>
                <p><ref
                            target="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/help/whatis_wh.htm"
                            type="external">http://eebo.chadwyck.com/help/whatis_wh.htm</ref></p><p><ref
                            target="http://impactocr.wordpress.com/"
                            type="external">http://impactocr.wordpress.com/</ref></p><p><ref
                            target="http://panini.northwestern.edu/mmueller/vospos.pdf"
                        type="external">http://panini.northwestern.edu/mmueller/vospos.pdf</ref></p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>