<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-221">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Cataloguing linguistic diversity: Glottolog/Langdoc</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Nordhoff, Sebastian</name>
                    <affiliation>Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>sebastian_nordhoff@eva.mpg.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Hammarström, Harald</name>
                    <affiliation>Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>harald_hammarstroem@eva.mpg.de</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            
        <div>
        <head>Overview</head>
        <p>Glottolog/Langdoc is a comprehensive database linking 180k bibliographical references to
            21k languoids (language families, languages, dialects). It provides extensive query
            possibilities for human users and subscribes to the principles of Linked Open Data
            (Heath &amp; Bizer 2011) as far as machine users are concerned.</p>
            <p>The aim of Glottolog/Langdoc to provide near-total bibliographical coverage of descriptive
            resources to the world’s languages. Every reference is treated as a resource, as is
            every ‘languoid’ (Good &amp; Hendryx-Parker 2006). References are linked to the
            languoids which they describe, and languoids are linked to the references described by
            them.</p>
            <p>Computational treatment and modeling of language resources has so far
            mainly concentrated on major languages with a research tradition in NLP and some
            commercial viability. When we leave the industrialized countries, languages resources
            become very scarce. Treebanks or annotated corpora seem like fanciful ideas when the sum
            total of resources treating a language amounts to a description of its verbs and a
            treatise of its phonology from a local university, which is for instance the case of the
            Niger-Congo language Aduge. Before one can start thinking about developing a WordNet or
            similar larger resources for these languages, one must take stock of the resources which
            exist, however arcane they might be. This is one of the aims of the Glottolog/Langdoc
            project. The resources are tagged for resource type (grammar, word list, text collection
            etc), macroarea (roughly, continents), and language.</p>
        </div>
        
        <div>
        <head>Use cases</head>
        <p>Four different user groups can be distinguished: language diversity researchers,
            statisticians, Semantic Web engineers, and linguistic empiricists.</p>
        
        
        <div>
        <head>Linguistic diversity researchers</head>
        <p>The first groups covers linguists interested in the world-wide distribution of linguistic
            diversity (cf. Evans &amp; Levinson 2009), for the largest part typologist. These
            researchers are for instance interested in the distribution of subject, verb, and object
            in the languages of the world (SVO, SOV, VSO, OVS, OSV, VOS), or in the size of the
            phonemic inventory. The emerging patterns can be related to human cognition on the one
            hand hand (SOV and SVO have distinct processing advantages Hawkins 2004) and known
            migration patterns of humans as they settled the global land mass (Atkinson 2011). In
            order to acquire the necessary data points, description of various languages have to be
            perused, respecting genetic and geographical. This means that substantial
            bibliographical information has to be collected. Glottolog/Langdoc aims at providing
            near-total coverage of literature of the world’s lesser known languages, including grey
            literature. Note that Glottolog/Langdoc only provides the bibliographical records, not
            the references themselves. All bibliographical information can be downloaded as txt,
            html or bibtex. Zotero integration is also provided. The provision of references is
            complemented by links to sites where a copy could be obtained (WorldCat, GoogleBooks,
            Open Library).</p>
            
        </div>
        <div>
        <head>Statistical analysis</head>
        <p>The links established between 180k references and 21k languoids allow for statistical
            analyses of the following kinds:</p>
        
            <xmt:uList>    
            
        <item>What is the descriptive coverage of a particular language?</item>
        <item>What is the descriptive coverage of a particular language family or area
            (Hammarström &amp; Nordhoff, in press)?</item>
                
            </xmt:uList>
                     
                        <table>
                            <row>
                                <cell>   </cell>
                                <cell> Austronesian </cell>
                                <cell> non-Austronesian </cell>
                                <cell> Total </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell> grammar </cell>
                                <cell> 93 (17.82)% </cell>
                                <cell> 114 (13.82%) </cell>
                                <cell> 207 (15.37%) </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell> grammar sketch </cell>
                                <cell> 104 (19.92%) </cell>
                                <cell> 148 (17.94%) </cell>
                                <cell> 252 (18.71%) </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell> phonology or sim. </cell>
                                <cell> 55 (10.54%) </cell>
                                <cell> 54 (6.55%) </cell>
                                <cell> 109 (8.09%) </cell>
                            </row>
                            <row>
                                <cell> wordlist or less </cell>
                                <cell> 270 (51.72%) </cell>
                                <cell> 509 (61.70%) </cell>
                                <cell> 779 (57.83%) </cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
            <xmt:uList>
        <item>How many languages have so far been described  (Hammarström &amp; Nordhoff 2011)?</item>
        <item>Status of the least described language families in the world (Hammarström 2010)?</item>
        <item>In which geographic area is the research focus on phonology, in which area is
            syntax deemed more interesting?</item>
                
            </xmt:uList>
            
        </div>
        
        <div>
        <head>Semantic Web engineers</head>
        <p>Next to XHTML, Glottolog/Langdoc data are also available as RDF, making use of a number
            of established ontologies such as rdfs, skos,<note><ref target="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/" type="external">http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/</ref></note>
            gold,<note><ref target="http://linguistics-ontology.org" type="external">http://linguistics-ontology.org</ref></note> lexvo,<note><ref target="http://lexvo.org" type="external">http://lexvo.org</ref></note>, wgs84,<note><ref target="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos" type="external">http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos</ref></note> 
            bibo,<note><ref target="http://bibliontology.com/" type="external">http://bibliontology.com/</ref></note> and Dublin core.<note><ref target="http://dublincore.org/" type="external">http://dublincore.org/</ref></note>
            This means that Glottolog/Langdoc data can be integrated into other projects making use
            of the aforementioned ontologies.</p>
            
        </div>
        
        <div>
        <head>Empiricists</head>
        <p>There are a number of researchers who are at unease with the current way how languages
            are defined and language codes assigned by the current registrar, SIL international.
            Some spurious languages do get codes, while some existing languages do not get a code.
            Some language families see a multiplication of their members (e.g. there are over 40
            Quechuan languages) while this ‘splitter’ approach is not observed in other areas of the
            world (Nordhoff &amp; Hammarström 2011). SIL draws on the Ethnologue<note><ref target="http://www.ethnologue.com" type="external">http://www.ethnologue.com</ref></note> for the set of living languages it provides codes for. The Ethnologue
            lists about 7000 languages, but does not always disclose the information the inclusion
            is based on. As a result, there are a number of ‘languages’ which do not seem to relate
            to anything in the real world, dangling pointers so to speak. They have an Ethnologue
            entry, a name, a code assigned by SIL, but no referent. Glottolog has the stated goal to
            give a reference for every language it includes. The project distinguishes ‘established
            languoids’, for which scientific documentation is available, for ‘provisional
            languoids’, for which we do not have dedicated descriptions. The long term goal is to
            get rid of ‘provisional languoids’ by either finding a description, making them
            ‘established’, or by discarding them. This will allow linguists to always be able to
            ascertain on what grounds a given language is argued to exist.</p>
            
        </div>
  
        </div>
            
        <div>
        <head>Technologies</head>
        <p>Glottolog/Langdoc draws on over 20 input bibliographies, which are enriched with
            information about document type and languages covered using machine-learning techniques
            (Hammarström, 2011). The project uses the pylons web framework. Glottolog/Langdoc
            supports content-negotiation (XHTML and RDF) and is part of the Linguistic Linked Open
            Data Cloud (Chiarcos et al. 2012).</p>
            
        </div>
        
        <div>
        <head>Comparison</head>
        <p>There are a number of related projects with slightly different foci. The <hi rend="bold"
            >WEBALL</hi> project for instance<note><ref target="http://sumale.vjf.cnrs.fr/Biblio/" type="external">http://sumale.vjf.cnrs.fr/Biblio/</ref></note> lists genetic,
            bibliographic, and geographic information about the languages of Africa, but not beyond.
            We incorporate a recent version of the WEBALL database in Glottolog/Langdoc. <hi
                rend="bold">OLAC</hi><note><ref target="http://www.language-archives.org/" type="external">http://www.language-archives.org/</ref></note> aggregates references to linguistic
            resources, but has a slightly different data model. Furthermore, OLAC uses federated
            data aggregated via OAI-MHP while Glottolog/Langdoc uses a static repository. OLAC does
            include genetic information, but this seems to be ad hoc. For instance, OLAC includes
                <hi rend="italic">Austronesian</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Eastern
                Malayo-Polynesian</hi>, but not the lower grouping <hi rend="italic">Oceanic</hi>
            (still over 1000 languages). Furthermore, the coverage of OLAC and Glottolog/Langdoc is
            different. OLAC has more information on major languages, an area Glottolog/Langdoc
            disregards. Many of the higher numbers from OLAC come in fact from a single
            documentation project hosted at the MPI for Psycholinguistics in Nijmegen. These high
            numbers have technical reasons (every recording of the MPI archives is counted as one
            resource) and do not translate to an equally high number of publications. The following
            table gives the top languages as far as number of references are concerned for OLAC and
            Glottolog/Langdoc. A dagger † signals languages which profit from overcounting of
            resources from corpus1.mpi.nl.</p>
            
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">OLAC</hi>
                    </cell>
                    <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">Glottolog/Langdoc</hi>
                    </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>English (9044)</cell>
                    <cell>Swahili (1826)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>German (5770)</cell>
                    <cell>Hausa (1542)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Dutch (5239)</cell>
                    <cell>Nama (Namibia) (1270)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Japanese (4317)</cell>
                    <cell>Afrikaans (1155)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Spanish (3331)</cell>
                    <cell>Central Yupik (1129)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Turkish (3091)</cell>
                    <cell>Standard French (1059)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>French (1964)</cell>
                    <cell>Zulu (1048)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Yuracare (1576) †</cell>
                    <cell>South Levantine Arabic (990)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Oxchuc Tzeltal (1390) †</cell>
                    <cell>Tlingit (987)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Central Yupik (1312)</cell>
                    <cell>Gwich’in (905)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Turkish Sign Language (1157) †</cell>
                    <cell>Yoruba (900)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Yele (1152) †</cell>
                    <cell>Kabyle (879)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Aleut (1135)</cell>
                    <cell>Aleut (740)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Beaver (1080) †</cell>
                    <cell>Thai (730)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Dutch Sign Language (1063) †</cell>
                    <cell>Koyukon (728) </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Tlingit (1028)</cell>
                    <cell>Xhosa (728)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>North Alaskan Inupiatun (1024)</cell>
                    <cell>Akan (709)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Gwich’in (955)</cell>
                    <cell>Pulaar (703)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Czech (943)</cell>
                    <cell>Ewe (693)</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Polish (892)</cell>
                    <cell>Tswana (690)</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            
            <p>Multitree’s<note><ref target="http://multitree.org/" type="external">http://multitree.org/</ref></note> focus is on gathering all genetic
            classifications of the world’s languages, not so much on references. Glottolog uses
            Multitree information for lower levels, but an own, more conservative, classification
            for higher levels. Multitree has 141 families while the Glottolog main tree has 429
            (including isolates).</p>
            <p>The Ethnologue<note><ref target="http://www.ethnologue.com" type="external">http://www.ethnologue.com</ref></note> finally lists languages and references, but
            does not subscribe to the document-centric approach Glottolog/Langdoc employs. These
            projects cover similar ground, but with different specializations. As an example,
            Ethnologue lists 45 references for Hausa, while Glottolog lists 1826; The figures for
            Thai are 37 and 730, respectively. Ethnologue has a similar number of languages families
            as Multitree (132), which is less ‘splitting’ than Glottolog. The Ethnologue lists
            population figures and language development; this information is not found in
            Glottolog.</p>
        <p>The current technical limitations mean that there is a substantial duplication of work.
            It is hoped that the use of RDF and related technologies will lead to a decrease of this
            duplication of work. There is for instance no need that all these projects keep their
            own database mapping geographical coordinates and countries to languages, neither is
            there a need to have several databases of language names. Publication of these resources
            according to the principles of Linked Data (Chiarcos et al. 2012) will mean that the
            data can easily be repurposed and integrated into other applications.</p>
        <p>Glottolog/Langdoc provides URIs for references and languoids so that other resources can
            easily link to or retrieve from Glottolog/Langdoc. While Glottolog/Langdoc takes a
            critical stance towards ISO 639-3, all relevant information can nevertheless also be
            accessed via the ISO 639-3 code.</p>
        </div>
        </body>
        
        <back>
            <div>
                <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Atkinson, Q. D.</hi> (2011). Phonemic
                    Diversity Supports a Serial Founder Effect Model of Language Expansion from
                    Africa. <hi rend="italic">Science</hi> 332: 346.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Chiarcos, C., S. Nordhoff, and S. Hellmann,
                        eds.</hi> (2012). <hi rend="italic">Linked Data in Linguistics. Representing
                        Language Data and Metadata</hi>. Springer. Companion volume of the Workshop
                    on Linked Data in Linguistics 2012 (LDL-2012), held in conjunction with the 34th
                    Annual Meeting of the German Linguistic Society (DGfS), March 2012,
                    Frankfurt/M., Germany.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Evans, N., and S. Levinson</hi> (2009). The
                    myth of language universals: Language diversity and its importance for cognitive
                    science. <hi rend="italic">Cognitive and Brain Sciences</hi> 32: 429-492.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Fabre, A.</hi> (2005). Diccionario
                    Etnolingüístico y guía Bibliográfica de los Pueblos Indigenas Sudamericanos.
                    Book in Progress at <ref
                        target="http://butler.cc.tut.fi/fabre/BookInternetVersio/Alkusivu.html"
                        type="external"
                        >http://butler.cc.tut.fi/ fabre/BookInternetVersio/Alkusivu.html</ref>
                    accessed May 2005.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Good, J., and C. Hendryx-Parker</hi> (2006).
                    Modeling Contested Categorization in Linguistic Databases. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Proceedings of the EMELD 2006 Workshop on Digital Language Documentation:
                        Tools and Standards: The State of the Art</hi>. Lansing, Michigan. June
                    20-22, 2006 <ref
                        target="http://www.linguistlist.org/emeld/workshop/2006/papers/GoodHendryxParker-Modelling.pdf"
                        type="external"
                        >http://www.linguistlist.org/emeld/workshop/2006/papers/GoodHendryxParker-Modelling.pdf</ref>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Hammarström, H.</hi> (2010). The Status of
                    the Least Documented Language Families in the World. <hi rend="italic">Language
                        Documentation &amp; Conservation</hi> 4: 177-212.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Hammarström, H.</hi> (2011). Automatic
                    Annotation of Bibliographical References for Descriptive Language Materials. In
                    P. Forner, J. Gonzalo, J. Kekäläinen, M. Lalmas, and M. de Rijke (eds.),
                    Proceedings of the CLEF 2011 Conference on Multilingual and Multimodal
                    Information Access Evaluation, <hi rend="italic">LNCS</hi>, vol. 6941. Berlin:
                    Springer, pp. 62-73.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Hammarström, H., and S. Nordhoff</hi>
                    (2011). How many languages have so far been described? Paper presented at NWO
                    Endangered Languages Programme Conference, Leiden, April 2011.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Hammarström, H., and S. Nordhoff</hi> (in
                    press). Achievements and Challenges in the Description of the Languages of
                    Melanesia. In M. Klamer and N. Evans (eds.), Melanesian languages on the Edge of
                    Asia, Special Issue of <hi rend="italic">Language Documentation &amp;
                        Conservation</hi>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Hawkins, J. A.</hi> (2004). <hi
                        rend="italic">Efficiency and Complexity in Grammars</hi>. Oxford UP.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Heath</hi><hi rend="bold">, T., and C. Bizer</hi> (2011). <hi
                        rend="italic">Linked Data - Evolving the Web into a Global Data Space</hi>.
                    San Rafael: Morgan &amp; Claypool.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Maho, J.</hi> (2001). <hi rend="italic"
                        >African Languages Country by Country: A Reference Guide</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">Göteborg Africana Informal Series</hi>, vol. 1. Department of
                    Oriental and African Languages, Göteborg University, 5th ed.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Nordhoff, S., and H. Hammarström</hi> (2011). Glottolog/Langdoc:
                    Defining dialects, languages, and language families as collections of resources.
                    In Proceedings of the First International Workshop on Linked Science 2011, <hi
                        rend="italic">CEUR Workshop Proceedings</hi>, vol. 783<hi rend="italic">CEUR
                        Workshop Proceedings</hi>, vol. 783. URL <ref
                        target="http://iswc2011.semanticweb.org/fileadmin/iswc/Papers/Workshops/LISC/nordhoff.pdf"
                        type="external">
                        http://iswc2011.semanticweb.org/fileadmin/iswc/Papers/Workshops/LISC/nordhoff.pdf</ref>.</p>
            </div>
        </back></text>
</TEI>