<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-200">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Wiki Technologies for Semantic Publication of Old Russian Charters</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Varfolomeyev, Aleksey</name>
                    <affiliation>Petrozavodsk State University, Russian Federation</affiliation>
                    <email>avarf@psu.karelia.ru</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Ivanovs, Aleksandrs</name>
                    <affiliation>Daugavpils University, Latvia</affiliation>
                    <email>aleksandrs.ivanovs@du.lv</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
            <p>The term ‘semantic publication’ denotes an electronic text publication that is
                provided with additional information layers, which represent knowledge about the
                text in a formalized way suitable for automatic processing. In the modern Web
                environments, semantic publications, especially in digital libraries and electronic
                journals, have become quite topical (Baruzzo et al. 2009; Shotton et al. 2009; de
                Waard 2010). Their advantages are rather obvious. Firstly, semantic publications
                provide better facilities for searching for information, since such publications
                draw together search algorithms used by humans and computers. For instance, if in an
                ontology is mentioned that a definite term has a synonym, searching for the term and
                its synonym can be performed simultaneously; and it is not necessary to mention the
                synonym in the request. Secondly, since formalized knowledge can generate new
                knowledge, semantic publications can be used as a knowledge base in order to advance
                hypotheses for further research by means of automatic inference.</p>
            <p>It seems that semantic publications of historical records have one more advantage
                different from the above-mentioned common advantages: semantic layers in the
                publications of historical records reflect researchers’ interpretations, which can
                be verified by means of formalized, computer-based procedures.</p>
            <p>In order to reveal the advantages of semantic editions in research of medieval
                documentary records, this paper presents a prototype of the semantic publication of
                the 13th century Old Russian charter corpus, which forms a constituent part of the
                vast collection of medieval and early modern records ‘Moscowitica–Ruthenica’ kept in
                the Latvian State Historical Archives, a structural unit of the Latvian National
                Archives (Riga, Latvia). This collection of documents provides historians with
                firsthand information about relations of Old Russian and Byelorussian lands and
                towns (Smolensk, Novgorod, Pskov, Polotsk, etc.), as well as Lithuania (later –
                Poland-Lithuania) with Riga, Livonia, Hanseatic League and some German towns in the
                late 12th – early 17th centuries. For the first time, ‘Moscowitica–Ruthenica’ – a
                historical name of this document collection – was mentioned in the archival
                inventories dated back to the 1630s. Although ‘Moscowitica–Ruthenica’ as a
                department of the Latvian State Historical Archives does not exist any more, its
                documents constitute a natural complex of historical records, which should be
                studied as a whole (Ivanovs &amp; Varfolomeyev 2005).</p>
            <p>In the prototype of the semantic publication, five interconnected charters have been
                used (Charters nos. 1, 3a, 4, 5, and 6, see Ivanov &amp; Kuznetsov 2009). Actually,
                there should be mentioned twelve charters that reveal the course of relations
                between Riga and Smolensk in the 13th – first half of the 14th century, however, the
                presentation has its limits, therefore the basis of the prototype has been reduced.
                In the centre of the semantic network represented in the prototype, there is the
                Missive of Archbishop of Riga Johann II to Fedor Rostislavich, Prince of Smolensk,
                blaming inhabitants of Vitebsk for unjustified complaint against Rigans (Charter no.
                6, 1285–1287). </p>
            <p>In order to provide the texts with additional descriptive metadata, information about
                persons, sites, documents, etc. mentioned in the charters is revealed and linked
                with the corresponding data extracted from different specialized ontologies. In the
                last years, a great number of different ontologies have been created, including
                those intended for historical and source studies, e.g. ontology CIDOC CRM. In this
                ontology, there are classes and relations that can be used in description of
                historical persons, sites, and historical events, which are related to museum
                objects (Doerr 2003). On the basis of this ontology, a number of specialized
                ontologies for description of definite historical aspects have been elaborated.
                There can be mentioned ontologies created within Pearl Harbor Project in the USA
                (Ide &amp; Woolner 2007) or CultureSampo Project in Finland (Ahonen &amp; Hyvönen
                2009). Unfortunately, such ontologies can not meet all the requirements of the
                semantic publication of charter corpora, since they do not reflect the specificity
                of written historical records. Therefore, the authors of the paper propose a
                document-oriented approach to creation of ontologies (in contrast with
                event-oriented approaches accepted in the above-mentioned ontologies).</p>
            <p>The semantic publication of the charters constitutes two kinds of semantic links.
                First, there are links between historically and thematically interconnected charters
                (these interconnections emerged when the charters were drawn up, in the course of
                documenting of relations between Smolensk and Riga in the 13th century). Thus,
                diverse links between information reflected in the charters within this complex of
                historical records can be revealed. Second, there are links with other historical
                records, which do not belong to the complex ‘Moscowitica–Ruthenica’. In this case,
                information extracted from the complex of charters ‘Moscowitica–Ruthenica’ (it can
                be called ‘internal information’) is linked with ‘external’ information, provided
                either directly (by other historical records), or indirectly (by research papers,
                specialized ontologies, etc.).</p>
            <p>Within the semantic publication, relations between its objects are described using
                triplets: ‘a charter is written by a person’, ‘a charter is sent to a person’, ‘a
                charter mentions a person’. As it is commonly done in different ontologies, inverse
                relations can also be introduced, e.g. ‘a person is mentioned in a charter’. It
                should be noted that this publication is partly based on hypothetical data;
                hypothetic nature of some relations may be reflected using definite combinations of
                words (‘probably refers to’ instead of ‘refers to’).</p>
            <p>However, production of semantic publications on the basis of ontologies, which are
                recorded using Semantic Web technologies – RDF or OWL, is time-consuming. It seems
                that opportunities and tools provided by semantic Wiki-systems can facilitate this
                process. For instance, Semantic MediaWiki (Krötzsch et al. 2007) offers specialized,
                rather simple markup tools that can be used to indicate different objects
                (place-names, persons’ names, etc.) in the texts of the charters and to supply the
                texts with meta-information. The principle feature of this system is the use of
                typified hyperlinks between pages. These pages constitute the objects of the
                semantic network, but hyperlinks – denote relations between the objects.</p>
            <p>On the site http://histdocs.referata.com, the text of the Charter no. 6 is presented.
                The text has been translated from Old Russian into English and published applying
                Semantic MediaWiki. In the published text, hyperlinks to other pages of this
                semantic network have been marked out. These pages contain texts of the charters of
                the complex ‘Moscowitica–Ruthenica’, as well as data related to historical persons,
                places, etc. Below the text, the facts related to a definite charter are mentioned
                (e.g. ‘Charter 6 mentions Helmich’, ‘Charter 6 probably refers to Charter 4’, etc.)
                These facts are linked with the text, and this linkage is based on researcher’s
                interpretation of the document.</p>
            <p>It should be noted that within the semantic network different facts about the
                objects, which are recorded by means of Semantic MediaWiki tools, can be
                automatically transformed into RDF triplets. Therefore, Wiki-systems can be used for
                production of semantic publications of charters and other written documents.</p>
            <p>However, some shortcomings of Wiki-systems can be mentioned. For example,
                non-standard fonts can not be used in transcription of the texts; the texts of the
                charters can not be linked with raster images of the documents; the texts can not be
                marked up on the basis of XML markup standard (e.g. in accordance with TEI or CEI
                markup schemes). Therefore, a specialized Wiki-system for charters’ editing purposes
                should be developed. In the presentation of the paper, some possible solutions to
                the problems mentioned above are examined.</p>
            </div>
            </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <head>References</head>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Ahonen, E., and E. Hyvönen</hi> (2009). Publishing Historical Texts
                on the Semantic Web – A Case Study. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Third IEEE
                    International Conference on Semantic Computing (ICSC2009)</hi>. Berkeley, pp.
                167-73.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Baruzzo, A., et al. </hi>(2009). Toward Semantic Digital Libraries:
                    Exploiting Web2.0 and Semantic Services in Cultural Heritage <hi rend="italic"
                        >Journal of Digital Information</hi> 10( 6). <ref
                        target="http://journals.tdl.org/jodi/article/viewArticle/688/576"
                        type="external"
                        >http://journals.tdl.org/jodi/article/viewArticle/688/576</ref> (accessed 14
                    March 2012).</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">de Waard, A.</hi> (2010). From Proteins to Fairytales: Directions in
                Semantic Publishing. <hi rend="italic">IEEE Intelligent Systems</hi> 25( 2):
                83-88.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Doerr, M.</hi> (2003). The CIDOC Conceptual Reference Module: An
                    Ontological Approach to Semantic Interoperability of Metadata <hi rend="italic"
                        >AI Magazine</hi> 24( 3): 75-92.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Ide, N., and D. Woolner</hi> (2007). Historical Ontologies. In K.
                Ahmad, C. Brewster and M. Stevenson (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Words and Intelligence
                    II: Essays in Honor of Yorick Wilks</hi>. Dordrecht: Springer, pp. 137-52.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Ivanov, A., and A. Kuznetsov </hi>(2009). <hi rend="italic"
                        >Smolensko-rizhskie akty, XIIIv. – pervaia polovina XIVv.: Dokumenty
                        kompleksa Moscowitica–Ruthenica ob otnosheniiakh Smolenska i Rigi</hi>
                    [Treaties between Smolensk and Riga: 13th – First Half of the 14th Century:
                    Documents of the Complex Moscowitica–Ruthenica about Relations between Smolensk
                    and Riga]. Riga. </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Ivanovs, A., and A. Varfolomeyev</hi> (2005). Editing and Exploratory
                    Analysis of Medieval Documents by Means of XML Technologies. In <hi
                        rend="italic">Humanities, Computers and Cultural Heritage</hi>. Amsterdam:
                    KNAW, pp. 155-60.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Krötzsch, M., et al.</hi> (2007). Semantic Wikipedia. <hi
                        rend="italic">Journal of Web Semantics</hi> 5( 4): 251–61.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Shotton, D., et al.</hi> (2009). Adventures in Semantic Publishing:
                Exemplar Semantic Enhancements of a Research Article. <hi rend="italic">PLoS
                    Computational Biology</hi> 5( 4): e1000361. <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000361" type="external">http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000361</ref> (accessed 14 March 2012).</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>