<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-287">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mapping the Information Science Domain</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Arazy, Ofer</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Alberta, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>ofer.arazy@ualberta.ca</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Ruecker, Stan</name>
                    <affiliation>Illinois Institute of Technology, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>sruecker@ualberta.ca</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Rodriguez, Omar</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Alberta, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>omar.rodrigueza@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Giacometti, Alejandro</name>
                    <affiliation>University College London, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>alejandro.giacometti@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Zhang, Lu</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Alberta, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>lu.eva.zhang@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Chun, Su</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Alberta, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>schun@ualberta.ca</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
            <p>In the scholarly community, there has been for the last fifteen years an increasing
                interest in interdisciplinary projects, where researchers with different
                disciplinary backgrounds form teams to collaborate in addressing problems that are
                either not clearly within a single research domain, or that can best be approached
                by combining a variety of approaches. However, there also remain a number of
                research areas where interdisciplinary approaches seem to be warranted, but scholars
                in single disciplines have continued to work largely in isolation from their
                colleagues in other domains. We focus on one specific scientific field – information
                science – which is investigated in various disciplines: library and archival
                studies, computer science, management (and specifically, management information
                systems), and engineering, to name just a few.</p>
                <p>Prior works in the area have discussed the disconnect between various areas within the broad field of
                information science, relying primarily on co-citation techniques and content
                analysis. These studies concluded that although all domains within this area are
                focused on the concepts of information, people, and (information and communication)
                technologies, the disciplines remain disjunct in terms of their disciplinary
                recognitions and topic of research. Despite some similarities in research
                methodology (‘research approach’ and ‘level of analysis’) (Glass et al. 2004), there
                are substantial differences in terms of co-citation patterns (Ellis et al. 1999;
                Sawyer &amp; Huang 2007), indicating the fields are distinct. Furthermore, although
                the research in these various areas may often appear to be similar on the surface,
                the contents of research are varied as well (Ellis et al. 1999). Glass et al. (2004)
                concluded that ‘overall, we see that there was minimal topic overlap’ among the
                various disciplines, and Sawyer and Huang (2007) summarize that these areas of
                scholarship ‘have overlapping, but substantively different, research foci.’</p>
                <p>Despite these interesting findings, extant research suffers from three primary
                limitations. First, previous studies are limited in scope, often focusing on just a
                subset of the academic units that publish articles in the domain. Second, prior
                research often relied on manual analysis, limiting the number of articles that are
                studied. Third, previous research in the area made little usage of information
                visualization techniques; recent advancements in the field of visualization have
                provided tools for exposing intricate relationships in data, and have the potential
                to reveal interesting patterns in interdisciplinary science. </p>
                <p>Furthermore,
                although research on earlier data describes a disjoint domain, recent years have
                seen what appear to be the first signs of convergence in the various sub-fields
                within the broad information science discipline. We see more and more
                cross-departmental collaborations, journals with a much broader scope (e.g. <hi
                    rend="italic">JASIST</hi>), and there is a move across North America to
                amalgamate these various departments under one institutional roof (often referred to
                as the ‘information school’ or simply ‘iSchool’). </p>
                <p>The objective of this
                paper is to address these previous limitations and map developments in the
                information science domain in the last fifteen years, using novel visualization
                techniques. We revisit the question of the divergence/convergence within the
                sub-disciplines, and propose a scalable method for analyzing (through both
                statistical analysis and advanced visualizations) the semantic and usage patterns in
                information science research articles. We focus our attention on three pre-defined
                topics that cross boundaries and are investigated in many sub-domains. For example
                the notion of ‘Trust’ was defined as ‘designing tools that would help alleviate the
                problem of trust in e-commerce, e.g. rating and reputation mechanisms’, and was
                represented using the following keywords: ‘trust’, ‘online’, ‘web’, ‘e-commerce’,
                ‘electronic commerce’, ‘e-business’, ‘trustworthiness’, ‘rating’, ‘reputation’,
                ‘reputation mechanism’, ‘system’, and ‘information system’.</p>
                <p>Our method
                involved the following steps: (a) defining each of the three topic areas – ‘trust’,
                ‘text mining’, and ‘web services’ - through a series of search keywords; (b) running
                these keywords on the Thompson Reuters Web of Knowledge (<ref
                    target="http://wokinfo.com/" type="external">http://wokinfo.com/</ref>http://wokinfo.com/) corpus of research articles,
                repeating the query separately for the 15 years under investigation, and choosing
                the 500 highest ranked (in terms of matching the query) research articles at each
                time period; (c) analyzing the relationships between the 500 articles in each time
                period using both co-citation and content analysis; and (d) developing novel
                visualization to expose how the patterns of relationships develop over the fifteen
                years.</p>
                <p>Traditionally, citation patterns have been visualized using a
                network diagram, where the articles are represented as nodes and the citations are
                shown as lines connecting the nodes (e.g. Shen et al. 2006). Others have developed
                variations on this form of visual representation (Nakazono et al. 2006; Brandes
                &amp; Willhalm 2002; Ibekwe-SanJuan &amp; SanJuan 2009).</p>
                <p>Our approach
                builds on the Eigenfactor method (Bergstrom &amp; West 2008), which applies an
                algorithm similar to Google’s PageRank (Brin &amp; Page 1998) to determine which
                nodes in a networks (in this case, journals) are most important, and how nodes
                connect with one another. The importance depends on where a journal resides in this
                mesh of citation links: the more citations a journal receives, especially from other
                well connected journals, the more important the journal is.</p>
                <p>We model our
                visualization technique after the <hi rend="italic">well-formed eigenfactor</hi>
                method (Stefaner 2009) that utilizes Eigenfactor, and was used in the past to track
                the evolution of the Neuroscience domain (<ref
                    target="http://well-formed-data.net/archives/331/neuroscience-infoporn"
                    type="external">http://well-formed-data.net/archives/331/neuroscience-infoporn</ref>). That analysis
                pre-determined the association of journals to disciplines, and then analyzed the
                relationships between disciplines as they evolve over time. We, however, sought a
                more organic approach, which recognizes that a journal could publish articles
                belonging to various areas (and even a specific article may belong to more than one
                area). Thus, we employed the classification of articles to categories provided by
                the Web of Knowledge. </p>
                <p>Building on prior work in the field (Ellis et al.
                1999; Glass et al. 2004), we analyze relationships both in terms of content and
                citation patterns. For each of the three topics, and for each of the time periods,
                we analyzed the 500 research articles to create similarity matrixes – in terms
                respectively of content and citation pattern – and then aggregated the data to
                calculate similarities between Web of Knowledge categories. These categories
                similarity matrixes were the input for our visualization method.</p>
                <p>The
                results of our analysis are 3 pairs of visualizations, where each pair represents
                the evolution in the information science domain in terms of content and citation
                pattern for one topic. Figures 1a-c below depict the evolution in the ‘trust’ area,
                when using citation patterns as the method of analysis.</p>
                
                <p><figure><graphic url="img287-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 1a: the evolution in the ‘Trust’
                    topic; each line represents a Web of Science category; each cluster is made up of
                    similar categories, corresponding to a specific scientific discipline</head></figure></p>
                
                <p><figure>
                        <graphic url="img287-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>Figure 1b: the ‘Information Science &amp; Library Science’
                            category, and how it evolved in terms of clustering with other
                            categories</head>
                    </figure></p>
                
                <p><figure><graphic url="img287-3.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 1c: the cluster that includes
                    the ‘Information Science &amp; Library Science’ category; on the right: the list of
                    categories in this cluster; each colored line represents a category and its
                    origins</head></figure></p>
           
                <p>Figure 2, below, represents the visualization for the same topic – ‘Trust’ – this
                    time based on the content of the research articles.</p>
               
                <p><figure>
                        <graphic url="img287-4.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>Figure 2: the evolution in the ‘Trust’ topic, when analysis is
                            based on the contents of articles</head>
                    </figure></p>
            
           <p>There are two
                interesting findings from our analysis. First, we see substantial differences
                between co-citation patterns and the patterns based on content (i.e. comparing
                Figures 1a and 2a). While the topical analysis shows one primary cluster, the
                co-citation visualization depicts many small clusters. Thus, while there is a
                substantial convergence in terms of contents, the information science field remains
                disjoint in terms of citation patterns. Some of the primary clusters correspond to
                the domains of management information systems, computer engineering, medical
                informatics, health information systems, physics, law, and computer science. Second,
                there are differences between topics. While the ‘Trust’ topic seem to have emerged
                from one area, and then broken into smaller sub-areas over the years (see Figure
                1a), the ‘Text mining’ topic remains relatively consistent in terms of its
                decomposition to clusters.</p>
                <p>We conclude that our novel data analysis and
                visualization methods have revealed patterns that have never been described before,
                highlighting the differences between topics of investigation within the broad
                information science discipline. In our next iteration of the project will include
                (a) the analysis of a larger corpus of research articles, trying to capture this
                entire domain, (b) refined data analysis methods, and (c) the exploration of new
                visualization techniques, which would help us to discover additional hidden
                patterns.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Funding</hi></p>
            <p>This research was supported in part by SSHRC, the Social Sciences and Humanities
                Research Council of Canada.</p>
            
            </div></body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
                
            <p><hi rend="bold">Bergstrom, C. T., and J. D. West</hi> (2008). Assessing Citations
                    with the Eigenfactor™ Metrics. <hi rend="italic">Neurology</hi> 71:
                    1850-1851.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Brandes, U., and T. Willhalm</hi> (2002). Visualization of
                    Bibliographic Networks with a Reshaped Landscape Metaphor. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Proceedings of the Symposium on Data Visualisation,</hi> Barcelona, Spain,
                    May 27-29, 2002. </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Brin S., and L. Page</hi> (1998). The Anatomy of a Large-Scale
                Hypertextual Web Search Engine. <hi rend="italic">Computer Networks</hi> 30:
                107-117.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Ellis, D., D. Allen, and T. Wilson</hi> (1999). Information Science
                    and Information Systems: Conjunct Subjects Disjunct Disciplines. <hi
                        rend="italic">Journal of the American Society for Information Science and
                        Technology</hi> 50(12): 1095-1107.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Glass, R. L., V. Ramesh, and I. Vessey</hi> (2004). An Analysis of
                    Research in Computing Disciplines. <hi rend="italic">Communications of the
                        ACM</hi> 47(6): 89-94.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Ibekwe-SanJuan, F., and E.  SanJuan</hi> (2009). The Landscape of
                    Information Science: 1996-2008. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 9th
                        ACM/IEEE-CS Joint Conference on Digital Libraries,</hi> Austin, TX, USA,
                    June 15-19, 2009). </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Nakazono, N., K. Misue, and J. Tanaka</hi> (2006). NeL2: Network
                Drawing Tool for Handling Layered Structured Network Diagram. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Proceedings of the 2006 Asia-Pacific Symposium on information Visualisation, –
                    Volume 60</hi> (Tokyo, Japan). K. Misue, K. Sugiyama, and J. Tanaka (eds.). ACM
                International Conference Proceeding Series, vol. 164. Australian Computer Society,
                Darlinghurst, Australia, pp. 109-115.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Sawyer, S., and H. Huang</hi> (2007). Conceptualizing Information,
                    Technology, and People: Comparing Information Science and Information Systems
                    Literatures. <hi rend="italic">Journal of the American Society for Information
                        Science and Technology</hi> 58(10): 1436-1447.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Shen, Z., M. Ogawa, S. T. Teoh, and K. Ma</hi> (2006). BiblioViz: a
                System for Visualizing Bibliography Information. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of
                    the 2006 Asia-Pacific Symposium on information Visualisation - Volume 60</hi>
                (Tokyo, Japan). K. Misue, K. Sugiyama, and J. Tanaka, Eds. ACM International
                Conference Proceeding Series, vol. 164. Australian Computer Society, Darlinghurst,
                Australia, 93-102.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Stefaner, M.</hi> (2009). Well-Formed Eignefactor, <ref
                        target="http://well-formed-data.net/archives/192/well-formed-eigenfactor"
                        type="external"
                        >http://well-formed-data.net/archives/192/well-formed-eigenfactor</ref></p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>