<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-285">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Recovering the Recovered Text: Diversity, Canon Building, and Digital Studies</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Earhart, Amy</name>
                    <affiliation>Texas A&amp;M University, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>aearhart@tamu.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>

            <p>This paper examines the state of the current digital humanities canon, provides a
                historical overview of the decline of early digitally recovered texts designed to
                expand the literary canon, and offers suggestions for ways that the field might work
                toward expansion of the digital canon. The early wave of small recovery projects has
                slowed and, even more troubling, the extant projects have begun to disappear, as is
                apparent from looking through the vast number of projects that are if we are lucky,
                ghosts on the wayback machine. Alan Liu’s <hi rend="italic">Voice of the
                    Shuttle</hi> provides a good measure of the huge number of lost early recovery
                projects. A quick perusal of ‘The Minority Studies’ section reveals that of the six
                sites listed in ‘General Resources in Minority Literature,’ half cannot be located
                with a careful search, suggesting that they have been removed.  The same trend is
                found with other projects listed on the site. While the ‘General Resources in
                Chicano/Latino Literature’ section, only 50% of projects are still online, other
                areas, such as Asian American literature, have a higher percentage of active
                projects. Some projects, such as Judith Fetterley’s<hi rend="italic"> 19th Century
                    Women’s Bibliography</hi>, are the living dead and have not been updated for
                years. Similarities exist among the extinct projects. Most were produced in the late
                1990s by single scholars at institutions that did not have an etext center or a
                digital humanities center, never attracted external support, and never upgraded to
                SGML or TEI. The canon problems are driven by the dual issues of preservation and
                the stagnation of digitization recovery efforts.</p>
            <p>We should find it troubling that the digital canon is losing the very texts that
                mirrored the revised literary canon of the 1980s. If we lose a large volume of these
                texts, and traditional texts such as Whitman, Rossetti, and Shakespeare are the
                highlighted digital literary texts, we will be returning to a new critical canon
                that is incompatible with current understandings of literature. The early digital
                recovery work I am discussing is not easily available. Few of these texts are in
                print. A few more are available on for-profit databases or on microfilm, but most
                are available only with a return to the one or two libraries that own the original
                physical copy of the book, journal, or newspaper. </p>
            <p>Some have posited that a structural problem in the emergence of digital humanities
                contributes to the selection of materials for digitization and preservation. Martha
                Nell Smith contends that digital humanities developed as a space to which
                practitioners hoped to flee from the shifts in the profession that arose out of the
                cultural studies movement. Smith highlights the digital humanities’ retreat into
                modes of analytics, objective approaches as ‘safe’ alternatives to the messy
                fluidities found in literary studies. If Smith is correct, then there should be no
                surprise that recovery of messy lost texts has not been a priority for the field.
                Others, such as Kenneth Price, view the funding mechanism as a contributing factor
                to the increasingly traditional canon of digitized texts. Price notes that the
                criteria of impact, crucial to the granting decision, favor the canonical text. The
                National Endowment of Humanities (NEH) awarded 141 start-up grants from 2007 through
                2010. Of those grants, only twenty-nine were focused on diverse communities and
                sixteen on the preservation or recovery of diverse community texts. It is striking
                to examine the authors and historical figures individually cited in the list of
                funding: Shakespeare, Petrach, Melville, and Jefferson. While there are grants to
                support work on indigenous populations, African and African American materials, and
                Asian American materials, in addition to other populations, the funding of named
                great men of history deserve scrutiny. </p>
            <p>In addition, the turn to increased standardization (TEI) and big data troubles our
                efforts at small-scale recovery project, as DIY scholars, outside the DH community,
                have difficulty gaining access to required technical skills for small projects,
                leading to a decline in small-scale digital recovery projects. The poor literary
                data sets impact digital humanities efforts to experiment with visualization and
                data mining techniques. For example, the UC Berkley WordSeer tool is remarkably
                useful, but the data set used to test the tool and the conclusions drawn about the
                texts are problematic. The team chose to examine the slave narratives housed at <hi
                    rend="italic">Documenting the American South</hi>. They ran an analysis on the
                set to see if the literary conventions of the text corresponded with critic James
                Olney’s claim that autobiographical slave narratives follow a list of tropes such as
                ‘I was born’ or ‘Cruel slavemaster.’ However, the chosen data set was not
                appropriate for the research question. The 300 narratives labeled slave narratives
                at this site are actually a mixed bag of first person narratives that are fictional
                and non-fictional, black authored and white authored, pre and post Civil War, some
                autobiographical, some biographical and some anti and some pro slavery, or at least
                apologetic. Given the narratives, it is hard to believe that Olney’s criteria, which
                he says are to be applied to autobiography, would be able to be proven by the test
                set of data. Literary datamining is still in its infancy, but, to date, the most
                successful literary results are those that utilize smaller, curated data sets, such
                as Tanya Clement’s fascinating Stein project. </p>
            <p>Dan Cohen writes, ‘Instead of worrying about long-term preservation, most of us
                should focus on acquiring the materials in jeopardy in the first place and on
                shorter-term preservation horizons, 5 to 10 years, through well-known and effective
                techniques such as frequent backups stored in multiple locations and transferring
                files regularly to new storage media, such as from aging floppy discs to DVD-ROMs.
                If we do not have the artifacts to begin with, we will never be able to transfer
                them to one of the more permanent digital archives being created by the
                technologists.’ I want to spin out the two crucial points that I take from Dan’s
                argument. 1) we must continue to focus on acquiring artifacts and 2) we must work
                with short term preservation strategies to stop immediate loss.</p>
            <p>If Matt Kirschenbaum is correct and preservation is not a technical
                problem but a social problem, then it follows that the digital humanities community
                should be able to address the lack of diversity in the digital canon by attention to
                acquisition and preservation of particular types of texts.  We need a renewed effort
                in digitizing texts that occurs in tandem with experimental approaches in data
                mining, visualization and geospatial representations. Recent critiques have tended
                to separate the two, a mistake that will damage both efforts. We can create
                infrastructure to support scholars interested in digital recovery. Leveraging
                existing structures to support new, small scale scholarship, continued outreach and
                training for scholars not interested in become digital humanists but interested in
                digital recovery is crucial.</p>
            <p>Preservation of existing digital recovery projects needs to begin immediately. We
                need a targeted triage focused on digital recovery projects that allow access to
                materials that are not accessible in print or other digital form. Using existing
                structures of support, like NEH’s Access and Preservation Grant and Brown’s newly
                launched TAPAS, we might build an infrastructure to ingest selected digital recovery
                projects. While it is unlikely that we can preserve the entirety of the project we
                might, as Dan Cohen has argued, preserve simply. We may not preserve the interface,
                but if we can preserve the recovery core – the text – then we will not lose the
                valuable work that the early digital pioneers completed.</p>
            <p>We need to examine the canon that we, as digital humanists, are constructing, a canon
                that skews toward traditional texts and excludes crucial work by women, people of
                color, and the GLBTQ community. We need to reinvigorate the spirit of previous
                scholars who believed that textual recovery was crucial to their work, who saw the
                digital as a way to enact changes in the canon. If, as Jerome McGann suggests, ‘the
                entirety of our cultural inheritance will be transformed and reedited in digital
                forms,’ (72), then we must ensure that our representation of culture does not
                exclude work by diverse peoples.</p>
        </div>  
        </body>
        <back><div>
                <head>References</head>
            
            <p><hi rend="bold">Clement, T. E.</hi> (2008). ‘A Thing Not Beginning and Not Ending’:
                Using Digital Tools to Distant-read Gertrude Stein’s The Making of Americans. <hi
                    rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi> 23(3): 361-381. </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Cohen, D. J</hi>. (2005). The Future of Preserving the Past. <hi
                    rend="italic">CRM: The Journal of Heritage Stewardship</hi> 2(2): viewpoint.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Cole, J. L.</hi> (2004). Newly Recovered Works by Onoto Watanna
                (Winnifred Eaton): A Prospectus and Checklist. <hi rend="italic">Legacy: A Journal
                    of American Women Writers</hi> 21(2): 229-234.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Cole, J. L.</hi> Winnifred Eaton Digital Archive. Formerly <ref target="http://etext.virginia.edu/eaton/" type="external">http://etext.virginia.edu/eaton/.</ref></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Liu, A</hi>. Voice of the Shuttle <ref target="http://vos.ucsb.edu/" type="external">http://vos.ucsb.edu/</ref>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">McGann, J.</hi> (2005). Culture and Technology: The Way we Live Now,
                What is to be Done? <hi rend="italic">New Literary History</hi> 36(1): 71-82. </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Olney, R</hi>. (1984). I Was Born: Slave Narratives, Their Status as
                Autobiography and as Literature. <hi rend="italic">Callaloo</hi>
                (20): 46-73.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Price, K. M.</hi> (2009). Digital Scholarship,
                Economics, and the American Literary Canon. <hi rend="italic">Literature
                    Compass</hi> 6(2): 274-290. </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Smith, M. N.</hi> (2007) The Human Touch: Software of the Highest Order: Revisiting Editing as
                Interpretation. <hi rend="italic">Textual Cultures</hi> 2(1): 1-15.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">University of Virginia Library</hi>. Electronic Text Center <ref
                        target="http://www2.lib.virginia.edu/digitalcuration/etext.html"
                        type="external"
                    >ttp://www2.lib.virginia.edu/digitalcuration/etext.html</ref>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Wordseer</hi>. The University of Berkley, California 
                        wordseer.berkeley.edu.</p>

        </div>
        </back>
        
    </text>
</TEI>