<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-259">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Content Creation by Domain Experts in a Semantic GIS System</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Nakhimovsky, Alexander</name>
                    <affiliation>Colgate University, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>adnakhimovsky@colgate.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Myers, Tom</name>
                    <affiliation>N-Topus Software, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>tommyers@dreamscape.com</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>The focus of this paper is on how an ontology-based GIS system can be populated
                    with class instances and further maintained by domain experts with no support
                    from ontological engineers. This is an old goal of knowledge engineering. We
                    present our approach in the context of a specific Semantic GIS system called
                    EventMap (Nakhimovsky 2010), but the techniques we propose should be of general
                    interest. At the core of our approach are two simple observations. First,
                    instances of a given class can be described by a table in which each row
                    corresponds to an instance and each column to a property. Such tables can be
                    created in a context that allows data validation for data properties and, for
                    object properties, provides access to already created instances of the object
                    class. If the tables are kept in the cloud (e.g., Google spreadsheets) then we
                    have a ready-made environment for joint distributed authoring, essential for
                    creating community-based resources. The second observation is that map layers
                    can be described by KML documents which can be created using a variety of tools
                    ranging from ArcGIS to the free KML editor built into Google Maps / My Places.
                    This is a flexible arrangement that makes simple things easy and difficult
                    things possible.</p>
                <p>Specifically, in this paper we present two mechanisms for data entry: via a blog
                    with links to KML data, in which each blog entry corresponds to an event; and
                    via a Web application that reads in the relevant subset of an ontology
                    (expressed as metadata tables) and provides a form that validates new class
                    instances against that ontology.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The EventMap Framework</head>
                <p>An EventMap is a sequence of annotated maps produced by a GIS system and
                    controlled by a Timeline: each map corresponds to a time interval, and together
                    a map and a time interval represent an Event. The Timeline makes it possible to
                    navigate event sequences and observe changing event patterns over time; the
                    patterns depend on the query posed to the GIS system. Every event is linked to
                    an annotation that can contain arbitrary web content, including images,
                    multimedia, and output from Web applications. Internally, the content is
                    represented by RDF graphs; specific event sequences, their maps, and their
                    annotations are produced by a SPARQL query (DuCharme 2011). </p>
                <p>Instead of thinking of an EventMap as a sequence of maps each corresponding to a
                    time interval and annotated by a web page, one can think of it as a sequence of
                    pages each annotated by a map. A good example of this kind of book is McEvedy
                    (2003). EventMap is a framework for creating such books online.</p>
                <p><figure><graphic url="img259-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 1: An Event Representation</head></figure></p>
                
                <p>Figure 1 shows a Google map overlaid with a scanned and edited map of
                    Afghanistan’s borders in 1879. It corresponds to the historical event of the
                    treaty of Gandamak, formalizing the British occupation of the mountain passes
                    into Afghanistan in response to rapid Russian advance into Central Asia. Pink
                    strips on the Timeline correspond to events and link to event descriptions. The
                    controls help navigate the events.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>The Architecture of the Framework</head>
                    <p>The overall structure of the EventMap framework is shown in Figure 2.
                            EventMap data are kept in a Primary Store, with links to other
                            materials. The Store can be in any data structure that can be serialized
                            in the Comma-Separated Values (CSV) format; this includes spreadsheet
                            and relational database. The Store can be located in the cloud, which
                            creates a framework for collaborative authoring that does not require
                            advanced computer skills or server maintenance. We have been using
                            Google spreadsheets, partly because Google provides HTML forms for
                            editing them, and we can write code to validate user input and
                            pre-populate the forms with data that the author must verify but rarely
                            needs to type.</p>
                    <p><figure><graphic url="img259-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 2: EventMap Architecture</head></figure></p>
                    
                    <p>In more detail, the Primary Store contains a number of Repositories, each a
                        container of material on a specific topic, such as the history of
                        Afghanistan borders, or the history of Arctic research during the Second
                        International Polar Year. A repository contains the following kinds of
                        materials:</p>
                    <xmt:uList>
                        
                            <item>data tables, each corresponding to a class of objects or
                                events</item>
                        
                        <item>
                            metadata tables, one for each data table; they describe the
                                table’s schema.
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           an OWL ontology that defines the classes of objects and
                                events in data tables, and provides axioms about them.
                        </item>
                    </xmt:uList>
                    <p>When a repository is loaded, all the data tables are linearized as CSV
                        (Comma-Separated Values) and passed to a Java servlet, together with the
                        ontology. The servlet invokes the Jena library to build one big RDF graph
                        out of the tables and the ontology. Individual EventMaps (e.g., the story of
                        a particular Arctic expedition, or the changing patterns of networks of
                        international cooperation) are produced by SPARQL queries from the
                        repository graph, and sent to the timemap library (Timemap 2012) that
                        controls the display of the map and the timeline.</p>
                </div></div>
            <div>
                <head>Creating a Repository</head>
                <p>To create a new repository one needs to </p>
                <xmt:uList>
                    <item>add to the ontology as needed;
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        populate data tables, using an HTML form with ontology-based
                            validation;
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        create map layers, as KML files;
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        create annotations, which are Web content.
                    </item>
                </xmt:uList>
                <p>Only the first of these tasks requires a practicing ontologist; the rest is done
                    by domain experts. The ontology and the data tables are aligned, in the sense
                    that if a class has a certain property then the data table has a column whose
                    header is the name of that property. In addition, if the class name has a
                    Wikipedia entry with an infobox, we use the same property names as the infobox,
                    gaining additional alignment with DBPedia. </p></div>
            <div>
                <head>Eventmap Authoring</head>
                <p>We can usefully distinguish two levels of authoring: working with events within
                    an existing EventMap, and creating a new EventMap. To add an event, one first
                    needs to create a KML file with a placemark or several Placemarks for the event,
                    and an HTML file with the event’s description. This is the creative part; the
                    rest is just filling out a form with time data and links to resources. To edit
                    an existing event the user works with the same tools, but requires a different
                    level of access to the repository. Creating a new EventMap involves creating a
                    metadata table for it, which may be too complex for some domain experts,
                    although most of them will probably be able to copy an existing metadata table
                    and modify it for their needs. </p>
                <p>To recapitulate, we are trying to provide a range of options for data entry
                    by domain experts. At one end are users who have access to ArcGIS, Adobe
                    Dreamweaver, and competent designers who transform their knowledge and data into
                    compelling maps and Web pages. At the opposite end are users who are content
                    with simple vector-graphics layers, and a simple arrangement of text and images,
                    to tell a story or to visualize a process. For this latter case, we provide a
                    Blogger-based interface that makes it possible to create an EventMap as a
                    sequence of blog entries. The only constraint is that each entry needs to
                    specify the start and end times of the event, and a link to the KML file that
                    describes the placemark(s).</p></div>
            <div>
                <head>Comparison to similar efforts</head>
                <p>As a story-telling and history-writing framework, EventMap resembles two other
                    efforts: (Visual Eyes 2012) (formerly History Browser)  and (Pleiades 2012).
                    Compared to Visual Eyes, EventMap requires less of a learning curve, and is more
                    cleanly based on standard technologies. Compared to Pleiades, EventMap is more
                    flexible because based on dates rather than a closed list of named ‘epochs.’ </p>
                <p>EventMaps should also be considered in the context of the larger Historical GIS
                    effort (Gregory &amp; Ell 2007). While EventMaps cannot match the scope of large
                    national databases of geospacial data, Google spreadsheets’ storage capacity and
                    computational power provide an adequate platform for many projects in which GIS
                    databases are used. EventMaps can use a database as well, but databases are
                    expensive to create, maintain, and make globally accessible, while Google
                    servers offer an unparalleled global network for free.</p></div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Acknowledgements</hi></p>
                <p>This work was supported by the National Science Foundation [7017695 to A.N.].</p></div>
            
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
             
                    <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">DuCharme, B.</hi> (2011). <hi rend="italic">Learning SPARQL</hi>.
                    Sebastopol, CA: O’Reilly.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Gregory, I., and P. S. Ell</hi> (2007). <hi rend="italic"
                        >Historical GIS: Technologies, Methodologies and Scholarship</hi>.
                    Cambridge: Cambridge UP.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">McEvedy, C.</hi> (2003). <hi rend="italic">The New Penguin Atlas
                        of Ancient History: Revised Edition. </hi>London: Penguin.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Nakhimovsky, A.</hi> (2010). Timelines, Google Maps, and
                    Visualization of History. Paper presented at the Biannual European Social
                    Science History Conference (ESSHC) Ghent, April 13-16.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Pleiades</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(2012). <ref
                    target="http://pleiades.stoa.org/" type="external">http://pleiades.stoa.org/</ref>. Accessed March
                    1, 2012.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Timemap</hi> (2012). http://code.google.com/p/timemap/ Accessed
                    February 28, 2012.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Visual Eyes</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>(2012). <ref
                        target="http://www.viseyes.org/" type="external">http://www.viseyes.org/</ref>. Accessed March 1,
                    2012.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>