<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-280">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Modeling Medieval Handwriting: A New Approach to Digital Palaeography</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Stokes, Peter</name>
                    <affiliation>King’s College, London, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>peter.stokes@kcl.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
      
                <p>As many hundreds of thousands of medieval manuscripts are now being digitised,
                    with many millions of pages becoming available, the question of how to find
                    specialised content in this material is becoming increasingly urgent. In this
                    paper I present a new conceptual model for the description and therefore
                    retrieval of features of handwriting in Western medieval script. Digital
                    Humanities requires first a theoretical model which outlines all of the features
                    of a given domain and the relationships between them (McCarty 2004), and this is
                    the focus of the present paper. However, the implications of this work are very
                    much wider: just as the TEI has lead to ‘a new data description language that
                    substantially improves our ability to describe textual features’ (Renear 2004:
                    235), so the formal model of handwriting presented here sharpens and could even
                    resolve long-standing problems in palaeographers’ own terminology and
                    practice.<note>For initials expression of the ideas in this paper see the DigiPal blog (Stokes 2011).</note></p>
                
                
                <div>
                    <head>The Problem</head>
                    <p>Common research questions in palaeography include finding examples of a
                        particular way of writing a given letter, or scribes who constructed letters
                        in particular ways. For example, it has been asserted that a specific form
                        of <hi rend="bold">t</hi> was used only by English scribes in the ninth
                        century (Dumville 1984: 249-250), and that ‘Square’ features in
                        Anglo-Caroline minuscule of the late tenth century is distinctive of
                        Canterbury (Bishop 1972: xxii). These assertions have generally been made
                        with little supporting evidence, in part because the corpus of surviving
                        manuscripts is too large to support systematic analysis, but one should now
                        be able to overcome this by producing an online resource for searching and
                        viewing scribal practices and examples of script. This is an objective of
                        the DigiPal project,<note><ref target="http://digipal.eu" type="external">http://digipal.eu/.</ref></note> which will provide an online
                        catalogue of about 1,200 samples of English handwriting from the eleventh
                        century, along with annotated digital images of about half of these.
                        However, this objective is made very difficult by several factors. Image
                        retrieval is very well studied, with approaches ranging from Content Based
                        Image Retrieval (CBIR) such as that used by Google Images, to tagging with
                        complex taxonomies like IconClass, as well as intermediate combinations of
                        the two such as that provided by font identification software.<note><ref target="http://www.iconclass.nl" type="external">http://www.iconclass.nl</ref>; <ref target="http://www.identifont.com/" type="external">http://www.identifont.com/</ref>; <ref target="http://new.myfonts.com/WhatTheFont" type="external">http://new.myfonts.com/WhatTheFont</ref></note> However, CBIR cannot easily be tuned to scholars’
                        criteria if these do not match the machine’s perception of ‘content’.
                        Similarly, systems like IconClass are very large, very intimidating, and
                        require specialised training to use effectively. IconClass also depends on a
                        shared vocabulary and this is famously absent from palaeography: the <hi
                            rend="italic">Comité international de paléographie latine</hi> was
                        established in 1953 partly for this purpose but it has not produced even a
                        draft document some fifty-eight years later.<note><ref target="http://www.palaeographia.org/cipl/ciplGen.htm" type="external">http://www.palaeographia.org/cipl/ciplGen.htm</ref>. See further Derolez 2003: 6-9, and Stokes 2010: 1229-1230.</note> This
                        can partly be overcome by thesauri which map equivalent terms from different
                        practices, but an even more fundamental lack is that of a rigorous
                        conceptual model for handwriting itself. The textual community has been
                        debating ‘what text is’ for some time, partly because of the TEI (Pierazzo
                        &amp; Stokes 2011: 399-401), but no discussion like this has yet arisen in
                        palaeography (though see Stokes 2010: 1228-1230). With neither a clear model
                        nor a common vocabulary, it is hardly surprising that the few attempts at
                        digital catalogues to date have been unsuccessful.<note>See the Palaeographic Catalogue at <ref target="http://www.arts.manchester.ac.uk/mancass/C11database/letter_catalogue.php" type="external">http://www.arts.manchester.ac.uk/mancass/C11database/letter_catalogue.php</ref>, and that by Stokes (2007/8: §§24-26). The shortcomings of both are discussed by Stokes (forthcoming).</note></p>
                </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>The Model</head>
                <p>To illustrate the difficulties, consider the following list of possible
                    research questions:<note>These emerged from a workshop for the DigiPal project at King’s College London, 6 September 2011.</note></p>
                <xmt:uList>
                        <item>
                            Show me a list of all manuscripts containing the ‘Insular’
                                form of a (Fig. 1a).
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            Show me images of all occurrences of the ‘Caroline’ form of s
                                written by scribes who otherwise wrote Insular minuscule (Fig.
                                1b).
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            Tell me which scribe(s) habitually wrote the ‘rounded’ form of
                                a in combination with a hooked top-stroke of t (Fig. 1c).
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            Give me images of all letters with forked ascenders (Fig.
                                1d).
                        </item>
                  
                    
                </xmt:uList>
                
                    <table>
                        <head>Figure 1: Examples of Medieval Handwriting</head>
                        <row>
                            <cell><figure><graphic url="img280-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Fig. 1a: ‘fela’</head></figure>
                                </cell>
                            <cell><figure><graphic url="img280-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Fig. 1b: ‘kynges</head></figure>
                                </cell>
                            <cell><figure><graphic url="img280-3.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Fig. 1c: ‘wat’</head></figure>
                                </cell>
                            <cell><figure><graphic url="img280-4.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Fig. 1d: ‘hit’</head></figure>
                                </cell>
                        </row>
                        
                    </table>
                    
                    <p>Although these questions may look similar, they have a range of important
                        differences which are largely concealed by the ambiguous word ‘letter’. The
                        challenge is therefore how to model handwriting in sufficient detail to
                        represent these nuances, considering not only a scribe’s general practice
                        but also its specific instances. It requires first a clear distinction
                        between <hi rend="italic">script</hi> (‘the model which the scribe has in
                        mind’s eye when he writes’), and <hi rend="italic">(scribal) hand</hi>
                        (‘what he actually puts down on the page’: Parkes 1969: xxvi). The word
                        ‘letter’ is also ambiguous, and so further terms are useful here. Starting
                        with the most concrete, a <hi rend="italic">graph</hi> is an instance of the
                        letter as written on the page. In contrast, an <hi rend="italic"
                            >idiograph</hi> is ‘the way (or one of the ways) in which a given writer
                        habitually writes’ a given letter, and an <hi rend="italic">allograph</hi>
                        is a recognised way of writing the given letter, as shared by a group rather
                        than being distinctive of any given individual (Davis 2007: 254-255; cf.
                        also Emiliano 2011).<note>Idiograph should not be confused with ideograph, a ‘symbol that primarily denotes an idea or concept’ (Unicode 2011).</note> A <hi rend="italic"
                            >grapheme</hi> is a letter-entity as an idealized, abstract, discrete,
                        unit of a writing system. Also useful is Unicode’s <hi rend="italic"
                            >character</hi> to refer to the intermediate level between grapheme
                        (which by definition has no physical form) and allograph. Thus the grapheme
                        &lt;a&gt; has (at least) two characters, ‘capital’ <hi rend="bold">A</hi>
                        and ‘small’ <hi rend="bold">a</hi>. The second of these has many allographs,
                        one of which is Insular <hi rend="bold">a</hi>, this is normally found in
                        the script known as Insular cursive minuscule; in Figure 1a and 1c we have
                        two distinct allographs of <hi rend="bold">a</hi>; and so on. Grapheme and
                        character are both ‘emic’, whereas allograph, idiograph and graph are all
                        ‘etic’.</p>
                    <p>Two further terms are required to describe specific details of letters. <hi
                            rend="italic">Component </hi>refers to the basic parts which make up
                        characters, such as ascenders, descenders, serifs and so on; components may
                        themselves have further components. <hi rend="italic">Features</hi> are
                        descriptive labels which may apply to one or more components: thus a
                        descender may be straight or curved, long or short, and so on. Finally, we
                        also need general stylistic features which may not refer to any specific
                        component, such as the thickness and angle of the pen.</p>
                    <p>From these terms, a formal model has been developed which captures these
                        entities and the relationships between them; this is represented in a
                        simplified UML diagram in Figure 2 below.</p>
                <p>According to this model, a grapheme has one or more characters, each character
                    can be represented by an arbitrary number of allographs which in turn are
                    represented by any number of idiographs and those in turn by graphs; a scribal
                    hand comprises a set of graphs, scribal practice a set of idiographs, and so on.
                    Each character, allograph, idiograph and graph can be made up of components,
                    every component has at least one feature, and so on. </p>
                <p><figure><graphic url="img280-5.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 2: A Simplified UML Diagram showing the conceptual model of medieval handwriting</head></figure></p></div>
            
            <div>
                <head>Significance and Usage</head>
                    <p>This model allows us to phrase palaeographical research questions much more
                        precisely. It also allows structured descriptions of both habitual and
                        specific writing-practices, thereby allowing complex queries. For example,
                        we can specify:</p>
                <xmt:oList rend="arabic">
                   
                        <item> A set of possible <hi rend="bold">characters</hi> and the <hi
                            rend="bold">components</hi> that each character must have. </item>
                        <item> A <hi rend="bold">script</hi>, namely a set of allographs which are
                        normally written together, including their <hi rend="bold">components</hi>
                        and <hi rend="bold">features</hi>. </item>
                        <item> A <hi rend="bold">scribal hand</hi>, namely the set of idiographs
                        which a scribe normally uses. </item>
                        <item> A set of <hi rend="bold">graphs</hi>, for example those in an image
                        of a particular manuscript page. </item>
                </xmt:oList>
                
                    <p>This model is also significant for capturing not only forms of letters but
                        also specific stylistic features which apply across letters: not only
                        particular forms of <hi rend="bold">b</hi>, for example, but also the type
                        of wedges on ascenders of any letter, or indeed wedges on ascenders of all
                        letters <hi rend="italic">except</hi><hi rend="bold">b</hi>.</p>
                    <p>An important further advantage is that if one level is fully defined then
                        many details of the levels below that can be inferred automatically and so
                        only exceptions need be recorded. For example:</p>
                
                <xmt:oList>
                        <item> The character <hi rend="bold">b</hi> has an ascender and a bowl. </item>
                        <item>
                            Insular minuscule script normally features wedges on
                                ascenders.
                        </item>
                        <item> It follows from (1) and (2) that allographs of <hi rend="bold">b</hi>
                        in Insular minuscule will normally have wedges on ascenders. </item>
                       
                </xmt:oList>
                
                    <p>This allows rapid data capture despite the highly detailed model – a crucial
                        point in a context where many thousands of graphs and idiographs will need
                        to be described in order to be worthwhile. One limitation of the model is
                        that it allows one simply to record the presence of a feature, rather than
                        (for example) numerical values to indicate ‘fuzzy’ cases where a feature is
                        only partially present. The model could easily be adapted to accommodate
                        this, but the increased time in data-entry would be prohibitive. Instead, in
                        the implementation used for DigiPal, many features have n-ary distinctions
                        instead: for example, ascenders can be wedged or clubbed or barbed or
                        deeply-split or without decoration, and so on (see further Stokes 2011, Part
                        v).</p>
                    <p>This paper will present the model and also demonstrate its use in practice
                        through an annotation tool and search interface which are being developed
                        for the DigiPal project. Reference will also be made to alternative uses
                        which are being planned in the near future, including (we hope) application
                        to Hebrew and Cuneiform script. The paper will also reflect on the process
                        as an example of Digital Humanities bringing rigour to an existing
                        discipline. McCarty has argued that modeling and the computer’s ‘demand for
                        complete consistency’ leads directly ‘to the epistemological question <hi
                            rend="italic">of how we know what we know</hi>’ (2004). However, this
                        question is itself fundamental to palaeography, where one of the biggest
                        challenges has been to make explicit the apparently subjective judgments of
                        experts. As Derolez wrote of these, ‘their great deficiency … lies in the
                        difficulty of putting them into words’, and, more generally, he asked
                        ‘whether morphological features [i.e. the shapes of letters] can be
                        described in an unambiguous way’ (2003: 7). If a model such as this can
                        achieve what fifty-eight years of the <hi rend="italic">Comité</hi> could
                        not then that would surely be a significant achievement in a field which has
                        often viewed quantitative approaches and the Digital Humanities with
                        significant mistrust (Derolez 2003: 7-9; Stokes 2009).</p>
                   
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <head>References</head>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Bishop, T. A. M.</hi> (1971). <hi rend="italic">English
                            Caroline Minuscule</hi>. Oxford: Clarendon Press.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Davis, T.</hi> (2007). The Practice of Handwriting
                        Identification. <hi rend="italic">The Library</hi>, 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> series, 8:
                        251-276.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Derolez, A.</hi> (2003). <hi rend="italic">The Palaeography
                            of Gothic Manuscript Books</hi>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dumville, D. N.</hi> (1983). Motes and Beams. <hi
                            rend="italic">Peritia</hi> 2: 248-256.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Emiliano, E.</hi> (forthcoming 2011). Issues in the
                        Typographic Representation of Medieval Primary Sources. In Y. Kawaguchi and
                        M. Minegishi (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Corpus Analysis and Diachronic
                            Linguistics</hi>. Amsterdam: John Benjamins.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">McCarty, W.</hi> (2004). Modeling: A Study in Words and
                    Meanings. In S. Schreibman, R. Siemens and J. Unsworth, <hi rend="italic">A
                        Companion to Digital Humanities</hi>. Oxford: Blackwell. 254-270.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Parkes, M. B.</hi> (1969). <hi rend="italic">English Cursive
                            Bookhands 1250-1500</hi>. Oxford: Oxford UP.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Pierazzo, E., and P. A. Stokes</hi> (2010). Putting the Text
                        Back into Context. In F. Fischer et al. (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Kodikologie und Paläographie im Digitalen Zeitalter</hi>. Norderstedt:
                        Books on Demand, vol. 2, pp. 397-430 <ref target="http://kups.ub.uni-koeln.de/4360/" type="external">http://kups.ub.uni-koeln.de/4360/</ref>.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Renear, A.</hi> (2004). Text Encoding. In S. Schreibman, R.
                        Siemens and J. Unsworth, <hi rend="italic">A Compa</hi><hi rend="italic"
                            >nion to Digital Humanities</hi>. Oxford: Blackwell, pp. 218-239.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Stokes, P. A.</hi> (2007/08). Palaeography and Image
                        Processing. <hi rend="italic">Digital Medievalist</hi> 3 <ref target="http://www.digitalmedievalist.org/journal/3/stokes/" type="external">http://www.digitalmedievalist.org/journal/3/stokes/</ref>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Stokes, P. A.</hi> (2009). Computer-Aided Palaeography:
                        Present and Future. In M. Rehbein et al. (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Kodikologie und Paläographie im Digitalen Zeitalter</hi>. Norderstedt:
                        Books on Demand, pp. 309-338 <ref target="http://kups.ub.uni-koeln.de/volltexte/2009/2978/pdf/KPDZ_I_Stokes.pdf" type="external">
                            http://kups.ub.uni-koeln.de/volltexte/2009/2978/pdf/KPDZ_I_Stokes.pdf</ref>.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Stokes, P. A.</hi> (2010). Scripts. In A. Classen (ed.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Handbook of Medieval Studies</hi>. Berlin: de Gruyter,
                        vol. 3, pp. 1217-1233.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Stokes, P. A.</hi> (2011). Describing Handwriting (Parts i–).
                        London: King’s College <ref target="http://digipal.eu/blogs/blog/describing-handwriting-part-i/" type="external">
                            http://digipal.eu/blogs/blog/describing-handwriting-part-i/</ref>.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Stokes, P. A.</hi> (forthcoming). Palaeography and the
                        “Virtual library”. In B. Nelson and M. Terras (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                            >Digitizing Medieval and Early Modern Material Culture</hi>. Arizona:
                        Center for Medieval and Renaissance Studies.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Unicode Consortium</hi> (2011). <hi rend="italic">Glossary of
                            Unicode Terms</hi><ref target="http://unicode.org/glossary/" type="external">
                                http://unicode.org/glossary/</ref>.</p>
           
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>