<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-215">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Underspecified, Ambiguous or Formal. Problems in Creating Maps Based on Texts</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Eide, Øyvind</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Oslo, Unit for Digital Documentation, Norway</affiliation>
                    <email>oyvind.eide@edd.uio.no</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>How can a reading of a textual description of a landscape be expressed as a map?
                    Maps form a medium different from verbal texts, and the differences have
                    consequences not only for <hi rend="italic">how</hi> things are said, but also
                    for <hi rend="italic">what</hi> can be said at all using maps. Where are these
                    limitations to be found? </p>
                <p>In this abstract, I will discuss the relationship between verbal and map based
                    geographical communication. I have created a model of the geographical
                    information read from a source text, then tried to express the contents of the
                    model as maps. I will show that types of geographical information exist that can
                    be stored in and read from verbal texts, but which are impossible to express as
                    geographical maps without significant loss of meaning.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> Object of study </head>
                <p>I used a set of Scandinavian border protocols from the eighteenth century
                    (Schnitler 1962) as source material for this research. The text is based on
                    interrogations about geography with more than 100 different persons, of whom
                    many presumably did not use maps very much if at all. It was created in a
                    society, or a set of societies, on the brink of the transformation from oral to
                    written cultures, where some were firmly placed within the written culture,
                    while others had only been exposed to the activity of reading texts for a few
                    decades. The voices in the text represent persons coming from different ethnic
                    and professional backgrounds, e.g., Sami reindeer herders, Norwegian farmers,
                    and Danish military officers, thus bringing a set of different perspectives into
                    the geographical conversation.</p></div>
                <div>
                    <head> Method </head>
                <p>Modelling is to create and manipulate models in order to learn from the
                    experiences we gain through the process. Models are in this context
                    representations of something which is created for the purpose of studying what
                    is modelled more closely (McCarty 2005: 24). In the work reported on here, a
                    computer based model was constructed based on the source text. Through
                    experiments on this model, new knowledge about the text was gained. The creation
                    of the model itself also led to problems giving new insights, so it was part of
                    the series of experiments. The same can be said of the development and tailoring
                    of the software used.</p>
                <p>The whole experiment was performed in a qualitative manner. Occurrences in the
                    text were not counted and compared, they were rather evaluated as individual
                    cases, in accordance with traditional humanities research where seeking local
                    knowledge about specific cases is the main activity (Galey 2010: 95-100).</p>
                <p>The point of a modelling exercise lies in the process, not in the model as a
                    product. Modelling mediates epistemologically between modeller and the modelled,
                    that is, between the researcher and the data. The model was built through a
                    combination between computer based tools and a thorough close reading in which
                    all geographic information I was able to extract from the text was included. The
                    model was stored as a set of connected facts in a computer application I
                    developed in Java for this research.</p>
                <p>In the application the results of the close readings are stored as triplets in a
                    fact database. Then the ‘raw’ triplets go through several steps of
                    interpretation, leading to more and more formal structures. These steps
                    eventually result in the standard format RDF<note>Resource Description Framework:
                        <ref target="http://www.w3.org/RDF/" type="external">http://www.w3.org/RDF/</ref> (checked 2011-10-31)</note>, then
                    further interpretation leads to geographical vector data in a simplified version
                    of the GML format<note>Geography Markup Language:
                        <ref target="http://www.opengeospatial.org/standards/gml/" type="external">http://www.opengeospatial.org/standards/gml/</ref> (checked 2011-10-31)</note> which can be imported to GIS
                    software to be viewed as maps. </p>
                <p>The modelling process thus involves several steps, each formalising the data in a
                    stricter sense. For each step, what ‘falls off,’ what is difficult to avoid
                    loosing, is the interesting part. This ‘falling off’ will include things that
                    cannot survive a transfer from one system to another, which misses the added
                    level of formality. Through this process I attempted to translate geographical
                    information from one medium to the other. The ‘fall-offs’ show us what was lost
                    in the process; this was not always because of differences between the media,
                    but candidates for further examination were found in the ‘fall-offs’. Examples
                    from this modelling work will be shown in the paper, including some situations
                    where ‘fall-off’ occurs.</p>
                <p>As the goal is to understand how texts express geographical information, I made
                    an effort to base the maps on what I read from the text only. While it is
                    impossible to exclude all context information, I tried hard to exclude any local
                    context based on geographical knowledge of the area. This makes the process
                    different from mapping place name information in literary texts, as done by e.g.
                    Smith and Crane (2001). The latter process includes adding a significant amount
                    of contextual knowledge to the process through what is learned from the
                    pre-existing map. </p></div>
                    <div><head>Main results</head>
                <p>The issues faced in the modelling experiments led to the development of the
                    following typology of textual expressions:</p>
                <p>1.  <hi rend="bold">Under-specified texts.</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Based on such a text, more than one map can be drawn, and at
                        least two of these maps are significantly different.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>This situation occurs when the geographical information in a text can be
                    expressed as more than one significantly different map. This happens when
                    directions such as ‘east’ or measurements such as ‘1-2 miles’ are used: given
                    lack of other evidence in the text, a number of different geometrical
                    interpretations of the statements are possible.</p>
                <p>2.  <hi rend="bold">Fully specified textual descriptions.</hi><hi rend="italic">
                        Only one map can be drawn based on the description. If the text mentions
                        something, it is fully specified geometrically.</hi></p>
                <p>Texts in formal languages, such as GML, are typical cases. I have not found
                    examples of this type in natural language texts. </p>
                <p>3.  <hi rend="bold">Ambiguity and negation.</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">The text includes expressions in the forms ‘A or B is located
                        at C’ (ambiguity) or ‘There are no A’s in B’ (negation).</hi></p>
                <p>The spatial information read from the text cannot be represented as one single
                    map; one will need two or more maps, a dynamic map or a map with its geometry
                    corrected by a textual description.</p>
                <p>The choice of the words ‘significantly different’ as opposed to merely
                    ‘different’ in the description of type 1 is necessary and highlights how the
                    border to type 2 is fuzzy. Two maps can always be made which are slightly
                    different, but which will occur as similar to the reader. Small adjustments in
                    location are routinely made in cartographical work in order to improve the
                    readability of maps. The choice of symbols can also change without its leading
                    to significantly different maps. Any text, also of type 2, could be represented
                    by two slightly different maps.</p>
                <p>In the case of Schnitler, type 1 situations are abundant, we see a handful of
                    type 3, and none of type 2. The groups are partly exclusive: 1 and 3 can exist
                    in the same textual description, but is hard to see how a textual description
                    can be both 2 and 1 or both 2 and 3.</p></div>
            <div><head> Discussion </head>
                <p>The discussion of the relationship between geographical maps and verbal texts
                    fall into the long tradition of inter-art and intermedia studies. Two important
                    oppositions established by Lessing (1893) can be summarised this way:</p>
                <p>1.  Actions in time should be applied in poetry, and bodies in space in painting. </p>
                <p>2.  What is hidden is not seen in painting, while things hidden can still be seen
                    in poetry. </p>
                <p>Whereas Lessing’s dichotomy between poetry and painting has been questioned,
                    e.g., by Frank (1963) and Mitchell (1980) in connection to their discussions of
                    spatial form in literature, it has never been eliminated. A recent way of
                    formalising such distinctions is the model of Elleström (2010). Instead of
                    starting from a set of different media or art forms, he takes a bottom-up
                    approach, starting from a set of media modalities. His set includes four,
                    namely, the material, sensorial, spatiotemporal and semiotic modalities. The
                    differences between texts and maps fall mainly in the latter two categories.</p>
                <p>The two problem areas found in the modelling of Schnitler, <hi rend="italic"
                        >under-specified texts</hi> and <hi rend="italic">ambiguity and
                        negation</hi>, are both connected to Lessing’s thinking. When ‘east’ in a
                    text can mean a number of different things, potentially covering half of the
                    possible directions from a place, the direction between two features on a map is
                    measurable, with only a limited inaccuracy. Space is expressed differently in
                    the two media. And when disjunction is hard to put on a map, it is also
                    connected to the fact that the sign systems used to refer to the external
                    reality are different. This will be discussed in light of Lessing’s opposition
                    and Elleström’s system in the paper. Some comments will also be made as to how
                    this links to narratology.</p></div>
             
                
            
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Elleström, L</hi>. (2010). The Modalities of Media: A Model for
                    Understanding Intermedial Relations. In L. Elleström (ed.), <hi rend="italic"
                        >Media borders, multimodality and intermediality</hi>. Basingstoke: Palgrave
                    McMillan, pp. 11-48.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Frank, J.</hi> (1963). Spatial Form in Modern Literature. In <hi
                        rend="italic">The widening gyre: crisis and mastery in modern
                        literature</hi>. (First published: 1945). New Brunswick, N.J.: Rutgers UP,
                    pp. 3-62</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Galey, A.</hi> (2010). The Human Presence in Digital Artefacts.
                    In W. McCarty (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Text and Genre in Reconstruction: Effects
                        of Digitalization on Ideas, Behaviours, Products and Institutions</hi>. Open
                    Book Publishers, pp. 93-117.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Lessing, G. E.</hi> (1893). Laokoon: oder über die Grenzen der
                    Mahlerey und Poesie. Erster Theil. In K. Lachmann and F. Muncker (eds.), <hi
                        rend="italic">Gotthold Ephraim Lessings sämtliche Schriften. Neunter
                        Band</hi> (3., aufs neue durchges. und verm. Aufl.). Stuttgart: Göschen.
                    Photographic reprint. Berlin : de Gruyter 1968, pp. 1-177. First published:
                    1766. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">McCarty, W.</hi> (2005). <hi rend="italic">Humanities
                        computing</hi>. Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Mitchell, W. J. T.</hi> (1980). Spatial Form in Literature:
                    Toward a General Theory. <hi rend="italic">Critical Inquiry</hi> 6 (3):
                    539-567.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Schnitler, P.</hi> (1962). <hi rend="italic">Major Peter
                        Schnitlers grenseeksaminasjonsprotokoller 1742 - 1745</hi>, Volume 1. Oslo:
                    Norsk historisk kjeldeskrift-institutt.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Smith, D. A., and G. Crane</hi> (2001). Disambiguating Geographic
                    Names in a Historical Digital Library. In <hi rend="italic">Research and
                        Advanced Technology for Digital Libraries: 5th European conference, ECDL
                        2001</hi>. Darmstadt: Springer, pp. 127-136.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>