<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-241">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Information Discovery in the Chinese Recorder Index</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Hsiang, Jieh</name>
                    <affiliation>National Taiwan University, Taiwan</affiliation>
                    <email>jhsiang@ntu.edu.tw</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Kong, Jung-Wei</name>
                    <affiliation>National Taiwan University, Taiwan</affiliation>
                    <email>dino.kong@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Sung, Allan</name>
                    <affiliation>National Taiwan University, Taiwan</affiliation>
                    <email>allan.sung@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
         <div>
                <head>The Chinese Recorder</head>
                <p>Chinese Recorder (CR) is a (first bi-monthly, then monthly) journal published by
                    the Protestant missionaries in China between 1867, a few years after the 1860
                    treaty that allowed missionaries to enter China, and 1941, when the U.S. became
                    engaged in the Pacific theater of the Second World War. Except for the
                    nineteen-month interruption from June 1872 to the end of 1873, CR was the
                    longest running English missionary journal in China. The period that CR covered
                    was a tumultuous time in Chinese history, when the country went through the
                    Taiping Rebellion, the Boxer Rebellion, the various wars with the foreign
                    powers, the Republic Revolution of 1911, the civil wars among the war lords, the
                    rise of communism, the invasion of Japan, and the great cultural and social
                    transformation during the late 19th and early 20th century. Being based within
                    China, CR provided a close look at all spectrum of the Chinese society, not only
                    missionary affairs, but also issues such as Chinese civilization, healthcare,
                    education, political situation, opium, and other social issues of the day. CR is
                    unique in that the articles were written by missionaries in China for the
                    benefit of their fellow missionaries. Being supported by missions and not
                    sponsored by any government, Chinese or foreign, the views presented in CR were
                    more candid and not blurred by political agenda. It, thus, provides an angle
                    unlike any others. Although one cannot say that CR is not biased, at least it is
                    biased in its own special way.</p>
         </div>
         
         <div>
              <head>The Chinese Recorder Index</head>
              <p>With its 73 volumes, one for each year, and over 50,000 pages in total, CR is
                    difficult to use on its own. In 1986 Kathleen Lodwick published the 2-volume <hi
                        rend="italic">The Chinese Recorder Index: a Guide to Christian Missions in
                        Asia, 1867–1941</hi> (CRI), which made it much easier for scholars to
                    utilize CR in their research (Lodwick 1986).</p>
             <p>CRI is more than an index.
                    It consists of 3 indices and 6 special lists (of Persons by Affiliation, Persons
                    by Location, List of Women, etc). The <hi rend="italic">Person Index</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">PI</hi>) includes 8,391 names with 192,149 page records; the
                        <hi rend="italic">Mission/Organization Index</hi> (<hi rend="italic"
                    >MI</hi>) 712 mission entries with 34,851 page records; and the <hi
                        rend="italic">Subject Index</hi> 4,691 entries with 83,636 page records.
                    Altogether, there are 13,794 entries and 310,626 page records, averaging 22.5
                    page records per entry.</p>
             <p>Unlike a conventional book index that only
                    provides the pages in which an entry appears, CRI assigns tags to PI and MI,
                    thus provides additional information about the nature of the occurrence of the
                    entry on that page. Tables 1 and 2 give the names, nature, and numbers about the
                    tags that we have tabulated.</p>
             
             
             
                     
             <p>There is a great wealth of information
                    hidden in the tags. For example, if a certain page appears in a person name
                    entry A, and if that page also appears in another person name entry B under an
                    ART (article) tag, then we know that A appears in an article written by B. Using
                    the same page number to check all entries, and we can find all person names,
                    locations, missions, subjects, etc that appear in the same article. If the same
                    page appears in a Subject Index entry indicating a certain event, then we may
                    even ‘guess’ what the article is about without reading the article itself.</p>
                <p>As another example, the ATT (attacks) tag tells how many attacks of missions and
                    missionaries had been reported in CR, who were attacked, in what years did they
                    occur and where. This information should be valuable to someone studying the
                    attitude of the Chinese society towards Christianity when it was re-introduced
                    to China in the late 19th century. However, since ‘attack’ is not an entry by
                    itself, this information is scattered all over CRI. One has to pore through the
                    13,000 entries to collect every relevant bit of information.</p>
                 
             <table>
                 <head>Table 1: Person Index</head>
                 <row>
                     <cell>
                         <hi rend="bold">Tag name of Person Index</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                         <hi rend="bold">Tag value</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                         <hi rend="bold">number/no value</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                         <hi rend="bold">explanation</hi>
                     </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell>AFF (Affiliation)</cell>
                     <cell>Name of mission</cell>
                     <cell>27,678 / 14</cell>
                     <cell>Affiliation</cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell>ARR (Arrival)</cell>
                     <cell>Year </cell>
                     <cell>8,705 / 6,283</cell>
                     <cell>Arrival year (if no value, then it’s indicated by volume number)
                     </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell>ART (Articles)</cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell>11,125 </cell>
                     <cell>Article written by person</cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell>ATT (Attacks)</cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell>1,164</cell>
                     <cell>Attack on the person</cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell>CHI (Children)</cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell>7,765</cell>
                     <cell>Children of the person</cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell>CON (Conferences)</cell>
                     <cell>Location, year</cell>
                     <cell>3,449 / 1,793</cell>
                     <cell>Conference attended</cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell>COR (Correspondence)</cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell>2,276</cell>
                     <cell>Correspondence to the editor</cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell>DAT (Dates in China)</cell>
                     <cell>Year</cell>
                     <cell>139 / 2</cell>
                     <cell>Dates in China</cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell>DEA (Death)</cell>
                     <cell>Precise year</cell>
                     <cell>2,459 / 2,035</cell>
                     <cell>Death (if no value, then it’s indicated by volume number)</cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> DEP (Departures) </cell>
                     <cell> Year of departure </cell>
                     <cell> 5,496 / 5,000 </cell>
                     <cell> Departure in the year(if no value, then it’s indicated by volume
                         number) </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> ITI (Itinerancy) </cell>
                     <cell> Location </cell>
                     <cell> 445 / 413 </cell>
                     <cell> Itinerancy </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> LOC (Location) </cell>
                     <cell> Location </cell>
                     <cell> 39,744 / 8 </cell>
                     <cell> Location </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> OTH (Other Publications) </cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell> 10,095 </cell>
                     <cell> Other publications </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> POS (Positions) </cell>
                     <cell> Title and mission </cell>
                     <cell> 6658 / 2 </cell>
                     <cell> Position of the person </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> SPO (Spouse) </cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell> 13,212 </cell>
                     <cell> Spouse of the person </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> UNS (Unspecified) </cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell> 51,739 </cell>
                     <cell> Unspecified </cell>
                 </row>
             </table>
             
             
             
             <table>
                 <head>Table 2: Mission/Organization Index</head>
                 <row>
                     <cell>
                         <hi rend="bold">Tag name</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                         <hi rend="bold">Tag value</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                         <hi rend="bold">Number/no value</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                         <hi rend="bold">explanation</hi>
                     </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> ATT (Attacks) </cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell> 275 </cell>
                     <cell> Attacks on the M/O </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> CON (Convert) </cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell> 996 </cell>
                     <cell> Converts </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> FIN (Finances) </cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell> 1,585 </cell>
                     <cell> Finances of the M/O </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> HIS (History) </cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell> 650 </cell>
                     <cell> History of the M/O </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> HOS (Hospitals) </cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell> 639 </cell>
                     <cell> Hospital </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> MEE (Meetings) </cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell> 2,340 </cell>
                     <cell> Meeting </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> LOC (Location) </cell>
                     <cell> Location </cell>
                     <cell> 9,533 / 32 </cell>
                     <cell> Location </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> OPR (Opium Refuges) </cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell> 0 </cell>
                     <cell> Opium refuge </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> ORD (Ordained Asians) </cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell> 349 </cell>
                     <cell> Asians ordained by mission </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> ORP (Orphanages) </cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell> 32 </cell>
                     <cell> Orphanages </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> PER (Personnel) </cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell> 1,520 </cell>
                     <cell> Personnel </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> PRE (Press) </cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell> 1,554 </cell>
                     <cell> Press </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> REP (Reports) </cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell> 772 </cell>
                     <cell> Reports by the M/O </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> SCH (Schools) </cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell> 1,309 </cell>
                     <cell> School run by the M/O </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> STA (Statistics) </cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell> 2,510 </cell>
                     <cell> Statistics about the M/O </cell>
                 </row>
                 <row>
                     <cell> UNS (Unspecified) </cell>
                     <cell>   </cell>
                     <cell> 10,763 </cell>
                     <cell> Unspecified </cell>
                 </row>
             </table>
</div>
            <div>
                 <head>Reindexing the CRI</head>
                  <p>To fully utilize the wealth of information embedded in CRI, we developed a system
                    that incorporates the 3 indices of CRI into one uniform framework, under which
                    the indices are fully integrated and cross referenced. This integration enables
                    the user to explore the rich information hidden within CRI.</p>
                     <p>Our
                    approach starts with a data structure that decomposes an index entry into a
                    number of <hi rend="italic">page records</hi>, each consists of the entry name
                        (<hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">n</hi></hi>), a volume number (<hi
                        rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">vol</hi></hi>) and page numbers (the start
                    page and the end page, <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">s</hi></hi> and <hi
                        rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">e</hi></hi>), a tag (<hi rend="bold"><hi
                            rend="italic">t</hi></hi>) and a tag value (<hi rend="bold"><hi
                            rend="italic">v</hi></hi>). (The tag part may not be present if it is
                    not indicated.) Thus, a page record is a tuple (<hi rend="bold"><hi
                            rend="italic">n</hi></hi>; <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic"
                        >vol</hi></hi>:<hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">s</hi></hi>-<hi rend="bold"
                            ><hi rend="italic">e</hi></hi>; <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic"
                        >t</hi></hi>:<hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">v</hi></hi>). If there is
                    only one page indicated, then the start page and the end page will be the same.
                    For instance, the first page record in the George Leslie Mackay entry (Figure 1)
                    is (Mackay, George Leslie; 13:74-74; AFF: CPM) and the second page record is
                    (Mackay, George Leslie; 13:312-312; AFF: CPM). (The George Leslie Mackay entry
                    as shown in this example becomes 46 page records.) This process will decompose
                    the 13,794 entries in the three indices into 310,626 page records. We then
                    designed algorithms to mine the relationships among the page records, mainly
                    using the page numbers and the tags as reference points (Kung 2011). While the
                    detail of the algorithms cannot be covered in this abstract, we will use two
                    simple examples to demonstrate the outcome.</p>
                     
                     <p><figure><graphic url="img241-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 1: The ‘George Mackay’ entry in Person Index</head></figure></p>
                   </div>
            
            <div>
                     <p>One of the page records in the Person
                    Index entry of George Mackay is (Mackay, George Leslie; 16:214-214; LOC: Fukien,
                    Amoy). Since in the entry of Thomas Barclay, there is a page record (Barclay,
                    Thomas; 16:214-215; ART), we know that Mackay was mentioned in an article
                    written by Barclay. Other page records show that the same page appeared in the
                    Subject Index of Sino-French War (1884–1885), the Person Index of James Maxwell,
                    William Thow, etc. (Figure 2), plus others. Thus, when issuing George Mackay as
                    a query, instead of simply returning Vol. 16, p. 214 as one of the pages in
                    which Mackay appears, all information in CRI about that page will be organized
                    and returned (Figure 3). (Indeed, it was an article written by Barclay about the
                    returning of the missionaries from Amoy to Taiwan after the lifting of the
                    blockade of Taiwan at the end of the Sino-French War.) Figure 4 shows the
                    webpage resulting from the query ‘George Mackay’. Note that a chronological
                    distribution is presented and a foldable/expandable classification of the return
                    is on the left.</p>
                <p><figure><graphic url="img241-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 2: Some entries containing Vol. 16, p. 214</head></figure></p>
                <p><figure><graphic url="img241-3.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 3: Information returned about Vol 16, p214 when given query ‘George Mackay’</head></figure></p>
                <p><figure><graphic url="img241-4.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 4: Query result of ‘George Mackay’</head></figure></p>
            </div>
            
             <div>
                 
             <p>Figure 5 shows the return of
                    the query ‘attack’, for which a total of 574 different pages in the entire CR
                    are retrieved. (There are all together 1,439 page records with the ATT tag. But
                    some referred to the same pages.) The peak occurred in 1900, during the Boxer
                    Rebellion, which may not be surprising. However, the post-classification of the
                    query result (Figure 6), an important feature of our system, shows the lists of
                    authors, persons, missions, which might provide interesting information for
                    scholars to pursue further.</p>
                 <p>The method and system that we have
                    developed provide a more global view of both CR and CRI. It integrates the three
                    indices of CRI and thus reveals relations among them and information implicitly
                    embedded. Our work should make CR and CRI more accessible to the research
                    community. The approach that we have taken is also a general one that can be
                    applied to any index with a similar structure.</p>
                 
                 <p><figure><graphic url="img241-5.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 5: summary of query ‘attack’</head></figure></p>
                 <p><figure><graphic url="img241-6.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 6: Classifications of the query result of ‘attack’ according to Author, Person,
                            Mission, and Subject</head></figure></p>
             </div>
            
            
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <head> References </head>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Kong, J.-W.</hi> (2011). <hi rend="italic">Design and Implementation
                    of a Retrieval System for the Chinese Recorder Index</hi>. MS Thesis, National
                Taiwan University. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Lodwick, K.</hi> (1986). <hi
                    rend="italic">The Chinese Recorder Index: A Guide to Christian Missions in Asia,
                    1867-1941</hi>. Scholarly Resources Inc. Washington D.C.</p>
        
        </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>