<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-258">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Towards a bibliographic model of illustrations in the early modern illustrated book</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Bradley, John</name>
                    <affiliation>Department of Digital Humanities, King’s College London,
                        UK</affiliation>
                    <email>john.bradley@kcl.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Pigney, Stephen</name>
                    <affiliation>Goldsmith’s College, London, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>s.pigney@gold.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>James Knapp, in his book <hi rend="italic">Illustrating the Past in Early Modern
                    England</hi> (Knapp 2003) points out that the History of the Book research has
                been ‘re-evaluating the relation of books to texts’ (p 9). However, he then goes on
                to say that an ‘overwhelmingly large amount of visual material’ could be found ‘on
                the pages of early modern English books’ (p 37), and that these books tell a complex
                story that interconnects books not only with their texts but with their
                illustrations too.  In this paper we will take up Knapp’s observation about visual
                material in books and will present a bibliographic conceptual model of the
                relationship of images, texts, and their makers that could support the enhancement
                of our understanding of the creation of books from the early modern period.</p>
            <p>We come by an interest in this topic honestly, since we were collaborators, with the
                project’s Principal Investigator Professor Michael Hunter (Birkbeck) on a project
                called <hi rend="italic">British Printed Images until 1700 </hi>(BPI1700) that has
                resulted in what the front page of its website calls ‘a database of thousands of
                prints and book illustrations from early modern Britain in fully-searchable form’.
                At present, bpi1700’s materials come from the extensive collection of primarily
                single-sheet prints held by the British Museum’s Department of Prints and Drawings
                and the Victoria and Albert Museum. Clearly, although the focus of bpi1700 has been
                on single-sheet prints up to now, the project is anxious to progress into the
                question of illustrations in printed books.</p>
            <p>To understand the scale of such an undertaking, it is useful to realise that <hi
                    rend="italic">many</hi> early printed books contained illustrations. James Knapp
                claims that English printers in the mid 16th century commonly used many
                illustrations for books on historical subjects (Knapp 2003: 2). Luborsky and Imgram
                catalogued more than 5,000 woodcuts and engravings in English books printed between
                1536 and 1603 alone, and a further study published by bpi1700 reveals thousands more
                for the period 1604-1640.  There is plenty of material to work with. However, the
                numbers tell only a part of the story: what is the nature of the interaction between
                an intellectual study of the illustrations as prints with the intellectual study of
                the books as books, so that their parallel, but interconnected, histories can be
                more clearly recognised?</p>
            <p>To help us explore these issues from a bibliographic perspective, we took up the
                approach described in the Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records (<hi
                    rend="italic">FRBR</hi>) (Tillet 2004) to identifying the nature of the
                published illustrations and the books themselves. FRBR was developed primarily to
                clarify the bibliographic analysis of modern printed books, and is developed out of
                four different senses in which the word ‘book’ can be used. The base sense of book,
                as a physical item that takes up space in a library, is called an ‘item’. A
                particular publication is called a ‘manifestation’, and roughly corresponds to an
                edition in modern publishing. FRBR identifies a higher level of structure in its
                entity ‘expression’, which, as Tillett describes it, organises a particular text by
                a specific language or media of delivery. Finally, the fourth and top level of
                abstraction is the ‘work’, the ‘conceptual content that underlies all the linguistic
                versions’, and represents things like the story being told, or the ideas in the
                author’s head (Tillett 2004: 3).</p>
            <p>Although bpi1700 was about printed images rather than modern printed books, FRBR had
                already proven to be useful in our growing understanding of the nature of prints.
                Bpi1700’s ‘impressions’ were the actual paper objects held by the museums, and
                represented by digital surrogates in bpi1700, and these seemed to be modelled best
                by FRBR’s ‘item’. Metadata about them were provided for bpi1700 by our partner
                museums. Of course, many impressions would be printed from a single plate that had
                been created by the print maker. Thus, among all the holdings in the museums it was
                not unusual for the same print to turn up more than once. Out of this realisation
                came the concept of bpi1700’s ‘work’ that fit FRBR’s ‘work’ category: a bpi1700 work
                represented a single plate or woodcut and captured the creative act of the print
                maker when she or he created it. Finally, in early modern times a plate was often
                modified over time, and these modifications would then be witnessed in surviving
                prints. A print of Charles I might first show him as a boy, but another impression
                from what was manifestly the same plate would show him as a young man instead.
                Between the production of these two impressions, the image of the king on the plate
                had been modified. Bpi1700 called each of these surviving versions of the plate a
                ‘state’ (using terminology already in use by print cataloguers), and concluded that
                this most closely corresponded to FRBR’s ‘manifestation’ category.</p>
            <p>Early Modern printed books (in the time of the hand-press), on the other hand,
                although apparently closer in nature to what FRBR was developed for than print
                images might be, did not turn out to be entirely aligned to modern print practice
                for which FRBR had been designed. Works and editions were much more fluid than they
                are today and early modern books have therefore presented a challenge to the
                conventional cataloguing rules developed to handle more modern material (see the
                discussion of this in the context of ‘rare books’ in Moriarty 2004). We chose to
                examine the British Library’s <hi rend="italic">English Short Title Catalogue</hi>
                (ESTC 2011) for information about our books. It operates at two levels. Its top
                level consists of records that correspond broadly to book printings – this, in turn,
                maps broadly to FRBR’s ‘manifestation’ category, since Moriarty (Moriarty 2004: 40)
                reminds us that in the hand-press era a reprinting of a book was really often like a
                new edition because it required the hand re-assembly of the type to print the pages
                again. Within each <hi rend="italic">printing</hi> entry ESTC stores information
                about particular copies (which broadly correspond to FRBR’s ‘Items’) which are
                grouped by holding institution. There is no explicit structural object corresponding
                to FRBR’s ‘Work’ or ‘Expression’ in ESTC, although one can use the search forms
                provide to filter data by author and title, which conceptually allows for materials
                to be selected by something similar to FRBR’s Work.</p>
            <p>So, if we consider both the books’ texts and their illustrations as both having an
                intellectual history that interests us, we have, then, two parallel and
                interconnected FRBR hierarchies in operation in early modern printed books. The
                issue is made more interesting by the fact that in the early modern period plates
                and/or woodcuts for illustrations were owned by printers and were often reused in
                more than one book. So, the same illustration might appear accompanying two
                completely different texts. Although a printer might decide to reprint a book, he or
                she could at the same time decide to change the illustrations that appeared in it
                to, say, increase the market for it. Furthermore, illustrations from plates had to
                be printed by a process separate from that used for the text, and these
                illustrations had to be inserted into the text pages by hand – a process subject to
                variability and error. Finally, because book binding was often arranged by the book
                buyer to be applied after she or he purchased the printed pages, book buyers often
                added illustrations they liked into printed books – a process called <hi
                    rend="italic">extra-illustration</hi> and described in more detail in the Folger
                library’s online exhibition ‘Extending the Book’ (2010). Thus, a bibliographic model
                that accommodates both the text and the illustrations – that represents the
                intellectual history of these two intertwined objects needs to accommodate a complex
                set of reasons why a set of illustrations (with their creative history) appears with
                the text of a particular book (with its separate history too).</p>
            <p>In our presentation, we will examine some examples of illustrations in early modern
                books and show how this intertwining operated in practice. We believe that the
                parallel and intertwined existence of books and illustrations reveals a new and
                interesting story in the history of the book. We will present our model that
                represents the parallel FRBR-like nature of the images and the book with their
                complex web of possible interconnections, and we will discuss some of the possible
                significance of this for those interested in exploring the role of illustration in
                these early printed volumes.</p>
            <p>(This paper is based on a presentation given by the authors at the Digital Humanities
                Day at Sheffield Hallam University on 13 December 2010, but will be extended beyond
                what was presented there with a more detailed presentation of the model for the
                data, as is suitable for a DH audience.)</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">Bbi1700</hi>. <hi rend="italic">British Printed Images before
                        1700. </hi>Online at <ref target="http://www.bpi1700.org.uk" type="external">http://www.bpi1700.org.uk</ref></p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">ESTC</hi> (2011). <hi rend="italic">English Short Title
                            Catalogue.</hi> British Library. Online at http://estc.bl.uk/</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Folger Shakespeare Library</hi> (2010). Extending the Book:
                        The Art of Extra-Illustration. An exhibition January 28-May 25, 2010. Online
                        version available at <ref
                            target="http://www.folger.edu/template.cfm?cid=3346"
                        type="external">http://www.folger.edu/template.cfm?cid=3346</ref></p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Knapp, J. A.</hi> (2003). <hi rend="italic">Illustrating the
                            Past in Early Modern England: the representation of History in Printed
                            Books</hi>. Aldershot: Ashgate Publishing.   </p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Luborsky, R., and E. Ingram</hi> (1998). <hi rend="italic"
                            >Guide to English Illustrated Books 1536-1603</hi>. Tempe, AZ: MRTS.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Moriarty, K. S</hi>. (2004). <hi rend="italic">Descriptive
                            Cataloging of Rare Materials (Books) and Its Predecessors: A History of
                            Rare Book Cataloging Practice in the United States</hi>. A Master’s
                        paper for the M.S. in L.S. degree. November, 2004. 100 pages. Advisor: Jerry
                        D. Saye.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Tillett, B.</hi> (2004). <hi rend="italic">FRBR? A Conceptual
                            Model for the Bibliographic Universe</hi>. Washington: Library of
                        Congress Cataloguing Distribution Service. Online at <ref
                            target="http://www.loc.gov/cds/downloads/FRBR.PDF" type="external">http://www.loc.gov/cds/downloads/FRBR.PDF</ref></p>
                
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>