<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-208">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Towards Wittgenstein on the Semantic Web</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Pichler, Alois</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Bergen, Norway</affiliation>
                    <email>Alois.Pichler@uni.no</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Zöllner-Weber, Amélie</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Bergen, Norway</affiliation>
                    <email>amelie.zoellnerweber@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>Ludwig Wittgenstein’s 20,000 pages of manuscripts and typescripts (his
                        ‘Nachlass’) display his continuous philosophical development and contain
                        revisions, rearrangements and ‘multiple versioning.’ Their publication poses
                        a number of challenges, for book as well as for digital editions (Huitfeldt
                        1994). Since its creation in 1990, the Wittgenstein Archives at the
                        University of Bergen (WAB) has tried to meet these challenges through
                        digital editorial philology. In 2000, WAB’s ‘Bergen Electronic Edition’
                        (BEE) of Wittgenstein’s Nachlass was published by Oxford University Press,
                        and in 2009, 5000 pages from the Nachlass were made freely available (Open
                        Access) on the Web (<ref target="http://www.wittgensteinsource.org/" type="external">
                            http://www.wittgensteinsource.org/</ref>, cf. Fig. 1). Since 2001, XML-based
                        text encoding (TEI P5) has been one of several central ingredients through
                        which WAB has worked continuously to improve access to Wittgenstein’s
                        manuscripts.</p>
                <p><figure><graphic url="img208-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 1: Screenshot of the Wittgenstein Source Bergen Text Editon</head></figure></p>
            
                    
            
                    <p>One key aspect of making Wittgenstein better and widely available is to
                        prepare his works for the Semantic Web (Krüger 2007, Pichler 2010, Erbacher
                        2011). This, in turn, creates new possibilities for achieving deeper
                        insights into his philosophy and intertextual relations within and between
                        his work(s). A case study for developing an ontology for Wittgenstein’s <hi
                            rend="italic">Tractatus</hi> (1922) was published in 2007 (Zöllner-Weber
                        &amp; Pichler 2007). Work with the ontology received a significant boost
                        from the EU-supported DISCOVERY project (2006-09, Smith 2007) and
                        established that the ontology should permit interlinked browsing of
                        philosophical concepts and primary sources. Therefore the Wittgenstein
                        ontology includes both classes for sources and for philosophical concepts as
                        well as properties which relate these classes. The ontology was implemented
                        using OWL. A visualization tool (cf. Fig. 2) which allowed for coordinated
                        use of both classes was created: Philospace/SwickyNotes which is today being
                        further developed towards a collaborative Web based ontology browser and
                        annotation tool (Morbidoni &amp; Nucci 2010).</p>
            
                <p><figure><graphic url="img208-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 2: Extract from the Wittgenstein ontology in Philospace/SwickyNotes</head></figure></p>
                
                    <p>From its start, the project was faced with a major challenge: Wittgenstein’s
                        work and philosophy are highly dynamic, multi-facetted and in continuous
                        development. One example is Wittgenstein’s concept of ‘meaning’ which in his
                            <hi rend="italic">Tractatus</hi> is primarily linked to reference, in
                        the middle period to rules, in the <hi rend="italic">Philosophical
                            Investigations</hi> (1953) to usage and practice, and in his last years
                        includes yet other aspects such as ‘the atmosphere of a word.’ Even within
                        the same period and work a term can be used in different and not always
                        consistent ways. Many of Wittgenstein’s works are characterized by
                        presenting a range of different views and approaches (cf. Fig. 3).
                        Wittgenstein commentators often disagree and propose conflicting
                        interpretations. How can such challenges be dealt with in ontologies?</p>

                <p><figure><graphic url="img208-3.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 3: Elements of the Wittgenstein ontology</head></figure></p>

                <p>In our view, providing a frame for documenting and explicating different
                        models of the world and its domains belongs to the assets of an ontology –
                        irrespective of these models agreeing with one other or not. Disagreement
                        and alternative proposals can be made visible, sharable and debatable
                        exactly through such an ontology. We regard the implementation of an
                        ontology in the field of philosophical interpretation as an opportunity
                        rather than as a hindrance.</p>
                
                    <p>When conceiving the ontology, WAB analysed different dictionaries and indices
                        of Wittgenstein’s work, including Hanjo Glock’s valuable <hi rend="italic"
                            >Wittgenstein Dictionary</hi> (Glock 1996), and philosophical
                        dictionaries and works of reference more generally. Obviously, WAB needed a
                        bottom-up rather than a top-down approach since its ontology should support
                        the use of specific texts, such as the 5000 pages of Wittgenstein Source.
                        Another important aspect was that the ontology should match and support
                        specific tasks that WAB and its partners, including guest researchers, were
                        involved in, such as teaching a class on Wittgenstein’s <hi rend="italic"
                            >Tractatus</hi>, or joint research on Wittgenstein’s philosophy of
                        psychology. In this way, the ontology could be tested in research as well as
                        learning environments and developed further in cooperation with Wittgenstein
                        experts.</p></div>
            <div>
                    <head>Description of the ontology</head>
                    <p>On the top level, the Wittgenstein ontology is divided into two branches: <hi
                        rend="italic">Source</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Subject</hi> (see Fig. 4).
                    The <hi rend="italic">Source</hi> class houses primary and secondary sources
                    relevant for Wittgenstein research; the subclass <hi rend="italic"
                        >PrimarySource</hi> divides further into Wittgenstein sources and external
                    sources (e.g. Augustine’s <hi rend="italic">Confessiones</hi>). The lowest
                    subclass of Wittgenstein primary sources is <hi rend="italic">Bemerkung</hi> and
                    denotes the Wittgensteinian <hi rend="italic">remark</hi>: typically  not longer
                    than half a page and separated from other remarks by one or more blank
                    lines.</p>
                    <p>The <hi rend="italic">Subject</hi> class contains four subclasses: <hi
                            rend="italic">Issue, Perspective, Point</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                            >Field</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Issue</hi> refers<hi rend="italic"
                        > </hi>to subjects dealt with by Wittgenstein himself or in Wittgenstein
                        research, e.g. ‘elementary proposition’, ‘logical independence’, ‘picture’
                        and ‘state of affairs’. They denote the subjects which one would typically
                        expect to be included in the ‘subject index’ of a comprehensive study of
                        Wittgenstein’s philosophy. <hi rend="italic">Point</hi> is a specific
                        category developed at WAB: it refers to the point made or confirmed by an
                        individual Wittgensteinian remark and typically contains an entire statement
                        or a question like ‘The elementary proposition is a picture of a state of
                        affairs’.  Via the <hi rend="italic">Source </hi>properties <hi
                            rend="italic">discussesIssue </hi>and<hi rend="italic"> hasPoint</hi>
                        instances of <hi rend="italic">Point </hi>can be interlinked with instances
                        of <hi rend="italic">Issue</hi>.</p>
                    
                <p><figure><graphic url="img208-4.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 4: Main classes of the Wittgenstein ontology</head></figure></p>
                    
                    <p>In order to provide for different modelling of the relations a
                        Wittgensteinian subject can have, as well as to serve different user needs,
                        WAB introduced the class <hi rend="italic">Perspective</hi>. This class
                        contains subclasses which each represent a specific grouping or filtering of
                        the instances of <hi rend="italic">Issue</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                            >Point</hi>. As an example the following may serve: Logical analysis
                        (which is an instance of <hi rend="italic">Issue</hi>) is central to the
                        method of the philosophy from the perspective of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Tractatus</hi>, while it is not from the perspective of the <hi
                            rend="italic">Investigations</hi>. A course on the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Tractatus</hi> will draw positive attention to that term, while a
                        course on the <hi rend="italic">Investigations</hi> may not even have it in
                        its list of important subjects or start from the following instance of <hi
                            rend="italic">Point</hi>: ‘Logical analysis is not central to
                        philosophy’. One and the same instance of <hi rend="italic">Issue</hi> can
                        enter different configurations, and even configurations which contrast with
                        each other. For example, the subjects ‘elementary proposition’ and ‘logical
                        independence’ are in the <hi rend="italic">Tractatus</hi> (1922) and “Some
                        Remarks on Logical Form” (SRLF, 1929) combined to configurations contrasting
                        with each other. The first work claims: ‘Elementary propositions are
                        logically independent from each other’, while the later denies this. The <hi
                            rend="italic">Tractatus</hi> perspective will include the claim
                        ‘Elementary propositions are logically independent from each other’, while
                        the later work’s perspective will include a negation (property <hi
                            rend="italic">deniesPoint</hi>) of this claim or the explicit claim:
                        ‘Elementary propositions are not logically independent from each other’ (see
                        Fig. 3).</p>
                
                    <p>In addition, the class <hi rend="italic">Field</hi> was created as suggested
                        by Grenon &amp; Smith 2011. This field connects the Wittgenstein domain with
                        other domains in philosophy and research more generally, e.g. epistemology
                        or aesthetics. Users not familiar with Wittgenstein at all can enter
                        Wittgenstein research with fields and debates from this class as their
                        starting points. Each instance of <hi rend="italic">Issue</hi> can be
                        affiliated with one or more such field.</p>
                    <p>The name of an <hi rend="italic">Issue</hi> instance consists of a
                        German-English compound; this enables both German and English speakers to
                        work more smoothly on the ontology, and in addition provides welcome means
                        for precisely disambiguating and identifying the domain’s instances. Users
                        browse the ontology with a specific language set as preference: each
                        instance can, via <hi rend="italic">rdfs:label</hi>, in principle be
                        identified and rendered in all languages. Currently, the ontology contains
                        about 700 <hi rend="italic">Issue</hi> instances which are rendered in
                        German, English and Danish. Renderings in Norwegian, French and Finnish are
                        being added. WAB’s vision is that users of the ontology shall as much as
                        possible be enabled to browse and access the Wittgenstein ontology in a
                        language of their preference. The ontology is intended for use in the
                        research and learning environments of different languages.</p>
                    <p>Properties are key in WAB’s ontology: they provide the relations which allow
                        for interlinked browsing of the ontology and Wittgenstein primary sources.
                        Properties of <hi rend="italic">Bemerkung</hi> which is the most important
                        instance of <hi rend="italic">Source</hi>, include: isPartOfSource,
                        hasAuthor, hasDifferentVersion, refersToPerson, refersToText,
                        discussesIssue, hasPoint, deniesPoint a.o. Properties of an <hi
                            rend="italic">Issue</hi> instance can be: assertsPerspective,
                        isRelatedToIssue, isRelevantForField, a.o. Each <hi rend="italic"
                            >Bemerkung</hi> of Wittgenstein’s <hi rend="italic">Nachlass</hi> shall
                        eventually be associated by <hi rend="italic">discussesIssue</hi> to at
                        least one instance of <hi rend="italic">Issue</hi>, but also take on <hi
                            rend="italic">Point</hi> properties such as <hi rend="italic"
                            >hasPoint</hi>, directing to the class <hi rend="italic">Point</hi>.
                        Thereby, a scholar searching for discussions of certain issues will be
                        steered to certain remarks, and vice versa looking at a specific remark
                        one’s attention will be drawn also to specific issues or points.</p></div>
            <div>
                <head>Summary</head>
                    <p>WAB’s Wittgenstein ontology is still in its infancy, especially with regard
                        to its <hi rend="italic">Subject</hi> branch. WAB naturally cannot achieve
                        its goal of a comprehensive Wittgenstein ontology alone: while the first
                        version of the ontology and its overall structure were developed in the
                        frame of the DISCOVERY project by WAB staff, it has since 2010 been
                        strengthened by international cooperation (see <ref target="http://wab.uib.no/wab_philospace.page" type="external">http://wab.uib.no/wab_philospace.page</ref>). A key challenge in developing this
                        ontology was to reflect Wittgenstein’s dynamic and multi-facetted work, but
                        also Wittgenstein research’s different interpretations of this work. This
                        was dealt with by introducing among others the class <hi rend="italic"
                            >Perspective</hi>, allowing for concurring models in and about
                        Wittgenstein’s work while maintaining a technically valid ontology. The
                        instances of <hi rend="italic">Issue</hi> are the only stable entities of
                        the Wittgenstein subject domain; through the subclasses of <hi rend="italic"
                            >Perspective</hi> they can be combined and filtered in different ways
                        which can even contradict each other. The ontology is related to
                        Wittgenstein primary sources via properties, enabling fast and easy studying
                        of Wittgenstein within a common platform. In this way, research and learning
                        about Wittgenstein can be significantly enhanced.</p>
                </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <head> References </head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Erbacher, C.</hi> (2011). Unser Denken bleibt gefragt: Web
                        3.0 und Wittgensteins Nachlass. In S. Windholz and W. Feigl (eds.), <hi
                            rend="italic">Wissenschaftstheorie, Sprachkritik und Wittgenstein</hi>.
                        Heusenstamm: ontos, pp. 135-146.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Glock, H.</hi> (1996). <hi rend="italic">A Wittgenstein
                        dictionary.</hi> Oxford: Blackwell.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Grenon, P., and B. </hi> (2011). Foundations of an ontology of philosophy.<hi rend="italic">Synthese</hi> 182(2): 185-204.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Huitfeldt, C.</hi> (1994). Toward a Machine-Readable Version
                        of Wittgenstein’s <hi rend="italic">Nachlaß</hi>. Beihefte zu <hi
                            rend="italic">editio</hi> 6: 37-43.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Krüger, H. W.</hi> (2007). Wittgenstein registrieren. In <hi
                            rend="italic">Papers of the 30th International Ludwig
                            Wittgenstein-Symposium</hi>. Kirchberg a.W.: ALWS, pp. 119-121.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Morbidoni, C., and  M. Nucci</hi> (2010). <hi rend="italic"
                    >SwickyNotes user guide</hi>. <ref target="http://www.swickynotes.org/docs/SWickyNotesStartingGuide.pdf" type="external">http://www.swickynotes.org/docs/SWickyNotesStartingGuide.pdf</ref>.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Pichler, A.</hi> (2010). Towards the New Bergen Electronic
                        Edition. In N. Venturinha (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Wittgenstein After His
                            Nachlass</hi>. Houndmills: Palgrave Macmillan pp.157-172.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Smith, D. C. P.</hi> (2007). Re-Discovering Wittgenstein. In:
                            <hi rend="italic">Papers of the 30th International Ludwig
                            Wittgenstein-Symposium</hi>. Kirchberg a.W.: ALWS, pp. 208-210.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Wittgenstein, L.</hi> (1922). <hi rend="italic">Tractatus
                        Logico-Philosophicus</hi>. London: Kegan Paul.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Wittgenstein, L.</hi> (1953).<hi rend="italic"> Philosophical
                            Investigations</hi>. Oxford: Blackwell.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Zöllner-Weber, A., and A. Pichler</hi> (2007). Utilizing OWL
                    for Wittgenstein’s Tractatus. In: <hi rend="italic">Papers of the 30th
                        International Ludwig Wittgenstein-Symposium</hi>. Kirchberg a.W.: ALWS,
                    pp.248-250.</p>
             </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>