<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-222">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Catch + Release: Research and Creation of a Digital New Media Exhibition in the Context of a Cultural and Heritage Museum</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Beer, Ruth</name>
                    <affiliation>Emily Carr University of Art and Design, Vancouver, Canada</affiliation>
                    <email>rbeer@ecuad.ca</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
            <p>We will present, <hi rend="italic">Catch + Release: Mapping Stories of Geographic and
                    Cultural Transition</hi> (2009-2012), a research and creation project funded by
                the Social Sciences and Humanities Council of Canada. It is a case study of a
                collaborative, interdisciplinary digital new media practice in community engagement
                and informal learning. It looks at local/global environmental, socio-cultural and
                historical interplays related to multi-cultural community perspectives, including
                First Nations, on changes due to the demise of the fishing industry. Historically,
                fishing was one of the primary reasons for the multi-cultural immigration that
                helped to foster the settlement, economic development, and social growth on the west
                coast of Canada.</p>
            <p>We will discuss our interactive digital new media
                exhibition <hi rend="italic">Catch + Release</hi> installed in The Gulf of Georgia
                Cannery Museum National Historic Site, a social history museum in Steveston, British
                Columbia, a small city on Canada’s Pacific coast. The exhibition proposes to advance
                an encounter with history as critical inquiry into contemporary life of the region.
                The researchers’ backgrounds in new media art, new media education, cultural theory,
                and interactive design, come together to explore how research and creation
                contributes to informed discourse that engages with the region’s cultural history
                and social, cultural and ecological present. Our new media exhibition that uses
                sensor technologies and immersive interactivity to overlay stories from the
                community together with those of the museum, is intended to foster a sense of
                belonging and deeper understanding of historical and current circumstances. While
                our study is localized, these conditions and stories resonate in other coastal
                communities that once relied on fishing, thus, our project addresses cultural and
                marine environmental sustainability in many similar contexts.</p>
            <p>This project draws on qualitative inquiry informed by practice-based research
                    methodologies in education and visual art and is impacted by the fields of new
                    media art, cultural studies, museum studies and the history of art as a
                    discipline vital to the analysis of how history, including the past and
                    just-past, is mediated through images, objects, and experiences (Benjamin 1968). </p>
            <p>Our project at the intersection of
                socially-engaged interactive new media art and pedagogy, views the museum as an
                essentially social institution that requires interdisciplinary analysis as an
                informal site of learning and as space for promoting critical thinking. The Gulf of
                Georgia Cannery Museum National Historic Site, a museum since the closing of the
                cannery in 1970 and that still features the intact production line, is an important
                pedagogical space for school groups, tourists and local visitors, and subsequently a
                major source of regional identity.</p>
            <p>For the <hi rend="italic">Catch + Release</hi> exhibition, we designed
                    situation-specific, new media interactive art experiences for contributing
                    diverse perspectives; catching and releasing stories that challenge the
                    seamlessness of those historical narratives typically represented by museum
                    displays of artifacts and information panels. The exhibition is intended to
                    generate polyphony of diverse voices to make viewers feel a part of their
                    regional museum, and exposes them to multiple viewpoints about their (local)
                    relationship to the (global) ecology-making visitors more aware of their
                    relationship to and impact on the local ecology and history. In this way, the
                    project did not seek to create an exhibition in the space, but rather used the
                    space to exhibit the place in which it is situated.</p>
            <p>Our
                presentation will describe the conceptual basis and rationale for the inclusion of
                the new media artworks that comprise the exhibition. They include: interactive
                projections of live-stream visualization of data from underwater sensors of Canada’s
                ocean observatory; clusters of light and sound digital sensor activated interactive
                sculptures that reference the marine geoscape and communication devices used by
                fisherman; and a montage of video interviews with people whose stories expose
                sometimes oppositional views on the fishing industry. The polyphony of multiple and
                diverse voices argues for a more open-ended and complicated way of dealing with the
                representation of history. We will discuss how immersive technology can provide
                unique opportunities for teaching and learning experiences and embodied ways of
                knowing through a rich multi-sensory environment that engages the viewer with how
                culture and memory come together in new forms.</p>
            <p>Our study is also intended
                to stimulate interest the historical role of the museum by inviting the community to
                participate in the creation and complication of historical narratives. Cultural and
                heritage museums, specifically, have become multi-purpose, spaces where museum
                professionals strive to expand their programmes and define new communication
                approaches capable of engaging broader publics (Prior 2008). In this context, recent
                interactive technologies are seen to offer museums an ability to create a sense of
                spectacle and excite audiences (Hemsley, Cappellini &amp; Stanke 2005).
                Increasingly, however, the reification of technologized display raises concerns
                about the type and quality of museum experience (Griffiths 1999). Despite the
                potential of multi-media displays to address the diverse needs of different
                audiences or audience members by combining information and physical spaces and
                presenting interactive storytelling<hi rend="italic">, </hi>there is still a
                tendency to rely on basic interactive terminals with mouse, keyboard and monitor.
                While this may be an efficient way to deliver information, our project contributes
                aesthetic and expressive possibilities for actively engaging audiences. Recent
                discourse around new media art practices and new museums has encouraged an interest
                in technology beyond fixed modalities of story authoring, to sensory-driven,
                interactive processes of learning that allow visitors to engage with interactive art
                forms and digital technologies to construct their own learning experience in the
                museum (Henry 2010; Rogoff 2010). However more research is needed to assess new
                models for establishing and maintaining dialogues with visitors and new ideas about
                how to connect these dialogues with the broader audiences (Cutler 2010).
                Contemporary new media artwork that invites users to interpret or experience content
                and function through a range of physical and sensorial interactions are seen to be
                extremely promising (Hornecker &amp; Buur 2006). Their ability to author embodied,
                responsive engagements are well suited to the museums’ pedagogical programs.</p>
            <p>As contemporary art is transformed through the incorporation of new media practice,
                works like <hi rend="italic">Catch + Release</hi> offer a potentially innovative
                approach to learning. If as Ellsworth (2005) contends, new digital media contribute
                to pedagogic disruption and call for new ‘routes’ of relational thinking, they
                establish the ground of shared social interest drawing together artists, museum
                professionals and educators to discuss how the public becomes co-creators of meaning
                (or active learners) through experiential, participatory engagement (Bishop
                2006).</p>
            <p>Social history museums have begun to invite artistic inquiry,
                presenting temporary digital new media art exhibitions such as <hi rend="italic"
                    >Catch + Release</hi> that advance the idea of a complex cultural and social
                history, challenge conventional displays and provide alternate modes of visitors’
                participation, meaning making and knowledge construction (Bishop 2006), in these new
                spaces of artistic exchange or encounter.</p>
            
                <p><figure><graphic url="img222-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Benjamin, W.</hi> (1968). The Work of Art in the Age of
                    Mechanical Reproduction. In H. Arendt (ed), <hi rend="italic">Illuminations.
                    </hi>Translated from German by H. Zohn. New York: Shocken Books, pp.
                    217-251.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Bishop, C., ed.</hi> (2006). <hi
                            rend="italic">Participation</hi>. Cambridge: MIT Press.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Cutler, A.</hi> (2010, Spring). What is to
                        be done, Sandra? Learning in cultural institutions in the 21<hi rend="sup"
                            >st</hi> century. <hi rend="italic">Tate Papers 13</hi>.
                    <ref
                        target="http://www.tate.org.uk/research/tateresearch/tatepapers/10spring/cutler.shtm"
                        type="external">http://www.tate.org.uk/research/tateresearch/tatepapers/10spring/cutler.shtm</ref>
                        (accessed 1 October 2011).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Ellsworth, E.</hi> (2005). <hi rend="italic">Places of Learning:
                        Media, Architecture, Pedagogy.</hi> New York: Routledge.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Griffiths, A.</hi>
                        (1999). Media technology and museum display: A century of accommodation and
                        conflict. <hi rend="italic">MIT communications forum.</hi> <ref target="http://web.mit.edu/comm-forum/papers/griffiths.html#1" type="external">
                        http://web.mit.edu/comm-forum/papers/griffiths.html#1</ref> (accessed 1 October
                        2011).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Hemsley, J., V. Cappellini, and G.
                            Stanke</hi> (2005). <hi rend="italic">Digital Applications for Cultural
                            and Heritage Institutions.</hi> Burlington: Ashgate.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Henry, C.</hi> (2010). <hi rend="italic">The Museum
                            Experience: The Discovery of Meaning.</hi> Reston: National Art
                        Education Association.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Hornecker, E., and J. Buur</hi> (2006). <hi rend="italic">Getting
                        a Grip on Tangible Inter</hi><hi rend="italic">action: A Framework on
                        Physical</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Space and Social Interaction, Proceedings of the SIGCHI 2006
                        Conference on Human</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Factors in Computing System.</hi> New York: ACM Press, pp.
                    437-446. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Prior, N.</hi> (2008). Having One’s Tate and Eating
                        It: Transformations of the Museum in a Hypermodern Era. In McClellan, A.
                        (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Art and its Publics: Museum Studies at the
                            Millenium</hi>. Hoboken, NJ: Wiley-Blackwell, pp. 51-76.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Rogoff, I.</hi> (2010, Summer). Practicing research:
                    Singularising knowledge. <hi rend="italic">MaHKUzine,</hi> 9: 37-42. <ref target="http://www.mahku.nl/download/maHKUzine09_web.pdf" type="external">http://www.mahku.nl/download/maHKUzine09_web.pdf</ref>  (accessed 1 October
                    2011).</p>
                
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>