<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-363">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>DeRiK: A German Reference Corpus of Computer-Mediated Communication</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Lemnitzer, Lothar</name>
                    <affiliation>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>lemnitzer@bbaw.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Beißwenger, Michael</name>
                    <affiliation>Technische Universität Dortmund, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>michael.beisswenger@uni-dortmund.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Ermakova, Maria</name>
                    <affiliation>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>ermakovamd@googlemail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Geyken, Alexander</name>
                    <affiliation>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>geyken@bbaw.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Storrer, Angelika</name>
                    <affiliation>Technische Universität Dortmund, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>angelika.storrer@uni-dortmund.de</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            
            <div>
                <head>Project background and focus of the paper</head>
                <p>In view of the increasing amount of reading and writing that
                    people do on the Internet, corpus designers who set out to provide balanced
                    corpora that include all relevant text types of contemporary language should
                    also include samples of genres of computer-mediated communication (CMC) such as
                    e-mail, weblogs, microblogging on Twitter, discussion boards and wiki
                    discussions, chats and instant messaging conversations, and communication in
                    social network sites. In our paper we present selected aspects of an ongoing
                    project that aims at building a reference corpus of German CMC, called <hi
                        rend="italic">DeRiK</hi> (‘Deutsches Referenzkorpus zur internetbasierten
                    Kommunikation’).<note>Cf. <ref target="http://www.empirikom.net/bin/view/Themen/DeRiK" type="external">http://www.empirikom.net/bin/view/Themen/DeRiK</ref>. The project is embedded in the scientific network ‘Empirische Erforschung internetbasierter Kommunikation’ (<ref target="http://www.empirikom.net/" type="external">http://www.empirikom.net/</ref>), funded by the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG).</note> DeRiK is a joint initiative of TU
                    Dortmund University and the Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and the
                    Humanities (BBAW). The corpus will be integrated into the lexical information
                    system provided by the BBAW project <hi rend="italic">Digitales Wörterbuch der
                        deutschen Sprache</hi> (<hi rend="italic">DWDS</hi>, <ref target="www.dwds.de" type="external">www.dwds.de</ref>).<note>Another corpus of contemporary language which aims to include a CMC subcorpus is the Dutch SoNaR project (Reynaert et al. 2010).</note></p>
                <p>In our paper we will focus on the role of the DeRiK component in the DWDS
                    framework (section 2) and on CMC-specific issues of corpus annotation (section
                    3).</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>Integrating CMC discourse into a corpus of contemporary German: motivation and application fields</head>
                <p>DWDS (<ref target="www.dwds.de" type="external">www.dwds.de</ref>) is a lexical information system developed by and hosted at the
                    BBAW. The system offers one-click-access to three different types of resources
                    (Geyken 2007):</p>
                <p>a) <hi rend="italic">lexical resources:</hi> a common language
                        dictionary,<note>This dictionary is based on a six-volume paper dictionary,
                        the <hi rend="italic">Wörterbuch der deutschen Gegenwartssprache</hi> (WDG,
                        en.: ‘Dictionary of Contemporay German’) published between 1962 and 1977 and
                        compiled at the Deutsche Akademie der Wissenschaften (cf. [WDG]).</note> an
                    etymological dictionary, and a the­saurus;</p>
                <p>b) <hi rend="italic">corpus resources:</hi> a balanced reference corpus (called
                    ‘DWDS core corpus’) of German ranging from 1900 up to now, a set of additional
                    newspaper corpora, and specialized corpora;</p>
                <p>c) <hi rend="italic">statistical resources</hi> for words and word
                    combinations.</p>
                <p>These resources are displayed alongside one another in separate panels (cf. Fig.
                    1). The system offers the choice among several views, i.e. between several
                    profiles with predefined panel combinations.</p>
                <p><figure><graphic url="img363-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 1: Web frontend of the DWDS system (<ref target="http://www.dwds.de" type="external"
                    >http://www.dwds.de</ref>)</head></figure></p>
                <p>The CMC component <hi rend="italic">DeRiK</hi> (‘Deutsches Referenzkorpus zur
                    internetbasierten Kommunika­tion’) will be integrated into this framework both
                    as an independent panel and as a subcorpus of the DWDS core corpus. The sampling
                    of the CMC genres in DeRiK is guided by the findings of the
                    ‘ARD/ZDF-Onlinestudie’, a German online usage survey conducted once per year
                    (www.ard-zdf-onlinestudie.de). The findings of this survey allow us to derive a
                    key for the composition of our corpus. However, for practical reasons the
                    project will set out to acquire data of only those CMC applications on the
                    Internet for which the users have explicitly granted permission for
                    (re-)distributing and (re-)using their written utterances for non-commercial
                    purposes/academic research.<note>This is typically communicated by assigning certain subtypes of the ‘Creative Commons’ License to CMC documents or to web applications which specify the terms of (re-)use and (re-)distribution of their content.</note> The first partial corpus
                    of DeRiK will include discourse from <hi rend="italic">Wikipedia</hi> talk
                    pages, a selection of forum and weblog discussions, chat conversations, and
                    postings of selected <hi rend="italic">Twitter</hi> users who have licensed
                    their tweets under Creative Commons. We hope that in the long term changes in
                    IPR restrictions within the domain of discourse on the Internet will enable us
                    to apply more principled methods of data sampling.</p>
                <p>The integration of the CMC reference corpus into the DWDS system may be valuable
                    for various research and application fields, for example:</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">a) Language variation, language change and stylistics:</hi> A
                    general-language corpus that includes a CMC component will provide a broad
                    empirical basis (a) for further, corpus-based investigations of the usage and
                    dissemination of CMC-specific phenomena across linguistic varieties and digital
                    genres, and (b) for comparative analyses of the features of CMC discourse and of
                    “traditional” written genres (e.g. newspaper, fiction, scientific writing,
                    nonliterary prose); it will thus facilitate to track and describe how new
                    linguistic patterns and communicative genres emerge.<note>Overviews of the features of CMC discourse from a linguistic perspective can be found, e.g., in Herring (ed., 1996, 2010), Werry (1996), Runkehl et al. (1998), Beißwenger (2000), Crystal (2001, 2011), Beißwenger &amp; Storrer (2008), and Storrer (2012). The DeRiK corpus will include annotations of selected phenomena which are often described as being typical for language use on the Internet.</note></p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">b) Lexicology and lexicography:</hi> Besides genre-specific
                    discourse markers and netspeak jargon (like ‘lol’ <hi rend="italic">laughing out
                        loud</hi> or ‘imho’ <hi rend="italic">in my humble opinion</hi>), new
                    vocabulary is characteristic for CMC discourse, e.g. ‘funzen’ (an abbreviated
                    variant of ‘funktionieren’ <hi rend="italic">to</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                        rend="italic">function</hi>) or ‘gruscheln’ (a function of a German social
                    network platform, most likely a blending of ‘grüßen’ <hi rend="italic"
                        >greet</hi> and ‘kuscheln’ <hi rend="italic">cuddle</hi>). There are also
                    CMC-specific processes of lexical-semantic changes, e.g. the broadening of the
                    concept of ‘Freund’ (<hi rend="italic">friend</hi>). Up-to-date lexical
                    resources should document and describe these tendencies by integrating CMC data
                    into their data basis. Once the first partial corpora of the DeRiK corpus are
                    made available in the DWDS system, it is intended to extend the DWDS dictionary
                    component with entries describing new lexemes that have evolved from CMC
                    discourse. In addition, the DWDS corpus system will then allow one to track how
                    new vocabulary from CMC discourse (such as the examples mentioned above) spreads
                    into ‘traditional’ genres (e.g. newspaper, fiction, nonliterary prose).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">c) Language teaching:</hi> CMC has become an important part of
                    everyday communication. Language- and culture-specific properties of CMC should
                    thus also be regarded in communicative approaches to Second Language Teaching.
                    In this context, the DeRiK corpus and the documentation of CMC vocabulary in the
                    DWDS dictionary may be useful resources. In school teaching, students with
                    German as a native language may use the DWDS system to compare written language
                    with CMC and to explore how style varies across different genres.</p>
                
            </div>            
            
            <div>
            <head>Annotation of CMC-specific phenomena</head>
                <p>One advantage of integrating DeRiK into the DWDS system is that users can profit from the DWDS
                    corpus annotation and querying facilities: The corpus resources which are
                    currently available in the DWDS system are lemmatized with the <hi rend="italic"
                        >TAGH</hi> morphology (cf. Geyken &amp; Hanneforth 2006) and tagged with the
                    part-of-speech tagger <hi rend="italic">moot</hi> (cf. Jurish 2003). The corpus
                    search engine <hi rend="italic">DDC</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Dialing DWDS
                        Concordancer</hi>) supports linguistic queries on several annotation levels
                    (word forms, lemmas, STTS part-of-speech categories), filtering (e.g. by text
                    type) and sorting options.</p>
                <p>Since all corpus resources in the DWDS system are encoded according the
                    guidelines of the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI-P5), the project aims to use and
                    customize TEI for the appropriate base-level annotation of the CMC sub-corpus.
                    For this purpose, we have developed a TEI-compliant annotation schema that</p>
                
                <xmt:uList>
                    <item>
                        provides a macro-structure of CMC discourse which should cover as many
                            genres as possible (see section 3.1);
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        provides a suggestion for the description of CMC-specific phenomena which
                            is oriented mainly on surface features (for instance, the annotation
                            will cover interaction signs of various types; see section 3.2 for
                            details).
                    </item>
                </xmt:uList>
                
                    <p>The TEI-related details of this schema are described in Beißwenger et
                        al. (2012).<note> The RNG schema file, a TEI-compliant ODD documentation as well as encoding examples are available at <ref target="http://www.empirikom.net/bin/view/Themen/CmcTEI" type="external">http://www.empirikom.net/bin/view/Themen/CmcTEI</ref>.</note> The discussion in this paper will focus on
                    two annotation issues: The representation of CMC-specific micro- and
                    macrostructures (section 3.1) and the annotation of typical ‘netspeak’ elements
                    (section 3.2).</p>
                
                <div>
                <head>Annotation of CMC-specific micro- and macrostructures</head>
                <p>We introduced the category <hi rend="italic">posting</hi> as a basic element to
                    capture CMC micro- and macrostructures. A posting<hi rend="italic"> </hi>is
                    defined as a content unit that is being sent to the server ‘en bloc’. Postings
                    can usually be recognized by their formal structure, even if they have different
                    forms and structures across CMC genres. This facilitates the automatic
                    segmentation and annotation of CMC micro- and macrostructures.</p>
                <p>We use the term <hi rend="italic">microstructure</hi> to refer to the internal
                    structure of postings. There are cases in which a posting consists of exactly
                    one portion of text. In other CMC genres, e.g. in discussion groups, postings
                    may contain divisions and markup used by the author to structure their
                    content.</p>
                <p>We use the term <hi rend="italic">macrostructure</hi> to describe how the
                    postings are sequenced. While microstructures are generated by an individual
                    author, macrostructures do not emerge from the actions of just <hi rend="italic"
                        >one</hi> user but from all posting activities of <hi rend="italic">all</hi>
                    users involved in a CMC conversation plus server routines for ordering the
                    incoming postings.</p>
                <p>In our TEI schema, we represent structures on the microstructure level (which
                    result from the planning and composition decisions of <hi rend="italic">one</hi>
                    author) using the <hi rend="italic">&lt;p&gt;</hi> element (‘paragraph’) from
                    the TEI standard. Structures on the macrostructure level, in contrast, are
                    described using the <hi rend="italic">&lt;div&gt;</hi> element (‘division’). In
                    addition, we differentiate between two major types of CMC macrostructures:</p>
                
                <xmt:uList>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">logfile</hi> structures, which arrange the postings in
                            a linear chronological order based on when they reached the server.
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">thread</hi> structures, which arrange the postings in a
                            sequence and use two dimensions with specific semantics: the <hi
                                rend="italic">above/below</hi> dimension representing a temporal
                            ‘before/after’ relation; the <hi rend="italic">left/right</hi> dimension
                            (by indentation), which usually symbolizes the topical affiliation of
                            one posting to a previous posting.
                    </item>
                </xmt:uList>
                </div>
                
                <div>
                
                    <head>Annotation of interaction signs</head>
                <p>The corpus-based investigation of ‘netspeak’ jargon is interesting in many
                        research contexts (style variation and language change, discourse
                        management, language teaching etc.). Our annotation schema copes for a set
                        of ‘netspeak’ phenomena which we term ‘interaction signs’. The term builds
                        on the category ‘interaktive Einheiten’ which has been introduced in the <hi
                            rend="italic">Grammatik der deutschen Sprache</hi>, a three-volume
                        scientific grammar of the German Language (cf. Zifonun et al. 1997), to
                        classify <hi rend="italic">interjections</hi> (such as ‘hm’ or ‘oh my god’)
                        and <hi rend="italic">responsives</hi> (such as ‘yes’ and ‘no’) in spoken
                            discourse<note>In other grammars these units are described as <hi
                                rend="italic">interjections</hi> (e.g., Greenbaum 1996; McArthur et
                            al. 1998; Blake 2008) or <hi rend="italic">Interjektionen</hi>
                            (DUDEN-4<hi rend="sup">7</hi>), <hi rend="italic">inserts</hi> (Biber et al. 1999, 2002),
                                <hi rend="italic">discourse markers</hi> (Schiffrin 1986), <hi
                                rend="italic">discourse particles</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                                >Gesprächspartikeln</hi> (DUDEN-4<hi rend="sup">5</hi>).</note>. In contrast to
                        part-of-speech-categories, interaction signs are not syntactically
                        integrated and do not contribute to the compositional structure of
                        sentences. In spoken discourse, they serve as devices for conversation
                        management, i.e. they can be used to express reactions to the partners’
                        utterances or to display the speaker’s emotions. Our category ‘interaction
                        sign’ includes interjections and responsives as well as four CMC-specific
                        classes (cf. Fig. 2):</p>
                    
                    <p><figure><graphic url="img363-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 2: Typology of interaction signs (with examples)</head></figure></p> 
                
                <xmt:oList rend="arabic">
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Emoticons </hi>are iconic units that have been created
                            with the keyboard and which typically serve as emotion or irony markers
                            or as responsives. Being of iconic origin, the use of emoticons is not
                            restricted to a specific language. However, different styles of
                            emoticons exist – e.g, Western style emoticons such as <hi rend="italic"
                                >:-)</hi>, <hi rend="italic">:-(</hi>, <hi rend="italic">;-)</hi> or
                            the <hi rend="italic">:)</hi>, or Japanese style emoticons such as <hi
                                rend="italic">(^_^)</hi>, <hi rend="italic">\(^_^)/</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">(*_*)</hi>.
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Interaction words</hi> are symbolic linguistic units
                            whose morphologic construction is based on a word or a phrase. They may
                            describe gestures or facial expressions, e.g. <hi rend="italic">*g*</hi>
                            (&lt; “grins”<hi rend="italic"> grin</hi>), <hi rend="italic">*fg*</hi>
                            (&lt; <hi rend="italic">fat grin</hi>), <hi rend="italic">*s*</hi> (&lt;
                                <hi rend="italic">smile</hi>), or they are used for the simulation
                            of actions and events.
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Interaction templates</hi> are units that the user does
                            not generate with the keyboard but which are generated automatically
                            from a file with a previously prepared text or graphical element after
                            the user has activated a template. Due to their generation from
                            predefined templates, we do not classify them as emoticons, even though
                            some of them may have similar functions. Amongst others, this category
                            includes <hi rend="italic">*.gif</hi> files. Many of them portray not
                            just facial expressions but can depict almost everything; in the case of
                            animated graphics they can even portray entire scenes as moving
                            pictures.
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <hi rend="italic">Addressing terms</hi> are units which are used to
                            address an utterance to a particular interlocutor. The most widely used
                            form here is the one made out of the &lt;@&gt;-character together with a
                            specification of the addressee’s name.
                    </item>
                </xmt:oList>
                  
                
                </div>
                </div>
                
                <div>
                    <head>Conclusion and outlook</head>
                    <p>Up to now, many
                    assumptions about the Internet’s impact on language change have been based upon
                    small datasets. As a new component within the DWDS system, the DeRiK corpus is
                    meant to be a resource for the investigation of language usage in CMC genres on
                    a broader empirical basis. The annotation schema sketched in section 3 is used
                    and evaluated in the ongoing work of the DeRiK project. The categories proposed
                    in this schema will have to be further discussed within the CMC community. We
                    consider the development of this schema as a first step towards the development
                    of an annotation standard that will facilitate cross-language, cross-genre, and
                    micro-diachronic investigations of CMC phenomena on the basis of corpora. The
                    schema focuses on linguistic aspects, but it is open for extensions motivated
                    through other fields of research, i.e. cultural studies or sentiment
                    analysis.</p> 
                </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <head>References</head>

            <p><hi rend="bold">Beißwenger, M. </hi>(2000). <hi rend="italic">Kommunikation in
                        virtuellen Welten: Sprache, Text und Wirklichkeit</hi>. Stuttgart:
                    Ibidem.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Beißwenger, M., and A. Storrer</hi> (2008). Corpora of
                    Computer-Mediated Communication. In A. Lüdeling and M. Kytö (eds.), <hi
                        rend="italic">Corpus Linguistics</hi>. <hi rend="italic">An International
                        Handbook,</hi> vol. 1. Berlin: de Gruyter, pp. 292-308.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Beißwenger, M., M. Ermakova, A. Geyken, L. Lemnitzer, and A.
                    Storrer</hi> (2012). A TEI schema for the Representation of the
                Computer-mediated Communication. <hi rend="italic">TEI (Text Encoding Initiative)
                    Journal</hi>. (submitted 2012).</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Biber, D., et al.</hi> (1999). <hi rend="italic">Longman Grammar of
                    Spoken and Written English</hi>. Edinburgh: Pearson.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Biber, D., et al.</hi> (2002). <hi rend="italic">Longman Student
                    Grammar of Spoken and Written English</hi>. Edinburgh: Pearson.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Blake, B. J.</hi> (2008). <hi rend="italic">All About Language</hi>.
                New York: Oxford UP.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Crystal, D.</hi> (2001). <hi rend="italic">Language and the
                    Internet</hi>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Crystal, D.</hi> (2011). <hi rend="italic">Internet Linguistics. A
                    Student Guide.</hi> New York: Routledge.</p>
            <p>[DUDEN-4<hi rend="sup">5</hi>] <hi rend="bold">DUDEN</hi> (1995). <hi rend="italic">Die Grammatik</hi>.
                5th ed. Mannheim: Bibliographisches Institut.</p>
            <p>[DUDEN-4<hi rend="sup">7</hi>] <hi rend="bold">DUDEN</hi> (2005). <hi rend="italic">Die Grammatik</hi>.
                7th ed. Mannheim: Bibliographisches Institut.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Geyken, A. </hi>(2007). The DWDS corpus: A reference corpus for the
                German language of the 20th century. In Ch. Fellbaum (ed.), <hi rend="italic"
                    >Collocations and Idioms</hi>. London: Continuum, pp. 23-40.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Geyken, A., and Th. Hanneforth</hi> (2006). TAGH – A Complete
                Morphology for German based on Weighted Finite State Automata. In: A. Yli-Jyrä, L. Karttunen, and J. Karhumäki (eds),<hi rend="italic"> Finite State Methods and Natural Language
                    Processing – Proceedings of FSMNLP, 5th international workshop,</hi> Helsinki
                2005, Heidelberg: Springer (= Lecture Notes in Artificial Ingelligence 4002), pp.
                55-66.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Greenbaum, S.</hi> (1996). <hi rend="italic">The Oxford English
                    Grammar</hi>. New York: Oxford UP.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Herring, S. C. </hi>(1996). Introduction. In: S. C. Herring (ed.),
                    <hi rend="italic">Computer-Mediated Communication. Linguistic, Social and
                    Cross-Cultural Perspectives</hi>. Amsterdam/Philadelphia: John Benjamins, pp.
                1-10.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Herring, S. C., ed.</hi> (1996). <hi rend="italic">Computer-Mediated
                    Communication. Linguistic, Social and Cross-Cultural Perspectives</hi>.
                Amsterdam/Philadelphia: John Benjamins.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Herring, S. C., ed.</hi> (2010). Computer-Mediated Conversation, Part
                I. <hi rend="italic">Special Issue of Language@Internet</hi> 7. 
                <ref target="http://www.languageatinternet.org/articles/2010" type="external">http://www.languageatinternet.org/articles/2010</ref> (accessed 11 March 2012)</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Jurish, B.</hi> (2003). A Hybrid Approach to Part-of-Speech Tagging,
                Final report. <hi rend="italic">Project ‘Kollokationen im Wörterbuch’</hi>.
                Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften, Berlin. <ref
                    target="http://www.ling.uni-potsdam.de/~moocow/pubs/dwdst-report.pdf"
                    type="external">http://www.ling.uni-potsdam.de/~moocow/pubs/dwdst-report.pdf</ref>  (accessed 11 March
                2012)</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">McArthur, T., ed.</hi> (1998). <hi rend="italic">Concise Oxf</hi><hi
                    rend="italic">ord Companion to the English Language</hi>. Oxford: Oxford UP.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Reynaert, N., O. Oostdijk, H. de Clercq, et al.</hi>
                (2010). Balancing SoNaR: IPR versus Processing Issues in a 500-Million-Word Written
                Dutch Reference Corpus. In <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Seventh conference
                    on International Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC’10)</hi>. Paris,
                2693-2698. Online:
                <ref target="http://eprints.eemcs.utwente.nl/18001/01/LREC2010_549_Paper_SoNaR.pdf" type="external">http://eprints.eemcs.utwente.nl/18001/01/LREC2010_549_Paper_SoNaR.pdf</ref></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Runkehl, K., T. Siever, and P. Schlobinski</hi> (1998). <hi
                    rend="italic">Sprache und Kommunikation im Internet. Überblick und
                    Analysen.</hi> Opladen: Westdeutscher Verlag.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Schiffrin, D.</hi> (1986). <hi rend="italic">Discourse markers</hi>.
                Cambridge: Cambridge UP.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Storrer, A.</hi> (2012, in press). Sprachstil und Sprachvariation in
                sozialen Netzwerken. In B. Frank-Job, A. Mehler, and T. Sutter (eds.), <hi
                    rend="italic">Die Dynamik sozialer und sprachlicher Netzwerke. Konzepte,
                    Methoden und empirische Untersuchungen an Beispielen des WWW.</hi> Wiesbaden: VS
                Verlag für Sozialwissenschaften.</p>
            <p>[TEI-P5] <hi rend="bold">TEI Consortium</hi> (eds., 2007). <hi rend="italic">TEI P5:
                    Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange.</hi>
                <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5/"
                type="external">http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5/</ref> (accessed 11 March 2012).</p>
            <p>[WDG]: <hi rend="bold">Klappenbach, R., and W. Steinitz, eds.</hi> (1964-1977). <hi
                    rend="italic">Wörterbuch der deutschen Gegenwartssprache (WDG).</hi> 6 Bände.
                Berlin: Akademie-Verlag.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Werry, C. C.</hi> (1996). Linguistic and interactional features of
                Internet Relay Chat. In S. C. Herring (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Computer-Mediated
                    Communication. Linguistic, Social and Cross-Cultural Perspectives</hi>.
                Amsterdam/Philadelphia: John Benjamins, pp. 47-63.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Zifonun, G., L. Hoffmann, B. Strecker, et al., eds.</hi> (1997). <hi
                    rend="italic">Grammatik der deutschen Sprache.</hi> 3 Bände. Berlin, New York:
                de Gruyter.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>