<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-344">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Ptolemy’s Geography and the Birth of GIS</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Isaksen, Leif</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Southampton, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>leifuss@googlemail.com</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Geographike hyphegesis
                    </hi>of Claudius Ptolemy (c. 90-c. 168 CE) – more commonly known as the ‘<hi
                        rend="italic">Geography</hi>’ but hereafter referred to as <hi rend="italic"
                        >GH </hi>– is perhaps the most important text in the history of digital
                    cartography. While its fame derives from the enormous catalogue of ancient
                    places that have made it indispensable for those studying ancient geography, its
                    central innovations of presenting locations as tables of coordinates and
                    offering multiple projections by which to represent them make it the
                    foundational work for all modern Geographic Information Systems (GIS). Yet
                    despite this historic legacy it remains a deeply problematic text (Dilke 1987).
                    The sheer quantity, breadth and apparent precision of the catalogue greatly
                    surpass that of every other known work of ancient geography. How did a lone
                    scholar, working with only published materials, compile such a comprehensive
                    overview of the inhabited world (<hi rend="italic">oikumene</hi>)? And what
                    provoked his revolutionary shift in methodology?</p>
            <p>Several research
                    projects have used digital methods to examine aspects of Ptolemy’s Geography in
                    recent years. Most significant is Stückelberger and Graßhoff’s database of
                    coordinates (2006) which forms the baseline data for the research presented.
                    Despite creating this excellent resource, their analysis (Stückelberger &amp;
                    Mittenhuber 2009) remains a fairly traditional close reading of the text, makes
                    scant explicit use of the digital data. Tsorlini (2009) used digital methods to
                    show coordinate discrepancies between different manuscripts, although these
                    largely focus on the medieval maps, the provenance of which remains unclear
                    (Mittenhuber 2010). Kleineberg et al. used digital transformations in order to
                    ‘georectify’ the coordinates in the region of Germania Magna and thus propose
                    the identification of many hitherto unidentified locations with modern sites
                    (2010).</p>
            <p>Conventional wisdom is that <hi rend="italic">GH</hi> is the culmination of a long
                tradition of Greek geographical and astronomical science, augmented and improved at
                each stage by contemporary sources such as merchant’s reports, itineraries and
                astronomical observations (Berggren &amp; Jones 2000: 25-30). This paper will
                present several arguments based on digital methods to demonstrate that this view is
                almost certainly wrong and that Ptolemy’s treatise is a highly original work that
                fuses two distinct traditions for a specific purpose: the calculation of local
                celestial and solar phenomena for astrological prognostication. This goal required
                the combined data of Greek <hi rend="italic">geographic maps</hi> – which
                represented the inhabited world schematically but in relation to cosmological
                constants such as the poles and equator – and Roman <hi rend="italic">chorographic
                    maps</hi>, which represented the world in a series of densely populated but
                geospatially unanchored regional images. It was the challenge of bringing together
                these very different traditions which led Ptolemy to apply the data management
                techniques he had used for astronomical data in the <hi rend="italic">Almagest</hi>
                and thus the lay the groundwork for late medieval geography and ultimately the GIS
                systems of today. </p>
            <p>While
                        <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities</hi> is not the forum to lay out a full
                    argument for Ptolemy’s motives and the nature of his sources – which will be
                    expressed in a forthcoming paper – the following preliminary points should be
                    made. First, his astrological ambitions are no surprise. Ptolemy’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Tetrabiblos</hi> became the principle work on the topic for
                    almost a millennium and he explicitly refers to the practice of calculating
                    celestial phenomena for terrestrial locations in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Almagest</hi> (2.3; 8.6), <hi rend="italic">GH</hi> itself (1.1; 8.2) and
                    the <hi rend="italic">Manual to the Handy Tables</hi>. No other practical motive
                    is given for <hi rend="italic">GH</hi>’s construction and thus there is no
                    reason to believe that it was ever intended for an alternative purpose. The
                    second point is that while we have virtually no extant examples of pre-Ptolemaic
                    geographic or chorographic maps, the written sources – including Ptolemy’s
                    distinction between the two practices in <hi rend="italic">GH</hi> (1.1) – offer
                    some important clues. The mathematical precision of <hi rend="italic"
                        >geographia</hi> is explicitly stated by Ptolemy, but evidence as to the
                    paucity of its content can be adduced from fragments of the three authors most
                    likely to have been sources to Ptolemy – Eratosthenes, Hipparchus and Marinos of
                    Tyre. Ignoring those on the Persian Royal Road, the places they mention are
                    overwhelmingly (~90%) located on coastlines and boundaries. This is stark
                    contrast to <hi rend="italic">GH</hi> in which interior locations outnumber
                    liminal ones by about 3:2. In contrast, both Ptolemy and Strabo (<hi
                        rend="italic">Geog</hi>. 2.5.17) refer to the richness of chorographic
                    content but a strong indication of their unsuitability for astrology is given by
                    the absence of any geodetic information for the Agrippan ‘World Map’ and other
                    chorographic sources.</p>
            
            <div>
            <head>Statistical distributions of precision</head>
                <p>Ptolemy’s coordinates are expressed as fractions of a degree of latitude
                    (measured from the equator) and longitude (measured from an arbitrarily defined
                    prime meridian in the Atlantic ocean). Superficial examination makes clear that
                    the smallest latitudinal and longitudinal increment is 1/12 of a degree (or 5
                    minutes) of arc. As real world locations are themselves distributed randomly, we
                    would expect a relatively even distribution of Ptolemaic locations with respect
                    to the fraction of degree upon which they fall. In fact their distribution is
                    highly uneven (Figure 1), a phenomenon also observed by Marx (2011). We know
                    that some locations (which we shall refer to as ‘high precision’ locations) must
                    have been assigned to the nearest twelfth of a degree, as they fall on divisions
                    that are indivisible by lower denominators.<note>At 5 minutes (1/12), 25 minutes (5/12), 35 minutes (7/12) and 55 minutes (11/12)</note> However,
                    the uneven distribution makes it clear that significantly more of the
                    coordinates are assigned at lower levels of precision: sometimes just to the
                    nearest degree. The challenge is to establish which of them have been plotted
                    more or less precisely. While it is not possible to do this by considering each
                    location individually the fact that Ptolemy’s principles are so closely aligned
                    with GIS make it an ideal tool for investigating the data’s underlying
                    structure.</p>
                
                <p><figure><graphic url="img344-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 1: Quantity of coordinates falling on latitudinal (white) and longitudinal (black) degree divisions (in minutes)</head></figure></p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>Spatial distribution of precision</head>
                <p>The first clues as to the spatial distribution of ‘high precision’ locations
                    emerge from plotting all locations which are definitely assigned to the nearest
                    twelfth of a degree in a GIS<note>Those that fall on the traditional 2nd, 4th, 11th, 12th, 13th, anti-2nd and anti-4th Greek parallels (which also happen to be ‘high precision’ for arbitrary reasons) have also been removed here for reasons which will become clear.</note> (Figure 2). This
                    demonstrates beyond all doubt that a core body of data – comprising Hispania,
                    Italia and its major island neighbours, Greece, Asia Minor, the Levant and Egypt
                    – contains virtually all known coordinates assigned to this high level of
                    precision. The phenomenon appears in both manuscript traditions. In contrast,
                    the peripheral regions, which include such well-established roman regions as
                    Gaul and Africa Proconsularis, are almost entirely devoid of ‘high precision’
                    locations. Furthermore, although latitude is generally more likely to be of high
                    precision than longitude, this is not caused by the well-known ‘Problem of
                    longitude’ (Sobel 1995). Latitude can be hopelessly incorrect in some ‘high
                    precision’ regions (such as Sardinia) so it is evident that these values have
                    not been determined from empirical measurements.</p>
                
                <p><figure><graphic url="img344-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 2: Coordinates know to be assigned at a precision of 1/12 of a degree of latitude or longitude. The effect is observed in both <foreign>Ξ</foreign> (black) and <foreign>Ω</foreign> (red) recensionsFigure 2: Coordinates know to be assigned at a precision of 1/12 of a degree of latitude or longitude. The effect is observed in both <foreign>Ξ</foreign> (black) and <foreign>Ω</foreign> (red) recensions</head></figure></p>
               
                </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>Linear interpolation</head>
                <p>The order in which Ptolemy’s coordinates are listed is not random. The
                    description of each region follows a strict sequence commencing with boundaries,
                    followed by physical geography, continuing with inland cities and concluding
                    with offshore islands. The boundaries and physical features are typically linear
                    in form and so topographically adjacent locations are listed consecutively to
                    facilitate the drawing of lines or iconography between them. Islands are also
                    listed in the sequence in which they follow a coastline wherever possible. Much
                    more interesting for this analysis are the cities of the interior, for there is
                    no natural order for Ptolemy to follow and so they may betray information as to
                    the manner in which they were obtained.</p>
           <p>We can visualize this order
                    very easily by simply ‘joining the dots’ in sequence and colour coding the
                    individual regions. Once again, the results display a striking disparity between
                    the core regions and the periphery. In the core data, coordinates group together
                    in tightly bunched clusters. At the periphery they are generally ‘sketched out’
                    in linear zig-zagging rows, usually horizontally (Europe, much of Asia) or
                    vertically (Africa), but occasionally in a NE-SW sweep (India). A comparison
                    with the ‘high precision’ coordinates over these features clearly demonstrates a
                    correlation between this stylistic variation and the ‘core’ data we identified
                    previously (Figure 3).</p>
                
                <p><figure><graphic url="img344-3.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 3: Detail showing lines interpolated between settlements overlaid with ’high precision’ coordinates</head></figure></p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                
                <head>Two Coordinate Systems</head>
                <p>We can push this further. Despite the apparent regularity of Ptolemy’s 180 x 360
                    coordinate grid (first developed by Hipparchus (Dicks 1960: 32-33)), he also
                    makes reference to a traditional series of irregular Greek parallels (based on
                    the length of the longest day) and tripartite divisions of the ‘hour intervals’
                    - the ‘time-zones’ of antiquity. So which coordinate system is Ptolemy using?
                    The answer is most clearly illustrated by examining Ptolemy’s regional map of
                    Arabia Felix and Karmania. Ptolemy lists a series of tribal and geographic
                    divisions along the coast of the Arabian peninsula and it is apparent that their
                    locations are defined with reference to the traditional coordinate system
                    (Figure 4). Yet the interior, which contains no differentiation and is simply a
                    list of towns conforms, to the entirely separate Hipparchan framework (Figure
                    5).</p>
                <p>We must be careful to jump to conclusions too readily for, as we
                    have seen, there is much regional variation in Ptolemy’s sources, but a
                    consistent pattern emerges in both core and periphery. Boundaries make reference
                    to the coarse-grained and irregular, traditional Greek framework whereas
                    internal cities generally conform to the fine-grained and regular coordinate
                    system. Returning to our earlier argument, there is an obvious explanation.
                    Ptolemy’s goals required him to use Greek <hi rend="italic">geographic</hi> maps
                    as a framework if he was to compare terrestrial and celestial locations. Yet we
                    know that the data they provide is scanty. His solution was to peg <hi
                        rend="italic">chorographic</hi> maps to this global framework, thereby
                    eliminating systemic error at the cost of local accuracy.</p>

                <p><figure><graphic url="img344-4.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 4: Ptolemy’s map of Arabia Felix and Karmania showing how tribal divisions and
                            structure are associated with traditional Greek parallels and divisions
                            of ‘hour intervals’</head></figure></p>
                <p><figure><graphic url="img344-5.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 5: Ptolemy’s map of Arabia Felix and Karmania showing how the order of undifferentiated cities of the interior is influenced by the Hipparchan coordinate system</head></figure></p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
        
            <p><hi rend="bold">Berggren, J. L., and A. Jones</hi> (2000). <hi rend="italic"
                        >Ptolemy’s Geography. An Anntoated Translation of the Theoretical
                        Chapters.</hi> Princeton: Princeton UP.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Dicks, D. R.</hi> (1960). <hi rend="italic">The Geographical
                    Fragments of Hipparchus.</hi> London: Athlone Press.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Dilke, O. A. W.</hi> (1987). The Culmination of Greek Cartography in
                    Ptolemy. In J. B. Harly and D. Woodward (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The History of
                        Cartography.</hi> Chicago: U of Chicago P, vol. 1, pp. 177-200.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Kleineberg, A., et al. (</hi>2010). <hi rend="italic">Germania und
                    die Insel Thule.</hi> Darmstadt: Wissenschaftliche Buchgesellschaft.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Marx, C.</hi> (2011). On the precision of Ptolemy’s geographic
                coordinates in his Geographike Hyphegesis. <hi rend="italic">History of Geo- and
                    Space Sciences</hi> 2(1): 29-37. </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Mercier, R.</hi> (2011). <hi rend="italic">Ptolemaiou Procheiroi
                    Kanones. Ptolemy’s Handy Tables</hi>. Leuven: Peeters.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Sobel, D.</hi> (1995). Longitude. The True Story of a Lone Genius Who
                Solved the Greatest Scientific Problem of His Time. London: Fourth Estate.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Jones, H. L.</hi> (1917). The Georgraphy of Strabo. London:
                Heinemann, vol. 1.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Stückelberger, A., and G. Graßhoff</hi> (2006). <hi rend="italic"
                    >Ptolemaios. Handbuch der Geographie.</hi> Basel: Schwabe.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Stückelberger, A., and F. Mittenhuber</hi> (2009). <hi rend="italic"
                        >Ptolemaios. Handbuch der Geographie.</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ergänzungsband.</hi> Basel: Schwabe.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Toomer, G. J.</hi> (1984). <hi rend="italic">Ptolemy’s Almagest</hi>,
                London: Duckworth.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Tsorlini, A.</hi> (2009). Higher Order Systematic Effect in Ptolemy’s
                Geographia Coordinate Description of Iberia. <hi rend="italic">e-Perimetron</hi>
                4(2): 117-130.</p>

</div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>