<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-370">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Digital Mellini Project: Exploring New Tools &amp; Methods for Art-historical Research &amp; Publication</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Rodríguez, Nuria</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Málaga, Spain</affiliation>
                    <email>nro@uma.es</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Baca, Murtha</name>
                    <affiliation>Getty Research Institute, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>mbaca@getty.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Albrezzi, Francesca</name>
                    <affiliation>Getty Research Institute, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>falbrezzi@getty.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Longaker, Rachel</name>
                    <affiliation>Getty Research Institute, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>rlongaker@getty.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Background</head>
                <p>This paper will present the project <hi rend="italic">Digital Mellini:</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Exploring New Tools &amp; Methods for Art-historical
                            Research &amp; Publication</hi>, a joint initiative of the Getty
                        Research Institute (Los Angeles) and the University of Málaga (Spain). This
                        paper shall discuss several aspects and challenges related to the
                        development of digital resources for art-historical research.</p><p>The main
                        objectives for the <hi rend="italic">Digital Mellini</hi> Project
                        are:</p>
                <xmt:oList rend="arabic">
                <item>To explore new methods and tools with which to reinvent the
                        concept of scholarly work and critical publishing in the field of
                        humanities, particularly in the context of art history, in which the
                        convergence of text and image is essential and provides an interesting
                        context for research – a context that has not yet been adequately
                        investigated.<note>Nevertheless, interesting research has been carried out on linking images to text. See Zweig 1998</note></item><item>To create a methodological model for developing collaborative digital publications that
                        incorporate texts, digital facsimiles, images, computational tools for
                        linguistic analysis and visual communication, and forums for exchanging
                        ideas and sharing knowledge. The ultimate goal is that the international
                        community of specialists can utilize this methodological model and apply to
                        a variety of art-historical projects.</item>
                </xmt:oList>
                <p>These objectives can be seen within the framework of the recent growing interest
                    that many of us in the art-historical community have in response to the
                    challenges offered by the digital society – we need to analyze and reflect
                    critically on the ‘digital status’ of the discipline of art history from both
                    the methodological and epistemological perspectives. We must be willing to open
                    innovative and creative paths in the design of digital resources for
                    art-historical research – paths that will lead to new lines of investigation and
                    new methods of and attitudes toward information-sharing.</p>
                <p>Art historians
                        must participate in the development of tools in the Digital Humanities. In
                        an article published in the <hi rend="italic">Chronicle of Higher
                            Education</hi> in 2009,</p>
                <p>Johanna Drucker pointed out that many of the critical debates that have
                    characterized the development of the humanities in recent decades – subjectivity
                    of interpretation, multicultural perspectives, a recognition of the social
                    nature of the production of knowledge, etc. – are absent in the design of
                    digital resources. Instead, more emphasis has been placed on adapting to the
                    characteristics of digital media than to the epistemological and interpretive
                    exigencies of the various humanistic disciplines.<note>‘Many humanities
                        principles developed in hard-fought critical battles of the last decades are
                        absent in the design of digital contexts (…) For too long, the digital
                        humanities, the advanced research arm of humanistic scholarly dialogue with
                        computational methods, has taken its rules and cues from digital exigencies’
                        (Drucker 2009).</note> Lev Manovich made similar observations in a Digital
                    Humanities conference held in June 2009 in Maryland, when he asked, ‘Is it
                    sufficient to borrow techniques from the fields of computer science, information
                    visualization and media art – or do we need to develop new techniques specific
                    to the humanities?’ (Manovich 2009: xv).</p>
                
                <p>Regarding the hope that Digital Humanities will assume
                        this new role, we perceive the need to build environments that are
                        intellectually productive and will facilitate interpretive and critical
                        studies above and beyond simple information systems designed for the storage
                        and retrieval of data.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Digital Mellini
                            Project</hi> is a response to these challenges, as the aim of the
                        project is to contribute to the development of virtual research environments
                        (VRE) to promote critical research in the field of art history.</p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Digital Mellini</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Project</hi> includes another desideratum that has emerged
                        in recent years: the production of knowledge based on aggregation and
                        collaboration. The culture of open, shared knowledge, which was already
                        being promulgated by UNESCO as early as 2005 as a fundamental way to
                        transition from the information society to the knowledge society, along with
                        the possibilities offered by Web 2.0 technologies, is an essential factor
                        within the evolution of digital scholarship.</p>
                <p>There are already
                        several projects oriented toward the development of collaborative
                        environments (NINES<note><ref target="http://www.nines.org/" type="external">http://www.nines.org/</ref> (accessed 15
                            October 2011).</note>, The VRE-SDM Project<note>Virtual workspace for the study
                                of Ancient Documents, University of Oxford. <ref
                                    target="http://bvreh.humanities.ox.ac.uk/VRE-SDM"
                                    type="external">http://bvreh.humanities.ox.ac.uk/VRE-SDM</ref> (accessed 15 October
                                2011).</note><hi rend="italic">, </hi>The Transcribe Bentham
                            Project<note><ref target="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/transcribe-bentham/"
                                type="external">http://www.ucl.ac.uk/transcribe-bentham/</ref> (accessed 15 October
                                2011)</note>, etc.); and there is a burgeoning
                        bibliography on this topic (Deegan &amp; McCarty 2011). Proof of this
                        interest has also been shown by the high percentage of presentations that
                        dealt with this problem in the last Digital Humanities conference, held at
                        Stanford University in June 2011.</p>
                <p>Electronic publications and digital
                        editions are not new in the realm of Digital Humanities; the first
                        reflections on what an electronic edition might be appeared in Finneran (1996) and Bornstein and Tinkle (1998). There are also reflections and proposals
                        relating to collaborative editions of unpublished manuscripts in which a
                        dispersed community of scholars could add annotations, as in the case of the
                        Peirce Project (Neuman et al. 1992) and the Codex Leningradensis (Leningrad Codex Markup Project 2000).</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, as Susan Hockey
                        (2004) states in her summary of the history of Digital Humanities, ‘The
                        technical aspects of this are fairly clear. Perhaps less clear is the
                        management of the project, who controls or vets the annotations, and how it
                        might all be maintained for the future’.</p>
                <p>Similarly, the <hi
                            rend="italic">Digital Mellini Project</hi> intends to continue this line
                        of research, addressing the questions that still remain open and launching
                        new ones, cultivating debate and reflection.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Digital Mellini Project: development and intellectual
                        questions</head>
                <p>The Digital Mellini Project focuses on a particular text, an unpublished
                    manuscript written in 1681 by Pietro Mellini, a Roman nobleman. This text
                    belongs to the Getty Research Library, Special Collections, found under the
                    title <hi rend="italic">Relatione migliori di Casa delle pittura Melini</hi>.
                    Pietro Mellini poetically described the best works as he inventoried the
                    collection of his family’s paintings. This text carries a self-interest for art
                    historical research due to its uniqueness – it is the only document known to
                    date that has a hybrid composition of ekphrastic description in poetic form with
                    a factual descriptive inventory. In addition, it is an important source for
                    studies related to collecting, the market valuation of art, the provenance of
                    collections, etc. Most of the works are unidentified and to analyze their
                    possible allocations through the descriptions provided by Pietro Mellini is a
                    very attractive task for art historians. Lastly, this text gives us an
                    opportunity to explore the possibilities that digital media offers to deepen the
                    relationships between text and image. One of the objectives of the critical
                    edition is to establish hypotheses about the identity of the works described
                    within the manuscript.</p>
                <p>To carry out this critical collaborative edition, the Digital Mellini Project is
                    developing a computational prototype. Exploring the possibilities of Drupal, a
                    digital environment is being designed and conceived specifically to this
                    analytic objective. Currently, the project team has completed an alpha version
                    of the digital workspace. The first prototype of a beta version is expected to
                    be finished by the end of 2012.</p>
                <p>This prototype was constructed around the object of the critical edition,
                    Mellini’s text, and it includes:</p>
               
                <xmt:uList>
                    <item>text itself - A diplomatic transcription encoded in XML-TEI, translations
                        into English and Spanish, and a digital facsimile – provided in an interface
                        that allows comparative analysis [Fig. 1];</item>
                </xmt:uList>
                
                    <p>
                        <figure>
                            <graphic url="img370-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                                mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 1</head>
                        </figure></p>
                <xmt:uList>    
                <item>A representative image gallery, consisting of images of works proposed by
                        experts as possible identifications of the paintings described by Mellini.
                        Additionally, provisions within the environment make it possible to
                        establish comparisons between images and with the linguistic descriptions,
                        so scholars can deepen the analysis of the word-image relationship; </item>
                    <item>Tools to complement or extend into other areas of research. For example, a
                        repository of thematic texts and/or those structurally related to the
                        Mellini’s text.</item>
                    <item>Tools for aggregating critical annotations to the text. These annotations
                        can be written by each participating scholar, according to a methodology of
                        action and interaction developed for this purpose. Also, these annotations
                        can be arranged as a response or reply to other entries, thus generating a
                        critical debate among the community of scholars participating [Fig.
                        2].</item>
                    <item>Space for debate and reflection on issues related to the text where it can
                        be more broadly discussed.</item>
                </xmt:uList>
                
                <p><figure><graphic url="img370-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 2</head></figure></p>
                
                <p>Note, therefore, that what is proposed as a digital critical edition is far from
                    the conventional academic model of a print publication, which would exist in a
                    static format as the end result of an interpretive study. The result may have
                    been made ​​by one or several specialists, but in the end, what we find is the
                    proposal of one particular interpretation. It is also far from the digital
                    editions that fit this model (eg Van Gogh Letters Project) or electronic
                    repositories focused mainly on the analysis and exploration of texts (The
                    Orlando Project-History of British Women’s Writing). The proposed model is
                    multifaceted. Digital Mellini simultaneously integrates multiple and sometimes
                    contradictory and paradoxical views. It is open and dynamic. Due to processing
                    system records and the dialogue between specialists in the critical annotation
                    process, we can reconstruct the interpretive process itself, as aggregation and
                    contributions grow over time. Therefore, the digital edition is not only the end
                    product of a study and/or research, but also the intellectual and interpretive
                    process through which it unfolds.</p>
                <p>In the digital edition, in addition to showing this prototype and its
                    performance, we will address in more detail the intellectual and methodological
                    questions that confront us while developing a resource of this kind, taking into
                    consideration the goal of advancing digital scholarship in the field of art
                    history and the Humanities in general. These topics include:</p>
                <xmt:oList rend="arabic">
                    <item>How to show different viewpoints contributed by specialists, and
                        displaying through visual means the diversity of interpretations and
                        perspectives that converge simultaneously on a text from different contexts
                        – geographical, ideological, theoretical, methodology, etc.?</item>
                    <item>How to deal with the problem of linguistic variability in a multilingual
                        community of specialists without circumscribing to the most prevalent
                        language?</item>
                    <item>How to face the problem of authorship? How to maintain the legitimate
                        intellectual property rights of each participant in a publication that
                        emerges from the aggregation of many?</item>
                    <item>What are the real behaviors and research practices of art historians using
                        such environments? Do these practices lead to the emergence of a new
                        art-historical knowledge of a digital nature or not?</item>
                    <item>How to develop specific methodologies and protocols for action to guide,
                        assist, and coordinate the participation and interaction of specialists in
                        this type of environment?</item>
                    <item>How to encourage the participation of specialists in the context of an
                        academic system that does not ‘recognize’ the work developed in these
                        digital environments? For example, what kind of scientific production –
                        monographs, articles, papers – are contributions that fit within critical
                        annotations to a digital edition when referenced in an academic CV? Should
                        we think, then, of the incorporation of new categories of scientific
                        production in line with the specificities of digital media?</item>
                </xmt:oList>
                <p>Finally, the conclusive question: how can the discipline of art history move away
                    from single authorial models toward more open, collaborative models of research
                    and publication? </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
                
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Bornstein, G., and T. Tinkle</hi> (1998). <hi rend="italic"
                            >The Iconic Page in Manuscript, Print, and Digital Culture</hi>. Ann
                        Arbor: U of Michigan P. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Deegan, M., and W.
                            McCarty</hi> (2011). <hi rend="italic">Collaborative Research in the
                            Digital Humanities</hi>. Surrey: Ashgate. </p><p><hi rend="bold"
                            >Drucker, J</hi>. (2009). Blind Spots. Humanist must plan their digital
                        future. <hi rend="italic">The Chronicle Review</hi> 55, is. 30.  <ref
                            target="http://chronicle.com/free/v55/i30/30b00601.htm" type="external"
                        >http://chronicle.com/free/v55/i30/30b00601.htm</ref> (acessed 15 October
                        2011).</p><p><hi rend="bold">Finneran, R. J</hi>. (1996). <hi rend="italic"
                            >The Literary Text in the Digital Age</hi>. Ann Arbor: U of Michigan P.
                            </p><p><hi rend="bold">Hockey, S</hi>. (2004). The History of Humanities
                        Computing. In S. Schreibman, R. Siemens, and J. Unsworth, eds (2004), <hi
                            rend="italic">A Companion to Digital Humanities. </hi>Oxford: Blackwell.
                             <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companion/"
                                type="external">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/companion/</ref> (accessed 15 October 2011).
                            </p><p><hi rend="bold">Leningrad Codex Markup Project</hi> (2000). <hi
                            rend="italic">Project </hi><hi rend="italic">‘</hi><hi rend="italic"
                            >EL</hi><hi rend="italic">’</hi><hi rend="italic">: The XML Leningrad
                            Codex</hi>. <ref target="http://www.leningradensis.org"
                                type="external">http://www.leningradensis.org</ref> (accessed 15 October 2011).</p><p><hi
                            rend="bold">Manovich, L</hi>. (2009). Activating The Archive, or: Data
                        Dandy Meets Data Mining. In<hi rend="italic"> Digital Humanities 2009</hi>.
                        Conference abstract. Maryland: Maryland Institute for Technology in the
                        Humanities, p. xv. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Neuman, M., M. Keeler, C. Kloesel,
                            J. Ransdell,  and A. Renear</hi> (1992). The Pilot Project of the
                        Electronic Peirce Consortium. In <hi rend="italic">ALLC-ACH92 Conference
                            Abstracts and Program.</hi> Oxford, pp. 25-27.</p><p><hi rend="bold"
                            >Rodríguez Ortega, N</hi>. (2010). Digital Resources for Art-Historical
                        Research: Critical Approach. In <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities Annual
                            Conference 2010. Books of Abstracts. </hi>London: Office for Humanities
                        Communication – Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King’s College, pp.
                        199-201. </p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Rodríguez Ortega, N</hi>. (2010). La cultura histórico-artística
                    y la Historia del Arte en la sociedad digital. Una reflexión crítica sobre los
                    modos de hacer Historia del Arte en un nuevo contexto. <hi rend="italic">Museo y
                        Territorio</hi> 2-3: 9-26.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Zweig, R. W</hi>. (1998).
                        Lessons from the Palestine Post Project.<hi rend="italic"> Literary and
                            Linguistic Computing</hi> 13: 89–97. </p><p><hi rend="bold">UNESCO</hi>
                        (2005). <hi rend="italic">Hacia las sociedades del conocimiento.</hi> París:
                        Ediciones UNESCO.</p>
                
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>