<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-331">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Aiding the Interpretation of Ancient Documents</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Roued-Cunliffe, Henriette</name>
                    <affiliation>Centre for the Study of Ancient Documents, University of Oxford, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>henriette.roued@classics.ox.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            
                <p>How can Decision Support System (DSS) software aid the interpretation process
                    involved in the reading of ancient documents? This paper discusses the
                    development of a DSS prototype for the reading of ancient texts. In this context
                    the term ‘ancient documents’ is used to describe mainly Greek and Latin texts
                    and the term ‘scholars’ is used to describe readers of these documents (e.g.
                    papyrologists, epigraphers, palaeographers). However, the results from this
                    research can be applicable to many other texts ranging from Nordic runes to 18th
                    Century love letters. </p><p>In order to develop an appropriate tool it is
                    important first to comprehend the interpretation process involved in reading
                    ancient documents. This is not a linear process but rather a recursive process
                    where the scholar moves between different levels of reading, such as
                    ‘understanding the meaning of a character’ or ‘understanding the meaning of a
                    phrase’ (Youtie 1963; Terras 2006). This realization has been paramount to the
                    development of the DSS prototype.</p>
                   <div><head>Aiding, not making decisions</head>
                    <p>When examining whether a tool such as DSS can aid the reading of ancient
                        documents it is important first to realize what such a tool can and should
                        do and what it cannot and should not do. I did not set out to develop a tool
                        that could automate the process of reading ancient documents without human
                        interaction. Firstly, I did not wish to see humans removed from this
                        interpretational process and replaced with robotics.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">Good reading is a reflective as well as a sensational
                        process which engages our abstract mental faculties, and we give it up at
                        our peril </hi>(Deegan &amp; Sutherland 2009: viii).</p>
                    <p>Secondly, interpretation is a part of the ‘higher levels of analytic and
                        creative functions which are the prerogative of the human mind’ (Busa 1980:
                        89) and the symbol-processing powers of a computer should not be mistaken
                        for this (Jonscher 2000: 149).</p>
                    <p>Instead this research has examined how the use of DSS technology can support
                        the interpretative process, among other things, by remembering the complex
                        reasoning that forms a large part of this interpretation process.
                        Remembering decisions and the complex reasoning leading up to decisions is
                        something that DSS is good at. The DSS prototype has demonstrated how this
                        is possible. </p>
                    <p>Furthermore the prototype has demonstrated other aspects of reading ancient
                        documents, apart from the interpretation process, where IT tools can provide
                        support such as searching huge datasets and the automated publishing of
                        editions.</p></div>
                
                    <div><head>The DSS Prototype</head>
                    <p>The prototype was developed as a proof of concept. First I used existing
                        research on reading ancient documents (Bowman &amp; Brady 2005; Terras 2006;
                        Tarte 2011) to model the network of interpretation (Roued-Cunliffe 2010),
                        and then I developed the DSS prototype to demonstrate how a DSS can aid the
                        interpretation process based on this model. </p>
                        <p><figure>
                        <graphic url="img331-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>Figure 1: Screenshot from the DSS prototype (Roued-Cunliffe 2012:
                            87)</head>
                    </figure></p>
                        
            <p>The prototype (Fig. 1) demonstrates how it would be possible to input data and
                    edit the structure and meaning of a document on different levels. Scholars can
                    begin by entering basic structure such as line or character elements and work
                    back and forth between this level and higher levels such as editing the meaning
                    of a letter or word. Furthermore, the prototype enables scholars to use the
                    letters and character elements they have input to search relevant corpora
                    databases for possible parallels. </p><p>The prototype uses the concept of
                    argumentation, which can be defined as ‘the process of constructing arguments
                    about propositions, and the assignment of statements of confidence to those
                    propositions based on the nature and relative strength of their supporting
                    arguments’ (Fox et al. 1996: 428). In the prototype these statements of
                    confidence are merely whether the user believes the reading to be right or
                    wrong. It does not require users to signify how much they believe in a certain
                    decision. Furthermore, the arguments are either <hi rend="bold">for</hi> or <hi
                        rend="bold">against</hi> the interpretation in question. No matter how many
                    arguments are <hi rend="bold">for</hi> or <hi rend="bold">against</hi> any one
                    interpretation the prototype will not try to persuade the user to make a certain
                    decision. The prototype is first and foremost flexible and user-driven and its
                    role is purely that of a good assistant, reminding users of their own decisions
                    and reflections. </p></div>
                    <div><head>
                        Future DSS</head>
                    <p>The DSS prototype, presented in this paper, has been successful in
                        illustrating how this technology can aid such a complex interpretation
                        process, as is the reading of ancient documents. However, in future this
                        prototype will need to be re-developed to contain, among others, a more
                        advanced user interface. With this in hand it would be possible to conduct
                        user testing, which would give a basis for the development of a fully
                        working DSS. I have a suggestion for a future layer-based system that would
                        be user-friendly and could work well in conjunction with a DSS and other
                        useful tools for aiding the reading of ancient documents.</p>
                        <p><figure>
                        <graphic url="img331-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>Figure 2: Drawing of the layer-based DSS concept (Roued-Cunliffe
                            2012: 132)</head>
                    </figure></p>
                        
            <p>The layer-based system would contain four types of layers that users can swap and
                    switch between so that they can edit the different layers at any time and edit
                    one layer while others are visible below (Fig. 2). The first types of layers are
                    the image layers. These image layers could be the original image of an object,
                    PMT images of an object (Earl et al<hi rend="italic">,</hi> 2011) or enhanced
                    images (e.g. with wood-grain removed or the illumination corrected (Tarte et
                        al<hi rend="italic">, </hi>2011)). The second type of layers are the editor
                    layers which can include a layer for hand-drawn transcriptions of the text, a
                    layer in which to edit the structure of the text (i.e. lines, words, characters
                    and spaces in the text) and a layer in which to add meaning to the text (i.e.
                    this letter is <hi rend="italic">b</hi>). The third type of layers is the DSS
                    layer which would resemble the DSS prototype. The fourth and final type of
                    layers are the suggestion layers from which it would be possible to retrieve for
                    example suggested words from a word search engine based on letters input in the
                    earlier editor layer.  </p></div>
                    <div><head>Conclusion</head>
                    <p>The research presented in this paper aims to illustrate how DSS software
                        could aid the interpretation of ancient documents and has been successful in
                        doing this through the development of the DSS prototype. The DSS prototype
                        covered different areas of the interpretation process from input to
                        argumentation <hi rend="bold">for</hi> and <hi rend="bold">against</hi>
                        different decisions. It has illustrated how DSS software can assist scholars
                        by remembering their complex reasoning and suggesting readings along the
                        way. Furthermore, the research describes an idea for a fully formed future
                        DSS based on the finding from the development of the prototype. </p></div>
                <div>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Acknowledgements</hi></p>
                    <p>This research is a part of the author’s thesis: ‘A Decision Support System
                        for the Reading of Ancient Documents’ at the Faculty of Classics, University
                        of Oxford. It is funded by an AHRC Doctoral Studentship attached to the
                        e-Science and Ancient Documents (eSAD) project
                        (<ref target="http://esad.classics.ox.ac.uk/" type="external">http://esad.classics.ox.ac.uk/</ref>). I wish to thank Prof. Alan Bowman, Prof.
                        Sir Michael Brady, Dr. Melissa Terras, Dr. Segolene Tarte, Dr. Charles
                        Crowther, Margaret Sasanow and John Pybus for their support throughout my
                        research.</p></div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
               
                    <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Bowman, A. K., and M. Brady</hi> (2005). <hi rend="italic">Images
                        and Artefacts of the Ancient World</hi>. London: British Academy.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Busa, R.</hi> (1980). The Annals of Humanities Computing: The
                    Index Thomisticus. <hi rend="italic">Computers and the Humanities</hi> 14:
                    83-90.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Deegan, M., and K. Sutherland</hi> (2009). <hi rend="italic"
                        >Transferred Illusions: Digital Technology and the Forms of Print</hi>.
                    London: Ashgate. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Earl, G., P. Basford, A. Bischoff, A. Bowman, C. Crowther, J.
                        Dahl, M. Hodgson, L. Isaksen, E. Kotoula, K. Martinez, H. Pagi, and K. E.
                        Piquette</hi> (2011). <hi rend="italic">Reflectance Transformation Imaging
                        Systems for Ancient Documentary Artifacts.</hi><ref
                        target="http://ewic.bcs.org/upload/pdf/ewic_ev11_s8paper3.pdf"
                        type="external">http://ewic.bcs.org/upload/pdf/ewic_ev11_s8paper3.pdf</ref>
                     (accessed 07.03.2012)</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Fox, J., P. Krause, and M. Elvang-Gøransson</hi> (1996).
                    Argumentation as a General Framework for Uncertain Reasoning. In D. Heckerman
                    and E. H. Mamdani (eds.), <hi rend="italic">UAI ’93: Proceedings of the Ninth
                        Annual Conference on Uncertainty in Artificial Intelligence, July 9-11,
                        1993, The Catholic University of America, USA</hi>. San Fransisco: Morgan
                    Kaufmann Publishers, pp. 428-434. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Jonscher, C.</hi> (2000).<hi rend="italic"> Wired Life: Who Are
                        We in the Digital Age?</hi> London: Anchor.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Roued-Cunliffe, H.</hi> (2010). Towards an Interpretation Support
                    System for Reading Ancient Documents. <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistics
                        Computing</hi> 25(4): 365-379.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Roued-Cunliffe, H.</hi> (2012). <hi rend="italic">A decision
                        Support System for the Reading of Ancient Documents</hi>. D.Phil Thesis,
                    Classics Faculty, University of Oxford. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Tarte, S.</hi> (2011). Papyroligical Investigations: Transferring
                    Perception and Interpretation into the Digital World. <hi rend="italic">Literary
                        and Linguistics Computing</hi> 26(2): 233-247.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Tarte, S., M. Brady, A. K. Bowman, and M. Terras</hi> (2011).
                    Image Capture and Processing for Enhancing the Legibility of Incised Texts. In
                    V. Vahtikari, M. Hakkarainen, and  A. Nurminnen, <hi rend="italic">Eikonopoiia.
                        </hi><hi rend="italic">Digital Imaging of Ancient Textual Heritage,
                        Technological Challenges and Solutions</hi>. Commentationes Humanarum
                    Litterarum 129. Helsinki: Academy of Finland, pp. 173-88. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Terras, M.</hi> (2006). <hi rend="italic">Image to
                        Interpretation: Intelligent Systems to Aid Historians in the Reading of the
                        Vindolanda Texts</hi>. Oxford Studies in Ancient Documents. Oxford: Oxford
                    UP.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Youtie, H. C.</hi> (1963). The Papyrologist: Artificer of Fact
                        <hi rend="italic">GRBS</hi> 4: 19-32.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>