<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-385">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Bridging Multicultural Communities: Developing a Framework for a European Network of Museum, Libraries and Public Cultural Institutions</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Innocenti, Perla</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Glasgow, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>perla.innocenti@glasgow.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Richards, John</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Glasgow, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>John.Richards@glasgow.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Wieber, Sabine</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Glasgow, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>Sabine.Wieber@glasgow.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            
            <p><hi rend="italic">Global migration is here to stay</hi></p>
                <p>Knut Kjeldstadli<note>Kjeldstadli, Knut (2010). Concepts of nation – and tasks of libraries, Keynote speech at IFLA Section Library Services to Multicultural Populations, IFLA Satellite Meeting, Copenhagen, 17-18 August 2010.</note>
                </p>
           
            
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Traditionally,
                    museums and libraries developed as historically separate institutional contexts
                    and distinct cultures. Trant<note>Trant, Jennife (2004). Emerging convergence? Thoughts on museums, archives, libraries, and professional training. Museum Management and Curatorship 24(4): 369-387.</note> noted how philosophies
                    and policies of museums and libraries reflect their different approach to
                    interpreting, collecting, preserving and providing access to objects in their
                    care. Bishoff remarked that ‘libraries believe in resource sharing, are
                    committed to freely available information, value the preservation of
                    collections, and focus on access to information. Museums believe in preservation
                    of collections, often create their identity based on these collections, are
                    committed to community education, and frequently operate in a strongly
                    competitive environment’<note>Bishoff, Liz (2004). The Collaboration Imperative. Library Journal, 2004. Accessed August 16, 2011. <ref target="http://www.libraryjournal.com/article/CA371048.html" type="external">http://www.libraryjournal.com/article/CA371048.html</ref>.</note>. In the last century policy
                    makers have attempted to group and bridge these communities of practices through
                    ‘their similar role as part of the informal educational structures supported by
                    the public, and their common governance’<note>Trant, Jennifer (2004). Emerging convergence? Thoughts on museums, archives, libraries, and professional training. Museum Management and Curatorship 24(4): 369.</note>. Such
                    commonalities are increasingly important to the sustainability of museums,
                    libraries (and archives) in a globalised world. However a theoretical framework
                    to scope and address such collaborative models still needs to be developed. This
                    is particularly urgent in the specific context of our transnational and
                    multicultural societies.</p>
                <p>One of the goals of the recently funded EU FP7
                    SSH MeLa Project<note>MeLa – European Museums in an Age of Migrations, <ref target="http://www.mela-project.eu/" type="external">http://www.mela-project.eu/</ref>. The work presented in this paper is being conducted within ‘MeLa Research Field 03 - Network of Museums, Libraries and Public Cultural Institutions.’ 
                        <ref target="http://wp3.mela-project.eu/" type="external">http://wp3.mela-project.eu/</ref>. Last accessed September 23, 2011. MeLa Research Field 03 is led by History of Art at the University of Glasgow (GU); the research team include staff members from Politecnico di Milano, Copenhagen Institute of Interaction Design, Museu d’Art Contemporani de Barcelona, Muséum National d’Histoire Naturelle/Musée de l’Homme, The Royal College of Art, L’Orientale University of Naples. 
                    </note>
                    is to fill this gap by investigating,
                    identifying and proposing innovative coordination strategies between public
                    European museums, libraries and public cultural institutions, for the benefit of
                    multicultural audiences and towards European integration and European cultural
                        commons
                    <note>The definition ‘European Cultural Commons’ has been recently used in relation to digital content within the European Cultural Commons conference (<ref target="europeanculturalcommons.eventbrite.com" type="external">europeanculturalcommons.eventbrite.com</ref>, videos at <ref target="http://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLE244178708CBB62C" type="external">http://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLE244178708CBB62C</ref>) organised by Europeana on October 12, 2011. Europeana, an initiative endorsed by the European Commission, is a single access point to millions of books, paintings, films, museum objects and archival records that have been digitised throughout Europe. In this paper we are using the definition in a wider and more general meaning.</note>.
                    The idea of laying the foundations for a
                    European network of museums, libraries and public cultural institutions that
                    address globalisation, migration and new media is particularly fitting for the
                    configuration of migrant communities, which ‘in the receiving countries can best
                    be described from a structural perspective as a network of organizations.’<note>Faist, Thomas (1998). Transnational social spaces out of the international migration: evolution, significance and future prospects. <hi rend="italic">Archives Européennes de Sociologie</hi> 39: 213-247.</note></p>
                </div>
            
                <div>
                <head>Collaborations between Museums and Libraries: Potentialities and Challenges</head>
                    <p>In the first phase of our MeLa research, we have been focusing in particular on collaborations between museums
                        and libraries. Some studies in this area<note>See for example: Hannah Gibson, Anne Morris and Marigold Cleeve (2007). Links between Libraries and Museums: Investigating Museum-Library Collaboration in England and the USA. Libri (57): 53-64. Accessed August 16, 2011 <ref target="www.librijournal.org/pdf/2007-2pp53-64.pdf" type="external">www.librijournal.org/pdf/2007-2pp53-64.pdf</ref>; Diane M. Zorich, Gunter Waibel, and Ricky Erway. Beyond the Silos of the LAMs: Collaboration Among Libraries, Archives and Museums. Report produced for OCLC Research, 2008. Accessed August 16, 2011 <ref target="www.oclc.org/research/publications/library/2008/2008-05.pdf" type="external">www.oclc.org/research/publications/library/2008/2008-05.pdf</ref>; Alexandra Yarrow, Barbara Clubb, and Jennifer-Lynn Draper. Public Libraries, Archives and Museums: Trends in Collaboration and Cooperation. The Hague: IFLA Headquarters, 2008. Accessed August  16, 2011 <ref target="www.ifla.org/VII/s8/pub/Profrep108.pdf" type="external">www.ifla.org/VII/s8/pub/Profrep108.pdf</ref> . The WP3 team is preparing a selected bibliography for the purpose of the workpackage activities.</note> have
                    highlighted the benefits of joining forces and resources in a variety of areas,
                    including but not limited to:</p>
                    
                    <xmt:uList>
                <item>library activities and programmes related to museum exhibits</item>
                <item>travelling museums exhibitions hosted in libraries</item>
                <item>links established between web-based resources in library and museum
                    websites</item>
                <item>library programs including passes to museums</item>
                <item>collaborative digitisation and digital library projects enhancing access
                    to resources in both museums and libraries</item>
                <item>collaborative initiatives to bring in authors as speakers</item>
                <item>museums and libraries partnerships with cultural and education
                    organisational for public programmes.</item>
                    </xmt:uList>
                    
                    
                        <p>The overall opportunities for
                    improving collections, increasing the number of users, leveraging experiences
                    and funding also represent some of the main benefit of such partnerships. These
                    studies also often included archives as a third player in museums and archives
                    collaborations. The aims and objectives of collaboration projects between
                    museums and libraries that have been investigated in previous studies, include:
                    educational focus (e.g. learning about past civilisations, encourage families
                    learning together etc.), cross-over visits between institutions, promoting
                    resources to various target groups, improving coordination between institutions,
                    demonstrating joint working or training activities, providing models for working
                    practices.</p>
                
                <p>The International Federation of Libraries Association (IFLA) remarked that
                    museums and libraries would indeed be natural partners for collaboration and
                        cooperation<note>Yarrow, Alexandra, Barbara Clubb and Jennifer-Lynn Draper.
                        Public Libraries, Archives and Museums: Trends in Collaboration and
                        Cooperation. IFLA Professional Reports N. 108. The Hague: IFLA Headquarters,
                        2008. Accessed August 16, 2011 <ref
                            target="www.ifla.org/VII/s8/pub/Profrep108.pdf" type="external"
                            >www.ifla.org/VII/s8/pub/Profrep108.pdf</ref>.</note>. In this context,
                    a study in the United States observed that ‘collaboration may enable […] museums
                    and libraries to strengthen their public standing, improve their services and
                    programs, and better meet the needs of a larger and more diverse cross-sections
                    of learners.’<note>Charting the Landscape, Mapping New Paths: Museums,
                        Libraries, and K-12 Learning. Institute of Museum and Library Services. Aug.
                        2004. Accessed August 16, 2011 <ref
                            target="http://www.imls.gov/assets/1/AssetManager/Charting_the_Landscape.pdf"
                            type="external"
                            >http://www.imls.gov/assets/1/AssetManager/Charting_the_Landscape.pdf</ref></note>
                    The nature of this collaboration can be multifaceted and varied, and the
                    terminology lends itself to diverse meanings, in particular regarding the degree
                    of intensity of the collaboration and its transformational capacity. Gibson,
                    Morris and Cleeve noted that ‘“<hi rend="italic">Library-museum
                        collaboration</hi>” can be defined as the cooperation between a library and
                    a museum, possibly involving other partners. […].’<note>Gibson, Hannah, Anne
                        Morris and Marigold Cleeve. Links between Libraries and Museums:
                        Investigating Museum-Library Collaboration in England and the USA. Libri
                        (57) 2007: 53-64. Accessed August 16, 2011, p.53 <ref
                            target="www.librijournal.org/pdf/2007-2pp53-64.pdf" type="external"
                            >www.librijournal.org/pdf/2007-2pp53-64.pdf</ref>.</note> Here, the
                    authors use the term ‘collaboration’ with the meaning indicated by Diamant-Cohen
                    and Sherman, as a ‘more involved cooperation where there is a more in-depth
                    sharing and pooling of resources.’<note>Diamant-Cohen, Betsy, and Dina Sherman.
                        Hand in Hand: Museums and Libraries Working Together. Public Libraries 42.2
                        (Mar./Apr. 2003): 102-105.</note></p>
                    <p>Museums and libraries seem
                    well positioned to synergically support and enable multicultural identities of
                    migration societies.
                        
                        <note>The definition of culture I am looking at can be found in the UNESCO 
                            Universal Declaration on Cultural Diversity: ‘culture should be regarded 
                            as the set of distinctive spiritual, material, intellectual and emotional 
                            features of society or a social group, and that it encompasses, in addition 
                            to art and literature, lifestyles, ways of living together, value systems, 
                            traditions and beliefs’ (UNESCO Universal Declaration on Cultural Diversity. 
                            UNESCO: 2002. Last accessed 18 August 2011, <ref target="http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0012/001271/127160m.pdf" 
                                type="external">http://unesdoc.unesco.org/images/0012/001271/127160m.pdf</ref>). 
                            In this paper the terms “multicultural”, “multiculturalism” and “cultural diversity” 
                            are considered synonymous.</note> As a result, museums are ideally placed to interpret 
                        and preserve culturally diverse heritage.<note> See for example Barker, Emma, ed. 
                            Contemporary Cultures of Display. London: Yale UP 1999; Bennett, Tony, The 
                            Birth of the Museum. History, Theory, Politics. London &amp; New York NY: Routledge, 
                            2009. Gonzalez, Jennifer A. Subject to Display. Reframing Race in Contemporary Installation 
                            Art. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press 2008. Graham, Beryl, and Sarah Cook Rethinking Curating. 
                            Art after New Media. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press 2010. Karp, Ivan, et al., eds. Museum 
                            Frictions. Public Cultures/ Global Transformations. Durham, NC, London: Duke UP 2006. Knell, Simon J., et al., eds. Museum Revolutions. How Museums Change and Are Changed. London, New York NY: Routledge 2007.</note> As centres for culture, information hubs, learning
                    and gathering, libraries seemingly represent service providers for culturally
                    diverse communities, enabling inter-cultural dialogue and education while
                    supporting and promoting diversity.<note>IFLA - Library Services to Multicultural Populations Section (ed.) 
                        The IFLA Multicultural Library Manifesto: The Multicultural Library. 2006. 
                        Accessed 18 August 2011: <ref target="http://www.ifla.org/VII/s32/pub/MulticulturalLibraryManifesto.pdf" 
                            type="external">http://www.ifla.org/VII/s32/pub/MulticulturalLibraryManifesto.pdf</ref>.</note></p>
                    <p>Nevertheless, the fruitful convergence between museums and libraries faces a
                        number of challenges. Some authors<note>Gibson, Hannah, Anne Morris and Marigold Cleeve. Links between Libraries and Museums: Investigating Museum-Library Collaboration in England and the USA. Libri (57) 2007: 53-64. Accessed August 16, 2011 <ref target="www.librijournal.org/pdf/2007-2pp53-64.pdf" type="external">www.librijournal.org/pdf/2007-2pp53-64.pdf</ref>; Walker, Christopher, and Carlos A. Manjarrez. Partnerships for Free Choice Learning: Public Libraries, Museums and Public Broadcasters Working Together. The Urban Institute and Urban Libraries Council. 2004. 22 May 2008 <ref target="http://www.urban.org/UploadedPDF/410661_partnerships_for_free_choice_learning.pdf" type="external">http://www.urban.org/UploadedPDF/410661_partnerships_for_free_choice_learning.pdf</ref>.</note> have highlighted
                    the risks and obstacles encountered on the road to establish a successful
                    collaboration between museums and libraries with respect to their different
                    missions, cultures, organisational and funding structures. In terms of change
                    management, Zorich, Waibel, Erway suggested that it is important to
                    differentiate between coordination and cooperation, and pointing to the
                    organisational changes required for a deep collaboration between libraries,
                    museums and archives<note>Zorich, Diane M., Waibel Gunter and Ricky Erway. “Beyond the Silos of the LAMs: Collaboration Among Libraries, Archives and Museums”. Report produced for OCLC Research, 2008. Accessed August 16, 2011, p. 5, <ref target="www.oclc.org/research/publications/library/2008/2008-05.pdf" type="external">www.oclc.org/research/publications/library/2008/2008-05.pdf</ref>.</note>. In particular for
                        collaboration on digital libraries, Bishoff<note>Bishoff, Liz. “The Collaboration Imperative”. Library Journal, 2004. Accessed August 16, 2011 <ref target="http://www.libraryjournal.com/article/CA371048.html" type="external">http://www.libraryjournal.com/article/CA371048.html</ref></note> and
                        Innocenti <hi rend="italic">et alii</hi><note>Innocenti, Perla, MacKenzie Smith, Kevin Ashley, Seamus Ross, Antonella De Robbio, Hans Pfeiffenberger, John Faundeen. Towards a Holistic Approach to Policy Interoperabilityin Digital Libraries and Digital Repositories. The International Journal of Digital Curation 6 (2011): 1, accessed August 16, 2011, <ref target="http://ijdc.net/index.php/ijdc/article/view/167/235" type="external">http://ijdc.net/index.php/ijdc/article/view/167/235</ref></note> remarked
                    that interoperability is critical to the digital library community. Innocenti
                        <hi rend="italic">et alii</hi> further stressed the diverse organisational,
                    semantic and technical interoperability levels that need to be addressed in a
                    digital library, using the classification of the European Interoperability
                    Framework for eGovernment services.<note>IDABC. “ European interoperability framework for pan-European eGovernment services”. Luxembourg: European Commission 2004.</note> Achieving
                    effective organisational interoperability between digital libraries can imply a
                    radical change in the way that organisations work, manage and share their
                    digital assets.</p>
                </div>
            
            <div>
                    <head>Towards a European Network of Museum,
                        Libraries and Public Cultural Institutions</head>
                    <p>In the MeLA project, the ongoing research programme on a Network of Museums, Libraries and
                    Public Cultural Institutions is articulated through a series of enquiries that
                    intend to:</p>
                
                <xmt:uList>

                    <item>
                        Investigate the relations between transnational museums, library and
                            public cultural institutions collaborations and the society of
                            migration.
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        Identify and describe how transnational museums, library and public
                            cultural institutions collaborating together present themselves to
                            various public communities.
                    </item>
                    <item>
                       Understand and evaluate the effects (benefits and disadvantages) of
                            transnational museums, library and public cultural institutions
                            collaborations.
                    </item>
                </xmt:uList>
                
                <p>The results of this research will be made available in three books (a
                    source book, proceedings of an international conference<note>More information on the forthcoming International Conference for MeLa Research Field 03 are available at <ref target="http://wp3.mela-project.eu/wp/pages/research-field-03-international-conference" type="external">http://wp3.mela-project.eu/wp/pages/research-field-03-international-conference</ref>.</note> and a reference book), including a coordination framework and
                    policy briefs for the museum Community, policy makers and for European
                    Commission. It is our wish that this coordination framework will contribute to
                    new collaborative models of museums and libraries, testing the possibility of a
                    European ‘imagined community’<note>For the concept of ‘imagined communities’ see the seminal book by Anderson, Benedict. Imagined Communities. Reflections on the Origina and Spread of Nationalism, Verso, London and New York, new edition 2006.</note> and the idea of
                    European cultural commons, encompassing both cultural and scientific expressions
                    and artefacts.</p>
                <p>At the DH 2012 Conference we are presenting an overview of the desk and field
                    investigation on selected case studies, organised in four thematic clusters:
                    Collaboration models, European cultural and scientific heritage, Migration and
                    mobility, Narratives for Europe. Each cluster includes case studies articulated
                    in primary, secondary and tertiary level, with additional information from an
                    online survey on museum collaborations with libraries and public cultural
                        institutions.<note>Research Field 03: Online Survey, <ref
                            target="http://wp3.mela-project.eu/wp/pages/research-field-03-online-survey"
                            type="external"
                            >http://wp3.mela-project.eu/wp/pages/research-field-03-online-survey</ref>.
                        Accessed March 12, 2012.</note> Areas of collaboration explored in our
                    research include the core activities of archiving, preserving and framing memory
                    and the associated categories of hierarchies of cultural value and historical
                    identity. The geographic coverage comprises trans-national and trans-local
                    connections of museums and libraries, to allow more flexible and heterogenic
                    connections to be considered, both within Europe – where for example public
                    libraries are at the forefront of leading initiatives addressing multicultural
                    diversity – and outside its assumed confines (for example the Mediterranean),
                    also in terms of European Union legitimacy and identity.<note>See for example
                        Fuchs, Dieter and Andrea Schlenker. “European Identity and the Legitimacy of
                        the EU“. EU FP6 Consent Network of Excellence, 2006. Last accessed September
                        23, 2011. <ref target="www.eu-consent.net/click_download.asp?contentid=1258"
                            type="external"
                            >www.eu-consent.net/click_download.asp?contentid=1258</ref>.</note> We
                    will provide an overview of differences and current tension points between
                    museums, libraries and public cultural institutions investigated in our
                    research, and will discusssome initial suggestions on how they may overcome the
                    challenges built into their infrastructure<note>Karp, Ivan, et al., eds. Museum
                        Frictions. Public Cultures/ Global Transformations. Durham NC &amp; London:
                        Duke University Press, 2006.</note> and manage the change conveyed by
                    collaborations and use of ICTs.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>Conclusions and Outlook</head>
                <p>Within the MeLa project, we are investigating
                    innovative coordination strategies of transnational European museums, libraries
                    and public cultural institutions, for the benefit of multicultural audiences and
                    towards European integration and European cultural commons. Our research aims to
                    provide evidence of collaborations and networks that can positively impact on
                    the visibility of institutions involved, the improvement of the diffusion and
                    accessibility of the collections, the effectiveness of an integrated
                    organisational structure at European level and the coherence with European
                    policies towards a common cultural and scientific heritage definition. We expect
                    that the results of our investigation, which will continue through 2013, will
                    contribute to the advancement of knowledge in this area, to provide museums,
                    libraries and public cultural institutions with collaboration model framework,
                    and to shaping European policies on multiculturalism and migration.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Funding</hi></p>
                <p>This work was supported by the European Commission within the MeLA - European
                    Museums and Libraries in/of the Age of Migration, EU co-funded FP7 Collaborative
                    Project, SSH-2010-5.2-2, 2011-2014 [Grant Agreement No. 266757].</p>
            </div>
                
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>