<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-315">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Myopia: A Visualization Tool in Support of Close Reading</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Chaturvedi, Manish</name>
                    <affiliation>Miami University, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>chaturm@muohio.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Gannod, Gerald</name>
                    <affiliation>Miami University, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>gannodg@muohio.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Mandell, Laura</name>
                    <affiliation>Texas A&amp;M University, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>Mandell@tamu.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Armstrong, Helen</name>
                    <affiliation>Miami University, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>armstrh@muohio.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Hodgson, Eric</name>
                    <affiliation>Miami University, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>eric.hodgson@muohio.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>Although the term ‘myopia’ typically has negative connotations, focusing on what is
                nearby is not always a bad idea. Literary critics value what they call ‘close
                reading’, the process of carefully reading a poem or other literary work
                word-by-word and line-by-line in order to analyze how different features of the text
                – sound, syntax and rhythm work together to create meaning. Through close reading,
                literary critics hope, the reader might eventually succeed in uncovering hidden
                connotations. Typically, multiple readings are necessary to understand the structure
                of a literary work and to unearth multiple meanings, especially in the case of
                poetry. Only then can the reader perceive the poem’s prosody. A non-abstract,
                enhanced visualization of the metrical, syntactical, and sonic structures of a poem
                can greatly ease this laborious process.</p>
            <p>There has been a recurrent effort to develop text visualization and visual
                statistical tools to better understand the underlying structures of chosen textual
                resources. Some of these tool suites provide opportunities for exploration and
                collaboration in area of textual analysis [5,6,9,10]; others are more narrowly
                focused on comparison of plain or encoded text, across versions [3, 7]. Despite
                attempts to do so these digital tools have not resulted in significantly easing the
                process of close reading [2]. The side-by-side method of highlighting differences is
                not conducive to spot connotations and analyses, and thus does not help in fully
                exploiting potential of digital tools in literature.</p>
            <p>At Miami University, we are developing the Myopia Poetry Visualization tool to
                facilitate display of a multidimensional representation of TEI [8] encoded poetry
                and text. Presenting an interactive visual representation of differently encoded
                versions of text, the Myopia tool seeks to amplify understanding and uncover new
                knowledge in the context of close reading. The tool currently is used to visualize
                text from The Poetess Archive currently moving to Texas A&amp;M University. The
                Poetess Archive includes a database of electronic documents encoded using the TEI
                (Text Encoding Initiative) schemas [8] extended with the Poetess Archive tag-set
                that has been derived from widely used terms in literary analysis and criticism.
                Even though one schema is used, a schema extended from the TEI schema, the elements
                of a poem that are interesting to literary scholars have been formalized as tags and
                attributes based on XML standards. But the tags relevant to any single poem must be
                spread across multiple documents. XML by its very nature is hierarchical, and these
                hierarchies cannot overlap within an XML document. The elements of prosodic
                structures of poetry however do overlap: a metaphor might begin in the middle of one
                poetic line and end in the middle of another. Different features thus need to be
                encoded in separate XML files making a composite analysis difficult. Moreover, the
                XML representation of literary texts is suitable for machine processing and
                electronic exchange of information, but it is not intuitively comprehensible even by
                those scholars who know about poetry and would be most likely to adopt an XML
                encoding system. A tool which fuses TEI encodings spread over separate files into a
                single visually integrated document could help overcome the limitations of encoding
                literary texts in XML. We are developing a visualization tool that seeks to
                integrate multiple encodings while allowing comparative analysis of multiple poems
                encoded using the extended TEI tag-set. The proposed solution is an interactive
                visual representation of differently encoded versions of text that can enhance
                cognition, and aid in uncovering of new knowledge. This approach facilitates
                identification of frequently changing hotspots in encoded text and aids in the
                process of close reading. </p>
            <p>Close reading means reading a poem word by word and then repeating the process line
                by line in order to explore sound, syntax, tropological figures, and the meter or
                underlying rhythm of the work. The reader might eventually succeed in uncovering
                hidden connotations. Multiple iterations are necessary to understand the structure
                and thus to unearth meanings from a poem. Only then is the reader in a position to
                describe underlying prosodic elements in literary text. A non-abstract, enhanced
                visualization of syntax and sound structures of a poem can greatly ease this
                laborious process.</p>
            <p>The brain’s capacity to rapidly process visual information, and discern visual
                patterns forms the basis for any visualization. Pirolli and Card developed a theory
                of information access to help designing interfaces to visual cognitive tools. People
                follow a scent as they forage for information, making just-in-time decisions about
                which path to follow [11]. An ideal cognitive loop between a computer and human
                would require the computer providing exactly the information needed at any given
                time. Thus only relevant information should be on screen, allowing users to forage
                as they explore the interface. In the Myopia tool, the cost of visual queries is
                reduced by the minimal layering of visual information, a layering that users can
                control.</p>
            <p>The effectiveness of a given visualization is directly related to the properties of
                the mapping between the raw data and its rendering. In general any mapping should
                allow the user to access the underlying data, so that he or she can be assured that
                the visualization actually relates to the source data being rendered. In our
                visualization tool the textual content of the encoded poetry being visualized is
                always available to the user. The ability to revert to the source text at any stage
                of the visualization from abstract graphical mappings is a conscious design choice
                that we made in building our tool, and we believe that allowing users to see the
                text enhances the tool’s effectiveness [12]. Myopia employs a direct representation
                of textual content overlaid with graphical metaphors to aid in literary analysis of
                poetry.</p>
            <p>The User Interface of the <hi rend="italic">Myopia </hi>tool is split into three
                distinct visual regions</p>
            <xmt:uList>
                <item>The Main Visualization Area that displays and allows users to interact with
                    the rendered text.</item>
                <item>A Key/Legend at bottom of the visualization panel that holds a tabbed display
                    of keys associated with the loaded visualization.</item>
                <item>GUI Panel at the right of the Visualization panel. This allows loading and
                    manipulating source TEI documents and the resulting3D visual elements.</item>
            </xmt:uList>
            <p><figure><graphic url="img315-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 1: Myopia Tool – Principal Characteristics and Layout</head></figure></p>
            
            <p>The <hi rend="italic">Myopia </hi>Poetry Visualization tool has been developed in
                Python and utilizes open-source Python libraries for rendering multidimensional
                graphics integrated with an intuitive user interface. The framework used for
                multidimensional graphics is called Panda3D, which was developed at Carnegie Mellon
                University [4]. It is useful to mix two-dimensional interface design elements with
                higher dimension graphical design elements. Navigational controls should always be
                visible and accessible to the user. In the Poetry Visualization tool the
                two-dimensional Graphical User Interface (GUI) elements are created using the
                wxPython framework.</p>
            <p>We are conducting user studies to evaluate the effectiveness of our approach in
                helping the process of close reading. To achieve this objective we utilize the
                Pre-Experimental Design methodology known as Pretest-Posttest Experiment design ex-
                plored by Campbell, Stanley et. al. [1]. The experiment seeks to measure the
                effective- ness, adequacy and usability of the <hi rend="italic">Myopia </hi>Poetry
                Visualization tool. The research questions of the study seek to determine the three
                aspects of the tool: its effectiveness, its adequacy, and its usability.</p>
            <p>Reading literature closely is a time-consuming activity. Often combining the results
                of close reading can be difficult. By using Information Visualization, new knowledge
                about text can be synthesized. We are presenting a method to support close reading
                of literary texts using multi-dimensional composite visualizations. Offering an
                interactive visual representation of a poem’s literary qualities, the Poetry
                Visualization tool al lows for a multidimensional representation of TEI-encoded
                poetry and text. Presenting an interactive visual representation of differently
                encoded </p>
            <p>versions of text, the tool seeks to amplify understanding and uncover new knowledge.
                This tool will facilitate identifying hotspots in an encoded text and will visualize
                the attendant changes in areas of interest across various TEI documents: a poem may
                be most interesting metaphorically in one line, but metrically it may be more
                interesting in another. The goal is to help scholars analyze the original documents
                in new ways and explore information visualization as a rhetorical device in literary
                criticism. The contributions of this research are in the areas of Information
                Visualization and Digital Humanities. The purpose of the research is to support
                reading literature closely using information visualization. This will facilitate
                abstract analysis of literary texts by fusing multiple perspectives.</p>
            <p><figure><graphic url="img315-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 2: Myopia Tool – Multiple Perspectives</head></figure></p>
            
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
                <p>[1] <hi rend="bold">Campbell, D. T., and J. C. Stanley </hi>(1966). <hi
                        rend="italic">Experimental and quasi-experimental designs for research</hi>.
                    Boston: Houghton Mifflin.</p>
                <p>[2] <hi rend="bold">Bulger, M., E. Lagresa, et al.</hi> (2008). Close reading
                    re-visited. <ref
                        target="http://english236-w2008.pbworks.com/Visualization-Project"
                        type="external">http://english236-w2008.pbworks.com/Visualization-Project</ref>
                        (accessed 11 March 2012).</p>
                <p>[3] <hi rend="bold">Mittelbach, A.</hi> (2009). Tei-comparator in  my  element. <ref
                        target="http://blogs.oucs.ox.ac.uk/jamesc/2009/09/04/tei-comparator"
                        type="external"
                        >http://blogs.oucs.ox.ac.uk/jamesc/2009/09/04/tei-comparator</ref>
                    (accessed  12 March 2012).</p>
                <p>[4] <hi rend="bold">Carnegie Mellon ETC </hi>(2010). Panda 3d - free 3d game
                    engine. <ref target="http://www.panda3d.org/" type="external">http://www.panda3d.org/</ref> (accessed
                    12 march 2012).</p>
                <p>[5] <hi rend="bold">UC BerkeleyVisualization Lab </hi>(2010). Flare data
                    visualization for the web. <ref target="http://flare.prefuse.org/"
                        type="external">http://flare.prefuse.org/</ref> (accessed 12 march 2012). August 2010.</p>
                <p>[6] <hi rend="bold">IBM</hi> (2011). Many eyes. <ref
                        target="http://manyeyes.alphaworks.ibm.com/manyeyes/" type="external"
                        >http://manyeyes.alphaworks.ibm.com/manyeyes/</ref> (ac- cessed 12 March
                    2012).</p>
                <p>[7] <hi rend="bold">Juxta</hi> (2011). Juxta collation software for scholars.
                        <ref target="http://www.juxtasoftware.org/about.html" type="external"
                        >http://www.juxtasoftware.org/about.html</ref> (accessed 12 March 2012).</p>
                <p>[8] <hi rend="bold">TEI </hi>(2011). TEI: Text encoding initiative. <ref
                        target="http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml" type="external"
                        >http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml</ref> (accessed 12 March 2012).</p>
                <p>[9] <hi rend="bold">University of  Nebraska </hi>(2011). Tokenx: a  text
                     visualization,  analysis,  and      play tool. <ref
                        target="http://jetson.unl.edu:8080/cocoon/tokenx/index.html?file=../xml/base.xml"
                        type="external">http://jetson.unl.edu:8080/cocoon/tokenx/index.html?file=../xml/base.xml</ref>
                    (accessed 12 March 2012).</p>
                <p>[10] <hi rend="bold">Bradfford Paley, W.</hi> (2011). Textarc.org home. <ref
                        target="http://textarc.org/" type="external">http://textarc.org/</ref>
                    (accessed 12 March 2012).</p>
                <p>[11] <hi rend="bold">Pirolli, P., S. K. Card, and M. M. van der Wege (</hi>2001).
                    Visual information foraging in a focus + context visualization.  <hi
                        rend="italic">Proceedings of the SIGCHI</hi></p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>