<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-388">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Digital editions with eLaborate: from practice to theory</title>
                <author>
                    <name>van Dalen-Oskam, Karina</name>
                    <affiliation>Huygens Institute for the History of the Netherlands – Royal Dutch
                        Academy of Arts and Sciences, The Netherlands</affiliation>
                    <email>karina.van.dalen@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>van Zundert, Joris Job</name>
                    <affiliation>Huygens Institute for the History of the Netherlands – Royal Dutch
                        Academy of Arts and Sciences, The Netherlands</affiliation>
                    <email>joris.van.zundert@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>The aim of this paper is to show how the development and use of a web based
                    scholarly environment for the creation of digital editions leads to meta
                    reflection and further theorizing on what a digital edition could or should be.
                    This effect of deploying and using virtual environments in turn may lead to
                    improved versions of such working environments or to improvements to other tools
                    facilitating the creation of digital editions.</p>
                <p>However creative and inventive scholars may be, it is extremely difficult to
                    contemplate all possibilities and consequences of digital editions without
                    actual hands on experience in a digital environment in which such editions can
                    be created and experimented with. For this and for other reasons, <hi
                        rend="italic">eLaborate</hi> was developed by the Huygens Institute for the
                    History of the Netherlands, an institute of the Royal Netherlands Academy of
                    Arts and Sciences. eLaborate is an online research environment in which scholars
                    can create an edition of a text, individually or in a group. They can upload
                    scans of the manuscript or printed book they want to edit, transcribe the text
                    using a zooming and panning tool, write annotations to the text, categorize
                    these according to their own needs, and publish the edition online with minimal
                    interference of IT developers. eLaborate version 3 was released in the Fall of
                    2011. eLaborate3 is built on a new IT architecture, because the wishes and needs
                    of users of eLaborate1 (2005) and eLaborate2 (2009) could not be accommodated in
                    the technological framework that was chosen as the base at the start of the
                    first project in 2003.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>How eLaborate changes editorial practice</head>
                <p>For more information about the changing organizational practices that arise in a
                    collaboratively made edition, we refer to (Beaulieu, van Dalen-Oskam &amp; van
                    Zundert [to be published] and Pierazzo 2008). In this paper, we will focus on
                    the edition itself, taking as the subject of our case one already published
                    online digital edition made with eLaborate2.</p>
                <p>The example we take is Marjolein Hogenbirk’s edition of the Middle
                    Dutch Arthurian romance <hi rend="italic">Walewein ende Keye</hi> (‘Gawain and
                    Kay’), published online at <ref target="http://www.waleweinendekeye.huygens.knaw.nl/"
                    type="external">http://www.waleweinendekeye.huygens.knaw.nl/</ref> (Hogenbirk 2009). The most
                    prominent representation of the edited text is per column in the manuscript. See
                    for example 182ra (<ref target="http://www.waleweinendekeye.huygens.knaw.nl/path/editie/kolom/182r/182ra"
                    type="external">http://www.waleweinendekeye.huygens.knaw.nl/path/editie/kolom/182r/182ra#</ref>).
                    eLaborate shows the facsimile of this column, the transcription, and at the far
                    right all the annotations to the transcription are listed. The user can adjust
                    the placement of the facsimile in its panel and zoom in, change the width of the
                    panels (cf. Fig. 1), or click panels away to give the other panels more
                    space.</p>
                
                <p><figure>
                        <graphic url="img388-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>Figure 1: The eLaborate <hi rend="italic">Walewein ende Keye</hi>
                            edition opened on colum 182ra</head>
                    </figure></p>
                
                <p>The freedom of customization available to the user goes even beyond this. The key here is the
                    ‘Options’ button in the top right of the screen, where the user can adjust the
                    display of abbreviations: show these in italics, or show these in roman font (in
                    the example they are shown in italics). Another choice concerns line numbers:
                    the user can choose the line numbers of the current edition as well as that of
                    an earlier edition, or choose not to see any of these (in the example only the
                    line numbers of the current edition are shown). The other Options-tab enables
                    the user to choose which of the annotations to see (Fig. 2). The edition of <hi
                        rend="italic">Walewein ende Keye</hi> has three different annotation
                    categories, which are marked with three different colours in the transcription
                    panel. Hovering over them with the mouse makes the content and categorization of
                    the specific annotation visible. All annotations are visible in the right hand
                    panel. But the user can deselect those categories that need not be visible for
                    now. When deselected, they immediately disappear as coloured markings in the
                    transcription panel and from the list in the right hand panel.</p>
                
                <p><figure>
                        <graphic url="img388-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>Figure 2: The eLaborate <hi rend="italic">Walewein ende Keye</hi>
                            options tab on ‘Annotatiecategorieeën’ (‘Annotation
                            categories’)</head>
                    </figure></p>
                
                <p>The editor has of course added markings of abbreviations,
                    line numbers, and annotation categories in the work environment. This leads us
                    to a very important new basic point of departure or principle for digital
                    editions derived from current practice: everything that is explicitly marked in
                    the edition should be easily made invisible on the fly by the user, whereas it
                    is impossible for the user (as well as for the editor himself) to add
                    non-systematical information on the fly. The occurrence of medieval
                    abbreviations e.g. is unpredictable and therefore cannot be added by current
                    technology correctly automatically. The same goes for the general presentation
                    of the edition. The edition was made column for column, and chapter headings
                    were marked. Therefore it can also be viewed chapter by chapter (‘Overzicht per
                    hoofdstuk’) or as a complete text (‘Volledige tekst’). Should the editor have
                    chosen for a complete text only, the column presentation would not have been
                    possible.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>How practice leads to new theory</head>
                <p>Simple as this new guideline may seem, it leads to a more theoretical reflection
                    on the nature of digital editions in general and on its possible future(s). For
                    example, we could also apply the principle to more fundamental levels. Based on
                    a.o. funding possibilities, an editor of medieval texts until now had to choose
                    for which audience he would prepare the edition. A diplomatic edition for
                    linguistic and literary scholars, with the exact spelling as in the manuscript
                    or print and with abbreviations marked in italics? Or a critical edition for
                    students, with adaptation of spelling, interpunction and capitalization, and
                    with solved abbreviations? With limited funding the last option usually seemed
                    best. But a critical edition closes the edition down for certain kinds of
                    research. Spelling and interpunction are changed and therefore cannot be
                    researched anymore. This also makes it much more difficult to establish the
                    probable date and location of writing. Such a ’closed-down’ edition has only
                    limited usability and limited influence on the general progress of knowledge. It
                    can even introduce difficult-to-check mistakes that could do harm (cf. van
                    Dalen-Oskam &amp; Depuydt 1997).</p>
                <p>Can we address both scholarly users and students in one and the same digital
                    edition without closing down the edition? The basic approach seems to be that
                    the text in a form as close as possible to the source is the basis of all types
                    of representations and that almost all kinds of interpretations by the editors
                    are kept separate from this basic text. The editor transcribes the words or
                    signs diplomatically, for instance the word <hi rend="italic">auenture</hi>
                    ‘adventure’. The word could receive an annotation that the critical
                    representation of this word is <hi rend="italic">aventure</hi> (generated
                    automatically if the editor has run a parser for lemmatization and
                    part-of-speech tagging, having confirmed or corrected the results). The form of
                    the added knowledge would be very different from now, but still depends on the
                    expertise of the editor. Ofcourse we do need a user-friendly way to add all
                    these layers of interpretation to the base text. It is clear that the stand-off
                    mark-up approach as advocated by a.o. (Schmidt 2010) is a necessity to make this
                    work. And then perhaps another problem can also be addressed. What if we have
                    several versions of a text and we want to reconstruct the version as it may have
                    functioned at a certain point in time? If we make one edition with one
                    reconstruction, other kinds of research would again be excluded. So we need to
                    experiment whether we can add a separate layer to editions based on the
                    different manuscripts, with its own annotation categories, which could generate
                    the text in the selection and the order the scholar needs. The user could then
                    toggle between a representation of the original sources and the reconstructed
                    text (van Dalen-Oskam, under review).</p>
                <p>Should this be possible, text and interpretation will be separate for ever,
                    making sure all kinds of research are still possible on (different
                    representations of) the same digital edition. But the role of the editor as
                    analyzing, reconstructing, and validating knowledge remains as firm as ever –
                    with a much higher level of reusability.</p>
            
            </div>
        </body>
        <back><div>
                <head>References</head>
            
            <p><hi rend="bold">Beaulieu, A., K. H. van Dalen-Oskam, and J. J. van Zundert</hi> (to
                be published). Between tradition and Web 2.0: eLaborate as social experiment in
                humanities scholarship. In T. Takseva (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Social Software and
                    the Evolution of User Expertise: Future Trends in Knowledge Creation and
                    Dissemination</hi>. To be published by IGI Global.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">eLaborate: eLaborate1</hi> (2005). Not available anymore.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">eLaborate: eLaborate2</hi> (2009). <ref
                        target="http://www.e-laborate.nl/en/" type="external"
                        >http://www.e-laborate.nl/en/</ref>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">eLaborate: eLaborate3</hi> (2011). <ref
                        target="http://www.elaborate.huygens.knaw.nl/" type="external"
                        >http://www.elaborate.huygens.knaw.nl</ref>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Hogenbirk, M., ed.</hi> (2009). <hi rend="italic">Walewein ende Keye</hi>. Een dertiende-eeuwse
                Arturroman overgeleverd in de <hi rend="italic">Lancelotcompilatie</hi>. Digitale
                editie, bezorgd door Marjolein Hogenbirk, met medewerking van W. P. Gerritsen.
                Eerste editie. November 2009, online op: <ref target="http://www.waleweinendekeye.huygens.knaw.nl"
                type="external">http://www.waleweinendekeye.huygens.knaw.nl</ref>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Pierazzo, E.</hi> (2008). Editorial Teamwork in a Digital
                    Environment: The Edition of the Correspondence of Giacomo Puccini. <hi
                        rend="italic">Jahrbuch für Computerphilologie</hi> 10, <ref
                        target="http://computerphilologie.tu-darmstadt.de/jg08/pierazzo.html"
                        type="externsl"
                        >http://computerphilologie.tu-darmstadt.de/jg08/pierazzo.html</ref>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Schmidt, D.</hi> (2010).’The inadequacy of embedded markup for
                cultural heritage texts. <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi>
                25(3); 337-356.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">van Dalen-Oskam, K., and K. Depuydt</hi> (1997). Lexicography and
                philology. In K. H. van Dalen-Oskam, K. A. C. Depuydt, W. J. J. Pijnenburg, and T.
                H. Schoonheim (eds),<hi rend="italic"> Dictionaries of Medieval Germanic Languages.
                    A Survey of Current Lexicographical Projects</hi>. Turnhout: Brepols, pp.
                189-197. (Selected Proceedings of the International Medieval Congress, University of
                Leeds, 4-7 July 1994).</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">van Dalen-Oskam, K.</hi> (under review). All in one, one for all? A
                possible world of digital editions. Under review for <hi rend="italic"
                    >Variants.</hi></p>
        </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>