<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-449">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Estimating the Distinctiveness of Graphemes and Allographs in Palaeographic Classification</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Levy, Noga</name>
                    <affiliation>Tel-Aviv University, Israel</affiliation>
                    <email>nogaor@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Wolf, Lior</name>
                    <affiliation>Tel-Aviv University, Israel</affiliation>
                    <email>wolf@cs.tau.ac.il</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Dershowitz, Nachum</name>
                    <affiliation>Tel-Aviv University, Israel</affiliation>
                    <email>nachumd@post.tau.ac.il</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Stokes, Peter</name>
                    <affiliation>King’s College London, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>peter.stokes@kcl.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Within the discipline of palaeography, the ‘morphological’ approach tries to describe
                    the letter-shape as a whole, so a letter may be described as a ‘Caroline <hi
                        rend="italic">a</hi>’ or as an ‘insular <hi rend="italic">r</hi>’. Aspects
                    of this approach are visible in almost all palaeographical handbooks,
                    particularly those that provide alphabets or selections of letter-forms. An
                    example is Albert Derolez’s, <hi rend="italic">Palaeography of Gothic Manuscript
                        Books,</hi> which also provides a useful discussion of morphology as a
                    palaeographical method.</p>
                <p>Commonly, a morphological system of descriptors contains two main categories: One category is the grapheme or
                    perhaps, more correctly, character: the letter as an abstract entity but with
                    physical form, such as <hi rend="italic">a,</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">æ</hi>, or a single punctuation mark. The second category is
                    the allograph, namely, a particular way of writing the letter; typical examples
                    include ‘Caroline’ or ‘insular’.</p>
                <p>A key question, given any system of descriptors, is to evaluate the relative importance of each of the components of
                    this system. For example, it is well known among palaeographers that the
                    grapheme <hi rend="italic">a</hi> is very distinctive for late Anglo-Saxon
                    minuscule (Ker 1957; Dumville 1988; Stokes 2005); however, subjective evaluation
                    of distinctiveness could potentially be misleading. It is therefore quite useful
                    to conduct a statistical analysis of significance, and potentially contribute
                    thereby to the practice of palaeography, provided the results can be presented
                    in a meaningful form.</p>
                <p>In this work, we employ methods that are commonly
                    used for mining insights from biological experiments regarding underlying
                    genetic mechanisms. We show that in the context of palaeography such an approach
                    also provides insightful observations.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>Methods</head>
                <p>A dataset consisting of 456 scribal handwritings in English Vernacular
                    minuscule, ca. 990 – ca. 1035, is used (Stokes 2005). ‘Scribal handwriting’ here
                    refers to a single stint or block of writing by one person; these samples are
                    spread across some 198 manuscripts and range from the main text of the book to
                    later additions and notes or glosses between the lines or in the margins.</p>
                <p>The handwritings were described using 289 descriptors (Stokes 2007-2008),
                    where each descriptor indicates whether a certain grapheme (or group of similar
                    graphemes) written as specific allograph(s) appear in the manuscript, as well as
                    forms of certain parts of letters such as ascenders, descenders, and pen-angle.
                    Every sample of handwriting is described by its known or predicted place of
                    writing (where possible) and the estimated range of dates of writing. For
                    classification purposes, the dataset was divided into classes that are
                    homogeneous in time and place.</p>
                <p>First, we measure for each descriptor how informative it is. This is done using
                    the <hi rend="italic">information gain</hi> method (Mitchell 1997), which is
                    often used for feature selection in text categorization tasks. The information
                    gain score measures the decrease in entropy when a descriptor is given vs. the
                    baseline in which it is absent. That is, the information gain measures the
                    discriminative power added by each single descriptor.</p>
                <p>Measuring the power of each descriptor by itself is
                    of limited power. That a certain descriptor is ranked high tells us very little
                    about how informative other similar descriptors are. Using an analogy to
                    biology, it is helpful to know which genes express differently in a specific
                    experiment testing different classes of biological conditions. However, if we
                    want to learn about biological functions and processes, we must go beyond the
                    level of the specific gene by aggregating the information from multiple genes of
                    the same family. In palaeography, the importance of a specific character, for
                    example, cannot be reliably detected just by looking at the ranking of one of
                    the associated descriptors, no matter how highly it is ranked.</p>
                <p>The Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (GSEA) is a statistically valid tool to evaluate how
                    prominent a set (that is, a family) of descriptors is (Subramanian 2005). This
                    computational method determines whether an a priori defined set of features
                    presents itself in a statistically significant and coherent manner among a
                    ranked list of descriptors.</p>
                <p>The input of the GSEA method is a ranked
                    list of features and a list of families of features. Context is important, and
                    so we conduct one experiment using families derived from graphemes and another
                    experiment for families of allographs. The GSEA method is based on elaborate
                    order statistic mechanisms that can compare, on a leveled ground, between large
                    and small families of features.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>Results</head>
                <p>The information gain method was used to automatically rank all 289
                    descriptors. The first, most significant, 30 features are listed in Table 1.</p>
            
                <p><figure><graphic url="tabl449-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Table 1: The 30 single descriptors that were found to be the most informative using the information gain score</head></figure></p>
            
            
                    
                    <p>GSEA was then applied to these results, finding 16 families of graphemes (and
                    stylistic issues, like aspect) that are ‘enriched’ in a statistically
                    significant way, and 20 families of ‘enriched’ allographs. Tables 2 and 4 show
                    the enriched families. The GSEA tool also provides another output: a list of
                    descriptor families that are statistically speaking irrelevant. These lists
                    (Tables 3 and 5) contain 5 graphemes and 9 allographs whose descriptors are
                    ranked so consistently low that it is unlikely to be by chance. As can be seen,
                    the GSEA results contain both expected results and surprising ones; see (Ker
                    1957; Dumville1988, 1993, 1994) for general background for script of this
                    period.</p>
                    <table>
                        <head>Table 2: The 16 graphemes (and stylistic issues) that were found to be
                            discriminative in a statistically significant way by the GSEA method.
                            The enrichment score (ES) reflects the degree to which a feature-set is
                            overrepresented at the top. The normalized ES accounts for differences
                            in set size and the correlations between the sets</head>
                        <row>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Rank</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Grapheme+</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>
                                <hi rend="bold">Normalized ES</hi>
                            </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> 1 </cell>
                            <cell> æ </cell>
                            <cell> 1.73 </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> 2 </cell>
                            <cell> 7 (Tironean nota) </cell>
                            <cell> 1.31 </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> 3 </cell>
                            <cell> a </cell>
                            <cell> 1.31 </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> 4 </cell>
                            <cell> c </cell>
                            <cell> 1.15 </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> 5 </cell>
                            <cell> f </cell>
                            <cell> 1.10 </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> 6 </cell>
                            <cell> d </cell>
                            <cell> 0.86 </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> 7 </cell>
                            <cell> g </cell>
                            <cell> 0.82 </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> 8 </cell>
                            <cell> Aspect </cell>
                            <cell> 0.79 </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> 9 </cell>
                            <cell> e </cell>
                            <cell> 0.76 </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> 10 </cell>
                            <cell> y </cell>
                            <cell> 0.64 </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> 11 </cell>
                            <cell> Ascender </cell>
                            <cell> 0.60 </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> 12 </cell>
                            <cell> h </cell>
                            <cell> 0.58 </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> 13 </cell>
                            <cell> Þð </cell>
                            <cell> 0.58 </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> 14 </cell>
                            <cell> k </cell>
                            <cell> 0.57 </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> 15 </cell>
                            <cell> Descender </cell>
                            <cell> 0.56 </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> 16 </cell>
                            <cell> s </cell>
                            <cell> 0.50 </cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>It is unsurprising that the ash (æ) is most significant, since it is a combination of
                        <hi rend="italic">a </hi>and <hi rend="italic">e</hi>, both of which are in
                    themselves significant (Dumville 1988). It is quite surprising that the Tironean
                    nota for <hi rend="italic">and</hi> (which looks like the numeral 7) is
                    discriminating, as this is not noted by any of the palaeographers cited. It also
                    came as a surprise that <hi rend="italic">c </hi>and <hi rend="italic">y
                    </hi>turned out to be highly significant, because they are not generally
                    recognised as such, though some of their specific forms certainly are (Dumville
                    1993). It was also surprising, from a palaeographer’s viewpoint, to see <hi
                        rend="italic">h</hi> in the list, as it is not included in those published
                    by palaeographers (Ker1957; Dumville 1993; 1994; Stokes 2005).</p>
                
                <table>
                        <head>Table 3: The five graphemes and stylistic issues that were found to be
                            irrelevant to the discrimination task to a statistically significant
                            degree</head>
                                <row>
                                    <cell>
                                        <hi rend="bold">Rank</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <hi rend="bold">Graphemes+</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                    <cell>
                                        <hi rend="bold">Normalized ES</hi>
                                    </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell> 1 </cell>
                                    <cell> Minim </cell>
                                    <cell> -1.20 </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell> 2 </cell>
                                    <cell> Pen </cell>
                                    <cell> -0.90 </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell> 3 </cell>
                                    <cell> hmn </cell>
                                    <cell> -0.76 </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell> 4 </cell>
                                    <cell> r </cell>
                                    <cell> -0.70 </cell>
                                </row>
                                <row>
                                    <cell> 5 </cell>
                                    <cell> ð </cell>
                                    <cell> -0.62 </cell>
                                </row>
                            </table>
                
                    <p>Here, it is very interesting to see that ð is
                    insignificant, since its form varies very widely between scribes. Perhaps some
                    of its features are better discriminants than others.</p>
                
                <p><figure><graphic url="tabl449-4.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Table 4: The 20 allographs that were found to be discriminative in a statistically significant way by the GSEA method</head></figure></p>
               
                    <p>Table 4 is also quite insightful. While HORNED is widely accepted as
                    significant (Ker 1957), ANGLED_SW (angled southwest quadrant) is not, although
                    it has been suggested as discriminative (Stokes, 2005). LONG_TONGUE is not
                    attested in the literature as significant, as are the related ANGLED_TONGUE and
                    HORIZ._TONGUE: it will be interesting to study if they are strongly correlated,
                    and if they are even more distinctive in combination. Since TEARDROP, ROUND, and
                    SEMI_CAROLINE are all forms of the letter <hi rend="italic">a</hi>, their
                    significance is expected and is supported by related literature on the minuscule
                    of the period (Ker, 1957; Dumville, 1994), and is strongly argued as relevant
                    for this period in the thesis from which this dataset is taken (Stokes 2005). 
                    ROTUND_MINIM is unrecognized as being discriminative. LOW_LIG (low ligature) is
                    less recognized in the literature than TALL_LIG (Ker, 1957) which is correlated
                    with it. BULGING_LIG is well recognized (Ker 1957; Stokes 2005). SQUINTING is
                    recognised as distinctive in Latin (Dumville 1993) but not in the script
                    normally used for the vernacular.</p>
                        
                <p><figure><graphic url="tabl449-5.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Table 5: The nine allographs that were found to be irrelevant in a statistically significant manner to the discrimination task. Most of these results are expected since these allographs are either very common in the corpus  or present the ‘default’ values for the script of the period</head></figure></p>
                    </div>
                
                
                
                <div>
                    
              <head>Discussion</head>
                    <p>Computerized systems that perform digital palaeography have been criticized in the past for reducing
                    script entirely to statistical processes that are themselves difficult or
                    impossible to evaluate (Stokes 2009). In fact, the struggle to elicit meaning
                    out of statistical inference tools is common to many scientific domains. Here we
                    begin to show that, by using the appropriate statistical tools, computers can be
                    used to mine meaningful insights in palaeography.</p>
                    <p>The proposed method is not without its limitations. First, it relies on a specific definition of
                    ‘distinctive descriptors’ that is derived from the choice of the feature ranking
                    algorithm used. The IG method used focuses on the ability to discriminate
                    between the classes; by choosing another ranking method one could focus, for
                    example, on scribal variation, which is also a question of interest to
                    palaeographers. A second limitation is that the method cannot go beyond the
                    assumptions made in the initial coding system. For example, there is a
                    normalization quality to GSEA, in the sense that, if the palaeographer recorded
                    more varieties of <hi rend="italic">a, </hi>say, than of other letters,
                    precisely because he expects that letter to be more significant, the GSEA method
                    will counterbalance this by looking at the overall distribution of all
                    varieties. However, presumably there could have been other letters and features
                    that are in fact more distinctive but that were not recorded in the database
                    because they were mistakenly deemed to be relatively insignificant. Future work
                    should therefore aim to augment the database with automatically extracted
                    features, with the potential benefit of adding a new (robotic) perspective to
                    morphological analysis. Another limitation of the method is its dependence on
                    verbal descriptors for features which are visual, or, indeed, which are a
                    function of the physical movements of the scribe’s arm, hand and pen,
                    particularly given the lack of standard palaeographical terminology for such
                    detailed features (Stokes 2011-2012). These difficulties could potentially be
                    overcome by providing greater rigour in nomenclature and by connecting these
                    labels to particular images. Both approaches are already being tested in the
                    DigiPal project (<ref target="http://digipal.eu/" type="external">http://digipal.eu/</ref>), and discussions are already underway to combine the work done there with
                    that described here.</p>
                    <p>Despite these limitations, the method described
                    is still very promising. One of the difficulties in palaeographical study is the
                    vast quantity of detail that must be processed, and so helping the human expert
                    to identify distinctive features would be enormously beneficial in managing that
                    data. For instance, identifying patterns in variation such as those by region,
                    date or group of scribes would be invaluable in identifying manuscripts by their
                    writing. Applying the method to other corpora of scribal handwriting could also
                    lead to valuable insights. For example, if particular features prove to be
                    discriminative across many different script-systems then this could be an
                    important clue into identifying scribes independently of the script that they
                    wrote, something very necessary given that most scribes routinely wrote in a
                    number of very different scripts. Finally, with further testing and refinement,
                    this approach promises an important and large step towards a method for
                    distinguishing handwriting that can be described explicitly, that can be
                    communicated effectively in ways that palaeographers and other humanities
                    scholars can understand, and that can also enjoy the support of quantitative
                    data. This goal is one that has been sought for a very long time (Stokes
                    2009).</p>
           
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
               <head>References</head>
               

            <p><hi rend="bold">Bishop, T. A. M.</hi> (1971). <hi rend="italic">English Caroline
                    Minuscule</hi>. Oxford: Clarendon Press.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Dumville, D. N.</hi> (1988). Beowulf come lately: some notes on the
                palaeography of the Nowell Codex. <hi rend="italic">Archiv für das Studium der
                    neueren Sprachen und Literaturen</hi> 225: 49–63.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Dumville, D. N.</hi> (1993). <hi rend="italic">English Caroline
                    Script and Monastic History</hi>. Boydell: Woodbridge.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Dumville, D. N.</hi> (1994). English Square Minuscule script: the
                mid-century phases. <hi rend="italic">Anglo-Saxon England</hi> 23: 133–64.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Ker, N. R.</hi> (1957). <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Manuscripts
                    Containing Anglo-Saxon</hi>. Oxford: Clarendon Press</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Mitchell, T. M.</hi> (1997). <hi rend="italic">Machine Learning</hi>.
                New York: McGraw-Hill.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Stokes, P. A.</hi> (2005). <hi rend="italic">English Vernacular
                    Script ca 990–ca 1035</hi>. Cambridge [unpublished Ph.D. dissertation].</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Stokes, P. A.</hi> (2007-2008). Palaeography and image-processing:
                    some solutions and problems. <hi rend="italic">Digital Medievalist</hi> 3. <ref
                        target="http://digitalmedievalist.org/journal/3/stokes/" type="external"
                        >http://digitalmedievalist.org/journal/3/stokes/</ref> (accessed 15 March
                    2012).</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Stokes, P. A.</hi> (2009). Computer-aided palaeography: present and
                future. In Rehbein, M., <hi rend="italic">et al</hi>. (eds), <hi rend="italic"
                    >Kodikologie und Paläographie im Digitalen Zeitalter</hi>. Norderstedt: Books on
                Demand. 309–338. <ref target="http://kups.ub.uni-koeln.de/2978/" type="external">http://kups.ub.uni-koeln.de/2978</ref> 
                    (accessed 15 March 2012).</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Stokes, P. A.</hi> (2011-2012). Describing script [Parts i–]. <hi
                rend="italic">DigiPal Project Blog</hi>. King’s College London. <ref target="http://digipal.eu/blogs/blog/describing-handwriting-part-i/"
                    type="external">http://digipal.eu/blogs/blog/describing-handwriting-part-i/</ref>
                (accessed 15 March 2012).</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Subramanian, A., et al.</hi> (2005). Gene set enrichment analysis: a
                knowledge-based approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles. <hi
                    rend="italic">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United
                    States of America</hi> 102(43): 15545-50.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>