<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-461">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Academic Research in the Blogosphere: Adapting to New Opportunities and Risks on the Internet</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Littauer, Richard</name>
                    <affiliation>Universität des Saarlandes, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>richard.littauer@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Winters, James</name>
                    <affiliation>Katholieke Universiteit Leuven, Belgium</affiliation>
                    <email>wintzis@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Roberts, Sean</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Edinburgh, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>S.G.Roberts@sms.ed.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Little, Hannah</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Edinburgh, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>H.R.Little@sms.ed.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Pleyer, Michael</name>
                    <affiliation>Ruprecht-Karls-Universität Heidelberg, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>Pleyer@stud.uni-heidelberg.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Benzon, Bill</name>
                    <affiliation>QuestionCopyright.org, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>BBenzon@mindspring.com</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
           <div>
            <p>Interdisciplinary research with the intent of publication to a wide audience is
                    increasingly desired. <hi rend="italic">Blogging</hi> offers new opportunities
                    for academics to collaborate with researchers from other fields and integrate
                    data. The power to publish results and theories freely and get rapid feedback
                    has positive and negative potential implications. On the positive side, new
                    ideas can be presented and discussed easily with progress potentially much
                    faster than a traditional journal peer-review. The internet also provides a
                    forum to engage the public about ongoing research, an increasing concern for
                    funding bodies. On the negative side, ideas can appear in public and affect
                    research without being properly assessed. This could dilute the impact of
                    relevant research. We review whether blogging can become part of research, by
                    examining the case study of our blog on language evolution.</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">ReplicatedTypo.org</hi> has received 120,000~ hits in 3 years
                    (counts gathered using Wordpress Analytics) and been awarded 8 editor’s
                    selections from <hi rend="italic">ResearchBlogging.com</hi>. As well as
                    reporting on recent publications and conferences, we have written basic
                    introductions to Linguistics, Evolution, mathematical modeling and animal
                    signaling. As a blog with multiple authors, our interests are varied, but our
                    central research theme – evolutionary approaches to language and culture –
                    remains the same. Our post topics include what makes humans unique, top-down
                    versus bottom-up approaches to language evolution, the evolution of colour
                    terms, Specific Language Impairment and Autism, the effect of second language
                    learners on linguistic structure, cultural evolution and the singularity and
                    genetic correlates of social sensitivity. We’ve written about the current trend
                    for large-scale statistical analyses of linguistic features and social features,
                    and contributed some of our own including phoneme inventory size and demography,
                    alcohol consumption and morphological complexity and whether linguistic
                    diversity is correlated with traffic accidents. As shown by the examples
                    provided, Language Evolution is an inherently interdisciplinary field with many
                    new ideas and which relies upon new techniques and analyses.</p>
                    <p>Blogs are a useful source for discovering current research and a forum for open
                    peer review, whether open (from the public) or closed (from co-authors on
                    drafts). Linguistics blogs have been around for many years (e.g. Language Log),
                    but blogs dedicated to language evolution have emerged, too (e.g. Babel’s dawn,
                    Shared Symbolic Storage, Culture Evolves!, Biolinguistics Blog, Replicated
                    Typo). One of these blog-authors has even published a book directed at a general
                    audience about the theories he developed on his blog (E. B. Bolles 2011).
                    However, there is no universal consensus on the method or acceptability of
                    citing ideas from blogs. We argue that the devaluing of research and criticism
                    appearing in open forums risks obstructing research. This is not merely a debate
                    in Linguistics; much ink has been spilled on a similar grounds in evolutionary
                    biology, in the so called <hi rend="italic">#arsenicgate</hi> scandal (see
                    Zimmer 2011). Scholarship will not take advantage of the collaborative potential
                    of the Internet if academic standards are not applied to Internet resources.
                    Concerns about standards and plagiarism, from work that might considered to be
                    in the public domain, are particularly important for blogs that are used to
                    disseminating original work in progress such as small-scale experiments and
                    theoretical essays. A particularly sensitive issue, in that it may stop one
                    blogging about personal research, is public access to experiment data and model
                    code. </p>
                <p>On a note unrelated to research dissemination and publication models, writing for
                    blogs can benefit students. It encourages wider reading, engagement with
                    cutting-edge topics and helps integrate students from diverse backgrounds into
                    the language evolution community. In an increasingly competitive academic
                    environment, blogs are a vital tool for career development. We would like to see
                    universities teach new media skills such as blogging.</p>
                <p>Our aims as science bloggers on Replicated Typo are: to highlight and discuss new
                    research on language evolution; to engage with the general public by presenting
                    language evolution research in an accessible way; to be a platform for open
                    science research into language evolution. We hope that presentation of research
                    and discussion on the internet can, in conjunction with journal peer-review,
                    lead to more productive, accurate and progressive research. Discussions of posts
                    on our own blog have lead to revisions of our research and new avenues of
                    research as well as collaborations and clarifications of research by the authors
                    of the studies reviewed. Releasing code on our blog has lead to interactions
                    that benefited both the readers and the researcher. We hope that model
                    transparency and the sharing of code can help foster links between language evolution and other fields who use similar
                    techniques and technologies (biology, informatics, etc.).</p>
                <p>The aim of this paper is to provide a forum at Digital Humanities 2012 for
                    discussing these issues, and the questions that arise from them, namely:</p>
               
               <xmt:uList>
                    <item>Can blogged research be taken as seriously as peer-reviewed
                    research?</item>
                <item>What are the risks of publicly accessible research?</item>
                <item>Is research blogging adaptable to other fields, in particular fields
                    involving minorities or low resource groups?</item>
                <item>Are there particular concerns with running experiments or soliciting
                    feedback online?</item>
                <item>Is the field of academia doing enough towards public engagement on the
                    internet?</item>
               </xmt:uList>
                   
                <p>We hope that providing a focus for these issues will ensure a
                    productive and balanced response.</p>
            
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <head>References</head>
            
            <p><hi rend="bold">Bolles, E., ed.</hi> (n.d.). <hi rend="italic">Babel’s dawn</hi>.
                <ref target="http://wwww.babelsdawn.com" type="external">http://wwww.babelsdawn.com</ref>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Bolles, E. B.</hi> (2011). <hi rend="italic">Babel’s dawn: A natural
                    history of the origins of speech.</hi> Berkeley, CA: Counterpoint.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Jordan, F. </hi>(n.d.). <hi rend="italic">Culture evolves!
            </hi> <ref target="http://evolutionaryanthropology.wordpress.com" type="external">http://evolutionaryanthropology.wordpress.com</ref>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Liberman, M., and G. Pullum, eds.</hi> (n.d.). <hi rend="italic"
                >Language Log</hi>. <ref target="http://languagelog.ldc.upenn.edu" type="external">http://languagelog.ldc.upenn.edu</ref>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Martín, T., ed.</hi> (n.d.). <hi rend="italic">Biolinguistics
                blog</hi>. <ref target="http://biolingblog.blogspot.com" type="external">http://biolingblog.blogspot.com</ref>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Munger, D., ed.</hi> (n.d.). <hi rend="italic">Research
                blogging</hi>. <ref target="http://www.researchblogging.com" type="external">http://www.researchblogging.com</ref>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Pleyer, M.</hi> (n.d.). <hi rend="italic">Shared symbolic
                storage.</hi> <ref target="http://sharedsymbolicstorage.blogspot.com" type="external">http://sharedsymbolicstorage.blogspot.com</ref>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Winters, J., ed.</hi> (n.d.). <hi rend="italic">Replicated typo.</hi>
                <ref target="http://www.replicatedtypo.com" type="external">http://www.replicatedtypo.com</ref></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Zimmer, C.</hi> (2011) Happy Birthday, #arseniclife. <hi rend="italic"
                >The Loom</hi>, December 2, 2011. <ref
                    target="http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/loom/2011/12/02/happy-birthday-arseniclife/"
                    type="external">http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/loom/2011/12/02/happy-birthday-arseniclife</ref> (accessed March 14 2012).</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>