<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-463">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Social Curation of large multimedia collections on the cloud</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Chong, Dazhi</name>
                    <affiliation>Old Dominion University, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>dchong@odu.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Coppage, Samuel</name>
                    <affiliation>Old Dominion University, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>scoppage@odu.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Gu, Xiangyi</name>
                    <affiliation>Old Dominion University, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>xxxgu001@odu.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Maly, Kurt</name>
                    <affiliation>Old Dominion University, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>maly@cs.odu.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Wu, Harris</name>
                    <affiliation>Old Dominion University, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>hwu@odu.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Zubair, Mohammad</name>
                    <affiliation>Old Dominion University, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>zubair@cs.odu.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
            <head>Introduction and Prior Work</head>
            <p>In previous Digital Humanities conferences we presented the Facet System, a system
                that improves browsing and searching of a large collection by supporting users to
                build a faceted (multi-perspective) classification schema collaboratively (Georges
                et al. 2008; Fu et al. 2010). The system is targeted for multimedia collections that
                have little textual metadata. In summary, our system (a) allows users to build and
                maintain a faceted classification collaboratively, (b) enriches the user-created
                facet schema systematically, and (c) classifies documents into an evolving facet
                schema automatically. It is hoped that through users’ collective efforts the faceted
                classification schema will evolve along with the users’ interests and thus help them
                navigate the collection. For the browsing and classification interfaces of the Facet
                System see Fig. 1 and Fig. 2. This paper discusses scalability challenges and
                improvements made to the system, cloud deployment, user studies and evaluation
                results.</p>
                <p><figure><graphic url="img463-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 1: Browsing of the system enabled by user-evolved faceted classification</head></figure></p>
          
                <p><figure><graphic url="img463-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 2: The click-and-drag classification screen</head></figure></p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
            <head>Scalability Issues and System Improvement</head>
            <p>Our Facet System allows users to collaboratively evolve a common, global schema that
                contains facets (perspectives such as <hi rend="italic">colour</hi>) and categories
                (such as red and green in the <hi rend="italic">colour</hi> facet) for a large
                multimedia collection, using a wiki-inspired interface. The global schema can then
                used by any users for browsing or searching the collection. The variety of user
                perspectives increases with the number of users. Even though we have taken measures
                to cure and reduce the global schema, we find that the global schema alone faces
                limitations in supporting a large number of users. Many users prefer to focus on a
                smaller subset of the schema or collection. To address this issue, we have improved
                the user interface to allow users switch between global and personal schemas. The
                personal schema allows users to organize digital documents in their own way. A group
                of people can share the same personal schema which applies to a subset of the large
                digital collection. On the backend, we developed a ‘merging’ algorithm that
                automatically enriches the global schema by merging items, categories and facets
                from personal schema into the global schema. The algorithm applies statistical
                techniques to item-category associations, category-subcategory and category-facet
                associations, and Wordnet-based similarities. Figure 3 shows both global and
                personal schemas that can be utilized by individual users or user groups. More
                technical details will be presented at the conference.</p>
            
                <p><figure><graphic url="img463-3.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 3: Global and personal (or local) schemas</head></figure></p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div>
            <head>Cloud Deployment</head>
            <p>A large repository with millions of multimedia items may consume terabytes of
                storage. To support millions of users, the system needs to be partitioned, mirrored,
                or load balanced across an array of servers. When user traffic and growth trends are
                not perfectly predicable, cloud computing is not only the most cost effective but
                also likely the only viable option.</p>
            <p>   After evaluating several cloud service providers, we find that Microsoft Azure
                Cloud provides the best cost-effectiveness for us to host large digital repositories
                that require scalable database support as well as network bandwidth. Our Facet
                System was built on an open source technology stack including Joomla, PHP and MySQL.
                Joomla is a leading open source content management system implemented in PHP.
                Initially we deployed the system on two server layers, Web (Joomla/PHP) and Database
                (MySQL) layers, utilizing Web and Worker roles in the Azure cloud (see Fig. 4). The
                scalability and manageability of the MySQL database turned out to be prohibitive. We
                found that true database scalability can be accomplished only by cloud-tailored
                solutions such as Microsoft SQL Azure. We spent significant efforts in porting
                Joomla from MySQL to Microsoft SQL Azure. In addition, we moved Joomla’s session
                management from the default storage in operating system files to Azure storage, to
                enable stateless load balancing across many servers on the Web layer. During the
                conference we will present more technical details which may benefit users of Joomla
                and other open source content management systems.</p>
            
                <p><figure><graphic url="img116-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 4: The deployment architecture in Microsoft Azure</head></figure></p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
            <head>Evaluation and user studies</head>
            <p>We evaluated the system using 15 classes (different sessions of a university-wide
                undergraduate introductory information technology class) during Spring 2011, and
                continue the evaluation with 22 classes during Fall 2011 semester using the cloud
                deployment of our system. Each class has around 30 students. The system was used to
                teach the digital humanities and social computing component of the class, by asking
                students to collaboratively curate a special library collection of un-cataloged
                local newspaper clippings and images on African American activism in United States.
                We captured detailed usage information as users completed a series of tasks
                involving searching, classification, tagging and voting (providing feedback on
                digital items and metadata). Each class of students work as a group using a single
                personal schema, which may be better labeled as ‘local schema’ in the future to
                avoid confusion. A backend algorithm periodically merges categories and facets from
                these local schemas into the global schema. While global schema is useful, we find
                that the students spend a lot of efforts on curating the collection through building
                the local schemas for their own classes. Therefore we refer to our current system a
                Social Curation System. The performance of the system and cloud deployment proves to
                be satisfactory and actually exceeded our expectation in certain aspects.</p>
            <p>A common challenge to curating digital collections is the lack of expertise necessary
                    to classify, catalog and create metadata structures for such collections. The
                    evaluation shows the feasibility of social curation by non-expert users
                    supplemented by suitable algorithms for reinforcing, combining and judging user
                    created associations and tags. From a social science perspective, we are
                    interested in the relationship between student’s prior experience and attitudes
                    about social computing and their current behavior in a social curation
                    environment. We used a pre-usage instrument to assess the users’ prior
                    experience with common social sites, then a post-usage instrument to measure
                    post-usage attitudes and conceptual understanding of the resulting metadata
                    among the users. We also measured students’ knowledge in digital humanities and
                    African American activism before and after the system usage. The change in
                    perceived usefulness of the archive from the beginning of the experiment to the
                    end was also measured. We will present the result of the data analysis at the
                    conference and hope that it will help future designs and implementations of
                    socially curated archives.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
            <head>Related Work and Conclusion</head>
            <p>There are many large scale multimedia collections on the Internet. Few of them,
                however, contain library-grade metadata for digital items. Researchers have proposed
                or studied how to build large, curated collections on the Internet. Recent Digital
                Humanities conferences have showcased efforts in trying to utilize multiple
                organizations’ collaborative efforts in building federated or related collections
                (Timothy et al. 2011). Our project utilizes cloud computing to explore the
                scalability limitations of collaborative curation, and implement algorithmic
                approaches to synthesize individual users’ or groups’ curation efforts. Our work on
                backend algorithms are build upon recent advancements in ontology building, text
                categorization and link mining (e.g. Wu et al., 2006a, 2006b; Heymann et al. 2006;
                Joachims et al. 1998;Schmitz et al. 2006). Evaluation results show the promise of
                our social curation approach.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Funding</hi></p>
            <p>This work was supported by the National Science Foundation [ grant number
                0713290].</p>
            
            </div></body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
                
            
            <p><hi rend="bold">Fu, L., K. Maly, H. Wu, and M. Zubair</hi> (2010). Building Dynamic
                Image Collections from Internet. <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities 2010</hi>,
                London, UK, 2010.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Georges, A., K. Maly, M. Milena, H. Wu, and M. Zubair</hi> (2008).
                Exploring Historical Image Collections with Collaborative Faceted Classification.<hi
                    rend="italic"> Digital Humanities 2008</hi>, Oulu, Finland, 2008.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Heymann, P., and H. Garcia-Molina</hi> (2006).Collaborative Creation
                    of Communal Hierarchical Taxonomies in Social Tagging Systems. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Stanford Technical Report InfoLab</hi>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Joachims, T.</hi> (1998) Text categorization with support vector
                    machines.<hi rend="italic"> 10th European Conference on Machine Learning</hi>.
                London, 1998.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Schmitz, P., and Yahoo! Research</hi> (2006). Inducing Ontology from
                Flickr Tags. <hi rend="italic">Workshop in Collaborative Web Tagging, WWW 2006,
                    2006, </hi>Edinburgh, UK.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Cole, T., N. Fraistat, D. Greenbaum, D. Lester, and E. Millon</hi>
                    (2011). Bamboo Technology Project: Building Cyberinfrastructure for the Arts and
                        Humanities.<hi rend="italic"> Digital Humanities 2011</hi>, Stanford, CA,
                    2011. </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Wu, H., M. Zubair, and K. Maly</hi> (2006). Harvesting Social
                Knowledge from Folksonomies. <hi rend="italic">ACM 17th Conference on Hypertext and
                    Hypermedia</hi>, 111-114, Odense, Demark, August 20-25, 2006.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold"> Wu, H., M. Gordon, K. DeMaagd, and W. Fan</hi> (2006). Mining Web Navigations for Intelligence. <hi rend="italic">Decision Support
                    Systems</hi> 41(3): 574-591.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>