<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="ab-423">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Experiments in Digital Philosophy – Putting new paradigms to the test in the Agora project</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Hrachovec, Herbert</name>
                    <affiliation>Faculty of Philosophy, University of Vienna, Austria</affiliation>
                    <email>herbert.hrachovec@univie.ac.at</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Carusi, Annamaria</name>
                    <affiliation>Oxford e-Research Centre, University of Oxford, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>annamaria.carusi@oerc.ox.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Huentelmann, Raphael</name>
                    <affiliation>Ontos verlag, Heusenstamm nr. Frankfurt, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>info@ontosverlag.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Pichler, Alois</name>
                    <affiliation>Wittgenstein Archives at the University of Bergen, Norway</affiliation>
                    <email>Alois.Pichler@fof.uib.no</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Antonio, Lamarra</name>
                    <affiliation>Istituto per il Lessico Intellettuale Europeo e la Storia delle Idee (ILIESI), Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche, Italy</affiliation>
                    <email>antonio.lamarra@iliesi.cnr.it</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Cristina, Marras</name>
                    <affiliation>Istituto per il Lessico Intellettuale Europeo e la Storia delle Idee (ILIESI), Italy</affiliation>
                    <email>cmarras@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Alessio, Piccioli</name>
                    <affiliation>Net7 srl, Internet Open Solutions, Pisa, Italy</affiliation>
                    <email>piccioli@netseven.it</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Lou, Burnard</name>
                    <affiliation>Oxford e-Research Centre, University of Oxford, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>Lou.burnard@retired.ox.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            
            <p>Agora extends an existing federation of
                    semantically structured digital libraries named <hi rend="italic">Philosource</hi>, a collection of high quality OA content from classical to
                    contemporary European philosophy. Agora intends to transform this federation
                    into a specialised and highly innovative OA archive and publishing venue for new
                    scholarship, by carrying out five experiments: (1) Semantic linking; (2) Linked
                    Open Data (LOD); (3) Advanced Scholarly Linking; (4) Open Peer review; and (5)
                    OA business models in the field of European philosophy. The LOD portal created
                    within experiment (2) will serve as unique access point to the philosophical
                    content of the federation and will expose its metadata to the LOD cloud. Agora’s
                    ultimate goal is to arrive at a model for establishing and accessing a growing
                    open research archive for scholarly publications in the humanities.</p>
                <p>The presentation will focus on the rationale for the Agora project’s vision of
                    innovative enhancement of Open Access resources in European Philosophy, and on
                    the TEI framework. The experiments and evaluation strategies will not be
                    presented in detail, and are briefly summarised below. More information can be
                    found on the project website: <ref target="http://www.project-agora.eu" type="external">www.project-agora.eu</ref>.</p>
            
            
            <div>
                <head>TEI Framework</head>
                <p>The general vision that underlies the Agora project, as well as the mark-up
                    challenges that arose during Agora’s initial phase focused on content
                    preparation for the experiments. It was decided to define a simple TEI-based
                    interchange format which could be used both for existing and for newly published
                    scientific journal articles, enabling different partners to combine these
                    secondary resources seamlessly with other resources within the evolving AGORA
                    framework. To define this format we surveyed about half a dozen different
                    TEI-based publishing systems, as used by different journal publishers in Europe
                    and North America, and identified a common subset of useful markup constructs.
                    We documented this using the TEI’s ‘ODD’ system, which is also used to generate
                    the schemas used to validate the content produced by all partners. For output to
                    readable PDF and HTML formats we rely on a customization of the TEI Stylesheet
                    library. In a parallel experiment, we have used the same library to define an
                    input mapping from ‘docx’ format into TEI, enabling partners to draft new
                    documents in the familiar Microsoft Word environment using a specially
                    customized Word stylesheet.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>Experiments</head>
                <p>Each of the Agora experiments is a trial of a mode of enhancing an aspect of
                    philosophical scholarship through the possibilities offered by digital
                    publications and repositories in philosophy.</p>
                <p>The Semantic Linking Experiment has as the goal of enabling a novel way of
                    building, querying, and browsing a knowledge network and to assess its
                    suitability as a collaborative research tool as well as a learning device. A
                    subset of the new content (secondary sources in the form of scholarly articles,
                    monographs) will be interlinked via semantic annotations among each other and
                    its underlying datasets (primary sources in the form of editions of texts,
                    manuscripts) most of which are already available in the Philosource Federation.
                    A subset of secondary sources will be connected with keywords that at the same
                    time will make up domain concepts of the secondary sources ontology. The
                    resulting ontology, in the form of RDF files, will be published on the web and
                    the users will be offered the possibility to browse it, use the ontology to tag
                    additional material, and add to the ontology generating their own notebooks. The
                    semantically linked content will enhance browsing, querying, collaboration and
                    learning.</p>
                <p>The Linked Open Data (LOD) Experiment aims to offer users and machines a unique
                    access point to the federation content and to augment the user search and
                    browsing experience. The Philosource Federation is already a federation in the
                    political sense by sharing common values and technological standards. The
                    Federation Portal will mainly serve as a centralised aggregator of all the
                    metadata (semantically structured and non-semantically structured) produced by
                    the federation nodes. It will thereby interlink the federation nodes, and link
                    the federation content with relevant external sources. It is hoped that the
                    linking will make the content more interoperable, easier to discover and
                    retrieve, and provide a richer context for the federation content. The metadata
                    made available through the portal API will make the federation content usable to
                    build other third party applications and aims to stimulate innovative and
                    creative re-uses of our data. The portal will offer a unique SPARQL endpoint to
                    access RDF metadata of all the federation content to third party data consumers;
                    semiautomatically enrich the data to link certain type of resources (most
                    notably books, people, places and events) via rdfs:sameAs properties, to other
                    LOD providers such as DBPedia, Freebase, The Library of Congress, The Open
                    Library, Geonames, Europeana; offering an augmented search facility by expanding
                    queries with data extracted from third party LOD providers. Enhanced search will
                    be offered in an appealing and easy to use interface, for example, by allowing
                    visually browsing search results on a map and on a timeline.</p>
                <p>The Open Collaborative Peer Review Experiment has as its goal to experiment in
                    the field of open peer review in order to enhance and determine standards for
                    peer review in the humanities and social sciences in the digital age. In this
                    experiment authors submit their papers to two new online journals (Nordic
                    Wittgenstein Review and Lexicon Philosophicum) via Open Journal System (OJS).
                    Papers will undergo a general eligibility and quality check by the editors and
                    editors-in-chief. Papers will undergo double blind review during which authors
                    and reviewers will remain anonymous. Papers that are accepted for publication
                    will go through one month of additional open review or commentary, during which
                    registered users will be asked to comment on and to discuss the accepted papers.
                    Editors and editors-in-chief will moderate discussions. Editors will proceed
                    with suggesting revisions on the basis of the open review. Authors will be able
                    to use the suggestions, comments and discussions from the open review / comment
                    stage in finalizing their paper for publication. The online publication of the
                    articles will include functionality for readers to evaluate, rate and recommend
                    articles in a comment stage. The user will then be able to select from different
                    criteria of evaluation, such as highest rated, most read, and most cited.</p>
                <p>The goal of the PPP OA Business Models Experiment carried out by the philosophy
                    publishing house Ontos is to experiment with different OA Business Models in
                    order to gain insight into their effects on commercial business. A commercial
                    publisher will republish a selection of monographs in digital format and make
                    them available in Open Access, under a Creative Commons Attribution-Non
                    Commercial-No Derivative license. It will study the effects on sales figures
                    over time of re-publishing online in OA existing inprint closed access
                    monographs. It will further study the effects of publishing the Nordic
                    Wittgenstein Review under hybrid and delayed business models.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>Evaluation Strategy</head>
                <p>The overarching evaluation strategy that is used has been adapted from Value
                    Sensitive Design (VSD), a design methodology geared towards the values that are
                    involved in technology customization and design, which consists of ongoing
                    evaluation on three levels: conceptual, empirical and technical. VSD has been
                    informed by philosophy from the outset of its development, and is therefore
                    closer to a philosophical ethos, and also makes room for a philosophical as well
                    as user-based evaluation of the technologies as they develop. Even though this
                    methodology has been primarily used for ethical values of technology design and
                    implementation, we will be extending it to epistemic values as well. This is
                    particularly appropriate for technologies for scholarship where the two forms of
                    values are very closely connected, and will also contribute to the further
                    development of VSD as a methodology.</p>
            
            </div>
         
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <head>References</head>

            <p><hi rend="bold">Bartscherer, T., and R. Coover, eds.</hi> (2011). <hi rend="italic">Switching Codes. Thinking through New Technology in the Humanities and the
                    Arts</hi>. Chicago: U of Chicago P.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Bizer, C., T. Heath, and M. Hepp, eds.</hi> (2009). Special Issue on
                Linked Data<hi rend="italic">. International Journal on Semantic Web and Information
                    System</hi> 5(3).</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">D’Iorio, P.</hi> (2008). L’île des savoirs choisis. De HyperNietzsche
                à Scholarsource: pour une infrastructure de recherche sur le Web. <hi rend="italic">Recherches &amp; Travaux</hi> 72. </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">D’Iorio, P., and M. Barbera</hi> (2011).  Scholarsource: A Digital
                    Infrastructure for the Humanities. In T. Bartscherer and R. Coover (eds.), <hi
                        rend="italic">Switching Codes. Thinking through New Technology in the
                        Humanities and the Arts</hi>. Chicago: U of Chicago P.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Galey, A.</hi> (2011). Reading the Book of Mozilla: Web Browsers and
                the Materiality of Digital Texts. In R. Crone and S.Towheed, <hi rend="italic">The
                    History of Reading, Vol. 3: Methods, Strategies, Tactics</hi>. New York:
                Palgrave Macmillan.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Luke, T. W., and J. Hunsinger, eds.</hi> (2009). <hi rend="italic">Putting Knowledge to Work and Letting Information Play</hi>. Blacksburg: Center
                for Digital Discourse and Culture.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Mika, P., C. Bizer, M. C. Schaefel, and L. Rutledge</hi> (2010).
                Semantic Web Challenge 2009: User Interaction in Semantic Web Research. Special
                Issues of <hi rend="italic">Journal of Web Semantics</hi> 8(4).       </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Pichler, A.</hi> 2010. Towards the new Bergen Electronic Edition. In
                N. Venturinha (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Wittgenstein After His Nachlass</hi>.
                Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan.</p>
            <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">Pichler, A., and S. Säätelä, eds.</hi> (2008). <hi rend="italic"
                        >Philosophy of the Information Society: Proceedings of the 30th
                        International Ludwig Wittgenstein Symposium, Kirchberg am Wechsel, Austria
                        2007</hi>. Frankfurt: Ontos.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>