<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-420">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Pelagios: An Information Superhighway for the Ancient World</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Barker, Elton</name>
                    <affiliation>Open University, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>e.t.e.barker@open.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Simon, Rainer</name>
                    <affiliation>Austrian Institute of Technology, Austria</affiliation>
                    <email>Rainer.Simon@ait.ac.at</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Isaksen, Leif</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Southampton, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>leifuss@googlemail.com</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>On-line resources that reference ancient places are multiplying rapidly, bringing
                huge potential for the researcher provided that they can be found; but users
                currently have no way of easily navigating between them or comparing their contents.
                Pelagios, a growing international cooperative of online ancient world projects,<note>Pelagios includes: Arachne, <ref target="http://www.arachne.uni-koeln.de"
                        >http://www.arachne.uni-koeln.de</ref>; CLAROS, <ref
                        target="http://explore.clarosnet.org" type="external"
                        >http://explore.clarosnet.org</ref>; GAP, <ref
                        target="http://googleancientplaces.wordpress.com" type="external"
                        >http://googleancientplaces.wordpress.com</ref>; Nomisma, <ref
                        target="http://nomisma.org" type="external">http://nomisma.org</ref>; Open
                    Context, <ref target="http://opencontext.org" type="external"
                        >http://opencontext.org</ref>; Perseus, <ref
                        target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu" type="external"
                        >http://opencontext.org</ref>; Pleiades, <ref
                        target="http://pleiades.stoa.org" type="external"
                        >http://pleiades.stoa.org</ref>; Ptolemy Machine, <ref
                        target="http://ptolemymachine.appspot.com" type="external"
                        >http://ptolemymachine.appspot.com</ref>; SPQR, <ref
                        target="http://spqr.cerch.kcl.ac.uk" type="external"
                        >http://spqr.cerch.kcl.ac.uk</ref>; Ure museum, <ref
                        target="http://www.reading.ac.uk/Ure" type="external"
                        >http://www.reading.ac.uk/Ure</ref>.</note> addresses the problems of
                discovery and reuse with the twin aims of helping digital humanists to make their
                data more discoverable, and of empowering real-world users (scholars, students and
                the general public) to find information about particular ancient places and
                visualize it in meaningful ways. While the project focuses on the ancient world, the
                methodology and tools developed will be of interest to anyone working with data
                containing spatial references. The Pelagios family purposefully includes partners
                maintaining a wide range of different document types including texts, maps and
                databases. In doing so we take some of the first steps towards building a Geospatial
                Semantic Web for the Humanities.<note>See Harris et al. (2010).</note></p>
            <p>In this paper we discuss two of the major workflows underpinning Pelagios.
                    First, we address the method by which the partners prepare their data so that it
                    can be linked together in an open and transparent manner: i.e. what are the
                    processes that you should undertake if you want to make your data Pelagios
                    compliant? Second, we consider the various ways in which the results can be
                    visualized, paying particular attention to the tools and technologies used and
                    the problems encountered. We end with a brief description of our visualization
                    services – both a Graph Explorer and various embeddable web widgets – which, we
                    believe, demonstrate the value of taking a lightweight Linked Open Data approach
                    to addressing problems of discoverability, interconnectivity and reusability of
                    online resources. At the same time, however, we use this paper to discuss
                    real-world practical concerns as well as engage in deeper speculation about the
                    significance of this type of approach for escaping the ‘siloing’ mentality that
                    inhibits many other data integration initiatives.</p>
            
            <div>
            <head>Ontology</head>
                <p>The first part of the paper will sketch out and reflect upon the architectural
                    aspects of Pelagios, in particular the requirements necessary to maximize the
                    exposure and interconnectivity of the data themselves. The structure of the data
                    is targeted at helping the user groups of each partner accomplish two kinds of
                    task:</p>
                <p>A) Discovering the references to places within a single document
                    (text, map, database);</p>
                <p>B) Discovering all the documents (texts, maps, databases) that reference a
                    specified place.</p>
                <p>In order to achieve this we (i) use a common RDF model
                    to express place references (the OAC model); and (ii) align all local place
                    references to the Pleiades Ancient World Gazetteer. The OAC annotation ontology
                    provides an extremely lightweight framework for associating global concepts
                    (such as places) with specific documents (and fragments of them).<note>OAC is a powerful information model in its own right and has recently been used as the basis for the SharedCanvas annotation system. See Sanderson et al. (2011)</note> An OAC
                    annotation is a set of RDF triples which identify a target document (by means of
                    its URI) and the body of the annotation itself, in our case a URI identifying a
                    specific place in Pleaides. An example is given below:</p>
                <p>ex:ann1 rdf:Type      oac:Annotation</p>
                <p>            dcterms:title “Example annotation”</p>
                <p>            oac:hasTarget &lt;some resource&gt;</p>
                <p>            oac:hasBody   &lt;http://pleiades.stoa.org/places/[PLEIADES
                    ID]&gt;</p>
                
                <p>The decision to use the OAC model typifies our pragmatic lightweight
                    approach, which has not been to reinvent the wheel but to reduce, reuse and
                    recycle wherever possible. Using a publicly available, lightweight core ontology
                    permits modular extensions for different kinds of document so that details
                    specific to each type do not add unnecessary complexity for users wishing to
                    publish data in conformance with the core ontology. We have also found that
                    Pelagios partners are afforded a great deal of flexibility in implementation.
                    For example, the RDF may be expressed in a number of different formats (RDF/XML,
                    Turtle, RDFa, SPARQL, etc.) and the simplicity of the ontology allows partners
                    to focus on the considerably more challenging task of aligning local place
                    referencing systems with the global Pleiades gazetteer.</p>

                <p>Pelagios has been documenting the various processes by which each partner has identified
                    place references and aligned those references to Pleiades: one significant
                    outcome of the project will be a ‘cookbook’ guide for those looking to adopt a
                    lightweight Linked Open Data approach to related domains, which we outline here.
                    The Pelagios process, however, has greater extensibility than provision for
                    digital classicists. Although we are using URIs for places in the ancient world,
                    the OAC ontology is equally applicable to other gazetteers (including those
                    based on modern placenames, such as GeoNames) or even non-spatial entities such
                    as periods or people.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>The Pelagios Explorer and Embeddable Widgets</head>
                <p>The second part of the paper assesses the possibilities for data exploration once
                    different projects have adopted the core model for representing place
                    references. Here we discuss the technologies exploited in developing the
                    Pelagios Explorer, a prototype Web application that makes discovery and
                    visualization of the aggregated data simple, and various web widgets that can
                    sit on partner websites to provide a window onto the Pelagios linked data world.
                    By aggregating Pelagios partners’ place metadata in a Graph Database, the
                    Explorer supports a number of common types of query using visually-oriented
                    interaction metaphors (‘which places are referenced in these datasets?’, ‘what
                    is the geographical footprint of these datasets?’, ‘which datasets reference a
                    particular place’) and displays results using a graph-based representation.<note>Network visualizations are ideal for representing bipartite networks such as this. See, for example: Schich et al. (2009).</note> In
                    addition, the Pelagios Explorer exposes all data available in the visualizations
                    through an HTTP API to enable machine-access. For their part the widgets that we
                    are currently developing provide more specific views on Pelagios data than the
                    graph explorer allows (such as an overview of the data about a particular
                    place). But equally we are exploring ways of making these widgets easy to
                    configure to, customise for and embed in external Websites, thereby maximizing
                    the potential reuse value of the data.</p>
                <p>There are at least two different
                    user groups whose interests and concerns we address. For the ‘super users’
                    interested in contributing data, adhering to the two principles of the OAC model
                    and Pleiades URIs is the essential step in order to prepare data for use in
                    these various Pelagios visualizations. With these basic issues established, we
                    go on to discuss more detailed control over how data can be represented in a
                    generic interface, for instance using names and titles to label data, or
                    structuring a dataset hierarchically into subsets, such as individual books,
                    volumes, chapters, and pages. Toolset and methods are still at an early stage
                    but some useful resources have already been made available for general use via
                    our blog.<note><ref target="http://pelagios-project.blogspot.com/p/useful-resources.html" type="external">http://pelagios-project.blogspot.com/p/useful-resources.html</ref></note></p>
                <p>Our second user group represents scholars, students and
                    members of the public who may wish to discover the resources that reference an
                    ancient place of interest. We consider how the Pelagios framework is beginning
                    to bring together an enormous diversity of online data – such as books that
                    reference places, and archaeological finds discovered there – which a user can
                    search through, combine and visualize in various ways depending on their needs.<note>See screencasts at: <ref target="http://pelagios.dme.ait.ac.at/screencasts/exploring-datasets.html" type="external">http://pelagios.dme.ait.ac.at/screencasts/exploring-datasets.html</ref>, and <ref target="http://pelagios.dme.ait.ac.at/screencasts/exploring-places.html" type="external">http://pelagios.dme.ait.ac.at/screencasts/exploring-places.html</ref>.</note> In particular, we consider the challenges, both technological and intellectual,
                    regarding the development, production and use of such tools or services that aim
                    to provide a useful and intuitive resource for non technically-minded subject
                    specialists.</p>
                <p>We conclude with a brief reflection on the processes by
                    which the Pelagios family has been developing. In particular we stress the
                    digital services that have made the coordination of such an international
                    initiative possible, and outline the challenges that remain to anyone wishing to
                    add their data to the Pelagios multiverse.<note>A vision that coincides well with the discussion of the future of Classical scholarship by Elliott and Gillies (2009).</note></p>
                
                <p><hi rend="bold">Funding</hi></p>
                <p>This work has been supported by JISC (the Joint Information Systems Committee) as part of
                    the Geospatial and Community Outreach programme (15/10) and the Resource and
                    Discovery programme (13/11).</p>
                <p>Screenshots of the Pelagios Explorer:</p>
                <p><figure><graphic url="img420-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
                <p><figure><graphic url="img420-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
            </div>
            
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>

                    <head>References</head>

            <p><hi rend="bold">Elliott, T., and S. Gillies</hi> (2009). Digital Geography and
                    Classics. <hi rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly</hi> 3(1).</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Harris, T. M., L. J. Rouse, and S. Bergeron</hi> (2010). The
                Geospatial Semantic Web, Pareto GIS, and the Humanities. In D. J. Bodenhamer, J.
                Corrigan, and T. M. Harris (eds.), <hi rend="italic">The Spatial Humanities: GIS and
                    the Future of Scholarship</hi>. Bloomington: Indiana UP.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Sanderson, R., B. Albritton, R. Schwemmer, and H. van de Sompel</hi>
                    (2011). SharedCanvas: A Collaborative Model for Medieval Manuscript Layout
                    Dissemination. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 11th ACM/IEEE Joint
                        Conference on Digital Libraries</hi>. Ottawa, Canada.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Schich, M., C. Hidalgo, S. Lehmann, and J. Park</hi> (2009). The
                    network of subject co-popularity in Classical Archaeology. In <hi rend="italic"
                        >Bolletino di Archaeologia On-line</hi>.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>