<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-427">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Intra-linking the Research Corpus: Using Semantic MediaWiki as a lightweight Virtual Research Environment</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Schindler, Christoph</name>
                    <affiliation>German Institute for International Educational Research, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>schindler@dipf.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Ell, Basil</name>
                    <affiliation>Karlsruhe Institute of Technology, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>basil.ell@kit.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Rittberger, Marc</name>
                    <affiliation>German Institute for International Educational Research, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>rittberger@dipf.de</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>In recent years, virtual research environments (VREs) emerged as a topic
                    referring to the established research field in the digital humanities: enabling
                    research practices with digital tools. First projects in this area are realized
                    and discussed by the community (Carusi 2010; Dunn 2009; Neuroth et al. 2009). In
                    the humanities, researchers point out that the so-called ‘<hi rend="italic">data
                        deluge</hi>’ (Hey et al. 2003), which has influenced several national and
                    supranational information policy agendas in the sciences, does not cover the
                    full range of aspects of research practices in the humanities. While digital
                    libraries and archives offer a new plurality of research resources in the
                    humanities, the ‘<hi rend="italic">complexity deluge</hi>’ (Dunn 2009)
                    formulates an opposite agenda addressing the sometimes fuzzy, interfering and
                    dispersed practices of humanities research.<note>It should be mentioned that a
                        similar field of tension is articulated for the sciences as ‘science
                        friction’ (Edwards et al. 2011) by addressing the problems of different
                        disciplines working on the same phenomena and trying to
                    interoperate.</note>In this paper we want to address this tension between
                    research data, metadata and collaborative action in the design of research
                    corpora carried out within a VRE. Therefore we will focus the ongoing corpus
                    re-arrangement and the potentials of <hi rend="italic">Social Semantic
                        Media</hi> technologies to expand metadata creation and use in qualitative
                    research. Tools for qualitative research target the flexible coding system, i.e.
                    allowing researchers to annotate research resources according to a
                    classification system that may evolve over time. However, the tools have been
                    criticized for the limited metadata interoperability of resources and research
                    findings (Corti et al. 2011). In our paper, we outline the aspects of
                    interoperability in qualitative corpora research and focus on researchers’
                    capabilities to intra-link the corpus. We use the term <hi rend="italic"
                        >intra-linking</hi><note>This term refers to the concept of ‘intra-action’,
                        which describes the interrelations and re-configurations of research
                        apparatuses in respect of ‘locally stabilized phenomena’ (Barad 2003:
                        817).</note>to address a main aspect in qualitative research: to create and
                    to describe entities while allowing for the ongoing re-arrangement of entities
                    and their properties in the research process. These capabilities will be
                    discussed and exemplified within the scope of the project <hi rend="italic"
                        >Semantic MediaWiki for Collaborative Corpora Analysis</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">SMW-CorA</hi>) which aims to reconfigure <hi rend="italic"
                        >Semantic MediaWiki</hi> as a lightweight virtual research
                        environment.<note>This project is realized in co-operation between the
                        German Institute for International Educational Research (DIPF), the
                        Karlsruhe Institute of Technology (KIT), the Library for Research on
                        Educational History (BBF) and educational researchers mainly of the
                        Georg-August-University Göttingen. See <ref
                            target="http://www.dipf.de/en/projects/virtual-research-environment-for-research-in-the-history-of-education-smw-cora"
                            type="external"
                            >http://www.dipf.de/en/projects/virtual-research-environment-for-research-in-the-history-of-education-smw-cora</ref>.</note></p>
                <p>The field of corpora centered research in the digital humanities offers
                    interesting insights into the design of VREs. In the early 1990s, Biber pointed
                    out main aspects of corpus design by problematizing <hi rend="italic">a priori
                    </hi>determinations of its boundaries and formal specifications. He recommends
                    the selection of relevant objects and the formal description to be realized as a
                    cyclic or iterative process of corpus work (Biber 1993: 256). While a linguistic
                    approach mainly aims at a statistical ‘representation’ in relation to a target
                    population, qualitative corpus research, which is focused here, pursues a so
                    called qualitative selection, i.e. a typification of yet unknown properties in
                    research (Bauer 2000: 20). We argue that this indeterminacy of entities and
                    properties in qualitative research emphasizes the affordance of a VRE enabling
                    researchers to intra-link the corpus – it means to give them the ongoing
                    capabilities to create, modify and re-arrange entities and properties while
                    doing research. This topic of qualitative corpus research addresses the research
                    and design desideratum of qualitative annotations (Juola 2008) and a demanded
                    shift to further capabilities for the researcher to control the data (Smith
                    2008: 178).</p>
                <p>While the <hi rend="italic">SMW-CorA</hi> project targets the re-use of its VRE
                    infrastructure in different research contexts in the mid-term, its initial
                    design is subject to a co-operation with a research project in the history of
                    education, involving a major library in this field. The educational research
                    project encompasses the analysis of a corpus of 25 educational lexica dating
                    from 1774 to 1942, reconstructing the development of educational science.
                    Discourse, field and content analysis are supported and applied to grasp the
                    networked relationships in this scholarly field. The Library for the History of
                    Education (BBF) hosts a large part of the lexica at the digital library <hi
                        rend="italic">Scripta Paedagogica Online</hi> (<hi rend="italic"
                            >SPO</hi>).<note>The lexica are available at <ref target="http://bbf.dipf.de/digitale-bbf/scripta-paedagogica-online/digitalisierte-nachschlagewerke" type="external">http://bbf.dipf.de/digitale-bbf/scripta-paedagogica-online/digitalisierte-nachschlagewerke</ref>.</note> The collection amounts to nearly
                    22,000 articles. Each lexicon is bibliographically described and accessible
                    online as image files. Participatory and agile design approaches are used to
                    offer an adequate shared space for the different stakeholders to articulate
                    possible potentials and boundaries of the VRE.</p>

            <p>The <hi rend="italic">SMW-CorA</hi> project builds on a <hi rend="italic">Social
                        Semantic Media</hi> technology which in turn is based on the Web 2.0
                software <hi rend="italic">MediaWiki</hi> (<hi rend="italic">MW</hi>),<note>See <ref target="http://www.mediawiki.org" type="external">http://www.mediawiki.org</ref></note> which is used at the well-known online encyclopedia
                    Wikipedia, and the extension <hi rend="italic">Semantic Media Wiki</hi> (<hi
                        rend="italic">SMW</hi>).<note>The extension Semantic MediaWiki is described at <ref target="http://www.semantic-mediawiki.org" type="external">http://www.semantic-mediawiki.org</ref> and offers further extensions at <ref target="http://semantic-mediawiki.org/wiki/Help:Extensions" type="external">http://semantic-mediawiki.org/wiki/Help:Extensions</ref>.</note> The latter enables the
                    use of semantic annotations and integration within the Semantic Web through
                    import and export of semantic data and linking to external entities. While other
                    VREs<note>Some interesting cases using MW or SMW as a VRE are <ref target="http://www.docupedia.de/" type="external">http://www.docupedia.de/</ref>, a reference work in the area of historical research, <ref target="http://wiki.digitalclassicist.org" type="external">http://wiki.digitalclassicist.org</ref> and in the context of archives (Isto, 2008). Some further examples of using SMW are listed on the webpage <ref target="http://smw.referata.com/wiki/Special:BrowseData/Sites?Data_type=Science" type="external">http://smw.referata.com/wiki/Special:BrowseData/Sites?Data_type=Science</ref>.</note> have been realized using this wiki
                    technology, the <hi rend="italic">SMW-CorA</hi> project promotes research on a
                    corpus by configuring the facilities of <hi rend="italic">MW</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">SMW</hi> and by developing further extensions to offer a
                    configurable and lightweight VRE. </p>
                <p>As such, the basic framework <hi rend="italic">MediaWiki</hi> offers some
                    facilities for creating and typifying entities in a corpus for research (in our
                    case: lemmas, authors, institutions etc.). The online encyclopedia Wikipedia
                    demonstrates, besides the collaborative creation of texts, the capability to
                    store documents and digital objects. Therein a wiki page can be related to other
                    entities by hyperlinks and arranged within a hierarchical category system. <hi
                        rend="italic">SMW</hi> extends this by offering an increased granularity for
                    describing and linking the corpus by adding metadata descriptions used in the
                    Semantic Web. The unspecific hyperlinks between entities can be typified by
                    metadata and thereby entities can be enriched with attributes or semantic
                    relations to other entities. Furthermore, it is possible to import and export
                    metadata in the Semantic Web standard RDF.</p>
                <p>Within the scope of the project a set of use-cases is explored comprising the
                    scholarly work in the research life cycle from importing research resources,
                    coding, classifying and analyzing these to the export for re-use. The supported
                    and envisaged use cases have in common that entities can be integrated, created,
                    modified and interlinked (i.e. intra-linking). This functionality is focused
                    within the project and supported by tools to enable researchers to carry out an
                    ongoing re-arrangement of their corpora. While the aspects of importing lexica
                    from a digital library and of exporting the bibliographic data in RDF are
                    discussed in (Schindler et al. 2011), further use cases exemplify these
                    capabilities. Besides this import functionality, the enrichment of entities such
                    as editors, authors, and related affiliations with properties by using <hi
                        rend="italic">Semantic Web Browsing</hi> technologies is a further
                        example.<note>A prototype of this SMW-based extension Semantic Web Browser
                        is developed in collaboration with KIT – Benedikt Kämpgen, Anna
                        Kantorovitch, and Denny Vrandečić – and is accessible at <ref
                            target="http://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Extension:Semantic_Web_Browser"
                            type="external"
                            >http://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Extension:Semantic_Web_Browser</ref>.</note>
                    Thereby, semantic properties from digital archives, libraries or further
                    collections can be integrated and adapted to the locally used metadata schema in
                    the VRE. This enables researchers for example to add biographical data of
                    authors or editors from authority files (e.g. German National Library GND).
                    Furthermore the import and collaborative development of taxonomies (e.g.
                    classification or coding schema) are supported by interlinking entities within
                    the VRE and linking entities into<hi rend="bold"> </hi>the Web of Data. These
                    links to the world external to the corpus, together with the data export
                    facilities of the VRE, enable the reuse of the content created within the VRE.
                    Additionally, the VRE provides functionalities for creating and re-arranging
                    metadata schema as well as a bottom-up task management to allow supervision of
                    the research process.</p>
                <p>To summarize, we identified the need of researchers to create, manage and
                    intra-link entities and metadata objects in a research corpus. This
                    functionality is relevant for multiple use cases where researchers perform a
                    qualitative analysis on a corpus of resources such as digital/digitized
                    documents and images. Our main contribution is the development of a lightweight
                    collaborative and adaptive VRE that enables researchers to perform these tasks
                    as well as to enable export of the created data and the content’s sharing and
                    reuse. Since the VRE is based on a flexible Open Source platform it can be
                    tailored by the researchers towards their specific needs. Therefore this
                    lightweight environment may serve as a starting point for further re-uses and
                    re-configurations in unforeseen research settings and functionalities required
                    in the future.</p>
        </div>
            
            <div>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Funding</hi></p>
                <p>This work was supported by the German Research Foundation (DFG) in the domain of
                    ‘Scientific Library Services and Information Systems’ (LIS). The funded project
                    is entitled: ‘Entwicklung einer Virtuellen Forschungsumgebung für die
                    Historische Bildungsforschung mit Semantischer Wiki-Technologie – Semantic
                    MediaWiki for Collaborative Corpora Analysis’ [INST 367/5-1, INST 5580/1-1]</p>
                
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <head>References</head>

            <p><hi rend="bold">Barad, K.</hi> (2003). Posthumanist Performativity: Toward an
                Understanding of How Matter Comes to Matter. <hi rend="italic">Signs: Journal of
                    Women in Culture and Society</hi> 28(3): 801-831. </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Bauer, M. W., and B. Aarts</hi> (2000). Constructing a research
                corpus. In M.W. Bauer and  G. Gaskell (eds), <hi rend="italic">Qualitative
                    researching with text, image and sound: a practical handbook</hi>. Thousand
                Oaks: Sage, pp. 19-37.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Biber, D.</hi> (1993). Representativeness in corpus design. <hi
                    rend="italic">Literary and linguistic computing</hi> 8(4): 243-257.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Carusi, A., and T. Reimer</hi> (2010). <hi rend="italic">Virtual
                    Research Environment. Collaborative Landscape Study. A JISC funded project</hi>.
                <ref target="http://www.jisc.ac.uk/media/documents/publications /vrelandscapereport.pdf" type="external">http://www.jisc.ac.uk/media/documents/publications /vrelandscapereport.pdf</ref> (accessed
                30 October 2011).</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Corti, L., and A. Gregory</hi> (2011). CAQDAS Comparability. What
                    about CAQDAS Data Exchange? <hi rend="italic">Forum: Qualitative Social
                        Research</hi> 12. <ref
                        target="http://www.qualitative-research.net/index.php/fqs/article/viewArticle/1634"
                        type="external"
                        >http://www.qualitative-research.net/index.php/fqs/article/viewArticle/1634</ref>.
                    (accessed 30 October 2011).</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Dunn, S.</hi> (2009). Dealing with the complexity Deluge – VREs in
                the arts and humanities. <hi rend="italic">Library Hi Tech</hi> (27)2: 205-216.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Edwards, P. N., M. S. Mayernik, A. L. Batcheller, et al.</hi> (2011).
                Science friction: Data, metadata, and collaboration. <hi rend="italic">Social
                    Studies of Science</hi> 415): 667-690.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Hey, T., and A. Trefethen</hi> (2003). The Data Deluge: An e-Science
                Perspective. In F. Berman, G. Fox, and T. Hey (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Grid
                    Computing: Making the Global Infrastructure a Reality</hi>. Chichester: John
                Wiley &amp; Sons, pp. 809-824.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Huvila, I.</hi> (2008). Participatory archive: towards decentralised
                curation, radical user orientation, and broader contextualisation of records
                management. <hi rend="italic">Archival Science</hi> 8(1): 15-36.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Juola, P.</hi> (2008). Killer Applications in Digital Humanities<hi
                    rend="italic">. </hi><hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguist Computing</hi> 23:
                73-83.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Neuroth, H., F. Jannidis, A. Rapp, and F. Lohmeier</hi> (2009).
                Virtuelle Forschungsumgebungen für e-Humanities. Maßnahmen zur optimalen
                Unterstützung von Forschungsprozessen in den Geisteswissenschaften. <hi
                    rend="italic">Bibliothek. </hi><hi rend="italic">Forschung und Praxis</hi> 2:
                161-169.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Schindler, C., C. Veja, M. Rittberger, and D. Vrandečić</hi> (2011).
                    How to teach digital library data to swim into research. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Proceedings of I-SEMANTICS 2011: 7th International Conference on Semantic
                        Systems, </hi>Sept. 7-9, 2011, Graz, Austria New York: ACM International
                    Conference Proceedings Series (2011), 142-149 </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Smith, N., S. Hoffmann, and P. Rayson</hi> (2008). Corpus Tools and
                Methods, Today and Tomorrow: Incorporating Linguists’ Manual Annotations<hi
                    rend="italic">.</hi>
                <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguist Computing</hi> 23: 163-180.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>