<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-492">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>A Frequency Dictionary of Modern Written and Oral Media Arabic</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Elmaz, Orhan</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Vienna, Austria</affiliation>
                    <email>orhan.elmaz@univie.ac.at</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Learning Arabic</head>
                <p>Having about 500 million speakers, Arabic is not just the only Semitic world
                    language but also one of the six UN-languages. The interest in Media Arabic more
                    specifically increased with the popularity of the satellite station al-Jazeera
                    and the modern necessity for reflecting the Arab perspective of what is going on
                    in the world. People interested in the Arab opinions about what is going on in
                    the Middle East as an example should read Arabic newspapers since in ‘Western’
                    media – as Mol (2006: 309f.) states: ‘often only information on the Arab world
                    gathered by people who have not mastered the Arabic language […] often only
                    interpretations of the Arab world from a Western view are found.’</p>
            </div>
            <div><head>Methods &amp; Results</head><p>On the base of newspaper texts (Written Media
                    Arabic) and – up to date disregarded – transcripts (Oral Media Arabic), a
                    learner’s vocabulary was developed and evaluated in a computer-assisted way. The
                    corpora put together comprise 23.5 million tokens (cp. Routledge Frequency
                    Dictionaries) and were edited in Perl (a.o. CP-1256 incompatible ligatures were
                    broken down and data read wrongly [about 2%] was deleted).</p>
                
                <p><figure><graphic url="tabl492-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
                
                <p/>
                    <p>The corpora were analysed using Tim Buckwalter’s word-stem based Buckwalter
                    Arabic Morphologic Analyzer (BAMA 1.0) the output of which was changed in such a
                    way that only possible lemmas per token could be saved (without any further
                    information). Then, line duplicates (semantic ambiguity) were deleted and the
                    line resp. lemma set frequencies were calculated. The latter were broken up and
                    analysed fully forming our primary knowledge base together with each lemma’s
                    estimated frequency in Google News. The material was analysed manually in a
                    top-down manner (average morphological ambiguity rate: 3 possible analyses per
                    token) and a frequency vocabulary of just above 3,500 lemmas (estimated to
                    correspond to CEFR B2) sorted by their roots resp. word families, was extracted.
                    It was demonstrated that these cover 95% of non-trivial, recent media texts
                    which were lemmatised manually! Further, the number of look-ups in dictionaries
                    is reduced to 24 ± 10 times for texts with an average length of about 550 ± 60
                    words. </p>
                <p>In order to be on line with the language of media, neologisms (extracted by word
                    length, patterns and concordances) and generally disregarded multi word items
                    (extracted by n-gram analyses, finding collocations [after Dunning 1993]) which
                    constitute integral elements of it, were dealt with separately.</p>
                <p>A discursive glossary including dialectal variants which textbooks published up
                    to now are lacking tops the study off.</p>
                <p><figure><graphic url="tabl492-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
                <p>The present material can be useful for reading courses in which students of different levels and
                        background come together in order to level differences in vocabulary.
                        Moreover, the corpora can be used for learning collocations with the help of
                        concordances in an explorative manner and make idiomatic corrections in
                        writing assignments.</p>
            
                
            </div>
           
           
                <div>
                    <head>Corpora</head>
                <p>The largest corpus is made up of texts published between 1 June 2008 and 31 May
                    2009 in the pan-Arab newspaper al-Quds al-<foreign>ʿ</foreign>Arabī (London) consisting of about 20
                    million tokens. In order to augment the sections of economy and sports a corpus
                    for each was built using texts from the Qatari newspaper al-Šarq. Oral Media
                    Arabic was regarded by creating a corpus of about 1,5 million tokens out of
                    al-Jazeera transcripts.</p>
                </div>
            <div>
                <head>Text coverage</head>
                <p>The following table informs about the contents and length of ten texts
                        (disregarding digits), for which the dictionary’s coverage was tested. The
                        first six are from Lahlali 2008. One finds the number of unknown words (NF),
                        the text coverage rate, the number of words which can be understood by
                        morphological and generative knowledge (NWB) and the number of therein
                        subsumed proper nouns (PN) as well as the therewith corrected coverage rate
                        and the number of look-ups (LU) in dictionaries.</p><p><figure><graphic url="tabl492-3.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p><p>Therefore, one can relativise the FSI classification of Arabic –
                        ex aequo with Chinese, Japanese and Korean – as super hard language and the
                        opinion of some natives who – as Belnap puts it ironically (2008: 59) –
                        ‘almost universally revere Arabic as the most difficult language in the
                        world and therefore essentially unlearnable by mortals.’
                </p>
                <p><figure>
                    <graphic url="img492-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                        mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    
                </figure></p>
                <p><figure>
                    <graphic url="img492-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                        mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    
                </figure></p>
                <p><figure>
                    <graphic url="img492-3.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                        mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    
                </figure></p>
                <p><figure>
                    <graphic url="img492-4.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                        mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    
                </figure></p>
            </div>
                    
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                                  <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Belnap, R. K.</hi> (2008). If you build it, they will come. In Z.
                    Ibrahim and S. A. M. Makhlouf (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Linguistics in an Age of
                        Globalization: Perspectives on Arabic Language and Teaching</hi>. Cairo: AUC
                    Press, pp. 53-66.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Buckwalter, T.</hi> (2002). <hi rend="italic">Buckwalter Arabic
                        Morphological Analyzer Version 1.0</hi>. Linguistic Data Consortium. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Dunning, T.</hi> (1993). Accurate methods for the statistics of
                    surprise and coincidence. <hi rend="italic">Computational Linguistics</hi>
                    19(1): 61-74.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Lahlali, El Mustapha</hi> (2008). <hi rend="italic">Advanced
                        Media Arabic</hi>. Edinburgh: Edinburgh UP.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Mol, M. van</hi> (2006). Arabic Receptive Language Teaching: a
                    new CALL approach. In K. M. Wahba et al. (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Handbook for
                        Arabic language teaching professionals</hi>. Mahwah: Lawrence Erlbaum, pp.
                    305-314.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>