<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-421">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Literary Wikis: Crowd-sourcing the Analysis and Annotation of Pynchon, Eco and Others</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Ketzan, Erik</name>
                    <affiliation>Institut für Deutsche Sprache, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>eketzan@lavabit.com</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Annotation of complicated texts – the <hi rend="italic">Bible</hi>, the works
                    of Shakespeare, experimental fiction – is a familiar concept. In 2005 I had an
                    idea: what if I used a wiki to create such a guide? Would anyone contribute to
                    it? Would anyone read it? Would the results be any good? Since then, hundreds of
                    users have annotations thousands of pages of experimental fiction by the authors
                    Thomas Pynchon and Umberto Eco, and the projects <hi rend="italic"
                        >PynchonWiki</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Umberto Eco Wiki</hi>.</p>
                <p>What have we learned from these projects? What can other digital humanities and
                    crowd-sourcing projects learn from their successes and failures? The Eco wiki
                    project is still ongoing, but I plan to present my findings and insights at DH
                    2012.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>The Queen Loana Wiki</head>
                <p>When Umberto Eco’s novel, <hi rend="italic">The Mysterious Flame of Queen Loana,</hi>
                    was published a few months later, I launched what I called the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Queen Loana Annotation Project</hi>, a wiki organized by chapter and
                    page.<note>The Mysterious Flame of Queen Loana Annotation Project was initially online at <ref target="http://queenloana.wikispaces.com/" type="external">http://queenloana.wikispaces.com/</ref>. Later it was moved to my own Literarywiki.org, and its contents will soon be migrated to the Umberto Eco Wiki (a project of the Institut für Deutsche Sprache), at <ref target="http://eco.ids-mannheim.de" type="external">http://eco.ids-mannheim.de</ref></note> Eco’s novel was a perfect test case for the
                    experiment I envisioned, a literary annotation wiki. First, Eco frequently
                    quotes texts without attribution, which led to wiki entries like:</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">P. 15, ‘you always said you could resist anything but
                        temptation’</hi></p>
                <p>quotation from <hi rend="italic">Lady Windermere’s Fan</hi> by Oscar Wilde.</p>
                
                <p>Second, many references in the novel were confusing to readers, making my wiki a <hi rend="italic"
                        >useful</hi> resource. According to a <hi rend="italic">Village Voice</hi>
                    review at the time, ‘Early reviews have dismissed <hi rend="italic">Mysterious
                        Flame</hi> as nostalgic and at times so personal as to be impenetrable. Eco
                    concedes he wrote it with his own generation in mind. “It’s a book for Italian
                    people of my age”.’ Thanks to the wiki, though, readers could easily read up on
                    all those references, with entries like this:</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">P. 382, ‘Rina Fort’</hi></p>
                <p>On November 30, 1946, a woman and her three children were found beaten to death
                    in their apartment in Milan. In January, 1950, Caterina Fort, the lover of the
                    woman’s husband, was condemned to life imprisonment for the murders.</p>
                
                <p>Third, Eco has written dozens of books and he frequently references the same
                    incidents, themes and ideas across them. For example:</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">P. 297, A rose by another other name</hi></p>
                <p>from <hi rend="italic">Romeo &amp; Juliet</hi>.</p>
                <p>Eco remarked in <hi rend="italic">Postscript to The Name of the Rose</hi> that
                    everyone assumed that the title, <hi rend="italic">Name of the Rose</hi>, was a
                    reference to this same line of Juliet. Eco emphasizes, however, that he meant
                    his title to mean the exact opposite: names <hi rend="italic">are</hi>
                    important.</p>
                <p>This kind of entry requires more than just Googling. Only
                    someone truly familiar with Eco’s previous works could have written it, thus
                    adding another <hi rend="italic">useful</hi> element to the wiki on par with
                    traditional published literary analysis and commentary.</p>
                <p>In short, the
                        <hi rend="italic">Queen Loana Annotation Project</hi> was a modest success.
                    A couple dozen contributors from around the globe added hundreds of high-quality
                    entries. This group of contributors, which briefly felt like a ‘community’,
                    annotated seemingly every last historical, literary, and artistic reference in
                    Eco’s novel. The quality of the annotations was also surprisingly good, on par
                    with a publishable guide book.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>Pynchonwiki.com</head>
                <p>The next year, 2006, a musician and writer
                    named Tim Ware converted his extensive online notes on the novels of Thomas
                    Pynchon into a wiki, which he aptly named Pynchonwiki.com. The works of Pynchon
                    were also perfect for a literary wiki, as Pynchon’s novels teem with countless
                    obscure references which, when analyzed, often illuminate his bigger themes and
                    messages. I joined Pynchonwiki as one the earliest contributors (under the
                    handle ‘Bleakhaus’) and created a section for page-by-page annotation in the
                    manner of the <hi rend="italic">Queen Loana Annotation Project</hi>. This one
                    took off beyond the wildest expectations of a literary annotation wiki geek.</p>
                
                <p>According to Ralph Schroeder and Matthijs den Besten, scholars at Oxford’s
                    Internet Research Institute and e-Research Centre who published a paper<note>Schroeder, R., and M. L. den Besten (2008). Literary Sleuths Online: e-Research Collaboration on the Pynchon Wiki. Information, Communication &amp; Society 11(2): 25-45. Available at SSRN: <ref target="http://ssrn.com/abstract=1086671" type="external">http://ssrn.com/abstract=1086671</ref></note> on Pynchonwiki, some successes of Pynchonwiki
                    include:</p>
                
                <xmt:uList>
                <item>Over 235 contributors</item>
                <item>Over 455,000 words (over twice as long as <hi rend="italic">Moby
                    Dick</hi>)</item>
                <item>1350+ alphabetical entries</item>
                <item>4000+ page-by-page entries</item>
                <item>>10,000+ edits</item>
                </xmt:uList>
                
                <p>Schroeder and den Besten also concluded that:</p>
                
                <xmt:uList>
                <item>‘the Wiki had covered all pages within three months of publication’</item>
                <item>‘the Pynchon Wiki can be put into the context of growing interest in
                    computer supported collaboration and e-Research’</item>
                <item>‘A common theme emerging from the facts and figures presented is the
                    tremendous attraction of the page-by-page style of annotation in the “Against
                    the Day” wiki’</item>
                <item>‘Wikis thus seem to be a good tool [for tasks] where endless detective work
                    is called for, and this may apply to other areas of e-Research or online
                    collaboration’</item>
                <item>‘the Wiki is bound to encourage learning among contributors’</item>
                    
                </xmt:uList>
                
                <p>Section for Pynchon’s other novels followed shortly at Pynchonwiki.com, and
                    in short order there existed annotations for almost all of the thousands of
                    pages in Pynchon’s oeuvre.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>What next? Umberto Eco Wiki and linguistic exploration</head>
                <p>Over the next few years, I thought vaguely about how the lessons and successes of the
                        <hi rend="italic">Queen Loana Annotation Project</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Pynchonwiki</hi> could be repeated. I created a site, Literarywiki.com, for
                    my own experiments in annotating different kinds of texts. But I quickly
                    discovered that most novels do not benefit from extensive commentary or
                    annotation. Only certain kinds of novels, those that teem with information,
                    references, and/or enigmas, benefited from such supplementary information. The
                    novels of Pynchon and Umberto Eco, I came to believe, were exceptions rather
                    than the rule.</p>
                <p>To explore these issues in greater depth, I will launch, this coming week, the
                    first of November, 2011, a new website named Umberto Eco Wiki, which I am
                    creating through the support of my current employer, the Institut für Deutsche
                    Sprache (Mannheim, Germany).<note>Umberto Eco Wiki, available at <ref
                            target="http://eco.ids-mannheim.de" type="external"
                            >http://eco.ids-mannheim.de</ref></note>To coincide with the German- and
                    English-language editions of Umberto Eco’s new novel, <hi rend="italic">The
                        Prague Cemetery</hi>, I will launch this wiki in the spirit of the
                    above-named projects.</p>
                <p>Umberto Eco Wiki has secions
                    for German and English annotations, and I plan to explore how successful and
                    useful such a resource in multiple languages can be.</p>

                <p>My proposed short paper for Digital Humanities 2012 will document the history of
                    the literary wiki as summarized above, relate the progress on the new Umberto
                    Eco Wiki, explore issues relating to the literary wiki concept, including how
                    its lessons can be applied to other digital humanities areas.</p>
                
            </div>
        </body>
        
    </text>
</TEI>