<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-451">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Electronic Deconstruction of an argument using corpus linguistic analysis of its on-line discussion forum supplement</title>
                <author>
                    <name>O’Halloran, Kieran Anthony</name>
                    <affiliation>King’s College, University of London, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>kieran.o’halloran@kcl.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>In the last few years, one technological innovation has been the appending of
                        discussion forum facilities to online arguments, such as in online versions
                        of newspapers. The facility allows readers to post responses to an argument
                        and to debate issues raised in it. Such online discussion forums can be
                        regarded as electronic supplements to these arguments.</p>
                <p>The aim of this presentation is to report on research which highlights the
                    utility value of this electronic supplementarity for critical reading of
                    arguments (see O’Halloran, 2010, 2011 2012). I show how a content analysis of an
                    online discussion forum appended to an argument can illuminate repression or
                    marginalisation in the latter of concepts which are used in normal discussion of
                    the argument’s topic. In turn, I demonstrate how this can reveal where the
                    rhetorical structure of the argument is unstable, where it deconstructs. Since,
                    to conduct such content analysis, I use corpus linguistic method – the analysis
                    of collections of electronic texts – I refer to this approach to critical
                    reading as <hi rend="italic">Electronic Deconstruction</hi>. The<hi
                        rend="italic"> </hi>theoretical stimulus for this approach comes from an
                    appropriation of ‘the supplement’, an idea of the French philosopher, Jacques
                    Derrida.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>Keyword Analysis</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Concepts normally used for discussion of a topic</head>
                    <p>If an online discussion forum is sufficiently large, and contains a
                        substantial number of critical posts, it can provide illumination of <hi
                            rend="italic">what </hi>concepts are normally used in discussion of a
                        particular topic regardless of <hi rend="italic">how</hi> these concepts are
                        used, e.g. whether these concepts are assented to or not. Should certain
                        concepts be salient in the forum as a whole but absent from, or at best
                        marginal in, the original argument, this can offer insights into what the
                        argument might be said to repress or marginalise from normal conceptual
                        discussion of its topic. Since the discussion forum is directly related to
                        the original argument, then arbitrariness will have been considerably
                        reduced in producing these insights.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Keywords</head>
                    <p>Salient concepts in an online discussion forum, or any collection of
                            electronic texts, can be revealed through keyword analysis using
                            appropriate corpus linguistic software. A keyword is ‘a word which
                            occurs with unusual frequency in a given text…by comparison with a
                            reference corpus’ (Scott 1997: 236). Keywords are established through
                            statistical measures such as log likelihood (see Dunning, 1993). A log
                            likelihood value of ≥ 7 (p &lt; 0.01) confers keyness on a word. The
                            larger the log likelihood value ≥ 7, the greater the salience of the
                            keyword. Importantly, the log likelihood value, as a statistical
                            measure, reduces arbitrariness in what is selected as salient.</p>
                        <p>Comparison of the highest value keywords in a discussion
                            forum with words in the original argument can be illuminating. For this
                            presentation, the following types of keyword are relevant:</p>
                    <xmt:uList>
                        <item>
                            high value keywords in the forum which are absent from the original
                            argument. These are candidates for the status of repressed concepts from
                            the argument;</item>
                        <item>high value keywords in the forum which are used
                            infrequently in the original argument. These are candidates for the
                            status of marginalised concepts in the argument.</item>
                    </xmt:uList>
                    
                    <p>Keyword analysis should not only be quantitative. They also need to be
                            qualitatively explored to understand how they are being used.
                            Qualitative exploration of keywords in the discussion forum can, in
                            turn, strengthen judgements as to marginalised / repressed candidacy in
                            the original argument.</p>
                    <p>In order to mobilise how I
                            use keywords in a discussion forum supplement for purposes of Electronic
                            Deconstruction, I take as stimulus how Derrida conceives of ‘the
                            supplement’.</p>
                    
                </div>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                    <head>Discussion forums as supplements</head>
                
                <div>
                    <head>Derrida’s supplement </head>
                    <p>
                        We normally think of the word ‘supplement’ as meaning something extra, an
                            add-on. For Derrida, the supplement is more subtle. This is because he
                            illuminates how a supplement ‘adds only to replace’ a lack of something.
                            So, while the supplement may seem like an add-on and thus <hi
                                rend="italic">outside</hi> that which is supplemented, in fact it
                            becomes simultaneously<hi rend="italic"> inside</hi> that which it is
                            added to. Derrida writes that every supplement:</p>
                    <p>…harbors within itself two significations whose cohabitation is as strange as
                        it is necessary […] [The supplement] adds only to replace. It intervenes or
                        insinuates itself <hi rend="italic">in-the-place-of</hi> (Derrida 1976
                        [1967]: 144-145).</p>
                    <p>Take, for example, a shop sign outside a bicycle shop. It is outside the shop
                        not part of the inside. It is an add-on, an extra, signaling the nature of
                        the shop. However, in being outside the shop it ‘adds to replace’ a ‘lack’
                        inside the shop – the shop cannot function unless it can attract custom. The
                        shop sign is thus simultaneously an add-on and an essential part of the shop
                        – it is both outside and oddly ‘inside’ the shop as well.</p>
                    
                </div>
                    <div>
                    <head>Discussion forums as Derridean supplements</head>
                    <p>If we apply the logic of the supplement to online discussion forums appended
                        to arguments, then a discussion forum is not just outside the original
                        argument. It is not just an add-on, an extra. On the logic of the
                        supplement, concepts which are normally used to discuss a topic as reflected
                        in keywords in an online discussion forum - but which are absent in the
                        original argument – can be seen as ‘lacking’ in the argument. In turn, this
                        can offer insights into repression or marginalisation in the argument (<hi
                            rend="italic">relative</hi> to the particular supplement). Furthermore,
                        since keywords are generated non-arbitrarily, we have in turn a
                        non-arbitrary basis for intervening in the argument. We can use these
                        keywords to ‘add to replace’ what can be perspectivised as deficient in
                        normal discussion of the argument’s topic, intervening to replace an absence
                            <hi rend="italic">inside</hi> the argument with keywords <hi
                            rend="italic">outside</hi> the argument. Via the logic of the
                        supplement, the border between an argument and its discussion forum
                        supplement is porous. </p>
                    <p>To be clear, my use of Derrida’s notion of the supplement is an appropriation
                        of his work. Though Derrida is synonymous with an approach to critical
                        reading called ‘Deconstruction’, I am not doing Derridean Deconstruction.
                        While I appropriate the idea of supplements as being simultaneously inside
                        and outside the things that are supplemented, this does not mean that I
                        concur with Derrida’s vision where meaning is ultimately undecideable.
                        Indeed, a corpus linguistic approach illuminates Derrida’s focus on
                        undecideability in language and meaning to be misguided (see O’Halloran
                        2012). </p>
                </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Using the supplement to investigate deconstruction in an argument </head>
                    <p>The next stage is to trace the extent to which an intervention in the
                        argument ‘to add to replace’ leads to instability in its cohesion. An
                        argument’s rhetorical structure is dependent on effective cohesion. If
                        cohesion is disturbed by this intervention, then the credibility of the
                        argument diminishes.</p>
                    </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The argument topic: ‘New Atheism’</head>
            <div>
                    <head>Orientation</head>
                    <p>I demonstrate the method of Electronic Deconstruction on an argument in an
                            online version of a British newspaper.<note>The argument consists of 926
                                words (42 sentences). The whole argument and the discussion forum
                                appended to it can be found at: <ref
                                    target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2007/dec/30/thenewatheism"
                                    type="external"
                                    >http://www.guardian.co.uk/commentisfree/2007/dec/30/thenewatheism</ref>.</note>
                            Written by the journalist Brendan O’Neill, the argument criticises ‘new
                            atheism’, the atheism associated with thinkers such as Richard Dawkins.
                            The entire argument rests on a rhetorical structural opposition: ‘old
                            atheism’ (e.g. the atheism of Karl Marx) is good while ‘new atheism’ is
                            bad. Using the corpus linguistic software WMatrix (Rayson 2008),
                        O’Halloran (2010, 2011) generates keywords in the discussion forum appended
                        to the argument.<note>The discussion forum appended to the argument consists
                            of 365 individual posts, which in total come to 69, 252 words. In order
                            for keywords to be revealed, WMatrix compares the discussion forum with
                            a <hi rend="italic">reference corpus </hi>of around 1 million words of
                            written English (which WMatrix accesses online).<hi rend="bold"
                            > </hi></note> ‘Faith’ is a keyword with high statistical significance,
                        its meaning mostly equivalent to ‘religious belief’; ‘belief’ in the sense
                        of ‘religious belief’ also has a high keyness value. Qualitatively examining
                        how the keywords are used in discussion forum posts, I found that discussion
                        of ‘new atheism’ is in relation to criticism of belief/faith in a
                        supernatural power. That ‘religious belief’ or ‘faith’ are key concerns of
                        ‘new atheism’ can be corroborated by examining relevant websites / books by
                        ‘new atheists’<note>In a three minute clip, Richard Dawkins summarises a
                            central argument of ‘The God Delusion’: ‘The great majority of people on
                            this planet do <hi rend="bold">believe</hi> that there is some kind of a
                            supreme being…historically it’s always been very important to people
                            their <hi rend="bold">belief</hi> in some sort of a supreme being…I give
                            in the book the argument…that there is no supernatural supreme being and
                            that <hi rend="bold">belief</hi> in such a being can under some
                            circumstances be rather a bad thing’ [my bold]. The clip can be viewed
                            at:  <ref
                                target="http://www.amazon.com/The-God-Delusion-Richard-Dawkins/dp/0618918248/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1330788377&amp;sr=8-1"
                                type="external"
                                >http://www.amazon.com/The-God-Delusion-Richard-Dawkins/dp/0618918248/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1330788377&amp;sr=8-1</ref>  
                            [Accessed March 2012].</note></p>
                
                    <p>Turning my attention to the argument, ‘faith’ is absent from it and
                        ‘religious belief’ is marginal, only occurring twice; in contrast, the
                        argument contains 21 instances of the general category ‘religion’. O’Neill
                        describes ‘new atheists’ as being critical of ‘religion’ generally rather
                        than of ‘faith’ / ‘religious belief’ in a supernatural power. In sum, we can
                        say that relative to normal discourse for ‘new atheism’ (as reflected in the
                        discussion forum), there is a deficiency in the argument of ‘faith’ /
                        ‘religious belief’.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head> Exploring possible deconstruction in rhetorical structure </head>
                    
                        <p>Below is an example of deconstruction in O’Neill’s argument. Sentences
                            8-10 set up the rhetorical structure of ‘new atheism’ (bad) versus ‘old
                            atheism (good)’:</p>
                    <p>8. History’s greatest atheists, or the ‘old
                            atheists’ as we are now forced to call them, were humanistic and
                            progressive, critical of <hi rend="bold">religion</hi> because it
                            expressed man’s sense of <hi rend="italic">higher</hi> ethical purpose
                            in a deeply flawed fashion [emphasis added].</p>
                    <p>9. The new atheists are screechy and intolerant; they see <hi rend="bold"
                                >religion</hi> merely as an expression of mass ignorance and
                            delusion.</p>
                    <p>10. Their aim seems to be, not only to
                            bring belief [in] God crashing back down to earth, but also to <hi
                                rend="italic">downgrade</hi> mankind itself [emphasis added].</p>
                    <p>Notice ‘new atheists’ are described as LOW and ‘old atheists’ as HIGH
                            (see italics).</p>
                        <p>What happens to the cohesion of this rhetorical structure if
                            I ‘add to replace’ the deficiency of ‘faith’ and ‘religious belief’ in
                            normal discussion of ‘new atheism’ (as reflected in the discussion
                            forum) in sentences 9 and 10? (I do not intervene in sentence 8 since
                            this relates to ‘old atheism’):</p>
                    <p>8. History’s greatest atheists, or the ‘old atheists’ as we are now forced to call them, were
                            humanistic and progressive, critical of <hi rend="bold">religion</hi>
                            because it expressed man’s sense of <hi rend="italic">higher</hi>
                            ethical purpose in a deeply flawed fashion [emphasis added].</p><lb/>
                        <p>9. The new atheists are screechy and intolerant; they see  <hi
                            rend="bold">{religion}</hi><hi rend="bold"> </hi><hi rend="italic"
                            >religious belief</hi> merely as an expression of mass ignorance and
                        delusion [emphasis added].</p>
                    <p>10. Their aim seems to be, not only to bring <hi rend="italic">belief</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">[in]</hi> God crashing back down to earth, but also to <hi
                            rend="italic">downgrade</hi> mankind itself [emphasis added].</p>
                    <p>As a
                            result of this intervention, the general category of ‘religion’ in
                            sentence 8 is no longer in cohesion with this general category in
                            sentence 9. Since the rhetorical structure of ‘old atheists’ = good /
                            high and ‘new atheists’ = bad / low is dependent on this cohesion, the
                            rhetorical structure can be said to deconstruct. Thus, once normal
                            discourse for ‘new atheism’ is instituted, the argument can be evaluated
                            as falling apart structurally.</p>
                    </div>
                
                </div>
        </body>
        <back><div>
                <head>References</head>
    
            <p><hi rend="bold">Derrida, J.</hi> (1976 [1967]). <hi rend="italic">Of
                    Grammatology</hi> [trans G.C. Spivak] Baltimore: Johns Hopkins UP.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Dunning, T.</hi> (1993). Accurate methods for the statistics of
                    surprise and coincidence. <hi rend="italic">Computational Linguistics</hi>
                    19(1): 61-74.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">O’Halloran, K. A.</hi> (2010). Critical reading
                of a text through its electronic supplement. <hi rend="italic">Digital Culture and
                    Education</hi> 2(2): 210-229.</p>
            <p><ref target="http://www.digitalcultureandeducation.com/cms/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/DCE1022_ohalloran_2010.pdf"
                type="external">http://www.digitalcultureandeducation.com/cms/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/DCE1022_ohalloran_2010.pdf</ref></p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">O’Halloran, K. A.</hi> (2011). Limitations of the
                logico-rhetorical module: Inconsistency in argument, online discussion forums and
                Electronic Deconstruction. <hi rend="italic">Discourse Studies</hi> 13(6):
                797-806.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">O’Halloran, K. A.</hi> (2012). Electronic deconstruction: revealing
                tensions in the cohesive structure of persuasion texts. <hi rend="italic"
                    >International Journal of Corpus Linguistics</hi> 17(1): 91-124.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Rayson, P.</hi> (2008). Wmatrix: a Web-based Corpus Processing
                Environment. Computing Department, Lancaster University. <ref
                    target="http://ucrel.lancs.ac.uk/wmatrix" type="external">http://ucrel.lancs.ac.uk/wmatrix</ref>.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Scott, M.</hi> (1997). PC analysis of key words – and key key
                words. <hi rend="italic">System</hi> 25(2): 233-45.</p>
        </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>