<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-457">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The MayaArch3D Project: A 3D GIS Web System for Querying Ancient Architecture and Landscapes</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Schwerin, Jennifer von</name>
                    <affiliation>University of New Mexico, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>jvonschw@unm.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Richards-Rissetto, Heather</name>
                    <affiliation>University of New Mexico, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>heathmrr@hotmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Agugiaro, Giorgio</name>
                    <affiliation>FBK Trento, Italy</affiliation>
                    <email>agugiaro@fbk.eu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Remondino, Fabio</name>
                    <affiliation>FBK Trento, Italy</affiliation>
                    <email>remondino@fbk.eu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Girardi, Gabrio</name>
                    <affiliation>GraphiTech Trento, Italy</affiliation>
                    <email>gabrio.girardi@graphitech.it</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>In this paper, we highlight the need in humanities research for 3D tools with
                enhanced analytical functionality and present an innovative 3D Web GIS system that
                we are developing – called QueryArch3D – for studies of ancient architecture and
                landscapes. We explore the role this tool is playing in the development of new
                methodologies and formulating and addressing research questions in humanities
                research. Specifically, we demonstrate how research and teaching on archaeology and
                art history can be dramatically assisted by a Virtual Research Environment that
                offers the ability to search and query segmented 3D models (both CAD and
                reality-based) that are linked to attribute data stored in a spatial database in the
                context of an online VR landscape – in this case, the eighth-century Maya kingdom of
                Copan, Honduras.  </p>
            <p>Modern sensor and computing technologies are changing the practice of art history and
                archaeology because they offer innovative ways to document, reconstruct, and
                research the ancient world (e.g., El-Hakim et al. 2008; Reindel &amp; Wagner 2009).
                3D digital models and virtual reality (VR) environments allow for remote viewing of
                objects, as well as multiple iterations of hypothetical reconstructions, and offer
                the sense of space and experience that researchers now desire (e.g., Barcelo et al.
                2000). But, as has been pointed out, there is a common perception that while 3D
                models are good for education or data conservation, they are not useful for research
                because they are often deemed as purely illustrative and not useful for analysis
                (e.g., Frischer &amp; Dakouri-Hild 2008). One promising opportunity offered by 3D
                models is to use them as visualization ‘containers’ for different kinds of
                information. Given the possibility to link their geometry to external data, 3D
                models can be analyzed, split into sub-components, and organized following proper
                rules. Powerful 3D visualization tools already exist, but often they implement no or
                only limited query functionalities for data retrieval, and very few of these are
                web-based. In contrast, Geographic Information Systems (GIS) include queries as
                standard functions and allow for complex spatial analyses – and therefore are
                well-suited to research (e.g., Bodenhamer et al. 2010; Conolly &amp; Lake
                2006). </p>
            <p>Along these lines, archaeologists are using GIS to perform quantitative analyses,
                such as visibility, accessibility, and network studies, to explore the structure of
                ancient societies and relationships between anthropogenic and natural phenomena. GIS
                software, however, falls short when dealing with detailed and complex 3D data. It is
                comprised of 2.5D data, which are not ideally suited to approaches such as
                performance studies, phenomenology and aesthetics, the relationship of architecture
                and landscape, and archaeoastronomy that are becoming increasingly common in
                archaeology and art history. 3D models of architecture are simply more appropriate
                for these kinds of investigations, but most 3D digital models of architecture are
                single objects, removed from the context of their place in the landscape and are not
                linked to scientific data.</p>
            <p>In 2009, the MayaArch3D Project (http://mayaarch3d.unm.edu) was begun to explore the
                possibilities of integrating GIS and 3D digital tools for humanities research. This
                interdisciplinary, international project was funded largely by two Digital
                Humanities Start-Up Grants from the National Endowment for the Humanities (USA) and
                brings together art historians, archaeologists, and cultural resource managers with
                experts in remote sensing, photogrammetry, 3D modeling, and virtual reality. The
                project was founded by Jennifer von Schwerin and Heather Richards-Rissetto at the
                University of New Mexico working with data from the UNESCO World Heritage site and
                ancient Maya city in Copan, Honduras, when they realized that their research goals
                would be better served if they could join their separate sets of data in a tool that
                linked GIS and 3D data in a virtual reality environment. Von Schwerin, an art
                historian, had turned to digital 3D tools in order to test her reconstructions of an
                eighth-century temple at Copan (Figure 1). But other aspects of her research seek to
                analyze the temple within its larger urban context and the role that space plays in
                human experience – something for which GIS is well-suited. Richards-Rissetto, an
                archaeologist, created a GIS for Copan to study the visual and spatial relationships
                between built forms and natural landscape features, but soon realized that her
                research could benefit from a 3D perspective, as the 2D perspective of GIS maps
                limited her interpretations (Figure 2<hi rend="bold">).</hi>  Working together, von
                Schwerin and Richards-Rissetto asked themselves: What are the real research
                possibilities for 3D models?  How can we create an online resource for researchers
                of Maya architecture where they can compare and study geo-referenced 3D models and
                attribute data? How can we perform quantitative and qualitative comparisons with
                other Maya structures and analyze architecture in larger spatial and temporal
                contexts?  </p>
            <p>To address these questions, the MayaArch3D Project developed a new computing pipeline
                in order to build a prototype tool for an online, searchable repository – called <hi
                    rend="italic">QueryArch3D</hi> – that brings together GIS data, 3D models, and
                virtual environments for teaching and research on ancient architecture and
                landscapes. This pipeline uses PostgreSQL as spatial repository back-end and allows
                for the import and export of standard GIS formats, as well as 3D models as
                triangulated meshes via<hi rend="bold"> </hi>the common obj format. Like traditional
                databases, this tool can curate, query, and compare 2D digital objects (such as
                drawings, maps, diagrams, text, photographs, and videos). However, what is unique
                and technologically cutting-edge is that QueryArch3D enables users to 1) integrate
                and edit 2D and 3D data of <hi rend="italic">multiple resolutions</hi>, 2) to
                perform attribute and <hi rend="italic">spatial</hi> queries of archaeological data,
                and 3) to visualize, compare and analyze <hi rend="italic">3D</hi> buildings and
                artifacts – all in a single <hi rend="italic">online</hi>, navigable virtual reality
                landscape. Developed in 2010 in collaboration with Fabio Remondino and Giorgio
                Agugiaro at the Bruno Kessler Foundation (FBK) in Trento, Italy, and Gabrio Girardi
                at Graphitech, in Trento, Italy, the QueryArch3D tool stores both low resolution
                models, high resolution reality-based, hybrid models and all ancillary attribute
                data in an open source spatial database, and then makes them queryable via a virtual
                reality environment that runs on the Unity 3 game engine. Currently the contents of
                the digital resource include collections on ancient Copan (Figure 3). Overall, our
                preliminary research results indicate the QueryArch3D tool is poised to offer a new
                level of collaborative work in any field that works with 3D models, GIS, and large
                data sets, because it allows researchers to bring 2D and 3D datasets from separate
                projects into a single environment and work in real-time using the online query and
                analysis capabilities.</p>
            <p>This paper presents this new tool and the results of the beta-testing that was
                carried out in fall 2011 with researchers, students, and educators in the
                humanities. Beta testers unanimously were enthused about the tool, particularly at
                having the ability to (1) navigate online through a virtual model of an ancient Maya
                city, (2) access higher resolution models of objects, (3) query the archaeological
                database via the model – and vice versa. Suggestions for improvement centered on
                decreasing the initial download time, improving the user interface (changes to
                navigation commands, adding a text search box), and adding a broader range of
                spatial queries.<hi rend="bold"> </hi>Because the project is still in its initial
                stages, the paper also summarizes current research problems, and the tasks to be
                solved in the project’s next stage of development, in collaboration with the German
                Archaeological Institute and the University of Heidelberg. The paper concludes with
                a critical assessment of the possibilities that 3D Web GIS systems currently offer
                scholars and educators in terms of organizing, searching, and visualizing data, and
                identifying patterns over space and time.</p>
            <p><figure><graphic url="img457-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
            <p><figure><graphic url="img457-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 1a and 1b: Working hypothetical reconstruction and 3D model of Temple 22 created by the
                        MayaArch3D Project (Graphic: Raul Maqueda, from von Schwerin et al.
                        2011)</head></figure></p>
            <p><figure><graphic url="img457-3.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 2: Copan GIS (Graphic: Heather Richards-Rissetto 2011)</head></figure></p>
            <p><figure><graphic url="img457-4.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 3: QueryArch3D tool showing different data visualization modes and levels of detail.
                        Graphic: Giorgio Agugiaro</head></figure></p>
            
        </body>
        <back><div>
                <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">a) Selected MayaArch3D Project Publications:</hi></p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="bold">Agugiaro G., F. Remondino, G. Girardi, J. von Schwerin, H.
                        Richards-Rissetto, and R. de Amicis</hi> (2011). QueryArch3D: Querying and
                    visualising three-dimensional archaeological models in a web-based interface. In
                        <hi rend="italic">Geoinformatics</hi>, Faculty of Civil Engineering, Czech
                    Technical University, ISSN 1802-2669.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Remondino F., A. Gruen, J. von Schwerin, H. Eisenbeiss, A. Rizzi,
                        S.Girardi, M. Sauerbier, and H. Richards-Rissetto</hi> (2009). Multi-sensor
                    3D Documentation of the Maya Site of Copan. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the
                        22nd CIPA</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Symposium,</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">11-15 October, 2009, Kyoto, Japan (2009). </hi><ref
                        target="http://cipa.icomos.org/KYOTO.html" type="external"
                        >http://cipa.icomos.org/KYOTO.html</ref>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Richards-Rissetto, H.</hi> (2012). Studying Social Interaction at
                    the Ancient Maya Site of Copán, Honduras: A Least Cost Approach to
                    Configurational Analysis.  In D. A. White and S. Surface-Evans (eds), <hi
                        rend="italic">Least Cost Analysis of Sociocultural Landscapes:
                        Archaeological Case Studies, </hi>Accepted by University of Utah Press,
                    January 2011.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">von Schwerin, J.</hi>  (2011). The Sacred Mountain in Social
                    Context: Design, History and Symbolism of Temple 22 at Copán, Honduras. <hi
                        rend="italic">Ancient Mesoamerica </hi>22(2): 271-300. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">von Schwerin, J., H. Richards-Rissetto, F. Remondino, G.
                        Agugiaro, M. Forte, and R. Maqueda  </hi>(2011). <hi rend="italic">The
                        MayaArch3D Project; Digital Technologies for Research in Maya
                        Archaeology</hi>. Final Performance Report and White Paper for NEH Digital
                    Humanities Level II Start- Up Grant.</p>
            </div><div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">b) Related Publications:</hi></p>
          
            <p><hi rend="bold">Barcelo, J. A., M. Forte, and D. Sanders D.</hi> (2000). <hi
                    rend="italic">Virtual Reality in Archaeology</hi>. BAR International Series 843,
                Oxford.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Bodenhamer, D. J., J. Corrigan, and T. M. Harris</hi> (2010). <hi
                        rend="italic">The spatial humanities: GIS and the future of humanities
                        scholarship</hi>.  Bloomington : Indiana UP.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold"
                    >Conolly, J., and M- Lake</hi> (2006). <hi rend="italic">Geographical
                    Information Systems in archaeology</hi>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Dear M., J. Ketchum, S. Luria, and D. Richardson</hi> (2011). <hi
                        rend="italic">GeoHumanities Art, History, Text at the Edge of Place.</hi>
                    New York: Routledge.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">El-Hakim, S., J.-A. Beraldin, F. Remondino, M. Picard, L.
                        Cournoyer, and M. Baltsavias</hi> (2008). Using terrestrial laser scanning
                    and digital images for the 3D modelling of the Erechteion, Acropolis of Athens.
                        <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the DMACH Conference, Digital Media and its
                        Applications in Cultural Heritage</hi>. Amman, pp. 3-16.</p>
                <p><hi
                    rend="bold">Frischer, B., and A. Dakouri-Hild</hi> (2008). <hi rend="italic"
                    >Beyond illustration: 2d and 3d digital technologies as tools for discover in
                    archaeology</hi>. Oxford: Archaeopress.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Llobera,
                    M.</hi> (2006). What you see is what you get?: Visualscapes, visual genesis and
                hierarchy. In P. Daly and T. Evans (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Digital Archaeology:
                    Bridging Method and Theory</hi>. New York, London: Routledge, Taylor and
                Francis, pp. 148-167.</p>
               <p><hi rend="bold">Manferdini, A. M., F. Remondino, S. Baldissini, M. Gaiani, and B.
                        Benedetti</hi> (2008). 3D modeling and semantic classification of
                    archaeological finds for management and visualization in 3D archaeological
                    databases. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of 14th Int. Conference on Virtual
                        Systems and MultiMedia</hi> (VSMM 2008), pp. 221-228</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Reindel, M., and G. A. Wagner, eds.</hi> (2009).
                New Technologies for Archaeology: Multidisciplinary Investigations in Palpa and
                Nasca, Peru. Natural Science in Archaeology. Heidelberg/Berlin.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Remondino, F., S. El-Hakim, S. Girardi, A. Rizzi, B. Benedetti,
                        and L. Gonzo</hi> (2009). 3D Virtual reconstruction and visualization of
                    complex architectures-The 3D-ARCH project. <hi rend="italic">IAPRS&amp;SIS</hi>
                    Vol.38(5/W1)</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Robertson, E., J. Seibert, D. Fernandez,
                    and M. Zender, eds.</hi> (2006). <hi rend="italic">Space and Spatial Analysis in
                    Archaeology</hi>. University of New Mexico and University of Calgary Press:
                Albuquerque and Calgary.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>