<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-506">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Interfacing Diachrony: Visualizing Linguistic Change on the Basis of Digital Editions of Serbian 18th-Century Texts</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Tasovac, Toma</name>
                    <affiliation>Center for Digtial HumanitiesBelgrade, Serbia</affiliation>
                    <email>ttasovac@humanistika.org</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Ermolaev, Natalia</name>
                    <affiliation>Program in Library and Information Science, Rutgers University, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>n.ermolaev@rutgers.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>

                <p>Analyzing, indexing and marking-up raw data and providing various types of
                    annotations and metadata, named entities and other contextual information is
                    essential for effective searching and retrieval of cultural heritage content
                    (Borin et al.; Borin et al. 2007; Schreiber et al. 2008; Christopher 2011). With
                    commercial search engines dominating our day-to-day interaction with information
                    and framing our data access with non-transparent page-ranking mechanisms, it is
                    especially important for institutions of learning and cultural preservation to
                    use available technologies to encourage meaningful and profound engagement with
                    digital content. In this respect, the interface must not only function as the
                    frame for direct access and data retrieval, but also as the platform for the
                    user’s cognitive, aesthetic and performative interaction with digital objects as
                    such. DH projects, however, often approach interface design in a haphazard way,
                    more as an afterthought than as an essential system component (Warwick et al.
                    2008). They also tend to be dominated by task-oriented and efficiency-driven
                    paradigms of machine engineering that disregard the performative nature of the
                    interface as a reading space (Drucker 2011a, 2011b). </p>
                <p>Ongoing research in digital humanities, human-computer interaction and interface
                    design is focusing on ways to explore textual data by visualizing relations
                    between different sets of data and identifying patterns such as word trends,
                    named entities, collocations etc. (Bederson &amp; Schneiderman 2003; Unsworth
                    2005; Don et al. 2007; Fry 2007; Greengrass &amp; Hughes 2008; Rockwell et al.
                    2010). Collins (2010) has explored interactive interfaces that provide direct
                    access to both the online natural language processes, such as statistical
                    translation, keyword detection, and parsing, and the outcomes of sophisticated
                    linguistic analysis. So far, however, no attempts have been made to visually
                    link the user’s subjective experience of archaic texts with a graphic
                    representation of diachronic changes in language. In this paper, we describe our
                    design and development of an interface for representing and highlighting
                    linguistic change on the basis of our annotated digital editions of Serbian
                    18th-century literary texts (Tasovac &amp; Ermolaev 2011). We treat the
                    interface not only as a dynamic framework for engaging with the text, but also
                    as a ‘provocation to cognitive experience’ (Drucker 2011a: 9). </p>
                <p>Unlike many European languages, which underwent relatively uninterrupted
                    linguistic and cultural evolutions, the modern Serbian literary language, as
                    codified by Vuk Stefanović Karadžić in the 19th century, was largely based on
                    the vernacular of his time and had little in common with the literary standards
                    of the previous epoch (<foreign>Ивић</foreign> 1990). As a consequence of this radical caesura,
                    18th-century texts pose a formidable challenge to the modern reader who is
                    unaccustomed to these archaic (Old Church Slavonic) and foreign (largely
                    Russian) imprints (Albin 1970). That is why the Digital Library of Serbian
                    Cultural Heritage of the 18th Century – a joint project of the Belgrade Center
                    for Digital Humanities and the National Library of Serbia – employs a host of
                    mark-up and annotating strategies to make these texts more accessible. The texts
                    are encoded as a word-aligned corpus of TEI XML documents in two versions: one
                    using traditional 18th-century orthography, including the graphemes that have
                    since disappeared from Serbian, and one using modernized and standardized
                    Serbian spelling that increases the legibility and, to a certain degree,
                    searchability of these texts for modern users. Furthermore, the corpus contains
                    lexical and semantic annotations that introduce a large number of modern-day
                    equivalents to the largely archaic vocabulary of the corpus, as shown in the
                    following table:</p>
            
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell> Original orthography </cell>
                    <cell> Modernized orthography </cell>
                    <cell> Modern-day equivalent </cell>
                    <cell> Type of change </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> <foreign>богъ</foreign> </cell>
                    <cell> <foreign>бог</foreign> </cell>
                    <cell> <foreign>бог</foreign> </cell>
                    <cell> orthographic </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> <foreign>любовъ</foreign> </cell>
                    <cell> <foreign>љубов</foreign> </cell>
                    <cell> <foreign>љубав</foreign> </cell>
                    <cell> phonetic </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> <foreign>утѣшенїе</foreign> </cell>
                    <cell> <foreign>утешеније</foreign> </cell>
                    <cell> <foreign>утеха</foreign> </cell>
                    <cell> morphological </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> <foreign>благодѣтель</foreign> </cell>
                    <cell> <foreign>благодетељ</foreign> </cell>
                    <cell> <foreign>доброчинитељ</foreign> </cell>
                    <cell> lexical </cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell> <foreign>любезница</foreign> </cell>
                    <cell> <foreign>љубезница</foreign> </cell>
                    <cell> <foreign>драга</foreign> <foreign>особа</foreign> (<foreign>женског</foreign> <foreign>пола</foreign>) </cell>
                    <cell> conceptual (term no longer lexicalized) </cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            
            <p>By applying basic techniques of cross-lingual information retrieval
                    to a historical dimension of one language, and making provisions for multiple
                    indexing and annotations, our project exposes a notoriously difficult chapter in
                    the development of the Serbian language to a wider audience, without sacrificing
                    the edition’s scholarly potential. The user can search the corpus not only using
                    modern standardized spelling, but also the above-mentioned range of modern-day
                    equivalents. This type of extended search, which results in a larger pool of
                    data than a search based on original, non-standardized orthographic forms alone,
                    has the potential of radically opening up the text for the modern reader and
                    leading to discoveries of previously unnoticed thematic similarities and
                    correspondences across different works and authors.</p>
                <p>The interface is built dynamically using XQuery and advanced JavaScript on top of
                the TEI XML files which are stored in the eXist database. We offer three basic views
                of the text: a <hi rend="italic">static view</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">user-driven
                    dynamic view</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">system-driven dynamic view</hi>.
                The <hi rend="italic">static view</hi> is the most basic: the user can choose to
                read the text in either the original orthography (OO) or its modernized version
                (MO). In either version, each word is also a hyperlink: clicking on a word reveals a
                pop-up window which lists the form of the corresponding orthographic version as well
                as the lexical or semantic annotation , when appropriate. In the static view, the
                user can also choose to <hi rend="italic">juxtapose </hi>(place side by side), <hi
                    rend="italic">interpolate </hi>(view line by line) or <hi rend="italic"
                    >superimpose </hi>(merge and differentiate by means of color) the two
                orthographic versions of the text. </p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">user-driven dynamic view</hi> stresses the evolution of
                linguistic change: it allows the reader to treat the original 18th-century text as a
                temporal snapshot – a frozen expression of a certain time and age – that can be,
                using the familiar UI device (slider) ‘updated’ (or ‘fast-forwarded’) to its other
                more modern linguistic forms. The stages of transformation include: modernized
                spelling that keeps the linguistic peculiarities of the original, phonetic changes
                morphological changes, lexical changes and, finally, conceptual reformulations. Each
                stage of transformation can be viewed separately or in combination with others. And
                each change takes place inside the text by means of in-line animated transformations
                of individual word forms. </p>
                <p>Finally, the <hi rend="italic">system-driven dynamic view</hi> is the most
                experimental: it creates a unique reading environment in which annotated words
                change their linguistic form in-line, but each at its own, randomly assigned speed.
                In this playful space, the linear reading act becomes predicated upon a chance
                encounter with a traditional or modern form, an exercise in Benjaminian translation
                (Benjamin 1972) where the site of alterity (in our case temporal alterity) quite
                literally (and never in quite the same sequence of transformations) disturbs the
                text’s imaginary stability. Reading becomes a performance in which the reader is
                performing the text, and vice versa. </p>
                <p>By providing these various visual interfaces in our Digital Library of Serbian
                    Cultural Heritage of the 18th Century, we address for the first time in the
                    framework of visual DH, the subjective perspective of the reader’s process of
                    decoding archaic language. We treat the linguistic expression of the
                    18th-century Serbian culture not as a stable and self-evident entity, but as a
                    locus of meaning that can (and should) be transformed by the reader. While the
                    interface provides access to systematic linguistic, cultural and historical
                    annotations, it also creates an opportunity for playful interaction with the
                    text as a space of linguistic and cultural mutability. </p>
                <p>The more possibilities at a user’s disposal to engage with a digital cultural
                    heritage object, the greater its impact will be at the levels of both individual
                    and institutional experience. The framework of the Digital Library of Serbian
                    18th-Century Texts can serve as a model for other smaller, lesser-resourced
                    languages struggling with the quest to keep their cultural heritage alive after
                    historical ruptures, linguistic caesuras, changes of alphabet etc.</p>
            
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <head>References</head>

            <p><hi rend="bold">Albin, A.</hi> (1970). The Creation of the Slaveno-Serbski Literary
                Language. <hi rend="italic">The Slavonic and East European Review</hi> 48(113):
                483-91.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Bederson, B., and B. Schneiderman</hi> (2003). <hi rend="italic">The
                        Craft of Information Visualization: Readings and Reflections.</hi> San
                    Francisco, CA.: Morgan Kaufmann.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Benjamin, W.</hi> (1972). Die Aufgabe des Übersetzers. <hi
                    rend="italic">Gesammelte Schriften IV/1</hi>, 9-21. Frankurt Main: Suhrkamp.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Borin, L., M. Forsberg, and D. Kokkinakis</hi> (2010). <hi
                        rend="italic">Diabase: Towards a diachronic BLARK in support of historical
                        studies</hi>. <ref
                        target="http://spraakbanken.gu.se/personal/lars/pblctns/lrec2010-diabase.pdf"
                        type="external"
                        >http://spraakbanken.gu.se/personal/lars/pblctns/lrec2010-diabase.pdf</ref>.
                    Accessed 15 March 2010.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Borin, L., D. Kokkinakis, and L.-J. Olsson</hi> (2007). Naming the
                    past: Named entity and animacy recognition in 19th century Swedish literature.
                        <hi rend="italic">Workshop on Language Technology for Cultural Heritage
                        Data</hi>, pp. 1-8.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Christopher, A. (Cal) Lee</hi> (2011). A framework for contextual
                information in digital collections. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</hi>
                67(1): 95-143.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Collins, Ch. M.</hi> (2010). <hi rend="italic">Interactive
                    Visualizations of Natural Language</hi>. University of Toronto.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Don, A., et al.</hi> (2007). Discovering Interesting Usage Patterns
                in Text Collections: Integrating Text Mining With Visualization. <hi rend="italic"
                    >Proceedings of the Sixteenth ACM Conference on Information and Knowledge
                    Management</hi>, pp. 213-22.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Drucker, J.</hi> (2011a). Humanities Approaches to Interface Theory.
                    <hi rend="italic">Culture Machine</hi>: 121-20.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Drucker, J.</hi> (2011b). Performative Materiality and Interpretative
                Interface. <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities 2011: Book of Abstracts</hi>, pp.
                39-40.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Fry, B.</hi> (2007). V<hi rend="italic">isualizing Data: Exploring
                    and Explaining Data With the Processing Environment. </hi>Sebastopol: O’Reilly
                Media.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Greengrass, M., and L. Hughes, eds.</hi> (2008). <hi rend="italic"
                    >The Virtual Representation of the Past. </hi>Aldershot Hants, England;
                Burlington VT: Ashgate.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Rockwell, G., et al.</hi> (2010). Ubiquitous Text Analysis. <hi
                    rend="italic">Poetess Archive</hi> 2(1): 1-19.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Schreiber, G., et al.</hi> (2008). Semantic annotation and search of
                cultural-heritage collections: The MultimediaN E-Culture demonstrator. <hi
                    rend="italic">Web Semantics: Science, Services and Agents on the World Wide
                    Web</hi> 6(4): 243-49.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Tasovac, T., and N. Ermolaev</hi> (2011). Encoding Diachrony: Digital
                Editions of Serbian 18th-Century Texts. <hi rend="italic">Lecture Notes in Computer
                    Science</hi>, 6966497-500.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Unsworth, J.</hi> (2005). <hi rend="italic">New Methods for
                    Humanities Research. The 2005 Lyman Award Lecture. November 11. National
                    Humanities Center. Research Triangle Park, NC</hi>.
                <ref target="http://www3.isrl.illinois.edu/~unsworth/lyman.htm" type="external">http://www3.isrl.illinois.edu/~unsworth/lyman.htm</ref>. Accessed June 10 2011.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Warwick, C., et al.</hi> (2008). If You Build It Will They Come? The
                LAIRAH Study: Quantifying the Use of Online Resources in the Arts and Humanities
                through Statistical Analysis of User Log Data. <hi rend="italic">Literary and
                    Linguistic Computing</hi> 23(1): 85-102.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold"><foreign>Ивић</foreign>, <foreign>Милка</foreign></hi> (1990). <hi rend="italic"><foreign>О</foreign> j<foreign>езику</foreign> <foreign>Вуковом</foreign> <foreign>и</foreign>
                        <foreign>вуковском</foreign></hi>. <foreign>Нови</foreign> <foreign>Сад</foreign>: <foreign>Књиж</foreign>. <foreign>за</foreign>j<foreign>едница</foreign> <foreign>Новог</foreign> <foreign>Сада</foreign>.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>