<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:x="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:exsl="http://exslt.org/common" xml:id="Paper-766">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Making Waves: Algorithmic Criticism Revisited</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Hoover</surname>, <forename>David L.</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>New York University, United States of America</affiliation>
          <email></email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
        <publisher>EPFL, Switzerland</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>EPFL Digital Humanities Laboratory</name>
          <address>
            <addrLine>GC D2 386</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Station 18</addrLine>
            <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
            <addrLine>frederic.kaplan@epfl.ch</addrLine>
          </address>
        </distributor>
        <pubPlace>Lausanne, Switzerland</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>EPFL</addrLine>
          <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="abstract">This paper takes chapter 1 of Stephen Ramsay's Reading Machines , "An Algorithmic Criticism" as its point of departure. Ramsay complains that computational approaches to literature lack "bold statements, strong readings, and broad generalizations," and that this helps to explain why computational approaches have not had much influence on literary study. Computational approaches, he says, have been too cautious, to tied to a (pseudo) scientific approaches to interest literary critics, who tend to want to open texts up to new interpretations rather than to solve problems. He begins an algorithmic approach to Virginia Woolf's The Waves in an attempt to model what he sees as a bolder, more provocative, freer kind of computational literary study. This paper reveals some drawbacks of Ramsay's approach, some problems in his algorithmic provocation, and some ways in which a more careful and rigorous approach can provide more insight into Woolf's novel.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
        <p>
          <date when="20140710"/>
          <time when="09:00:00"/>
        </p>
		<p n="session">4</p>
		<p n="room">413 - Amphimax</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
          <term>Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
          <term>Long Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
          <term>algorithmic criticism</term>
          <term>Virginia Woolf</term>
          <term>Stephen Ramsay</term>
          <term>computational stylistics</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
          <term>literary studies</term>
          <term>stylistics and stylometry</term>
          <term>text analysis</term>
          <term>english studies</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="paper">
    <front>

      <div>
        <p></p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>

        <p>In <hi rend="italic">Reading Machines: Toward an Algorithmic Criticism</hi>, Stephen Ramsay suggests that
computational literary studies remain marginalized because they lack “bold statements, strong
readings, and broad generalizations” (2011: 2). They are too cautious, too scientific, to interest
literary critics, who value opening texts to new interpretations over solving problems (10-11).
Ramsay suggests that a feminist discussion of <hi rend="italic">The Waves</hi> challenges algorithmic criticism:
“literary critical arguments of this sort do not stand in the same relationship to facts, claims, and
evidence as the more empirical forms of inquiry. There is no experiment that can verify the idea
that Woolf’s . . . ‘elision of corporeal materiality’ exceeds the dominant Western subject” (7).
Although many critical claims are computationally intractable, Woolf’s “elision of corporeal
materiality” surely has textual implications that might be tested computationally. Literary
criticism’s problematic relationship to facts, claims, and evidence seems more like a bug than a
feature, but here I want to re-examine and interrogate Ramsay’s algorithmic provocation.
</p>

        <p>Three male and three female characters in <hi rend="italic">The Waves</hi> speak in alternating monologues, an
experimental technique that has invited critical comment about what axes of difference or unity
characterize the novel. “The ‘problem’ . . . with Woolf’s novel is that despite evidence of a
unified style, one suspects that we can read and interpret it using a set of underlying distinctions.
We can uncover those distinctions by reading carefully. We can also uncover them using a
computer” (Ramsay 2011: 10-11).</p>

        <p>Ramsay treats the six monologues as a corpus of documents and investigates them with
tf-idf, from the field of information retrieval: tf*(N/df). This, he suggests, should identify each
monologue’s characteristic words more effectively than a traditional word-frequency list. Tf-idf
is the term’s frequency (tf) multiplied by the total number of documents (N; here 6) divided by
the number of documents containing the term (df; document frequency). Tf-idf reduces the
importance of function words and increases the importance of speakers’ characteristic words
because the frequencies of words used by only one speaker are multiplied by six (6/1), while the
frequencies of words used by all six speakers are multiplied by one (6/6) (Ramsay 2011: 11).
After identifying each speaker’s most characteristic words, he reveals that he has actually used
the formula, 1 + tf *log(N/df), which includes a log function (reducing the effect of a word’s
appearance in only one speaker), and adds 1 (preventing the measure from becoming negative).
The purpose of the alterations “is not to bring the results into closer conformity with ‘reality,’ but
merely to render the weighting numbers more sensible to the analyst” (Ramsay 2011: 15). Yet the
variants are not “merely” at the whim of the analyst; they have testable consequences.
</p>

        <p>But let us travel a bit further with Ramsay. He presents the words with the highest tf-idf
scores in Louis’s monologue (listed in Fig. 1, along with his tf-idf scores, my tf-idf scores, and  their frequencies), and suggests that “Few readers of <hi rend="italic">The Waves</hi> would fail to see some
emergence of pattern in this list” (12). For example, <hi rend="italic">western</hi> seems to echo Louis’s concern
about his <hi rend="italic">Australian accent</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">England</hi> (all top 25). But actually <hi rend="italic">western</hi>, <hi rend="italic">wilt</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">thou</hi> appear
only in Louis’s quotations from a sixteenth-century poem. Ramsay’s provocation ignores some
interesting questions: should Louis’s quotations be considered his speech (and retained?), or the
anonymous author’s (and omitted?). </p>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="DH2014_548_104-1"/>
          <p>Fig. 1: Louis’s Most Characteristic Words</p>
        </figure>
        <p>Trying to recreate Ramsay’s analysis reveals further interesting points. The mismatched
tf-idf scores (bold) reflect different word frequencies. His score for <hi rend="italic">beast</hi> requires 6 occurrences,
not 5, but the 6th is in the omniscient narration). His score for <hi rend="italic">accent</hi> requires 13 occurrences,
not 14, but Rhoda’s most characteristic words include <hi rend="italic">them</hi>– and <hi rend="italic">accent</hi> occurs once as accent–,
which presumably reduces his count by 1. (What constitutes a word is a surprisingly complex
question, but treating <hi rend="italic">accent</hi>– as a word seems odd.) The rarity of the words shows how strongly
tf-idf privileges words limited to one character (only <hi rend="italic">accent</hi> appears in 2). Ramsay’s intervention
raises interesting questions: What does it mean to choose this algorithm? How do the results





					affect our emerging reading of <hi rend="italic">The Waves</hi>? (Ramsay 15). But how to answer these questions? </p>
        <p>Even the identification of characteristic words is problematic. <hi rend="italic">Tick</hi> and <hi rend="italic">hoot</hi> both occur 4
times, only in Bernard, but all 8 occurrences are in 3 consecutive sentences. How “characteristic”
is that? Low occurs just 5 times, “only” in Bernard, yet it also occurs in the omniscient narration.
Analyzing only the 6 characters seems reasonable, but should Bernard’s characteristic words also
occur in the narration? (Some consider Bernard to be modeled on Woolf herself [Ramsay 2011:
13].) Including the narration seems both intriguing and problematic, not least because it is not
dialogue. Doing so removes <hi rend="italic">low</hi>, <hi rend="italic">canopy</hi>, <hi rend="italic">bowled</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">brushed</hi> from Bernard’s most
characteristic words and <hi rend="italic">beast</hi>, <hi rend="italic">steel</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">discord</hi> from Louis’s. What questions does this raise?
</p>
        <p>Most algorithms for computational approaches come from authorship attribution, where
ostensibly correct answers exist. But Ramsay is right that the existence of “correct” answers to
questions like “Do the men and women speak differently?” or “Do the characters have distinct
and consistent voices?” is precisely at issue. Examining <hi rend="italic">The Waves </hi>in the light of Ramsay’s
provocation raises so many intriguing questions that they cannot all be addressed here. But we
can approach the question of character individualization by using a radical deformation. I
randomly sorted the lines of the six monologues, then selected the first 6067 words of each, the
length of the shortest monologue (Susan’s). I identified the 50 most characteristic words using
Ramsay’s tf-idf formula, and tested how well they group with the remainders of the longer
monologues using cluster-analysis, starting with all 300 words (in descending tf-idf order), then
reducing the number gradually. The best result, for the 20 most characteristic words, is shown in
Fig. 2. </p>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="DH2014_548_104-2"/>
          <p>Fig. 2: Tf-idf and Character-Individualization</p>
        </figure>
        <p>Bernard’s and Louis’s sections group together, while Neville’s and Rhoda’s fail (Jinny and Susan
have too little text for 2 sections). A simple word frequency list, however, correctly groups all 4
in many analyses (see Fig. 3, based on the 300 mfw), providing a tentative answer to the question
of distinct voices. </p>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="DH2014_548_104-3"/>
          <p>Fig. 3: The Most Frequent Words and Character-Individualization</p>
        </figure>
        <p>Selecting the 50 most characteristic words for each monologue using Zeta (Craig and
Kinney 2011), also produces many perfect results (see Fig. 4, based on the 200 most
characteristic words). This very different method, which measures consistency of use rather than
frequency, confirms the distinctness of the voices. Finally, testing the six characters in
2,000-word sections with 2-grams (based on the six full monologues) also yields many
completely correct clusters (see Fig. 5 for an analysis based on the 900 mf2Grams). </p>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="DH2014_548_104-4"/>
          <p>Fig. 4: Zeta and Character-Individualization</p>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="DH2014_548_104-5"/>
          <p>Fig. 5: 2Grams and Character-Individualization</p>
        </figure>
        <p>Ramsay suggests that treating the question of whether the six characters in The Waves
share “the same stylistic voice” as a problem to solve is a “category error,” and that the proper
question–one computers cannot answer–is “Can I interpret (or read) it this way?” (2011: 9-10).
Critics still can read the novel as a single stylistic voice, and the six monologues undoubtedly
share many characteristics, but, in spite of a host of very interesting remaining questions about
the status of algorithms, arguments, and evidence, it seems reasonable to make the bold claim
that there are six distinct character voices in <hi rend="italic">The Waves</hi>.</p>
        <p>Ramsay’s provocative intervention is valuable for forcing us to re-examine our methods
and focus on questions of interest to traditional literary scholars. But further analysis of his
provocation and his algorithm suggests that more attention to the text, to the nature and function
of the algorithms, and to method may prompt bold claims that rest on a sounder foundation.
Further work will help us explore the boundary between computationally-tractable and
computationally-intractable questions and the significance of that boundary. </p>



      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="References">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            Ramsay does not analyze, then interpret, a method criticized by Fish (2012). He begins with a literary judgment, then investigates it. Despite Fish’s criticism, both methods seem valuable.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>
            Ramsay actually uses (1+LN(tf))*LN(N/df), not 1+tf *log(N/df). Many tf-idf formulas exist; for the 4 I tested, 20 of the 25 most characteristic words are the same.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>
            It also reveals that Ramsay has (not unreasonably) omitted Bernard’s final long “summing up” chapter, as I have also done.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>
            The characters do not group completely by gender in the graphs above, also suggesting a tentative answer to “Do the men and women speak differently?” that is different from Ramsay’s.
          </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Craig, H., and A. Kinney</hi>. (2010).<hi rend="italic"> Shakespeare, Computers, and the Mystery of Authorship</hi>. Cambridge
            UP.
          </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Hoover, D. L. </hi>(2007). <hi rend="italic">“The End of the Irrelevant Text: Electronic Texts, Linguistics, and Literary
            Theory,”</hi> Digital Humanities Quarterly 1(2).
          </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Ramsay, S</hi>. (2011). <hi rend="italic">Reading Machines: Toward an Algorithmic Criticism</hi>. Urbana: University of
            Illinois Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Fish, S.</hi> (2012) <hi rend="italic">“Mind Your P’s and B’s: The Digital Humanities and Interpretation,”</hi> The New York
            Times, online, January 23.. </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
