<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:x="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:exsl="http://exslt.org/common" xml:id="Paper-737">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Modeling Linguistic Research Data for a Repository for Historical Corpora</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Odebrecht</surname>, <forename>Carolin</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin</affiliation>
          <email></email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
        <publisher>EPFL, Switzerland</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>EPFL Digital Humanities Laboratory</name>
          <address>
            <addrLine>GC D2 386</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Station 18</addrLine>
            <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
            <addrLine>frederic.kaplan@epfl.ch</addrLine>
          </address>
        </distributor>
        <pubPlace>Lausanne, Switzerland</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>EPFL</addrLine>
          <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="abstract">Existing historical linguistic corpora vary a with respect to formats, corpus architecture, annotation types, values and preparation steps. The LAUDATIO-Repository (www.laudatio-repository.org) provides an open access environment to facilitate the management of such heterogeneous research data with an extensive, uniform and structured documentation and a facetted and free-text search without constraints such as formats or annotations. To this purpose, we developed a meta-model which is expressive enough to represent a large variety of corpus formats. This meta-model, described as a TEI-ODD specification (Burnard &amp; Rahtz 2004), is also the basis for the technical implementation in the repository.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
        <p>
          <date when="20140710"/>
          <time when="11:00:00"/>
        </p>
		<p n="session">5</p>
		<p n="room">315 - Amphipôle</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
          <term>Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
          <term>Short Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
          <term>research data</term>
          <term>modeling</term>
          <term>metadata</term>
          <term>historical corpora</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
          <term>corpora and corpus activities</term>
          <term>metadata</term>
          <term>data modeling and architecture including hypothesis-driven modeling</term>
          <term>interdisciplinary collaboration</term>
          <term>linguistics</term>
          <term>copyright</term>
          <term>licensing</term>
          <term>and Open Access</term>
          <term>history of Humanities Computing/Digital Humanities</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="paper">
    <front>
      
      <div>
        <p></p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        
        <p>Existing historical linguistic corpora vary a great deal with respect to formats, corpus
architecture, annotation types and values and preparation steps. The LAUDATIO-Repository
(www.laudatio-repository.org) provides an open access environment to facilitate the
management of such heterogeneous research data with an extensive, uniform and structured
documentation and faceted and free-text search without limitation with respect to formats or
annotations. For this purpose, we have developed a meta-model which is expressive enough to
represent a large variety of corpus formats. This meta-model, described as a TEI-ODD
specification with automatically generated schemas (Burnard &amp; Rahtz 2004), is also the basis
for the technical implementation in the repository.
</p>
        <p>Building and analyzing historical corpora often incorporates diplomatic transcriptions,
normalizations of these transcriptions and research specific annotation layers which will be
illustrated with the help of two corpora; the German Manchester Corpus (GerManC) and the
RIDGES Herbology Corpus. GerManC<ref target="n1" rend="sup">1</ref> (Durrell, Ensslin &amp; Bennett 2007) contains for
instance two formats (TEI XML and CoNLL) which represent different kinds of annotations
and analyses. The TEI XML format contains a diplomatic transcription and a register specific
mark-up. By contrast, the CoNLL format contains token annotations for normalization, part-
of-speech (POS) and lemmatization (e.g. the STTS tag set, Schiller et al. 1999) as well as
morphology and dependency annotation for syntactic relations between the tokens (e.g. Foth
2006). Thus, this corpus uses two formats for encoding different kinds of annotations and
analyses.<ref target="n2" rend="sup">2</ref> On the other hand, the second version of the RIDGES Herbology Corpus<ref target="n3" rend="sup">3</ref> contains
all annotations in one format (EXMARaLDA, Schmidt &amp; Wörner 2009) which is then
converted into the relANNIS format used by the ANNIS corpus system (Zeldes et al. 2009)
for search and visualization capacities. The corpus architecture of RIDGES is specific in the
following way: Via multiple segmentations, annotations can refer to different basic textual
data in the corpus (Krause et al. 2012). To normalize separate spellings of complex verbs in
historical German such as<hi rend="italic"> zusammen gesetzet </hi>to<hi rend="italic"> zusammengesetzt</hi> (RIDGES, Curioser
Botanicus oder sonderbares Kräuterbuch, 1675), the tokens need to be merged in the
normalized annotation whereas tokens need to be separated when normalizing <hi rend="italic">zuverstehen</hi> to
<hi rend="italic">zu verstehen</hi> (RIDGES, Alchemistische Praktik 1603). Every further annotation — for
instance the POS annotation may either refer to the diplomatic segmentation layer or to the
normalized segmentation layer.
</p>
        <p>Having identified what exactly needs to be described by a meta-model, we then define the
actual use-cases associated with this meta-model. With respect to range, specificity and user
scenarios, distinct requirements could only be designed for concrete applications. For this
study, the LAUDATIO-Repository (Krause et al. 2013) is taken as an example. In this case,
the meta-model will enable a retrieval of, a structured search on and a holistic and extensive
documentation of the heterogeneous historical corpora and their preparation (for further
details see Odebrecht &amp; Krause 2013 and Odebrecht &amp; Zipser 2013). It should be possible to
search for a distinct annotation type or content in several different corpora within the
repository. Along with the content requirements the repository needs a structured, machine
		
	
	
		
			
				
					readable metadata format which can be represented in a graphical interface for the display of
information and in the repository system for the different ways to search through the data, e.g.
faceted search and free-text search. The meta-model developed from these requirements
results in a metadata TEI XML format for the LAUDATIO-Repository but is also designed
for and may be applied to other use cases and applications.
</p>
        <p>The meta-model is designed as an analytic class diagram for which the Unified Modeling
Language is used<ref target="n4" rend="sup">4</ref>. Such a diagram is useful to document the important issues or concepts in
an abstract way. Therefore, the class concepts represent the concepts for the subject-specific
application domain ‘historical corpora’.<ref target="n5" rend="sup">5</ref></p>
        <p>Four main classes are defined: ‘corpus’, ‘document’, ‘annotationKey’ and ‘annotationValue’
which refer not only to historical corpora but to textual corpora in general: </p>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="DH2014_2_737-1"/>
          <p>Fig. 1: Meta-model of a corpus. For the sake of concision, the attributes of the classes are left out. </p>
        </figure>
        <p>As shown in figure 1, the meta-model<ref target="n6" rend="sup">6</ref> defines a corpus as the sum of all documents
regardless of their structure and size. A document is defined as the sum of all annotations
regardless of their structure, format and content. ‘Annotation’ is defined by the sum of all
annotation keys and values. For the meta-model, it does not matter whether they have flat,
hierarchical or semantic relations. Every concept carries its own attributes. A ‘corpus’ is a
conceptual collection of digitized and not only linguistically processed (here historical) text. It
carries among other things the attributes title, creator, creation date, revision history etc. The
class ‘document’ represents the actual historical text – source text - with its own attributes
such as author, date and publication history. The classes ‘annotationKey’ and
‘annotationValue’ constitute a document because the sum of transcriptions, normalizations,
including segmentations and further annotations build - technically speaking - a ‘document’.
‘AnnotationKey’ in turn carries attributes similar to ‘corpus’ and ‘document’ such as date,
author and revision history. For example, the attribute ‘author’ can refer either to the creator
of a historical text or to the annotator of a certain annotation layer and may also refer to the
same entity or person. This is important for corpus documentation. When re-using corpora,
for instance further annotations on an existing corpus are made by third parties, a clear
reference can be made to the copyrights. Attributes such as ‘date’ also refer to every class of
the meta-model, meaning that ‘corpus’ as well as ‘annotation’ may have a date of creation
like ‘document’ which genuinely has a publication date.
</p>
        <p>For the technical realization<ref target="n7" rend="sup">7</ref> we used a customization of TEI XML with an ODD
specification. The meta-model was mapped to three TEI header structures, one for each 		
concept: a header for ‘corpus’, ‘annotationKey’ and ‘annotationValue’, a header for each
‘document’ in the corpus and a header for each preparation step of the corpus in general: </p>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="DH2014_2_737-2"/>
          <p>Fig. 2: Technical mapping of the meta-model and the TEI xml header structure</p>
        </figure>
        <p>The attributes of each class are mapped into the corresponding TEI element sets. For example,
the attributes date and author correspond to the TEI elements &lt;date&gt;, &lt;author&gt; and &lt;editor&gt;
with a specifying attribute @role for “annotator” in the &lt;fileDesc&gt; element. The
&lt;publicationStmt&gt; element contains the attributes revision and/or publication history for each
class. The classes ‘annotationKey’ and ‘annotationValue’ are realized with the element set of
&lt;elementSpec&gt;. With the help of the attribute @corresp, references between the list of
annotation keys and values of the whole corpus to each document and to each preparation
step, including information about formats and annotation relations such as segmentations of
the annotations, are technically implemented. Each TEI header is customized with the help of
ODD<ref target="n8" rend="sup">8</ref>. The TEI headers are the technical basis for the uniform display and search of every
class and its attributes in the repository. For every corpus, e.g. RIDGES and GerManC, the
values for &lt;author&gt; referring to either a distinct annotation layer or a distinct document can
be uniformly searched via a faceted search or can be displayed in the corpus view.
</p>
        <p>The meta-model presented here provides a generic mechanism for the representation of
multiply annotated corpora that probably goes beyond the scope of historical corpora alone.
Our experience with dealing with a variety of available historical resources has shown how
flexible and reliable the model can be in this domain, though work remains to be done in
dealing with more relational annotation schemes describing disconnected sources such as
annotation between documents in the same or in different corpora. </p>
      
        
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="References">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            1. GerManC is freely available at <ref type="url" target="http://hdl.handle.net/11022/0000-0000-1D32-8">hdl.handle.net/11022/0000-0000-1D32-8</ref>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>
            2. GerManC is also available in the standoff format GATE which maps all annotations of the TEI XML and the CoNLL formats.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>
            3. The RIDGES Herbology Corpus is freely available at <ref type="url" target="http://hdl.handle.net/11022/0000-0000-1CDB-B">hdl.handle.net/11022/0000-0000-1CDB-B</ref>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>
            4. OMG (2009) OmG unied modeling languagetm (omg uml), infrastructure: <ref type="url" target="http://www.omg.org/spec/">www.omg.org/spec/</ref>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>
            5. For the sake of brevity, the attributes of the classes are left out in figure 1.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>
            6. All ODDs are freely available at <ref type="url" target="http://www.laudatio-repository.org/repository/documentation.">www.laudatio-repository.org/repository/documentation.</ref>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>
            7. For the technical implementation of the header in the basis systems of LAUDATIO-Repository with the help of elastic search &amp; co see <ref type="url" target="http://www.laudatio-repository.org/repository/technical-documentation/">www.laudatio-repository.org/repository/technical-documentation/</ref>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>
            8. Each ODD is freely available at <ref type="url" target="http://korpling.german.hu-berlin.de/schemata/laudatio/doc/S6/">korpling.german.hu-berlin.de/schemata/laudatio/doc/S6/</ref>
          </bibl>
        <bibl><hi rend="bold">Burnard, Lou, Rahtz, Sebastian</hi> (2004) <hi rend="italic">RelaxNG with Son of ODD</hi>. Extreme Markup
          Languages Proceedings 2004. Montréal, Québec.
        </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Durrell, Martin, Ensslin, Astrid, Bennett, Paul</hi> (2207) <hi rend="italic">The GerManC project</hi> In Sprache und
            Datenverarbeitung 31 (2007), pp. 71-80.
          </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Foth, Kilian A.</hi> (2006) <hi rend="italic">Eine umfassende Constraint-Dependenz-Grammatik des
            Deutschen</hi>. Technischer Report. Universität Hamburg. Hamburg.
          </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Krause, Thomas, Odebrecht, Carolin, Zielke, Dennis</hi> (2013) <hi rend="italic">Wie kann der Zugriff, die
            Wiederverwendung und langfristige Speicherung von linguistischen Korpora realisiert
            werden?</hi> 35. Jahrestagung der Deutschen Gesellschaft für Sprachwissenschaft
            (DGfS). 12.-15.03.2013. Potsdam Germany. </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Krause, Thomas, Lüdeling, Anke, Odebrecht, Carolin, Zeldes, Amir</hi> (2012) <hi rend="italic">Multiple
            Tokenization in a Diachronic Corpus</hi>. Exploring Ancient Languages through Corpora
            Conference (EALC). 14.-16.06.2012. Oslo Norway.
          </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Odebrecht, Carolin, Zipser, Florian </hi>(2013) <hi rend="italic">LAUDATIO - Eine Infrastruktur zur linguistischen
            Analyse historischer Korpora</hi>. DTA-/CLARIN-D Konferenz und -Workshops:
            Historische Textkorpora für die Geistes- und Sozialwissenschaften. Fragestellungen
            und Nutzungsperspektiven 18.-19.02.2013. Berlin Germany.
          </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Odebrecht, Carolin, Krause, Thomas</hi> (2013) <hi rend="italic">Metadata in an Infrastructure for Historical
            Corpora. SFB 732 Incremental Specification in Context</hi> - Colloquium 20.06.2013.
            Stuttgart Germany.
            http://www.uni-stuttgart.de/linguistik/sfb732/files/abstract_odebrechtkrause.pdf
          </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Schmidt, Thomas, Wörner, Kai</hi> (2009) EXMARaLDA - Creating, analysing and sharing
            spoken language corpora for pragmatic research. Pragmatics 19/4. pp.565-582.
          </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Schiller, Anne, Teufel, Simone, Stöckert, Christine, Thielen, Christine</hi> (1999) <hi rend="italic">Guidelines für
            das Tagging deutscher Textkorpora mit STTS</hi>. Technischer Report. Universität
            Stuttgart, Institut für maschinelle Sprachverarbeitung &amp; Universität Tübingen,
            Seminar für Sprachwissenschaft.
          </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Zeldes, Amir, Ritz, Julia, Lüdeling, Anke &amp; Chiarcos, Christian</hi> (2009), "<hi rend="italic">ANNIS: A Search
            Tool for Multi-Layer Annotated Corpora</hi>". In: Proceedings of Corpus Linguistics
            2009, July 20-23, Liverpool, UK. </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
