<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:x="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:exsl="http://exslt.org/common" xml:id="Paper-934">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Problems in Encoding Documents of Early Modern Japanese</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Kawase</surname>
            <forename>Akihiro</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>National Institute for Japanese Language and Linguistics, Japan</affiliation>
          <email>a_kawase@ninjal.ac.jp</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Ichimura</surname>
            <forename>Taro</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>National Institute for Japanese Language and Linguistics, Japan</affiliation>
          <email>tichimura@ninjal.ac.jp</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Ogiso</surname>
            <forename>Toshinobu</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>National Institute for Japanese Language and Linguistics, Japan</affiliation>
          <email>togiso@ninjal.ac.jp</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
        <publisher>EPFL, Switzerland</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>EPFL Digital Humanities Laboratory</name>
          <address>
            <addrLine>GC D2 386</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Station 18</addrLine>
            <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
            <addrLine>frederic.kaplan@epfl.ch</addrLine>
          </address>
        </distributor>
        <pubPlace>Lausanne, Switzerland</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>EPFL</addrLine>
          <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="abstract">The National Institute for Japanese Language and Linguistics (NINJAL) is conducting morphological analysis on Japanese classics. Digitization has been done thus far on the literature of several ages and various text corpora have been published. However, each element of the text corpora is marked up under NINJAL’s Document Type Definition, which is basically neither unified nor standardized. Under this circumstance it causes problems with structural analysis and numerical analyses between several corpora. Thus, it is necessary to mark up texts using a unified definition from a higher level to conduct analyses concurrently. In the previous study, we examined the possibility of converting classic documents with TEI-compliant XML by designing a tag-set and strictly structuring a wood-block printed book from Sharebon’s as a model case. In this study, we further examine the problems of (A) text formatting on character data level and (B) structuring ruby annotation which were previously unsolved.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
			<p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
			<p>
			  <date when="20140709"/>
			  <time when="13:45:00"/>
			</p>
			<p n="session">3</p>
			<p n="room">315 - Amphipôle</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
          <term>Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
          <term>Short Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
          <term>TEI</term>
          <term>corpus studies</term>
          <term>morphological analysis</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
          <term>archives</term>
          <term>repositories</term>
          <term>sustainability and preservation</term>
          <term>encoding - theory and practice</term>
          <term>text analysis</term>
          <term>asian studies</term>
          <term>xml</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="paper">
    <front>
      <head/>
      <div>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>1. Introduction</head>
        <p>As part of its KOTONOHA (meaning ‘words of the language’ in classical Japanese)
Project, the National Institute of Japanese Language and Linguistics (NINJAL) is
conducting a morphological analysis of Japanese classics. Both the selection and
digitization of classic documents are required in order to execute the analysis correctly.
Digitization and morphological analysis have been done thus far on the literature of
several ages and styles (Ogiso et al., 2012; Ichimura et al., 2012; 2013), and various text
corpora have been published. These text corpora are marked up with NINJAL’s original
Document Type Definition (DTD). However, some elements are used in common on all
corpora but basically are not unified nor standardized. Under this circumstance, it
enables structural analysis and string extraction from a single corpus but causes
problems with structural comparison and numerical analyses between several corpora.
Thus, it is necessary to design and mark up a unified definition from a higher level in
order to conduct analyses concurrently.</p>
        <p>In the previous study, we examined the possibility of converting classic documents with
TEI-compliant XML (Kawase et al., 2013), in particular, by designing a tag-set and
strictly structuring an old wood-block printed book from <hi rend="italic">Sharebon</hi>’s “<hi rend="italic">Keisei-kai
Futasuji-no-michi</hi>” (published in 1798, e.g. Fig. 1) as a model case, and sorted out this
problem. This work aims to provide further insights into those problems and propose a
solution.</p>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="DH2014_2_DH2014kawase-fig01F"/>
          <p>Fig. 1: Excerpt image of Sharebon's “Keisei-kai Futasuji-michi” (owned by NINJAL)</p>
        </figure>
        <head>2. Significance of Encoding Classic Documents</head>
        <p>The reason for choosing <hi rend="italic">Sharebon</hi> as a subject is because it is important primary
linguistic data from the early modern period (Keene, 1999) and it has the following
three features: (1) published in the broad age from the 18th to the first half of the 19th
century; (2) uses colloquial words and expressions among conversations between
characters; (3) abundantly describes things in Edo (former name of Tokyo) language
and Kamigata (Kyoto-Osaka region) language.
</p>
        <p>Therefore, describing <hi rend="italic">Sharebon</hi> in a machine-readable manner has profound
significance not only for bringing numerical analysis of unexplained colloquial
expressions of the modern period into reality but also for facilitating humanities
research in language history and descriptive bibliography. Furthermore, since many
texts that have a similar structure to <hi rend="italic">Sharebon</hi> were published over the same period of
time, this study will offer a common format for archiving coeval literature. </p>
        <head>3. Issues in Encoding <hi rend="italic">Sharebon</hi></head>
        <p>In order to analyze the manuscript from a corpus linguistic viewpoint, not only outward
mark-ups but also internal mark-ups of both document structure and linguistic structure
are required. In general, <hi rend="italic">Sharebon</hi> is composed of a combination of three parts: the front
matter; the narrative body that contains colloquial expressions and descriptive texts; and the back matter. For instance, in the case of “Keisei-kai Futasuji-michi”, the narrative
body is made up of two chapters, ‘Natsu-no-toko’ (Summer Alcove) and ‘Fuyu-no-toko’
(Winter Alcove). Since the composition of this whole document is well accorded with
the composition of an orthodox Western manuscript, we may mark up most of the
elements in reference to TEI P5: Guidelines (Burnard and Baumanm, 2007). Table
1 shows the list of elements with an explication of their roles used to mark up the
document.
</p>
        <p>The problems incurred in the process of encoding Sharebon can be broadly classified
into two matters: (A) text formatting on a #PCDATA (character data) level; and (B)
structuring ruby annotations. We will discuss these two matters in more detail in the
following sections. </p>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="DH2014_2_DH2014kawase-tab01F"/>
          <p>Fig. 2: List of elements with an explication of their roles to mark up Sharebon</p>
        </figure>
        <head>3.1 Text Formatting on #PCDATA </head>
        <p>To design and assure a high-quality corpus in terms of linguistic resources, it is
necessary to index information about lexical morphemes (e.g. word class, inflected
forms, pronunciations) at the body-text level. However, since there are three problems
in the sentences of early modern Japanese, it is difficult to conduct morphological
analysis properly: (A-1) voice markings called <hi rend="italic">dakuten</hi> are missing where they should
be; (A-2) corresponding phonetic characters called <hi rend="italic">hiragana</hi> and <hi rend="italic">katakana</hi> are not
unified; (A-3) iteration symbols called <hi rend="italic">odoriji</hi> are unmodified.
</p>
        <p>For example, <hi rend="italic">dakuten</hi> makes a phonetic shift from <hi rend="italic">ka</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ki</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ku</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ke</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ko</hi> (written
in hiragana letters as か, き, く, け, こ) to <hi rend="italic">ga</hi>, <hi rend="italic">gi</hi>, <hi rend="italic">gu</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ge</hi>, <hi rend="italic">go</hi> (rendered as が, ぎ, ぐ,
げ, ご). </p>
        <head>3.2 Structuring Ruby Annotations</head>
        <p>Such annotations are the small-text characters rendered alongside the base text. In
vertical writing, ruby is typically printed on the right-hand side. However, since the
three problems exist, it is difficult to mark up both outward information and the
linguistic structure simultaneously: (B-1) ruby text carries extended characters (gaiji),
damaged and missing characters, and some typographical errors and omissions; (B-2)
words of such text and base text are not in one-to-one correspondence; (B-3) There can
also be another ruby annotation on the left-hand side simultaneously.
</p>
        <head>4. Means for Solving the Problem</head>
        <head>4.1 Text Formatting on #PCDATA</head>
        <p>At NINJAL, for problems (A-1), (A-2), and (A-3), the character level is corrected using
the original elements of &lt;vMark&gt;, &lt;kana&gt;, and &lt;odoriji&gt;, respectively (Ichimura et al.,
2012; 2013). We accurately describe the text formatting in a uniform way by combining
the TEI elements &lt;seg&gt; and &lt;choice&gt; (e.g. Fig. 2).</p>
        <p>According to TEI P5: Guidelines (Burnard and Baumanm, 2007), &lt;seg&gt; (arbitrary
segment) represents any segmentation of text below the ‘chunk’ level, and &lt;choice&gt;
groups a number of alternative encodings at the same point in the text. Distinctions in
the corrections of (A-1), (A-2), and (A-3) can be shown by writing @type, holding
selectable values from vMark, kana, and odoriji, to the attribute of element &lt;seg&gt;. The
original text marked with TEI element &lt;orig&gt; (original form), along with the corrected
text (the optimal version for morphological analysis) marked with TEI element &lt;reg&gt;
(regularization) are written below the &lt;choice&gt; level.</p>
        <p>This description policy preserves both the outward and linguistic structure, even if
problems (A-1), (A-2), and (A-3) carry over extended characters or omissions in the
original manuscript, and brings morphological analysis into reality as well. </p>
        <head>4.2 Structuring Ruby Annotations</head>
        <p>At NINJAL, regarding structuring ruby annotation, since priority is given to
morphological analysis, words and characters are encoded using the original defined
element &lt;ruby&gt; with an attribute @rubyText (e.g. Fig. 3a). To express this structure
with TEI-compliant XML, we can simply substitute the element &lt;ruby&gt; with &lt;w&gt;
(word) and the attribute @rubyText with @ana (e.g. Fig. 3b). However, the important
ruby text information is described inside @ana as a value, we cannot solve problem
(B-1) under this policy. Depending on the technology, CSS, XHTML, and HTML5
platforms might be considered as alternatives in order to structure ruby annotation
(Benoit, 2010) (e.g. Fig. 3c).
</p>
        <p>Here, each &lt;ruby&gt;, &lt;rt&gt;, and &lt;rp&gt; represent inline elements that contain base text with
ruby annotation, the superscript which comes over the base text, and ruby parentheses
which are used to wrap around opening and closing parentheses &lt;rt&gt;, respectively.
However, since the ruby text comes over the #PCDATA level, we cannot solve problem
(B-2) under this policy. In addition, we have to solve the above problem and problem
(B-3), securing the coexistence of ruby on the right-hand side and left-hand side,
simultaneously.</p>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="DH2014_2_DH2014kawase-fig02F"/>
          <p>Fig. 3: Examples for encoding ruby annotations</p>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="DH2014_2_DH2014kawase-fig04F"/>
          <p>Fig. 4: Examples for ruby annotations on both sides</p>
        </figure>
        <p>Imaginably, as shown in Fig. 4a, we will be able to suggest one solution to express the
character on base text in a stand-off fashion, in case of the base text carries double ruby
on the both sides. However, the above suggestion may work only the character string
and both sides of ruby correspond each other. As shown in Fig. 4b, when ruby on either
side does not fit or exceed the each target character, this suggestion would be
inapplicable.</p>
        <p>Currently, we have difficulty in choosing a path that allows specifying both the object
outline and structure of Japanese language together; therefore, a new definition over
ruby annotation is needed as a means to this end. As shown in Fig. 5, our current
solution is to mark up the manuscript in a way which makes it possible to output two
types of XML file that specify the information of the object and the structure of
Japanese language separately, rather than to fulfill both at the same time.</p>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="DH2014_2_DH2014kawase-fig05F"/>
          <p>Fig. 5: Solution for problem (B); exporting two types of XML file</p>
        </figure>
        <head>5. Conclusion</head>
        <p>In this study, developing a corpus for historical documents in a comprehensive and
versatile way was considered the ultimate goal. We devised a tag-set based on the
TEI-element, and structured <hi rend="italic">Sharebon</hi>’s “<hi rend="italic">Keisei-kai Futasuji-michi</hi>” as a model case.
We examined the problems of (A) text formatting on #PCDATA level and (B)
structuring ruby annotations which were previously unsolved. For problem (A), a
concrete policy to bring morphological analysis into reality, by combing the element of
&lt;seg&gt; and &lt;choice&gt;, was considered. For problem (B), major difficulties of structuring
both outward information and the linguistic structure of Japanese documents at the same
time were presented, and problems to solve were pointed out. Especially, ruby
annotation is absolutely imperative for Japanese documents. This extra-textual addition is common and employed almost everywhere from historical documents to modern
comics for highlighting the pronunciation or meaning of a word. Our future challenge is
to examine a compromise that satisfies both structures simultaneously while working
out the problems with the TEI Council.
</p>
        <head>Funding</head>
        <p>This work was supported by the collaborative research project “Design of a Diachronic
Corpus” and “Study of the History of the Japanese Language Using Statistics and
Machine Learning” carried at the National Institute for Japanese Language and
Linguistics. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="References">
        <listBibl>
        <bibl><hi rend="bold">Benoit, G.</hi> (2010). <hi rend="italic">Expanding, Facilitating, and Applying Ruby to Explore User Engagement with Encoded Texts</hi>, http://web.simmons.edu/~benoit/rc/ruby/ Ruby-Poster.pdf (accessed 15 October 2013).</bibl>
        <bibl><hi rend="bold">Burnard, L. and Bauman</hi>, S.(2007).TEI P5: <hi rend="italic">Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</hi>, Text Encoding Initiative.Arlington, MA: TEI Consortium. http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5/ (accessed 15 October 2013).</bibl>
        <bibl><hi rend="bold">Ichimura, T., Kawase, A. and Ogiso, T. </hi>(2012). <hi rend="italic">Structuring Colloquial Early Modern Japanese Text and Its Issues of Definition</hi>, Proceedings of the 96th IPSJ SIG Computers and the Humanities, CH96: 1-8.</bibl>
        <bibl><hi rend="bold">Ichimura, T., Kawase, A. and Ogiso, T.</hi> (2013). <hi rend="italic">Structuing the Corpus of Share-bon</hi>, Proceedings of the 3rd Workshop on Corpus Japanese Linguistics, 249-258.</bibl>
        <bibl><hi rend="bold">Kawase, A., Ichimura, T. and Ogiso, T. </hi>(2013). P<hi rend="italic">roblems in TEI P5 Encoding on Colloquial Japanese Documents of the Early Modern Period</hi>, Proceedings of the IPSJ SIG-CH/PNC/ECAI/CIAS Joint Symposium 2013, 7-12.</bibl>
        <bibl><hi rend="bold">Keene, D. </hi>(1999).<hi rend="italic"> A History of Japanese Literature Volume 2: World Within Walls</hi>, Columbia University Press, New York.</bibl>
        <bibl><hi rend="bold">Ogiso, T., Komachi, M., Den, Y. and Matsumoto, Y.</hi> (2012). <hi rend="italic">UniDic for Early Middle Japanese</hi>, Proceedings of the 8th International Conference on Language Resource and Evaluation (LREC), 911-915.</bibl>
</listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
