<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:x="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:exsl="http://exslt.org/common" xml:id="Paper-849">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Digitizing the Dead and Dismembered: DH Technologies for the Study of Coptic Texts</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Schroeder</surname>, <forename>Caroline T.</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>University of the Pacific, United States of America</affiliation>
          <email></email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Zeldes</surname>, <forename>Amir</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Humboldt University, Berlin</affiliation>
          <email></email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
        <publisher>EPFL, Switzerland</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>EPFL Digital Humanities Laboratory</name>
          <address>
            <addrLine>GC D2 386</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Station 18</addrLine>
            <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
            <addrLine>frederic.kaplan@epfl.ch</addrLine>
          </address>
        </distributor>
        <pubPlace>Lausanne, Switzerland</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>EPFL</addrLine>
          <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="abstract">The Coptic language evolved from the language of the hieroglyphs of the pharaonic era and represents the last phase of the Egyptian language. It is pivotal for a wide range of humanistic disciplines, such as linguistics, biblical studies, the history of Christianity, Egyptology, and ancient history. Whereas languages like Classical Greek and Latin have enjoyed advances made in digital humanities with fully-fledged online research environments accessible to students and scholars (such as the Perseus Digital Library), until recently, no computational tools for Coptic have existed. Nor has an open digital research corpus been available. The research team developing Coptic SCRIPTORIUM (Sahidic Corpus Research: Internet Platform for Interdisciplinary multilayer Methods) is developing and providing open-source technologies and methodologies for interdisciplinary research across multiple disciplines in the Coptic language. This paper will address the automated tools we are developing for annotating and conducting research on a Coptic digital corpus.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
        <p>
          <date when="20140710"/>
          <time when="11:00:00"/>
        </p>
		<p n="session">5</p>
		<p n="room">412 - Amphimax</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
          <term>Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
          <term>Long Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
          <term>linguistics</term>
          <term>Coptic</term>
          <term>manuscripts</term>
          <term>antiquity</term>
          <term>history</term>
          <term>Egypt</term>
          <term>theology</term>
          <term>literature</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
          <term>classical studies</term>
          <term>corpora and corpus activities</term>
          <term>historical studies</term>
          <term>near eastern studies</term>
          <term>xml</term>
          <term>theology</term>
          <term>bibliographic methods / textual studies</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="paper">
    <front>

      <div>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p>The
Coptic language evolved from the language of the hieroglyphs of the pharaonic
era and represents the last phase of the Egyptian language.  It is pivotal for a wide range of humanistic
disciplines, such as linguistics, biblical studies, the history of Christianity,
Egyptology, and ancient history.  Whereas
languages like Classical Greek and Latin have enjoyed advances made in digital
humanities with fully-fledged online research environments accessible to
students and scholars (such as the Perseus Digital Library), until recently, no
computational tools for Coptic have existed. Nor has an open digital research
corpus been available.  The research team
developing Coptic SCRIPTORIUM (<hi rend="bold">S</hi>ahidic
<hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">C</hi></hi>orpus <hi rend="bold">R</hi>esearch: <hi rend="bold">I</hi>nternet <hi rend="bold">P</hi>la<hi rend="bold">t</hi>f<hi rend="bold">or</hi>m for <hi rend="bold">I</hi>nterdisciplinary m<hi rend="bold">u</hi>ltilayer
<hi rend="bold">M</hi>ethods) is developing and providing
open-source technologies and methodologies for interdisciplinary research
across multiple disciplines in the Coptic language.  This paper will address the automated tools
we are developing for annotating and conducting research on a Coptic digital
corpus.  </p>
        <p>Conducting digitally-assisted
and computational research in Coptic using available DH resources is complex
for several reasons.  Most texts are
preserved from damaged, incomplete, and dismembered manuscripts or papyri.  The DH project papyri.info has begun to
create an online open-access resource for the study of Greek papyri and is
beginning to digitize Coptic papyri and ostraca (ancient pot-shards with
writing).  These texts, however, are
primarily documentary, consisting of wills, contracts, personal letters,
etc.  Coptic literary and monastic texts,
the core of Coptic SCRIPTORIUM, are essential for the study of the Bible,
intellectual history, literary history, and religious history.  The manuscripts containing these texts were
removed from Egypt in the seventeenth through nineteenth centuries piece by
piece (sometimes page by page).  Some
have been published, many have not, and very few have been digitized in a
format suitable for digital and computational work.  Texts must be must be reconstructed from pieces
of manuscripts published in fragments and/or stored in various libraries and
museums worldwide. The status of Coptic
literary and monastic complicates metadata management and corpus
architecture:  what constitutes a “work”
– the codex in which a copy of the text appeared (and which may be dispersed
across multiple physical repositories)? the manuscript fragment housed in a
particular library or museum repository or the work, which only might survive
in fragments of multiple codices (all copies of a “book” from the monastery’s
library), and thus in fragments not only from more than one codex but also more
than one modern repository?</p>
        <p>Coptic
scholarship still lacks many standards for digital publication and language
research that are taken for granted in Greek and Latin. As with other ancient
languages, Coptic manuscripts are written without spaces.  However, in contrast to its ancient
counterparts, scholarly conventions on word division differ substantially from
scholar to scholar. Additionally, since Coptic is an
agglutinative language, the relevant unit for linguistic analysis is the
morpheme, below the ‘word’ level.  This
means that segmentation guidelines must be developed for both levels of
resolution. In order to search multiple texts, guidelines and tools for
normalization, part-of-speech tagging and lemmatization of Coptic must be
developed.  These tools need to take into
account Coptic’s agglutinative nature, e.g. normalizing and annotating on the
morpheme and word levels.</p>
        <p>Finally,
the development of the Coptic language during Egypt’s Greco-Roman era raises
questions about the origins of the language, its usage in a multilingual
context, and the language practices of its ancient speakers and writers.  Coptic consists of Egyptian grammar,
vocabulary, and syntax written primarily in the Greek alphabet; some Egyptian
letters were retained, and some Greek and Latin vocabulary was incorporated
into the language. The richness of the vocabulary’s languages of
origin varies from author to author, genre to genre.  And despite recent publications on the topic,
much research remains to be conducted on the extent and nature of
multilingualism in late antique Egypt, especially during the fourth and fifth
centuries. Additionally, due to the agglutinative nature
of the language, one word can be comprised of morphemes with different
languages of origin.</p>
        <p>This paper will focus on the
automated tools our project is developing to process the language, especially
tokenizing and part-of-speech annotations. 
Coptic SCRIPTORIUM has developed the first tokenizer and part-of-speech
tagger for the language, and in fact for any language in the Egyptian language
family. The presentation will address the unique challenges to processing and
annotating the Coptic language.  We will
present our current technical solutions, their accuracy rates, and the
potential for future research.  We will
also address the ways in which this language’s and corpus’s unique featured
differentiate them from other more widely studied ancient languages, such as
Greek and Latin.  Examples will be drawn
from the open-access corpora we are developing and annotating with these tools,
available at <ref type="url" target="http://coptic.pacific.edu">coptic.pacific.edu</ref>
(backup site <ref type="url" target="http://www.carrieschroeder.com/scriptorium">www.carrieschroeder.com/scriptorium</ref>).  The Coptic
corpora processed and annotated with these tools can be searched and visualized
in ANNIS, a tool for multi-layer annotated corpora.  We anticipate this presentation to be of
interest to scholars in digital humanities working with ancient languages and
manuscript corpora as well as DH linguists and corpus linguists.</p></div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="References">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Bentley Layton </hi>(2011), <hi rend="italic">A Coptic Grammar</hi>, 3rd Edition,
            Rev, Porta Linguarum Orientalium Neue Serie 20 (Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz, 2011),
            19–20.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Layton</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Coptic Grammar</hi>, 5.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">J. N. Adams, Mark Janse, and Simon Swain</hi> (2002), <hi rend="italic">Bilingualism
            in Ancient Society</hi> (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2002); Arietta
            Papaconstantinou, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Multilingual Experience in Egypt from the
              Ptolemies to the Abassids</hi> (Burlington: Ashgate, 2010).</bibl>
          <bibl>http://www.sfb632.uni-potsdam.de/annis/</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
