<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:x="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:exsl="http://exslt.org/common" xml:id="Paper-425">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Designing the next big thing: Randomness versus serendipity in DH tools</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Martin</surname>, <forename>Kim</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>University of Western Ontario</affiliation>
          <email>kimberleymartin@gmail.com</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Quan-Haase</surname>, <forename>Anabel</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>University of Western Ontario</affiliation>
          <email>aquan@uwo.ca</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
        <publisher>EPFL, Switzerland</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>EPFL Digital Humanities Laboratory</name>
          <address>
            <addrLine>GC D2 386</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Station 18</addrLine>
            <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
            <addrLine>frederic.kaplan@epfl.ch</addrLine>
          </address>
        </distributor>
        <pubPlace>Lausanne, Switzerland</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>EPFL</addrLine>
          <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="abstract">A number of DH tools have been recently developed that aim to re-introduce serendipity to online searches. This paper critically examines four of these tools and makes suggestions for future designs based on library and information science literature.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
        <p>
          <date when="20140710"/>
          <time when="09:00:00"/>
        </p>
		<p n="session">4</p>
		<p n="room">319 - Amphipôle</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
          <term>Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
          <term>Long Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
          <term>serendipity</term>
          <term>information discovery</term>
          <term>DH tools</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
          <term>information discovery</term>
          <term>serendipity</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="paper">
    <front>

      <div>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>

        <p>A number of recent initiatives
within the DH community promote the design, development, and implementation of
digital tools aimed at speeding up, clarifying, or otherwise improving the
research practices of humanities scholars. This year, the One Week | One Tool
(OWOT) summer institute, funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities,
resulted in the creation of Serendip-o-matic, a serendipity engine for digital
research. This tool relies on users to feed it a selection of text or citations
in order to create a list of keywords, which it then uses to find related
information. The documents returned are taken from the Digital Public Library
of America (DPLA), Europeana, and Flickr<ref target="n1" rend="sup">1</ref>. The participants of the
2013 OWOT initiative are not alone in their quest to design a digital tool
geared toward enhancing the chance encounter with information, resources,
ideas, research materials, and even people. Tim Sherratt, the manager of Trove
at the National Library of Australia, often includes an element of chance in
the tools he designs for use in the humanities. For instance, in his tool Trove
News Bot, Sheratt (2013) allows users to interact with a Twitter stream by
sending tweets with directions (such as #luckydip), which will return random
results from the National Archives of Australia’s digital collection<ref target="n2" rend="sup">2</ref>. Similar
tools have been developed that introduce serendipity into the collections of
the DPLA and the British Library.</p>
        <p>One motivation for the development
of digital tools aimed at enhancing serendipity in digital environments comes
out of the need to redesign and recreate the complexity of the research
environment found in library stacks and archival collections. It is often
argued that this complexity may be lost in digital environments, which are
highly predictable and primarily based on keyword search. To what extent
serendipity is reduced in digital search is debatable. Nonetheless, this
perception of loss directly affects how scholars, and in particular humanities
scholars, adopt and use digital tools. A study of historians’ research
practices suggests that these scholars are skeptical of conducting their
research exclusively in digital environments because they lack the ability to
encounter key resources (primary and secondary materials) that could have a
major impact on their research findings <ref target="n3" rend="sup">3</ref>. In
this study, the authors also found that historians were willing to experiment
with digital tools, if these could recreate opportunities for encountering
information. Hence, scholars perceive the discovery of resources, browsing, and
chance encountering as central elements of their research practice that can,
and need to, be supported online.</p>
        <p>Outside of academia, a number of
tools have emerged that try to introduce serendipity into the online
experience. What is less clear from the literature is how to best support this
process, as a wide range of approaches have been suggested ranging from
interactions in social media <ref target="n4" rend="sup">4</ref>, exploration in non-search
related digital environments, and information search in digital environments <ref target="n5" rend="sup">5</ref>. The approach most commonly taken is
to introduce serendipity into the online information search experience; this is
often done by introducing some element of randomness and thereby reducing the
predictability of search results. An example of this approach is BananaSlug,
which returns random results to a search query. Other approaches include
reversing or modifying the ranking in which search results are presented online <ref target="n6" rend="sup">6</ref>. This would draw attention to a
different set of items because users commonly tend to investigate only the
first and perhaps second pages of search results. All of these approaches aim
at broadening “the search space, promoting encounters with items that might
not, under existing algorithms, come to the attention of the user”. While the
majority of digital tools aimed at promoting serendipity have emerged outside
of the humanities, a series of tools have recently been developed with
humanists in mind. These tools have garnered considerable attention in the
field, but it remains unclear what element of serendipity they support. Part of
the problem is the fact that the concept of serendipity is elusive <ref target="n7" rend="sup">7</ref> and difficult to pinpoint. Reducing it to the introduction of randomness,
however, does not seem to be the best way to move forward, even though it is
the one most commonly utilized. A second problem, and perhaps more concerning,
is that scholars need to first understand that serendipity is not a
one-dimensional concept but, rather, includes a number of related facets, which
need to inform tool design and implementation. The present paper critically
examines four DH tools that encourage serendipitous results and attempts to
place these within current models of serendipity:</p>
        <list>
        <item>Serendip-o-matic (http://serendip-o-matic.com/)</item>
        <item>Trove News Bot (https://github.com/wragge/trovenewsbot)</item>
        <item>Mechanical Curator (http://mechanicalcurator.tumblr.com/)</item>
          <item>DP.LA Bot (https://github.com/wragge/trovenewsbot).</item>
        </list>

        <p>As a basis for this examination, we
have established the main facets of serendipity obtained from the extensive
literature in Library and Information Science (LIS). Through this comparative
study, we aim to accomplish two goals. First, there is a gap in understanding
exactly what aspects of serendipity digital tools support. By merging the
literature in LIS with tool design in DH, we hope to create greater clarity as
to what aspects have been supported. Second, the results of the study will determine
what future developments are needed to better support the work of humanists in
digital environments. </p>

        <p>Interviews with 20 history scholars
inform the first phase of this study. These scholars indicated a desire for
serendipitous encounters with material to remain a part of their research
process after the integration of digital texts to their work. After discovering
that historians were seeking new methods of information acquisition online,
further interviews were conducted with DH scholars to see what methods they
were using to browse information. The results of these two sets of qualitative
data will be discussed and used to demonstrate a need for a serendipity tool
within the DH community. </p>

        <p>The second phase of this research
is an in-depth exploration of the four information-discovery tools listed
above. These tools will be examined in terms of Erdelez’s (2004) model of
information encountering outlined below <ref target="n8" rend="sup">8</ref>. After analyzing each tool carefully, follow-up
interviews will be conducted with the creators of each tool to discuss their
intentions for and reflections upon, the use of the tool by humanist scholars.</p>

        <p>A wide range of models of
serendipity have been developed relying on very different data sets and
assumptions. Erdelez (2004) developed one of the first models and emphasized
the experience of information encountering (IE), which she defined as a type of
opportunistic acquisition of information. Erdelez’s (2004) utilized an
experimental setting, where participants were asked to look for information
related to a foreground problem and the researcher observed how they would
react to information related to a background problem. As part of her model,
Erdelez (2000) identified five elements:</p>
        <list>
        <item><hi rend="italic">noticing</hi>: the perception of encountered information; </item>
        <item><hi rend="italic">stopping</hi>: the interruption of the initial information seeking
activity; </item>
        <item><hi rend="italic">examining</hi>: the assessment of usefulness of the encountered information;
</item>
        <item><hi rend="italic">capturing</hi>: the extraction and saving of the encountered information for
future use; </item>
        <item>and <hi rend="italic">returning</hi>: the reconnection with the initial information
seeking task.</item>
        </list>

        <p>In Erdelez’s (2004) model, a person
is primarily focusing on the information needs related to a foreground problem.
However, cues related to another problem, a background problem, may catch the
person’s attention. If the person notices the cues and stops to examine the
newly encountered information, then there is an opportunity for discovering
unexpected resources. It is this process of noticing, examining, and capturing
that digital tools try to emulated or support. </p>

        <p>Each of the four tools reflects one
or more aspects of the serendipitous process as outlined by Erdelez, (see Table
1).</p>
        <table>
          <row>
            <cell role="data">
   
  </cell>
            <cell role="data">Noticing</cell>
            <cell role="data">Stopping</cell>
            <cell role="data">Examining</cell>
            <cell role="data">Capturing</cell>
            <cell role="data">Returning</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell role="data">
  Serendip-o-matic
  </cell>
            <cell role="data">
   
  </cell>
            <cell role="data">
   
  ✓</cell>
            <cell role="data">
   
  ✓</cell>
            <cell role="data">
   
  </cell>
            <cell role="data">
   
  </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell role="data">
  Trove News Bot
  </cell>
            <cell role="data">
   
  ✓</cell>
            <cell role="data">
   
  ✓</cell>
            <cell role="data">
   
  ✓</cell>
            <cell role="data">
   
  ✓</cell>
            <cell role="data">
   
  </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell role="data">
  Mechanical Curator
  </cell>
            <cell role="data">
   
  ✓</cell>
            <cell role="data">
   
  ✓</cell>
            <cell role="data">
   
  ✓</cell>
            <cell role="data">
  some
  </cell>
            <cell role="data">
   
  </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell role="data">
  DP.LA Bot
  </cell>
            <cell role="data">
  ✓</cell>
            <cell role="data">
  ✓</cell>
            <cell role="data">
  some</cell>
            <cell role="data">
   
  </cell>
            <cell role="data">
   
  </cell>
          </row>
        </table>

        <p>The tools listed above, with the
exclusion of Serendip-o-matic, select materials randomly and then present these
to followers on Twitter. Randomness, as we know, does not necessarily mean that
serendipity will occur. These tools all provide links to places that users can
go to receive extraneous materials in the hopes that something of interest will
come their way. </p>
        <p>Interestingly, the capturing
element of these tools seems to be largely disregarded. Considering the DH
community is acutely aware of the need to instantly capture digital documents
and the associated metadata with citation tools (Zotero), none of the examined
tools includes this element in their framework. This leads the authors to
conclude that future design could focus on this element of capturing
information, and could introduce a method that allows for the saving of
documents so users can retrace their footsteps after returning to the initial
task or foreground problem. Our critical analysis of various DH tools and how
they support serendipity provides opportunity to further enhance these tools as
well as a means to design additional tools that can impact the research
practices of humanities scholars.  </p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="References">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>1. <hi rend="bold">CHMN</hi>. (2013). <hi rend="italic">Serendip-o-matic: Let your sources surprise you</hi>. One Week | One Tool. Retrieved October 31, 2013, from <ref type="url" target="http://serendip-o-matic.com/about/">serendip-o-matic.com/about</ref>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>2. <hi rend="bold">Sherratt, T.</hi> (2013). <hi rend="italic">Conversations with Collections</hi>. discontents. Retrieved October 31, 2013, from <ref type="url" target="http://discontents.com.au/">discontents.com.au</ref>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>3. <hi rend="bold">Martin, K., &amp; Quan-Haase, A.</hi> (2013). <hi rend="italic">Are e-books substituting print books?</hi> Tradition, serendipity, and spportunity in the adoption and use of e-books for historical research and teaching. Journal of the American Society for Information Science and Technology. 64(5), 1016-1028.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>4. <hi rend="bold">Bogers, T., &amp; Björneborn, L.</hi> (2013). <hi rend="italic">Micro-serendipity: Meaningful coincidences in everyday life shared on Twitter</hi>. In Proceedings of iConference (pp. 196–208).
          </bibl>
          <bibl>5. <hi rend="bold">Quan-Haase, A., Burkell, J., &amp; Rubin, V. L.</hi> (n.d.). <hi rend="italic">The role of serendipity in digital environments.</hi> In Encyclopedia of Information Science and Technology. IGI Global.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>6. <hi rend="bold">Jansen, B. J., Spink, A., &amp; Saracevic, T.</hi> (2000). <hi rend="italic">Real life, real users, and real needs: A study and analysis of user queries and on the web</hi>. Information Processing &amp; Management, 36(2), 207–227.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>7. <hi rend="bold">Merton, R. K.</hi> (2004). <hi rend="italic">The travels and adventures of serendipity: a study in sociological semantics and the sociology of science.</hi> Princeton, N.J: Princeton University Press.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>8. <hi rend="bold">Erdelez, S.</hi> (2004). <hi rend="italic">Investigation of information encountering in the controlled research environment. </hi>Information Processing &amp; Management, 40(6), 1013–1025. doi:10.1016/j.ipm.2004.02.002
          </bibl>
          <bibl>9. <hi rend="bold">Erdelez, S.</hi> (2000). <hi rend="italic">Towards understanding information encountering on the Web</hi>. In Proceedings of the 63rd annual meeting of the American Society for Information Science (pp. 363–371). Medford, N.J.: Information Today.
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
