<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:x="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:exsl="http://exslt.org/common" xml:id="Paper-311">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Exploring the Intersection of Personal and Public Authorial Voice in the Works of Willa Cather</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Dimmit</surname>, <forename>Laura</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Nebraska Literary Lab, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</affiliation>
          <email>lkdimmit@gmail.com</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Kirilloff</surname>, <forename>Gabrielle </forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Nebraska Literary Lab, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</affiliation>
          <email>gkirilloff@gmail.com</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Warren</surname>, <forename>Chandler </forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Nebraska Literary Lab, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</affiliation>
          <email>chandlerawarren@gmail.com</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Wehrwein</surname>, <forename>James</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Nebraska Literary Lab, University of Nebraska-Lincoln</affiliation>
          <email>jawehrwein@gmail.com</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
        <publisher>EPFL, Switzerland</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>EPFL Digital Humanities Laboratory</name>
          <address>
            <addrLine>GC D2 386</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Station 18</addrLine>
            <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
            <addrLine>frederic.kaplan@epfl.ch</addrLine>
          </address>
        </distributor>
        <pubPlace>Lausanne, Switzerland</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>EPFL</addrLine>
          <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="abstract">This research began in a class taught by Matthew Jockers and has continued under his direction as a project of the newly formed Nebraska Literary Lab. Our work focused on mining the fiction and non-fiction works of Willa Cather that are housed in the Willa Cather Archive at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln (Jewell, Andrew. The Willa Cather Archive. U of Nebraska-Lincoln, 2004-2013. Web.). Largely regarded as a private person, Cather forbade the publication of her correspondences; only within the past year have her letters finally been published. With the publication of these letter comes the unique opportunity for scholars to research Cather’s personal thoughts and voice. Our research focused on using stylometrics to explore the ways in which the voice Cather used in her correspondences differs from the voice she used in her public writing; our conclusions point to similarities between Cather’s novel My Mortal Enemy, a work noted for both its economy of style and autobiographical features, and her recently published letters.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
        <p>
          <date when="20140711"/>
          <time when="14:00:00"/>
        </p>
		<p n="session">8</p>
		<p n="room">315 - Amphipôle</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
          <term>Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
          <term>Short Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
          <term>Cather</term>
          <term>voice</term>
          <term>correspondence</term>
          <term>stylometry</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
          <term>literary studies</term>
          <term>English studies</term>
          <term>text mining</term>
          <term>stylistics and stylometry</term>
          <term>text analysis</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="paper">
    <front>
      
      <div>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        
        <head>1. Introduction</head>
        <p><hi rend="bold"/> In a letter that Willa Cather wrote in response to a reader's critique in 1924, she claims:“I
 had a perfectly good reason for writing ‘Antonia’ in the first person, 
masculine—and I did not for one minute try to ‘talk like a man’. Such a 
thing as humbugging any one never occurred to me. It does not matter who
 tells a story. It is merely a point of view, a position which the 
writer takes in regard to his material...”.<ref target="n1" rend="sup">1</ref></p>
        <p>Looking
 into an author’s unpublished writings for additional insight is an 
analytic strategy with a long history in literature studies. With 
selections from Willa Cather’s extensive collection of correspondences 
now available for study, scholars are presented with the opportunity to 
compare Cather’s private letters with her published novels. A 
statistical examination of Cather’s letters has, until recently, been 
impossible; until the 2013 publication of <hi rend="italic">The Selected Letters of Willa Cather</hi>, Cather’s letters were not available to the public.<ref target="n2" rend="sup">2</ref>
 The publication of the letters offers a glimpse into the private life 
of Cather, a life that she kept carefully guarded. The collection 
contains approximately 550 letters, spanning her life from age 14 until 
just days before her death. While Cather often spent years working on 
her published writings, the fact that many of her correspondences were 
hurriedly dashed off indicates that an examination of the letters could 
reveal a style of writing that is less polished, worked, and 
intentional.</p>
        <p>The potential applications of 
this type of statistical analytic in literature studies as a whole are 
wide reaching. Many authors have left behind extensive collections of 
personal writing that could hold untapped insight about how they 
communicated in different settings, and how their writing evolved. By 
using similar tools to those we utilized in this exploratory research of
 Cather, scholars can continue to quantify the suppositions that 
traditional methods of literary analysis have yielded.</p>
        <head>2. Methodology</head>
        <p>Our research was divided into two main tasks. First, we 
established a “personal voice signal” from Cather’s correspondence. To 
derive a quantitative signal, we narrowed the available letters down to 
164 letters using the hclust() function in R (For additional 
information, see http://www.r-project.org/.). Setting the number of 
clusters to 18, we chose the cluster that contained the highest 
percentage of letters addressed to distinctly personal correspondents. 
The personal signal was created by using a mean frequency threshold to 
determine a set of frequently used words in the corpus of letters. In 
the tradition of Burrows and others working in authorship attribution, 
we elected to measure style based on the occurrence of high frequency 
word features.<ref target="n3" rend="sup">3</ref><ref target="n4" rend="sup">4</ref> This allowed us to both avoid arbitrarily selecting words, and to avoid using any context-sensitive words in our signal.<ref target="n5" rend="sup">5</ref>
 It is likely that the 15 frequency features, or function words, that we
 selected are also less dependent on an author’s conscious decision to 
vary his or her vocabulary.<ref target="n6" rend="sup">6</ref>
 Thus, function words might offer a better indication of the 
subconscious, intrinsic choices that inform a writer’s voice. It was our
 initial expectation that Cather’s personal voice signal would differ 
from the narrative voices present within her novels. Our initial 
research question revolved around the relationship between private and 
public authorship: how (if at all) did Cather’s fiction act as a 
mouthpiece for her personal voice?</p>
        <p>Once we 
generated a signal from Cather’s letters, we used a clustering function 
in R to compare the signal with 15 of her novels. In order to compare 
Cather’s novels with the personal voice signal derived from her 
correspondences, we used R to calculate two statistical measures of 
similarity: correlation coefficient and Euclidean distance. These two 
units of measure compare the similarity between Cather’s personal voice 
signal and her use of function words in the corpus of novels. Examining 
the Euclidean distance (with the dist() function) provides a way to 
calculate the numerical distance between the frequency of the function 
words within the personal correspondences and the frequency of the same 
set of function words within each of the five novels. The correlation 
coefficient measures the linear dependence between the function words in
 the correspondences and the function words in each novel. We divided 
each of the novels into 1,000 word chunks in order to track the extent 
to which portions of the novels were more similar to Cather’s personal 
voice than others. In order to calculate a unique Euclidean distance for
 each novel, as opposed to its parts, we averaged the distances for all 
the 1,000 word sections of each novel to determine a mean similarity 
between each novel and Cather’s personal voice signal.</p>
        
        <head>3. Observations</head>
        <p>While some of our findings on the similarity 
between Cather’s personal voice signal and her use of function words 
within her novels reaffirmed our initial hypotheses, some have defied 
initial expectations. We found that Cather’s use of function words 
within her novels was significantly different from the personal voice 
signal calculated from the correspondences. However, the frequency of 
function words did not vary significantly among 14 of the 15 novels we 
examined, regardless of the gender of the narrator. This would indicate 
that, while there is a difference between Cather’s “personal voice” and 
14 of her published novels, certain aspects of the voice she adopts in 
these novels remains constant regardless of the identity of the 
narrator. We did identify a single outlier among Cather’s novels. The 
frequency of function words within Cather’s novel <hi rend="italic">My Mortal Enemy</hi> more closely resembles the use of frequency words in Cather’s correspondences than any of the other novels we examined.<ref target="n7" rend="sup">7</ref></p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">My Mortal Enemy</hi>
 was published in 1926, approximately halfway through Cather’s 
publishing career. Previous scholarly commentary on Cather has also 
indicated that<hi rend="italic">My Mortal Enemy</hi> is a singular book in her 
fiction corpus. The novel focuses on two periods in the life of Myra 
Henshawe and her husband, Oswald. The narrator, Nellie Birdseye, who 
many scholars argue is modeled after Cather, acts primarily as a frame 
for sharing the Henshawe’s story. It is widely considered to be the 
embodiment of Cather’s own novelistic ideal, the novel demeuble.<ref target="n8" rend="sup">8</ref> For 
Cather, the novel demeuble was an evocative form of realism, stripped of
 unnecessary detail and embellishment. The unique style of narration 
present in <hi rend="italic">My Mortal Enemy</hi> raises interesting questions about similarities between this novel and Cather’s correspondences. If <hi rend="italic">My Mortal Enemy</hi>
 embodies Cather’s own idealized notion of stripped bare, to the point 
realism, than is it possible that Cather also adopted a similar style in
 her personal letters? </p>
        <p>Interesting questions are also raised by the way in which <hi rend="italic">My Mortal Enemy</hi>draws
 from Cather’s life. The novel’s autobiographical nature has largely 
been shrouded in mystery since Cather carefully attempted to conceal the
 events and people that influenced her novels. Charles Johanningsmeier 
has made one of the most thorough attempts at unraveling the 
connections, tracing the novel’s influences to Cather’s history with the
 McClure family.<ref target="n9" rend="sup">9</ref> In this sense, our work appears to support Cather 
studies by backing up scholarly claims about autobiographical influence 
with quantitative data. We believe that examining the relative 
similarity or difference between the ‘voice’ of Cather’s letters and 
fiction is relevant because of the claims she made. Based on comments 
made in some letters, it appears that she perceived differences in her 
writing that surpass the conventions of genre. If we assume that in 
writing about deeply personal issues, an author is likely to lapse into a
 more personal style, our findings seem to support the claim that <hi rend="italic">My Mortal Enemy</hi>
 was highly influenced by Cather’s personal life. This raises an 
interesting question: does the use of autobiographical details in 
Cather’s fiction indicate an unconscious use of a more personal style of
 writing?  </p>
        
        <head>4. Future Work</head>
        <p>In the future, we intend to deepen and expand 
the traits that define the personal voice signal we are deriving from 
Cather’s correspondences. Sentence length, structure, and the choice of 
infrequently appearing vocabulary are all elements of a writer’s unique 
voice. Our research team will be investigating the ways in which these 
characteristics impact the relationship between Cather’s private letters
 and her published works. </p>
        <p>It is 
also our hope that the research we have begun will lead towards further 
studies on the relationship between<hi rend="italic"> My Mortal Enemy</hi> and Cather’s 
letters. In addition, since scholars recognize the main character from 
<hi rend="italic">My Mortal Enemy</hi>, Nellie, as modeled after Cather, future research might 
begin to look specifically at the ways in which Cather’s personal voice 
is associated with specific characters in her novels. This question 
might again return to issues of gender; if it becomes clear that certain
 characters within Cather’s work speak in a way similar to Cather’s 
personal voice, the next question should revolve around what these 
characters have in common.  </p>
        
        
        
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="References">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>1. <hi rend="bold">Cather, Willa.</hi> (20139 <hi rend="italic">To Mr. Miller.</hi> The Selected Letters of Willa Cather. Ed. Andrew Jewell and Janis Stout. New York: Alfred A. Knopf. 362.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>2. <hi rend="bold">A. Knopf</hi> (2013).  <hi rend="italic">The Selected Letters of Willa Cather</hi>. Jewell Andrew, and Janis Stout, eds. The Selected Letters of Willa Cather. New York: Alfred.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>3. <hi rend="bold">Grieve, J.</hi> (2007). <hi rend="italic">Quantitative authorship attribution: an evaluation of techniques</hi>. Literary and Linguistic Computing: Journal of the Association for Literary and Linguistic Computing, 22(3): 251–70.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>4. <hi rend="bold">Burrows, J.</hi> (2002). <hi rend="italic">‘Delta’: a measure of stylistic difference and a guide to likely authorship.</hi> Literary and Linguistic Computing: Journal of the Association for Literary and Linguistic Computing, 17(3): 267–87.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>5. <hi rend="bold">Jockers, Matthew L., Daniela M. Witten, and Craig S. Criddle</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Reassessing Authorship of the Book of Mormon Using Delta and Nearest Shrunken Centroid Classification.</hi> Literary and Linguistic Computing, 23.4 (2008): 465-492.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>6. <hi rend="bold">Ray Siemens, John Unsworth</hi> (2004). <hi rend="italic">A Companion to Digital Humanities</hi>, ed. Susan Schreibman. Oxford: Blackwell.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>7. <hi rend="bold">Cather, Willa</hi> (1926). <hi rend="italic">My Mortal Enemy</hi>. New York: Alfred A. Knopf.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>8. <hi rend="bold">Cather, Willa.</hi> (1922) <hi rend="italic">The Novel Demeuble.</hi> The New Republic, 30.1: 5-6.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>9. <hi rend="bold">Johanningsmeier, Charles.</hi> (2003) <hi rend="italic">Unmasking Willa Cather’s ‘My Mortal Enemy.’</hi> Cather Studies, Volume 5: Willa Cather’s Ecological Imagination. n. pag. Web.
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
