<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:x="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:exsl="http://exslt.org/common" xml:id="Paper-924">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Seeing the Trees &amp; Understanding the Forest</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Montague</surname>, <forename>John Joseph </forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>University of Alberta, Canada</affiliation>
          <email>jmontagu@ualberta.ca </email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Rockwell</surname>, <forename>Geoffrey</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>University of Alberta, Canada</affiliation>
          <email></email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Ruecker</surname>, <forename>Stan</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>IIT - Institute of Design, USA</affiliation>
          <email></email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Sinclair</surname>, <forename>Stéfan</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>McGill University, Canada </affiliation>
          <email></email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Brown</surname>, <forename>Susan</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>University of Alberta, Canada</affiliation>
          <email></email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Chartier</surname>, <forename>Ryan</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>University of Alberta, Canada</affiliation>
          <email></email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Frizzera</surname>, <forename>Luciano</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>University of Alberta, Canada</affiliation>
          <email></email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Simpson</surname>, <forename>John</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>University of Alberta, Canada</affiliation>
          <email></email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
        <publisher>EPFL, Switzerland</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>EPFL Digital Humanities Laboratory</name>
          <address>
            <addrLine>GC D2 386</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Station 18</addrLine>
            <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
            <addrLine>frederic.kaplan@epfl.ch</addrLine>
          </address>
        </distributor>
        <pubPlace>Lausanne, Switzerland</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>EPFL</addrLine>
          <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="abstract">Big data analytics and computer-supported visualization offer ways to read collections as our cognitive abilities are stretched to their limit with the sheer volume of data available. It is important to question if the visual models emerging can better be designed to suit humanities exploration. In this paper we propose to examine visualization for text mining by surveying commonly used graphical representations, identifying the visualizations that humanists find most useful, scaling these so they can be used interactively to explore large data sets, and producing prototypes to verify our findings. The goal is visualizations that help researchers make sense of big data; visualizations that let us explore the forest, not just the trees so that we can draw accurate and appropriate inferences from the data.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
        <p>
          <date when="20140709"/>
          <time when="13:45:00"/>
        </p>
		<p n="session">3</p>
		<p n="room">414 - Amphimax</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
          <term>Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
          <term>Long Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
          <term>visualization</term>
          <term>interface</term>
          <term>design</term>
          <term>text-analysis</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
          <term>corpora and corpus activities</term>
          <term>interface and user experience design</term>
          <term>text analysis</term>
          <term>content analysis</term>
          <term>visualisation</term>
          <term>networks</term>
          <term>relationships</term>
          <term>graphs</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="paper">
    <front>

      <div>
        <p></p>

      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p>
          <hi rend="italic">“Humanists have always been explorers. They sail not on seas
of water but on seas of color, sound, and, most especially, words.” — John B.
Smith, 1984</hi>
        </p>
        <p>Why is big
data such a big deal? Modern digital communications are producing and recording
data at a feverish rate, with 90% of the world’s recorded data, most of it
unstructured, having been produced in just the last two years (Dragland,
2013). In addition, more
traditional texts are being digitized all the time, and Crane (2006) tells us
that while the largest academic digital libraries now hold tens of thousands of
books, a completed Google Library will likely have more than <hi rend="italic">ten million</hi>. To further Smith’s analogy,
we are adrift in a sea of data, and we
are at risk of floundering.</p>
        <p>

 Front page news events like Edward Snowden’s May 2013 revelations
disclosing the secret NSA (America’s National Security Agency) collection and
analysis of massive amounts of ostensibly private data both domestically and
internationally, are making big data analytics part of the public lexicon.  Major corporations, led by IBM with $1.3
billion in big data revenue in 2012, are scrambling to adopt practices that
will allow them to capitalize on the volume of information now being generated.
 Global big data related revenues in 2012
were $11.6 billion, and are projected to break $18 billion in 2013 (Kelly et
al.).</p>
        <p>While one might shudder
to think what the NSA will do with all that information, outside of the
world of politics and espionage, what can researchers and academics do with the
volume of information now, or at least soon to be at our disposal? Matthew Jockers asks, “How
do we mine them [texts] to find
something <hi rend="italic">we don’t</hi> already know?”
(University of Nebraska-Lincoln) To
utilize such massive corpora and avoid succumbing
to the dilemma of what McCormick et al (1987) refer
to as “information without interpretation” we need to find the most effective ways for
end-users to explore, visualize and interact with big data such that it is both
meaningful and understandable, if possible by both the trained and untrained
eye. </p>
        <p>Big data
analytics and computer-supported visualization offer ways to read collections
as our cognitive abilities are stretched to their limit with the sheer volume
of data available (Araya, 2003). However, as Franco Moretti has pointed out,
what we are reading when we use text mining methods and visualizations are
really models of the collections. (Moretti 2013, p. 157) It is important
therefore to survey the visual models emerging and question if they can better be
designed to suit humanities exploration. In this paper we therefore propose to
look at visualization for text mining in the following ways:</p>
        <list type="unordered">
          <item><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">Survey</hi></hi> text mining visualization in the
humanities. Who is using text mining and why? What kinds of visualizations do
they find compelling and why?</item>
          <item><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">Identify
and Combine</hi></hi> commonly
presented visualizations for modeling. What visual models could be used for the
exploration of large corpora? How could they be combined?  </item>
          <item><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">Model</hi></hi> interactive prototypes of different
combinations of visualizations for exploration. </item>
        </list>
        <p><hi rend="bold">Surveying: </hi>In a poster at DH 2013 we presented a
framework of text mining tools that are useful in the humanities. Now we will
survey the variety of visualizations used to present mining results. We will begin
with early discussions of visualization like Smith’s “Computer Criticism” (<hi rend="italic">Style</hi> 1978, p. 326), where he notes with
agreement Paul de Man’s observation that as late as 1973 there had been no evolution
beyond the close reading “techniques of description and interpretation” being
used by literary critics since the 1930s or 40s, and suggests “pictorial
representation” as one of the potential uses of computer aided text analysis. Brunet
in a 1989 article talks about exploiting large corpora and provides a number of
examples of visualizations. Our survey will examine advances in practice and
understanding in the intervening thirty plus years, leading to contemporary works
like Franco Moretti’s <hi rend="italic">Graphs, Maps, and
Trees</hi>, which, as the title suggests, introduces visual models for literary
exploration.</p>
        <p>Our survey pays particular attention to recent text mining
projects and tools including “The Proceedings of the Old Bailey”<hi rend="sup"/>, David
L. Hoover’s work with cluster analyses at NYU using “MiniTab”<hi rend="sup"/>, Matt
Jockers’ topic modeling work in “Macroanalysis”<hi rend="sup"/>, the University of
Waikato’s “WEKA”<hi rend="sup"/>, the open-source visualization tool “Gephi”<hi rend="sup"/>,
the UMass machine learning tool “MALLET”<hi rend="sup"/>, the research tools for
textual study reviewed on “TAPoR”<hi rend="sup"/>as well as some of our own INKE
related projects such as “Dynamic Table of Contents”<hi rend="sup"/>, “CiteLens”<hi rend="sup"/>,
“TextTiles”<hi rend="sup"/> and “dialR”<hi rend="sup"/>. </p>
        <p><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">Identifying and
Combining</hi>: </hi>While we recognize that output will assume a variety of formats including
for instance heat maps, topographic plots or scatter plots, our survey suggests
that text-mining projects commonly use five principal types of visualization:

</p>
        <list type="unordered">
          <item>1. <hi rend="italic">Dendrograms</hi>,
showing data clustering within sets</item>
          <item>2. <hi rend="italic">Histograms</hi>,
showing change over time</item>
          <item>3. <hi rend="italic">Network</hi><hi rend="italic">diagrams</hi>, showing how entities are connected within a network</item>
          <item>4. <hi rend="italic">Word</hi><hi rend="italic">clouds</hi>, representing topics of words</item>
          <item>5. <hi rend="italic">Scatter</hi><hi rend="italic">plots</hi>, showing words or parts in an abstract space</item>
        </list>
        <p>

 Visualizations that are presented in print are typically
Spartan, focusing the attention on the results through careful design. All
affordances are removed. The same types of visualizations automatically
generated from large data sets, however, tend to be too dense to be useful and
have to include affordances if meant to be interactive. Simple representative
visualizations, like histograms for instance, are insufficient to display
complex interrelationships. Dendrograms, especially if you are working with
massive data sets, quickly become an illegible mass of inter-connectivity. Word
clouds are good at showing the relative frequency of words in a text or topic,
but not at comparing one text or topic to another. Network diagrams produce some
beautiful results, but suffer from the same difficulties as dendrograms; large
data sets quickly lead to illegibility.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="italic">“By
visualizing information, we turn it into a landscape that you can explore with
your eyes, a sort of information map. And when you’re lost in information, an
information map is kind of useful.” — David McCandless, 2010</hi>
        </p>
        <p><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">Modeling</hi>: </hi>Our
research now is looking at ways to increase the exploratory power of
visualization of large data sets. Used in combination, visualizations can
provide otherwise elusive insight and clarity. They can also provide
affordances for each other – a histogram can be used to explore a dendrogram. We
have developed interactive prototypes using combinations of visualizations, and
focusing on not simply allowing, but even <hi rend="italic">encouraging</hi>
the user to truly explore the (big) data, “function[ing] almost instinctively”,
as McCullough (1996) stated, “to serve the process of development”. The more we
can encourage users to explore and play
with the data, the more likely they are to develop useful insights.</p>

        <figure>
          <graphic url="DH2014_548_640-1"/>
          <p>Fig. 1: Combination of a modified dendrogram showing clustering, and a diachronic timeline of 500 philosophy papers.</p>
        </figure>
        <p>Figure 1 shows a prototype of a combination of dendrogram
and histogram that we developed to visualize the clustering of 500 papers
published between 1966 and 2004. The prototype is a combination of a modified
dendrogram showing the clusters, and a diachronic visualization displaying the subjects
over time. The displayed data is intuitively explorable, and the modified dendrogram
is designed to encourage exploration. We developed the R code to prepare the
data for interactivity. In Voyant we have developed skins that combine scatter
plots and histograms, word clouds and histograms, and network diagrams with
other tools. Again, the tools are open for others to recombine.</p>
        <p>To conclude,
surveying commonly used graphical representations allowed us to identify
commonly used visualizations that humanists find useful. To scale these so that
they can be used interactively to explore large data sets we have prototyped
combinations, where one visualization can be used to explore another and vice
versa. The goal is visualizations that help researchers make sense of big data;
visualizations that let us explore the forest, not just the trees so that we
can draw accurate and appropriate inferences from the data. </p>



      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="References">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="italic">The Proceedings of the Old Bailey</hi> - http://www.oldbaileyonline.org/</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="italic">Cluster Analysis, Principal Components
            Analysis (PCA), and T-testing in Minitab</hi> - https://files.nyu.edu/dh3/public/ClusterAnalysis-PCA-T-testingInMinitab.html</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Jockers, M</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Macroanalysis</hi>.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="italic">Weka 3: Data Mining Software in Java</hi>
            - http://www.cs.waikato.ac.nz/ml/weka/</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="italic">Gephi - The Open Graph Viz Platform</hi> -
            https://gephi.org/</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="italic">Mallet - MAchine Learning for LanguagE Toolkit</hi> - http://mallet.cs.umass.edu/</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="italic">TAPoR - Research Tools for Textual Study</hi> - http://tapor.ca/</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="italic">Dynamic Table of Contents</hi> - http://www.ualbertaprojects.info/dyntoc/dyntoc_v3_5/Main.html</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="italic">CiteLens</hi> - http://labs.fluxo.art.br/CiteLens/</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="italic">TextTiles</hi> - http://dev.giacometti.me/textTiles/trunk/</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="italic">dialR</hi> - http://research.artsrn.ualberta.ca/~dialr/drMain.html</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">Allison, S., Heuser, R., Jockers, M., Moretti, F. and Witmore, M</hi>. </hi>(2012
            ). <hi rend="italic">Quantitative Formalism: An Experiment.</hi>Pamphlet 1, Stanford Literary Lab.
            Print.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">Araya,
            A. A.</hi></hi> (2003).
            <hi rend="italic">The Hidden Side of Visualization</hi>. Techné: Research in Philosophy and
            Technology; Vol 7, No 2,
            Print.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">Brunet, É</hi>.</hi> (1989). <hi rend="italic">L'Exploitation des Grands
            Corpus: Le Bestiare de la Littérature Française</hi>. Literary and Linguistic
            Computing, Vol. 4, No. 2,
            p. 121-134. Print.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Crane, G. (</hi>2006). <hi rend="italic">What Do You Do with a Million Books? D-Lib MagazineVol.</hi> 12 No. 3, Print.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">Dragland, Å.</hi></hi> (2013).<hi rend="italic"> Big Data, for better or worse</hi>. SINTEF.no. 22 May 2013. Web. 27 Oct.
            2013.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">Jockers, M.</hi></hi> (2013). <hi rend="italic">Macroanalysis : digital methods and literary history - University of Illinois Press,</hi> Urbana,
            Chicago &amp; Springfield.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">Kelly, J., Floyer, D., Vellante, D. and Miniman, S.</hi></hi>
            (2013). <hi rend="italic">Big Data Vendor Revenue and Market Forecast 2012-2017</hi>. Wikibon.org. 19 Feb. 2013. Web. 28 Oct.
            2013.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">McCandless, D</hi>.</hi> (2010).<hi rend="italic"> David McCandless: The beauty of data
            visualization</hi>. TED Talks. Web Video.  25 Oct.  2013. </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">McCormick, Bruce H., DeFanti, Thomas A., and
            Brown, Maxine D.</hi></hi> (1987). <hi rend="italic">Visualization
              in Scientific Computing</hi>. Computer
            Graphics 21, 6 (November). New York: Association for Computing Machinery,
            SIGGRAPH, Print.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">McCullough, M</hi>.</hi> (1996).  <hi rend="italic">Abstracting Craft: The Practiced
            Digital Hand</hi>; Cambridge, MIT Press, Print.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">Moretti, F.</hi></hi> (2013).<hi rend="italic"> The End of the Beginning: A
            Reply to Christopher Prendergast.</hi>Distant Reading. London: Verso, p.
            137-158. Print.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">Risen, J. and Poitras, L.</hi></hi> (2013). <hi rend="italic">NSA Gathers Data on Social
            Connections of U.S.</hi> Citizens, New York
            Times, 28 Sep. 2013. Web, 27 Oct, 2013.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">Simpson J.; Rockwell, G.; Sinclair, S.; Uszkalo, K.; Brown, S.; Dyrbye,
            A.; Chartier, R..</hi></hi> (2013). <hi rend="italic">Framework for Testing Text Analysis and Mining
              Tools.</hi>Poster presented at the Digital
            Humanities 2013 conference at the University of
            Nebraska-Lincoln. Lincoln, Nebraska, USA.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">Smith, J.</hi></hi> (1978). <hi rend="italic">Computer Criticism.</hi>Style. Vol XII, No 4. Print.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">Smith, J.</hi></hi> (1984). <hi rend="italic">A New Environment For
            Literary Analysis.</hi>Perspectives in
            Computing 4. 2/3, (1984): 20-31. Print.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">Tufte, Edward.</hi></hi> (1983). <hi rend="italic">The Visual Display of Quantitative
            Information</hi>; Cheshire, CT: Graphics Press, Print.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="bold">University of
            Nebraska-Lincoln.</hi></hi> (2012).
            <hi rend="italic">By text-mining the classics, UNL prof unearths new literary insights. </hi>UNL News Blog. 23 Aug. 2012.
            Web. 27 Oct. 2013.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
