<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:x="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:exsl="http://exslt.org/common" xml:id="Paper-373">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Trading Consequences: A Case Study of Combining Text Mining &amp; Visualisation to Facilitate Document Exploration</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Hinrichs</surname>, <forename>Uta</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>SACHI, University of St. Andrews</affiliation>
          <email>uh3@st-andrews.ac.uk</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Alex</surname>, <forename>Beatrice</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>ILCC, School of Informatics, University of Edinburgh</affiliation>
          <email>balex@staffmail.ed.ac.uk</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Clifford</surname>, <forename>Jim</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Department of History, University of Saskatchewan</affiliation>
          <email>jim.clifford@usask.ca</email>
        </author>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Quigley</surname>, <forename>Aaron</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>SACHI, University of St. Andrews </affiliation>
          <email>aquigley@st-andrews.ac.uk</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
        <publisher>EPFL, Switzerland</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>EPFL Digital Humanities Laboratory</name>
          <address>
            <addrLine>GC D2 386</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Station 18</addrLine>
            <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
            <addrLine>frederic.kaplan@epfl.ch</addrLine>
          </address>
        </distributor>
        <pubPlace>Lausanne, Switzerland</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>EPFL</addrLine>
          <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="abstract">Trading Consequences is an interdisciplinary research project between historians, computational linguists and visualization specialists. We use text mining and visualisations to explore the growth of the global commodity trade in the nineteenth century. Feedback from a group of environmental historians during a workshop provided essential information to adapt advanced text mining and visualisation techniques to historical research. Expert feedback is an essential tool for effective interdisciplinary research in the digital humanities.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
        <p>
          <date when="20140709"/>
          <time when="13:45:00"/>
        </p>
		<p n="session">3</p>
		<p n="room">414 - Amphimax</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
          <term>Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
          <term>Long Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
          <term>information visualisation</term>
          <term>user feedback</term>
          <term>text mining</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
          <term>digital history</term>
          <term>information visualisation</term>
          <term>text mining</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="paper">
    <front>

      <div>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>1. Introduction</head>
        <p>This paper reports on interdisciplinary work
carried out as part of Trading Consequences <ref target="n1" rend="sup">1</ref>, a two-year Digging into Data project <ref target="n2" rend="sup">2</ref>.  The focus of the project is to mine large
quantities of historical documents, extract information on commodity trading in
the nineteenth century British World and visualise the mined output in dynamic
and interesting ways, thereby bringing archives alive in ways that authors of
original documents would have never imagined. The Trading Consequences
interface is aimed at historians studying commodities and their environmental
consequences. Their studies have tended to focus on a manageable number of commodities
 (e.g. William Cronon's research on beef, lumber and wheat <ref target="n3" rend="sup">3</ref>).  The Trading Consequences Project aims at identifying
global trends in commodity trading for many different natural resources, raw
materials or lightly processed goods by correlating information extracted for
one commodity with that of others or showing all commodities relevant to
particular locations and dates.</p>
        <p>In this paper, we first present an overview of this collaborative project
that involved environmental historians,
text mining, database experts and visualization researchers. We then report
on lessons learned from a workshop where we collected feedback from historians
and geographers after they interacted with the interface prototype in a series
of exercises. This feedback informed the further adaptation of the underlying
technologies for historical research.</p>
        <p>

 </p>
        <head>2. Trading Consequences</head>
        <p>The Trading Consequences system encompasses
three main technical components: a text mining system, a database and a
web-based user interface with dynamic visualisations (Fig. 1). The data
analysed using this system is comprised up of several nineteenth century
British and Canadian text collections <ref target="n4" rend="sup">4</ref>. These sources amount to over 11 million pages
and over 7 billion analysed word tokens.</p>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="373_1"/>
          <p>Fig. 1: System architecture.</p>
        </figure>
        <head>2.1 Text Mining</head>
        <p>The text mining (TM) tools are developed by the Language Technology Group at the University of Edinburgh. We adapted an existing pipeline built on LT-XML2 and LT-TTT2 to process historic text <ref target="n5" rend="sup">5</ref>. The TM component is made up of a series of linguistic processing steps which build up the linguistic properties of the language in a given text.  A pre-processing stage includes tokenisation, sentence-splitting, part-of-speech tagging and lemmatisation to determine words and sentences, identify their syntax and compute canonical forms of word tokens. All of this information aids down-stream TM processes.  The next steps are named entity recognition and grounding. This means that mentions of locations, commodities and dates are automatically identified in the text and grounded to unique identifiers in existing knowledge databases.  We ground location mentions to GeoNames identifiers and their corresponding latitude/longitude values <ref target="n6" rend="sup">6</ref>. We use an adapted version of the Edinburgh Geoparser for this geo-referencing process <ref target="n7" rend="sup">7</ref>.  Commodity mentions are grounded to DBpedia <ref target="n8" rend="sup">8</ref> concepts in a semi-automatically constructed commodity lexicon developed in this project <ref target="n9" rend="sup">9</ref>. Finally, date mentions are grounded to year, month and date attributes.  The last TM step identifies relations between commodity, date and location mentions to identify the relevance of commodities in space and time. The extracted and enriched TM output is stored in a relational PostGreSQL database set up and hosted by EDINA <ref target="n10" rend="sup">10</ref> for subsequent querying and visualisation.</p>
        <head>2.2 Interactive Visualisations</head>

        <p>The strength of information visualisation is to make abstract concepts and relations within data visible and explorable <ref target="n11" rend="sup">11</ref>. In the context of Trading Consequences we aim at providing visualisations of the mined data to: </p>
        <list type="ordered">
          <item>- enable open-ended explorations of the document corpus beyond target search <ref target="n12" rend="sup">12</ref>, i.e., supporting visual querying along spatial, temporal, and conceptual dimensions, and </item>
          <item>- highlighting trends within a range of document data, for instance, relations between different commodity types.</item>
        </list>
        <p>While the first approach facilitates the discovery of related documents in ways that common text-based search interfaces cannot, the second approach can lead to new insights or research questions based on collection sizes that exceed possibilities of traditional research methods in the humanities. Our visualizations are web-based to make them easily accessible worldwide (see [1]). The implementation is based on JavaScript (D3.js and jQuery) and PHP.</p>
        <p>In this paper we briefly describe the Trading Consequences visualisation tool and how it was experienced by environmental historians as part of a workshop. Inspired by <ref target="n13" rend="sup">13</ref>, our visualisation consists of three interlinked representations (Fig. 2): a map showing the geographic context in which commodities were mentioned, a vertical tag cloud showing the 50 most frequently mentioned commodities, and a bar chart representing the temporal distribution of documents within the collection. A ranked document list provides direct access to the relevant articles.</p>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="373_2"/>
          <p>Fig. 2: Interlinked visualisations provide an overview of the document collection.</p>
        </figure>
        <p>Interaction with one visualisation acts as a filtering mechanism and adjusts the data shown in the other visualisations. For instance, zooming into the map adjusts the tag cloud to only include commodities mentioned in relation to visible locations; the bar chart only shows documents that include these commodity/location mentions (Fig. 3). Particular time frames can be selected to further filter the document corpus; the other visualisations are updated accordingly (Fig. 4).</p>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="373_3"/>
          <p>Fig. 3: Specifying the location adjusts the other visualisations.</p>
        </figure>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="373_4"/>
          <p>Fig. 4: Specifying a time frame adjusts commodities and locations shown in the tag cloud and map.</p>
        </figure>
        <p>Lastly, historians can specify commodities of interest,
either by textual query or by selecting commodities from the tag cloud. All
visualisations adjust, with the tag cloud showing commodities related to the
selected ones. An additional line chart presents the frequency of mentions of
selected commodities across time (Fig. 5).</p>
        <figure>
          <graphic url="373_5"/>
          <p>Fig. 5: Specifying particular commodities of interest further adjusts the visualisation.</p>
        </figure>

        <head>
          <hi rend="bold">3. Feedback from Historians</hi>
        </head>

        <p>To gain expert feedback on our approach of
combining text mining with visualisations to facilitate research in environmental
history, we conducted a half-day workshop where we introduced our visualisation
prototype to historians. The workshop was held at the Canadian History &amp;
Environment Summer School 2013 with over 20 environmental historians
participating <ref target="n14" rend="sup">14</ref>. At the workshop, we asked historians to
explore the visualisation tool in small groups (Fig. 6). To promote engagement
with the different visualisations and to fuel discussions, the explorations
were guided by a number of open-ended tasks, such as querying for commodities
of interest or focusing on a geographic area. 


</p>
        <p>Some historians immediately started to focus on
the Vancouver Island area where the workshop took place. Others experimented
with commodities and locations related to their own research. In general, these
first exploration periods were about verifying familiar facts to assess the
capabilities of the visualisation and the trustworthiness of the underlying
data. The historians quickly understood the general purpose and high-level
functionality of the visualisations and were able to start their explorations
immediately. There was some confusion, however, about lower level details. For
instance, the meaning of the size and number of clusters in the map was unclear
(e.g. do they represent number of documents, or number
of commodity mentions?). Observing changes in the visualisations while adjusting parameters
helped, but our observations highlight that clear labelling and tooltips are crucial
for visualisations in the context of digital humanities, not only because these
are a novel addition to traditional research methodologies, but also because
they can be easily misinterpreted. The meaning of visual representations needs
to be clear in order to make visualisations a valid research tool.</p>

        <figure>
          <graphic url="373_6"/>
          <p>Fig. 6: User workshop at CHESS 2013.</p>
        </figure>
        <p>Workshop participants found the meta-level
overviews of the visualisations valuable as these can aggregate information
about the document corpus beyond human capacity. In the short time of the
workshop, historians made (sometimes surprising) discoveries that sparked their
interest to conduct further research. While it is unclear if these discoveries withstand
more detailed investigation (there is still some noise in the data), this shows
that visualisation has the potential to support exploration and insight in the
context of history research.</p>
        <p>A large part of the discussions focussed on
what kind of insights can be gathered from the visualisations. Some historians
pointed out that the visualisations represent the rhetoric around commodity trading in the 19th century: they
show where and when a dialogue about particular commodities took place,
rather than providing information about the occurrence of commodities in
certain locations. This raises the question of how we can clarify what kind of
data the visualisations are based on to avoid misinterpretation.</p>
        <head>4. Conclusion</head>
        <p>In general, we received positive feedback
about our approach of combining text mining and visualisation to help research
processes in environmental history. Historians saw the largest potential in the
amounts of data that can be considered for research but also in the open-ended
character of the explorations that the visualisations support in contrast to
common database search interfaces. Other types of visualisations were suggested
to help analyse and discover relations and patterns in the data, something that
we are currently developing. </p>
        <p>Our future research will explore how our
approach integrates into research processes in environmental history and how it can produce
profound outcomes. This will involve controlled experiments including directed and open-ended tasks. 
We will also conduct long-term studies to evaluate the discoveries
and limitations that historians encounter when using our tools. The
wide-ranging feedback from the workshop was crucial in helping the
computer science team members understand priorities and research methodologies
of environmental historians. Expert feedback is an important component of
interdisciplinary research in digital humanities.</p>

      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="References">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>1. Trading Consequences: <ref type="url" target="http://tradingconsequences.blogs.edina.ac.uk/">tradingconsequences.blogs.edina.ac.uk/</ref>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>2. Digging Into Data: <ref type="url" target="http://www.diggingintodata.org/">www.diggingintodata.org/</ref>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>3. <hi rend="bold">William Cronon</hi> (1992). <hi rend="italic">Nature’s Metropolis: Chicago and the Great West</hi>. W.W. Norton, New York.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>4. Data collections: <ref type="url" target="http://tradingconsequences.blogs.edina.ac.uk/about/the-corpus/">tradingconsequences.blogs.edina.ac.uk/about/the-corpus/</ref>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>5. LT-XML2: <ref type="url" target="http://www.ltg.ed.ac.uk/software/ltxml2">www.ltg.ed.ac.uk/software/ltxml2</ref>; LT-TTT2: <ref type="url" target="http://www.ltg.ed.ac.uk/software/lt-ttt2">www.ltg.ed.ac.uk/software/lt-ttt2</ref>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>6. GeoNames: <ref type="url" target="http://www.geonames.org/">www.geonames.org/</ref>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>7. <hi rend="bold">Claire Grover, Richard Tobin, Kate Byrne, Matthew Woollard, James Reid, Stuart Dunn, and Julian Ball</hi> (2010). <hi rend="italic">Use of the Edinburgh Geoparser for georeferencing digitised historical collections</hi>. Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society A.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>8. DBpedia: <ref type="url" target="http://dbpedia.org.">dbpedia.org.</ref> We accessed DBpedia via the SPARQL endpoint (<ref type="url" target="http://dbpedia.org/OnlineAccess)">dbpedia.org/OnlineAccess)</ref>, most recently on 16/12/2013, corresponding to DBpedia version 3.9.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>9. <hi rend="bold">Ewan Klein, Beatrice Alex and Jim Clifford </hi>(2014). <hi rend="italic">Bootstrapping a historical commodities lexicon with SKOS and DBpedia</hi>, In: Proceedings of the LaTeCH 2014 workshop at EACL 2014.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>10. EDINA: Jisc-designated centre for digital expertise &amp; online service delivery; <ref type="url" target="http://edina.ac.uk/">edina.ac.uk/</ref>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>11. <hi rend="bold">Stuart K. Card, Jock D. Mackinlay, Ben Shneiderman</hi> (eds.) (1999). <hi rend="italic">Readings in Information Visualization: Using Vision to Think</hi>. Morgan Kaufmann Publishers, Chapter 1, pp. 1-34.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>12. <hi rend="bold">Gary Marchionini</hi> (2006). <hi rend="italic">Exploratory search: From finding to understanding</hi>. Communications of the ACM 49, 4, 41–46.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>13. <hi rend="bold">Marian Dörk, Sheelagh Carpendale, Christopher Collins and Carey Williamson </hi>(2008). <hi rend="italic">VisGets: Coordinated Visualizations for Web-based Information Exploration and Discovery</hi>. IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics, 14(6), pp. 1205-1212.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>14. CHESS 2013: <ref type="url" target="http://70.32.75.219/2013/04/12/cfp-canadian-history-and-environment-summer-school-2013-vancouver-island/">70.32.75.219/2013/04/12/cfp-canadian-history-and-environment-summer-school-2013-vancouver-island/</ref>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
