<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:x="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:exsl="http://exslt.org/common" xml:id="Paper-374">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>An XML annotation schema for speech, thought and writing representation</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Brunner</surname>, <forename>Annelen</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>Institut für deutsche Sprache</affiliation>
          <email>annelen_brunner@gmx.de</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
        <publisher>EPFL, Switzerland</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>EPFL Digital Humanities Laboratory</name>
          <address>
            <addrLine>GC D2 386</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Station 18</addrLine>
            <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
            <addrLine>frederic.kaplan@epfl.ch</addrLine>
          </address>
        </distributor>
        <pubPlace>Lausanne, Switzerland</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>EPFL</addrLine>
          <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="abstract">This contribution presents an XML schema for annotating a high level narratological category: speech, thought and writing representation (ST&amp;WR). It focusses on two aspects: Firstly, the original schema is presented as an example for the challenge to encode a narrative feature in a structured and flexible way and secondly, ways of adapting this schema to TEI are considered, in order to make it usable for other, TEI-based projects.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
        <p>
          <date when="20140709"/>
          <time when="11:00:00"/>
        </p>
		<p n="session">2</p>
		<p n="room">321 - Amphipôle</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
          <term>Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
          <term>Long Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
          <term>TEI</term>
          <term>speech/thought/writing representation</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
          <term>literary studies</term>
          <term>text analysis</term>
          <term>xml</term>
          <term>german studies</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="paper">
    <front>
      
      <div>
        <p></p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        
        <p>This contribution presents an
XML schema for annotating a high level narratological category: 
speech, thought and writing representation (ST&amp;WR). It focusses
on two aspects: Firstly, the original schema is presented as an
example for the challenge to encode a narrative feature in a
structured and flexible way and secondly, ways of adapting this schema
to TEI are considered, in order to make it usable for other, TEI-based projects.</p>
        <head>The phenomenon ST&amp;WR</head>
  
        <p>ST&amp;WR
refers to the way the voice of a character is embedded in the
narrator's text and is a feature that is present in most works of
fiction. It has been widely studied in narratology, as it contributes
to the construction of a fictional character, the narrator-character
relationship and fictional world-building in general. Though ST&amp;WR
is partly defined by formal features like punctuation, verb mode, and
sentence structure, narrative function is what is of interest in
literary studies (cf. <ref target="n1" rend="sup">1</ref> for an overview). The
challenge is to develop an annotation schema which is sufficiently structured
to allow consistent annotation (especially with multiple
annotators) and still captures nuances that are relevant for literary
scholars.</p>
       
        <p>The
schema presented here – called ST&amp;WR schema (ST&amp;WR-S) –
ties into literature studies as it uses categories agreed upon by most scholars and is similar to
categorial systems proposed by narratologists Genette and Leech/Short
(cf. <ref target="n2" rend="sup">2</ref>, <ref target="n3" rend="sup">3</ref>). The main influence was a
project of Semino and Short, who annotated a corpus of English
fictional, newspaper and (auto)biographical texts for ST&amp;WR with
an SGML-conformant schema (cf. <ref target="n4" rend="sup">4</ref>).</p>
        <head>

ST&amp;WR schema</head>
        <p>ST&amp;WR-S was
developed for manual annotation of a corpus of 13 German narrative
texts written between 1786 and 1917 (about 57 000 tokens). This
corpus was then used as a reference for the development and
evaluation of automatic methods for ST&amp;WR recognition (cf.
<ref target="n5" rend="sup">5</ref>). The purpose of ST&amp;WR-S was twofold: It allows for a
very fine-grained classification of ST&amp;WR instances which is
helpful in order to study the phenomenon and to do statistical
studies on manually annotated data, like in Semino/Short's project.
On the other hand it was designed to be modular and easily simplified
to accommodate for the rougher classifications of automatic
recognizers. Experiences during
corpus annotation strongly influenced the design of the annotation schema.</p>
        <p>ST&amp;WR-S
has three levels of specificity: Main categories, attributes and in
some cases different values for further specifications of certain attributes. These are modelled as XML tags with attributes and values. </p>
        <p>The manual
annotation was done in the GATE framework for natural language
processing (cf. <ref target="n6" rend="sup">6</ref>, http://gate.ac.uk). ST&amp;WR-S is
specified in XML schema files used by the plugin Schema_Annotation_Editor. Primarily, it is designed for inline XML, but GATE internally manages annotations as nodes and can convert them to a standoff XML format.
</p>
        <p>The main categories can be described with two axes: One axis represents the
medium – speech, thought or written text
(e.g. a quote from a character's letter). The second axis represents
the four most common techniques of ST&amp;WR: direct representation
("He said 'I am hungry.'"), free indirect
representation ("Well, where would he get something to eat now?"), indirect
representation ("He said that he was hungry."), and reported representation,
which can be a mere mentioning of a speech, thought or writing act
("They talked about lunch.").
This results in twelve main categories which are modelled as XML tags
(<hi rend="italic">direct_speech, </hi><hi rend="italic">direct_thought</hi>, etc.).
</p>
        <p>
However, such a set of categories
is necessarily rigid. When annotating a narrative phenomenon in
a real corpus you will find many instances which are not clear-cut
realisations of a predefined category. To deal with this fact, rather than just adding a
confidence marker to the annotation, attributes are used to classify
the type of deviation, so that the cases may be further studied and
contrasted. As all attributes are optional and can be added to any
main category, ST&amp;WR-S allows for different levels of detail very
easily. It is also possible to filter your annotation results afterwards by ignoring instances that carry a certain attribute.</p>
        <p>Structurally,
there is one numerical attribute (<hi rend="italic">level</hi>),
three attributes which are binary and just indicating whether the
feature is present or not <hi rend="italic">(</hi><hi rend="italic">narr, prag,
metaph</hi>), two with optional further
specification (<hi rend="italic">border, non-fact</hi>)
and one with mandatory further specification (<hi rend="italic">ambig</hi>).
All lists of attribute values are closed sets. Table 1 gives an
overview. 
</p>
        <table>
          <row>
            <cell role="label"> Attribute name</cell>
            <cell role="label"> Description</cell>
            <cell role="label">Values </cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell role="data"> <hi rend="italic">level</hi></cell>
            <cell role="data"> level of embedment</cell>
            <cell role="data"> numeric (default: 1)</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell role="data"> <hi rend="italic">ambig</hi></cell>
            <cell role="data"> ambiguity of the main category</cell>
            <cell role="data"> Name of an alternative main category</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell role="data"> <hi rend="italic">non-fact</hi></cell>
            <cell role="data"> non-factual (eg. negated or hypothetical ST&amp;WR) ("He did not admit that he loved her.") </cell>
            <cell role="data"> <hi rend="italic">neg, hyp, fut, ques, imp, plan, unspec</hi> (default: <hi rend="italic">unspec</hi>)</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell role="data"> <hi rend="italic">border</hi></cell>
            <cell role="data"> borderline case of ST&amp;WR("He knew that he had lost.")</cell>
            <cell role="data"> <hi rend="italic">percept, feel, state, unspec</hi>(default: <hi rend="italic">unspec</hi>)</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell role="data"> <hi rend="italic">narr</hi></cell>
            <cell role="data"> Ambiguity between ST&amp;WR and non-verbal action("She greeted her friends.")</cell>
            <cell role="data"> binary (dummy value: <hi rend="italic">yes</hi>)</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell role="data"> <hi rend="italic">prag</hi></cell>
            <cell role="data"> ST&amp;WR, but with non-representional intent (e.g. politeness("I suggest you leave now.")</cell>
            <cell role="data"> binary (dummy value: <hi rend="italic">yes</hi>)</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell role="data">
              <hi rend="italic"> metaph</hi>
            </cell>
            <cell role="data"> metaphorical use("His conscience told him to go.")</cell>
            <cell role="data"> binary (dummy value: <hi rend="italic">yes</hi>)</cell>
          </row>
        </table>
        <p>
Functionally,<hi rend="italic">level</hi> stands alone in the group as it
does not mark a non-prototypical instance but is rather a 'monitor
attribute'. It captures the level of embedment of a ST&amp;WR
instance, e.g. an instance of indirect thought that appears as part of an
instance of direct speech would be tagged as <hi rend="italic">level=”2”</hi>.
This marker can then be used to study the behaviour of such embedded
instances and compare their behaviour to non-embedded ones. 
</p>
        <p>
All other attributes deal
with instances that deviate from the prototypical idea of ST&amp;WR
in relation to the definition of the main categories. 
</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Ambig</hi>
and <hi rend="italic">narr</hi>
both mark ambiguity. While <hi rend="italic">ambig</hi>
indicates that there is uncertainty as to which main category should
be applied, <hi rend="italic">narr</hi>
signals that it is uncertain whether the instance is a case of ST&amp;WR
at all. 
</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Border</hi>
deals with uncertainty in regard to what is considered speech,
thought and writing respectively.
Especially thought representation is extremely tricky, as you have to
decide what constitutes a thought. For example, the sentence “He
knew he had lost.” would be marked as <hi rend="italic">&lt;</hi><hi rend="italic">indirect_thought
border=”state”&gt;</hi>, as “to know”
expresses a state of knowledge rather than a clear-cut thought.
<hi rend="italic">Border</hi> can
also be applied to speech representation, e.g. if it is unclear
whether there is a true verbalization like in the sentence “He
screamed bloody murder.”</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Non-fact</hi>
deals with instances where the ST&amp;WR is non-factual and thus not
a real 'representation' in the story world. Similarly, <hi rend="italic">prag</hi>
marks instances where ST&amp;WR forms are used for
non-representational purposes, especially politeness, and <hi rend="italic">metaph</hi>
represents metaphorical use of ST&amp;WR.
</p>
        <p>In addition to
that, the ST&amp;WR-S contains two special categories modelled as XML
tags. One is <hi rend="italic">frame</hi>, which
marks the framing clause of a direct representation which is not part
of the representation itself but still interesting in the context of
ST&amp;WR. The other is called <hi rend="italic">embedded</hi>.
It can
be used to mark embedded narratives which appear in direct
representation (usually direct speech), e.g. if a character tells a
story. Marking such cases with <hi rend="italic">embedded</hi>
essentially
shifts the whole annotation level into a new narrative frame and
gives it a different status than <hi rend="italic">direct_speech</hi>.
The use of <hi rend="italic">embedded</hi>
is optional and the tag can be easily transformed to <hi rend="italic">direct_speech</hi>
if this effect is not desired. 
</p>
        <head>Adaptation to TEI Guidelines</head>
        <p>
ST&amp;WR-S is
a valid XML schema but not compliant to TEI Guidelines. For
sustainability it would be desirable to adapt it, as this would allow
its usage in TEI-conformant documents without compromising their
validity. 
</p>
        <p>
However, such
an adaptation is not straightforward. The logical starting point is
<hi rend="italic">&lt;said&gt;</hi>,
a tag from the quotation context which is defined for passages
thought or spoken by real people or fictional characters (cf. <ref target="n7" rend="sup">7</ref>). Though
<hi rend="italic">&lt;said&gt;</hi>
is clearly intended to capture instances of ST&amp;WR, its scope is
narrower than the instances covered by ST&amp;WR-S. In its core form,
it only carries the attributes <hi rend="italic">aloud</hi>and
<hi rend="italic">direct</hi>, both
specified by truth values. <hi rend="italic">Aloud</hi>
is designed to distinguish between silent thought and passages spoken
aloud (speech), but does not accomodate writing representation.
<hi rend="italic">Direct</hi>
does not allow for any distinction between the ST&amp;WR categories free indirect,
indirect and reported. Of course, the rich attribute system of
ST&amp;WR-S does not have a predefined equivalent in TEI, either. </p>
        <p>Several possibilities are considered how to adapt ST&amp;WR-S while conserving its power as well as its
modularity as much as possible. Ideas include use of standoff markup, possibly
	via the <hi rend="italic">&lt;span&gt;</hi> tag, modelling of the complex
	categorizations via feature structures, referenced by the <hi rend="italic">@ana</hi>
	attribute, or extentions of exisiting
	TEI-tags (most likely <hi rend="italic">&lt;said&gt;</hi>).
 
</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="References">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>1. <hi rend="bold">McHale, B</hi> (2013). <hi rend="italic">Speech Representation</hi>, in: Hühn, Peter et al. (eds.): The living handbook of narratology, Hamburg: Hamburg University Press, 2013 URL: <ref type="url" target="http://www.lhn.uni-hamburg.de/article/speech-representation">www.lhn.uni-hamburg.de/article/speech-representation</ref> (last checked 17.10.2013).
          </bibl>
          <bibl>2. <hi rend="bold">Genette, G.</hi>(1980). <hi rend="italic">Narrative discourse</hi>. An Essay in Method, Oxford: Blackwell.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>3. <hi rend="bold">Leech, G. and Short, M.</hi> (2007). <hi rend="italic">Style in fiction</hi>. A Linguistic Introduction to English Fictional Prose 2. ed., London: Pearson Education Limited.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>4. <hi rend="bold">Semino, E. and Short, M.</hi> (2004). <hi rend="italic">Corpus stylistics</hi>. Speech, writing and thought presentation in a corpus of English writing, London/New York: Routledge.
          </bibl>
          <bibl>5. <hi rend="bold">Brunner, A</hi> (2013). <hi rend="italic">Automatic recognition of speech, thought, and writing representation in German narrative texts</hi>. Literary and Linguistic Computing 2013; doi: 10.1093/llc/fqt024
          </bibl>
          <bibl>6. <hi rend="bold">Cunningham, H. et al.</hi> (2011). <hi rend="italic">Text Processing with GATE (Version 6)</hi>: <ref type="url" target="http://www.tinyurl/gatebook">www.tinyurl/gatebook</ref> (last checked 01.11.2013).
          </bibl>
          <bibl>7. <hi rend="bold">Text Encoding Initiative</hi> (2013). <hi rend="italic">P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</hi>, URL: <ref type="url" target="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5/">www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5</ref> (last checked 31.10.2013)
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
