<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:x="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:exsl="http://exslt.org/common" xml:id="Paper-744">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>ClipNotes: Digital Annotation and Data­Mining for Film &amp; Television Analysis</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>deWaard</surname>, <forename>Andrew</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>University of California, Los Angeles, United States of America</affiliation>
          
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
        <publisher>EPFL, Switzerland</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>EPFL Digital Humanities Laboratory</name>
          <address>
            <addrLine>GC D2 386</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Station 18</addrLine>
            <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
            <addrLine>frederic.kaplan@epfl.ch</addrLine>
          </address>
        </distributor>
        <pubPlace>Lausanne, Switzerland</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>EPFL</addrLine>
          <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="abstract">This presentation will demonstrate a UCLA software project entitled ClipNotes, a collaborative, XML-based Windows/iPad app project that facilitates quick annotation, segmentation and presentation of film clips. The design of ClipNotes is deceptively simple: it allows users to mark up video files with metadata in easily-produced XML files that when connected to a video file, allow for precise, granular analysis that is easily disseminated and presented. All XML files are archived in a public database, which allows for widespread sharing of textual analysis and provides an invaluable teaching resource. Examples will be shown of traditional textual analysis amplified by software, as well as a demonstration of how ClipNotes can be integrated into the classroom, allowing students to contribute to an open-access database. ClipNotes demonstrates how software applications can be utilized to enact detailed analysis, archive and disseminate insights, and welcome students into the sphere of knowledge production.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
        <p>
          <date when="20140710"/>
          <time when="09:00:00"/>
        </p>
		<p n="session">4</p>
		<p n="room">415 - Amphimax</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
          <term>Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
          <term>Short Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
          <term>Audiovisual Analysis</term>
          <term>Digital Annotation</term>
          <term>Cultural Analytics</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
          <term>image processing</term>
          <term>audio</term>
          <term>video</term>
          <term>multimedia</term>
          <term>encoding - theory and practice</term>
          <term>film and cinema studies</term>
          <term>metadata</term>
          <term>software design and development</term>
          <term>text analysis</term>
          <term>xml</term>
          <term>content analysis</term>
          <term>bibliographic methods / textual studies</term>
          <term>media studies</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="paper">
    <front>
      
      <div>
        <p></p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p>In the age of Big Data and technology­assisted research, scholarship in the humanities is
developing innovative new approaches and methodologies, be they quantifiable and visual (Moretti,
2005), algorithmic (Ramsay, 2011), built upon ‘distant’ and ‘machine’ readings (Hayles, 2012) and
‘cultural analytics’ (Manovich, 2009), or of the many possibilities and techniques offered in the field of
Digital Humanities (Burdick et al, 2012). Film and television analysis, however, has been slow to adapt
digital data­driven research. This presentation will demonstrate a software project entitled ClipNotes, a
software application created by Dr. Stephen Mamber at UCLA along with a team of graduate students
that are helping to develop it. Examples will be shown of both traditional textual analysis amplified by the
software and my own research that quantifies product placement and brand integration in film and
television. </p>
        <p>Though cinema and media studies has rightfully continued on its course of splintering and
diversifying into a multitude of interdisciplinary amalgamations and sub­disciplines, close textual analysis
remains at the heart of what we do, particularly with regards to teaching. Technology has dramatically
increased our ability to deconstruct a film text, from VHS to DVD to digital interfaces which allow even
more minute control over image and sound. Creating clips and screengrabs is becoming easier and is an
increasingly common feature of lectures and presentations, but the method of visual analysis itself hasn’t
advanced very much, nor has the incorporation of many other research technologies. Notably, the use
of programming and algorithmic analysis is quite limited in film studies research compared to other
disciplines within the humanities which are utilizing digital tools to invigorate their methods and broaden their scope.</p>
        <p>ClipNotes is an iPad and Windows 8 app that facilitates quick segmentation, annotation and presentation of film clips, an example of the research possibilities that are provided in a collaborative,
database-­driven, XML-­based software environment. The design of ClipNotes is deceptively simple: it
allows users to mark up video files with metadata and present this analysis. Start/stop times, clip
descriptions, and captions are assembled in easily­produced XML files, which stands for extensible
markup language that is both human and machine readable. When the XML file is linked to the video
file, precise, granular analysis is made possible and is easily presented and disseminated. A public
repository for these XML files is available at clipnotes.org, which will allow for widespread sharing of
textual analysis and should provide an invaluable teaching resource. Users are encouraged to upload
their own XML files for inclusion and we have begun building an extensive database of freely available
teaching and research materials. For obvious copyright reasons, the films are not included, but guides
are available to demonstrate how DVDs can be easily and legally encoded into digital files under fair use
exemptions. Then, the video is linked together with the XML file by the application. In practice,
ClipNotes collapses the research and presentation process by bridging the two: your textual research
and analysis is the development of your presentation.
</p>
        <p>To get the archive started, a series of films have been coded in XML and are available for
teaching usage.<hi rend="italic"> Citizen Kane</hi>, of course, has been catalogued, providing quick access to its landmark
visual style. All instances of deep focus, triangular framings, door and window framings, graphic
matches, media representations, and the motifs of light and bulbs, bars and fences, and mirrors are
quickly and easily accessible through ClipNotes. The ability to quickly but briefly demonstrate a series
of scenes ­­ particularly ones involving sound or camera and character movement ­­ is a tremendous 		
	
	
		
			
				
					
						resource in a lecture or presentation situation. One of the distinct strengths of film is the symphonic
arrangement of audiovisual patterns, something that is lost in merely showing screen grabs or a few
extended scenes.</p>
        <p>Beyond this kind of instructional usage, however, the practice of granular analysis can reveal
new discoveries in even the most well­worn films. Hitchcock is likely the most thoroughly researched
auteur, but with the ability to isolate and compare shots on a frame­by­frame basis, very subtle visual
patterns can be identified. For instance, the ability to document the most minute patterns in <hi rend="italic">Psycho</hi>
reveals a micro­detailed facial dramaturgy that adds significant visual emphasis to Hitchcock’s already
complex exploration of identity. </p>
        <p>Douglas Sirk is another master of this kind of over-­determined mise-­en-­scene, and a fitting
subject for ClipNotes, as well as my own work that concerns the political economy of media as a textual phenomenon. <hi rend="italic">Written on the Wind</hi> is a fine example, and for my analysis I catalogued over 100
examples of 4 distinct patterns: frame within frames and obscured frames, the mirror motif, vertical
objects as phallic imagery, and what I hope is a new addition to the already ­extensive Sirk Studies
archive: the product shot. While Sirk’s satirical savvy is well­documented by scholars, the contradictory
impulse ­­ the ways in which he helped promote and fetishize the very consumer culture he was satirizing
­­ is a less prominent element of his legacy. Barbara Klinger provides a useful corrective of his body of
work in <hi rend="italic">Melodrama and Meaning: History, Culture, and the Films of Douglas Sirk</hi>, in which she
considers the various extra­-textual discourses (academic, industrial, trade, popular press, star, gossip,
camp) that have contributed to Sirk’s legacy, but she expressly decides not to engage in any textual
analysis, as her interest is in the surrounding discourse. I believe textual analysis could be a useful
addition to furthering her nuanced reading of Sirk, particularly the industrial and promotional elements of 		
	
	
		
			
				
					
						his work that get overlooked in favour of his more critical characteristics. </p>
        <p>Klinger shows how <hi rend="italic">Written on the Wind</hi> was heavily promoted in women’s magazines as a part of lifestyle marketing, particular tie-­ins with its fashion, make-­up and home decor. Textual analysis
of the film itself reveals a similar impetus for commercial promotion, catalogued here as the “product
shot.” At least two dozen shots of consumer products are featured in the film, most prominently luxury
cars, fashion, and jewellery. The first scene immediately establishes the patterns of framing, mirrors and
vertical objects, but it also quickly pronounces the importance of products, by featuring Kyle’s shiny,
yellow sportscar. Far from claiming that this kind of quasi­product placement deems Sirk some sort of
sell­out or salesman, I think a more complete picture of all that Sirk accomplished in his films just adds
to his stature. That he was able to satisfy the high standards of critics, scholars, studio executives, and
promotional agents is a testament to the complexity of his filmmaking ability. It also provides some
insight into the early history of product placement, brand integration, and transmedia.</p>
        <p>ClipNotes and XML­-encoding provides the opportunity to generate and catalogue large data sets of analytic material for audiovisual texts, lending quantification and data ­processing possibilities in
the future. Sound and image are inherently more difficult to catalogue and quantify than the written word,
which accounts for some of the delay in the use of digital humanities methods in cinema and media
studies, but creative new digital tools should be able to bridge this gap. Similar to the Text Encoding
Initiative, the data­mining prospects generated by ClipNotes are impressive. With the assistance of
digital tools, we will be able to both dig deep into solitary texts, discovering and quantifying
micro-­relationships, while also mapping broad, macro-­cultural dynamics as a result of this wide-­ranging
data. In a digital era marked by the vast proliferation of complex texts, software applications can be
utilized to enact a more rigorously detailed analysis, to archive and disseminate provocative insights, and 		
	
	
		
			
				
					
						to extend digital scholarship. </p>
        <p>Thank you, and please visit clipnotes.org for more information.</p>
     
        
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="References">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Burdick, Anne et al.</hi><hi rend="italic">Digital_Humanities</hi>. The MIT Press, 2012.
          </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Hayles, N. Katherine.</hi><hi rend="italic">How We Think: Digital Media and Contemporary Technogenesis</hi>. University
            Of Chicago Press, 2012.
          </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Klinger, Barbara.</hi><hi rend="italic">Melodrama and Meaning : History, Culture, and the Films of Douglas Sirk</hi>.
            Bloomington: Indiana University Press, 1994.
          </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Manovich, Lev.</hi><hi rend="italic">"Cultural analytics: Visualizing cultural patterns in the era of more media."</hi> Domus: 923
            (2009).
          </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Moretti, Franco</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Graphs, Maps, Trees: Abstract Models For A Literary History</hi>. Verso, 2005.
          </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Ramsay, Stephen</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Reading Machines: Toward an Algorithmic Criticism.</hi> University of Illinois Press,
            2011. </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
