<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:x="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:exsl="http://exslt.org/common" xml:id="Paper-733">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Less explored multilingual issues in the automatic processing of historical texts – a case study</title>
        <author>
          <name>
            <surname>Vertan</surname>, <forename>Cristina</forename>
          </name>
          <affiliation>University of Hamburg, Germany</affiliation>
          <email>cristina.vertan@uni-hamburg.de</email>
        </author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority/>
        <publisher>EPFL, Switzerland</publisher>
        <distributor>
          <name>EPFL Digital Humanities Laboratory</name>
          <address>
            <addrLine>GC D2 386</addrLine>
            <addrLine>Station 18</addrLine>
            <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
            <addrLine>frederic.kaplan@epfl.ch</addrLine>
          </address>
        </distributor>
        <pubPlace>Lausanne, Switzerland</pubPlace>
        <address>
          <addrLine>EPFL</addrLine>
          <addrLine>CH-1015 Lausanne</addrLine>
        </address>
        <availability>
          <p/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="abstract">Most digital libraries are made available not only to researchers in a certain Humanities domain (e.g. classical philologists, historians, historical linguists), but also to common users. This fact has posited new requirements to the functionalities offered by the Digital Libraries, and thus imposed the usage of methods from Language Technology for content analysis and content presentation in a form understandable to the end user. Language technology tools are mostly adapted in order to make corpus linguistics research but not really used as means for text processing. One of the main barriers is the text readability in terms of language style and terms. The aim of this paper, describing on-going work is to demonstrate that multilingual aspects in historical texts are a big challenge but can serve also for building a knowledge-based to be used in text presentation.</note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
        <p>
          <date when="20140709"/>
          <time when="13:45:00"/>
        </p>
		<p n="session">3</p>
		<p n="room">415 - Amphimax</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="category">
          <term>Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="subcategory">
          <term>Short Paper</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
          <term>language technology</term>
          <term>historical texts</term>
          <term>multilingualism</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
          <term>historical studies</term>
          <term>multilingual / multicultural approaches</term>
          <term>text analysis</term>
          <term>content analysis</term>
          <term></term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text type="paper">
    <front>

      <div>
        <p></p>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>1. Introduction</head>
        <p>Recently, the collaboration between the
Language Technology community and the specialists in various areas of the
Humanities has become more efficient and fruitful due to the common aim of
exploring and preserving cultural heritage data. It is worth mentioning the
efforts made during the digitisation campaigns in the last years and within a
series of initiatives in the Digital Humanities, especially in making Old
Manuscripts available in the form of Digital Libraries.</p>
        <p>Having in mind the number of contemporary
languages and their historical variants, it is practically impossible to
develop brand new language resources and tools for processing older texts.
Therefore, the real challenge is to adapt existing language resources and
tools, as well as to provide (where necessary) training material in the form of
corpora or lexicons for a certain period of time in history.  </p>
        <p>Another issue regarding historical documents is
their usage after they are stored in digital libraries. Historical documents
are not only browsed but together with adequate tools they may serve as basis
for reinterpretation of historical facts, discovery of new connections, causal
relations between events etc. In order to be able to make such analysis,
historical documents should be linked among themselves and should be linked
with modern knowledge bases. Activities in the area of Linked Open Data (LOD)
play a major role in this respect</p>
        <p>Most digital libraries are made
available not only to researchers in a certain Humanities domain (e.g.
classical philologists, historians, historical linguists), but also to common
users. This fact has posited new requirements to the functionalities offered by
the Digital Libraries, and thus imposed the usage of methods from Language Technology
for content analysis and content presentation in a form understandable to the
end user. </p>
        <p>There are several challenges related to the
above mentioned issues:</p>
        <list type="unordered">
          <item>Lack
of adequate training material for real-size applications: although the Digital
Libraries usually cover a large number of documents, it is difficult to collect
a statistically significant corpus for a period of time in which the language
remained unchanged.</item>
          <item>Historical
variants of languages lack firmly established syntactic or morphological
structures thus the definition of a robust set of rules is very difficult.  Historical texts often constitute a
mixture of multilingual paragraphs including Latin, Ancient Greek, Slavonic,
etc.</item>
          <item>Historical
texts contain a large number of anon-standardized abbreviations.</item>
          <item>The
conception of the world is somewhat different from ours, which makes it more
difficult to build the necessary knowledge bases. </item>
        </list>
        <p>Whilst these issues are generally accepted
there is still less research done towards the content annotation of old texts.
Language technology tools are mostly adapted in order to make corpus
linguistics research (Piotrowski 2012), (Vertan et. al 2012) but not really
used as means for text processing. One of the main barriers is the text
readability in terms of language style and terms. </p>
        <p>The aim of this paper, describing on-going work
is to demonstrate that multilingual aspects in historical texts are a big
challenge but can serve also for building a knowledge-based to be used in text
presentation.</p>
        <head>2. Selected materials</head>
        <p>The selected texts are works of Dimitire
Cantemir, prince of Moldavia at the end of the XVII century, but also
historian, philosopher, composer, musicologist, linguist and much other.</p>
        <p>As member of the Prussian Academy of Sciences
he was asked to write a history of the Ottoman Empire as well as a history of
Moldavia, both unknown territories for Western Europe at this time. These remarkable
works remained until the middle of XIXth century the only generally accepted
reference. Even if some historical aspects are interpreted in a subjective
manner, the works of Cantemir represent a unique testimony of that time. He is
not describing only dates and places of historical events but presents daily
life, occupations, country organisation as he saw himself as prisoner in
Istanbul and prince of Moldavia.</p>
        <p>The „History of growth and decay of the Ottoman
Empire“ and the §Description of Moldavia“ were written initially in Latin.
Later they were translated in German, and then the German Edition was
translated in English, French, Romanian and Russian. All these Editions are no
tone-to-one translation but in many cases they are influenced by the perception
of the translator.</p>
        <p>We consider that the works of Cantemir are of
particular importance fort he history of Easter-Europe, about which with
exception of specialists, is less known.</p>
        <p>The current project aims at the presentation
and explanation of these works, by means of language technology tools. For the
moment we concentrate on the German, English and Romanian Editions of the
„Description of Moldavia“, all available in the Library of our institution and
intend to extend the work to the other language editions.</p>
        <head>3. Exploiting Multilinguality</head>
        <p>Usually the multilingual problem of the old
texts is resumed to the fact that Latin and sometimes ancient Greek passages
are found. The works of Cantemir have the particularity that they introduce
words in the language of the described country, namely Romanian and Ottoman Turkish.</p>
        <p>Therefore a processing step is needed in order
to identify these words. State-of –the art methods in language identifications
based on n-grams cannot be used as both old Romanian were written with other
alphabets (church Slavonic) and the transliteration rules were not
standardised.</p>
        <p>Our method uses the multilingual versions of
his works help here in identifying the foreign words.</p>
        <p>Explanation paragraphs differ slowly but the
terms are preserved. Therefore we use comparison at sentence level in order to
identify common words, which we mark afterwards as Named Entities.</p>
        <p>Following
example form the „Descriptio of Moldavia“ in German is illustrative:</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="italic">„Der Watawul de Aprodschi de Tyrg ist Herr über
die Gerichtsdiener, welche den Tribut und andere Abgaben der Bürger eintreiben,
und andei Schazkammer liefern. „</hi>
        </p>
        <p>Here we
observe the following: the expression „Watawul de Aproschi de Tyrg“ is for a
language technology tool dealing with German completely noisy. On the other
hand the expression is an approximate transliteration of old Romanian written
in Church Slavonic. Nowadays the correct transliteration would be „vatavul de
aprozi de târg “.</p>
        <p>In
comparison here the entry in the R Romanian version</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="italic">„<hi rend="bold">Vatavul de aprozi</hi> de târg; este asupra slujitorilor divanului, cari
strâng birul si alte dări ale orăsenilor si le aduc la Visterie;</hi>
        </p>
        <p>Thus the algorithm
for the processing of the text involve the following steps:</p>
        <list type="ordered">
          <item>1. Sentence splitting of German and English
and Romanian texts </item>
          <item>2. Sentence alignment by means of
comparable corpora sentence extraction (Smith et. al. 2010)</item>
          <item>3. Identification of common identical
strings</item>
          <item>4. Extraction of common passages and
normalisation using resources in old Romanian /ottoman Turkish as well as
heuristic rules</item>
          <item>5. Marking of identified expressions as
named entities in order to be blocked from further processing.</item>
        </list>
        <p>We use the output of this process in
order to built a multilingual knowledge base, and match the terms on wikipedia
entries.</p>
        <head>4. Conclusions and further work</head>
        <p>Through
this contribution we want to raise the attention on less studied aspects of
multilinguality in historical texts and show how methods from multilingual
language technology, here exploitation of comparable corpora, can be used for
dealing with this issue. In the presentation we would describe in detail the
algorithms used for the construction of the multilingual knowledge base and
give relevant examples.</p>
        <p>As mentioned before, this is an on-going project. After creating the knowledge
base we intend to built a presentation interface where entries in the knowledge
base may-be available at the moment of text reading through a mouse-over
function. We intend also to asses how much from the found entries match
Wikipedia, and show that in fact the information is complementary. We intend
also to extend the methods to other works.</p>


      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div type="References">
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Cantemir, C,</hi><hi rend="italic">Descriptio Moldaviae Historisch-geographisch und politische Beschreibung
          der Moldau, nebst dem Leben des Verfassers (lat. - 1714-1716)</hi>;  germ. Beschreibung der Moldau, A. V. Büssch
          (Ed.), 1770</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Cantemir, C.</hi>,
            <hi rend="italic">Geschichte des Osmanischen Reichs nach seinem Anwachse und Abnehmen.
              Beschrieben  von Demetrie Kantemir, ehemaligem Fürsten in Moldau</hi>.
            Nebst den Bildern der Türkischen Kaiser, 
            Hamburg Herold, 1745.</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Piotrowki, M.</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Natural Language
            Processing for Historical Texts</hi>, Synthesis Lecture on Human Language
            Technologies, 2012 </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Smith, J and Quirk, C. and Toutanova, K</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Extracting
            parallel sentences from comparable corpora using document level alignment</hi>, Proceedings
            of the HLT '10 Human Language Technologies: The 2010 Annual Conference of the
            North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics, pages
            403-411</bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Vertan, C. and Osenova, P. and Slavcheva, M.
            and Piperidis, S.</hi><hi rend="italic">„Adapation of Language Processing and Tools for cultural
              heritage“</hi>, Proceedings of the Workshop at LREC 2012.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
