<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-154">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Computing and Visualizing the 19th-Century Literary Genome</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Jockers, Matthew</name>
                    <affiliation>Stanford University, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>mjockers@stanford.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Overview</head>
                <p>In literary studies, we have no shortage of anecdotal wisdom regarding the role
                    of influence on creativity. Consider just a few of the most prominent voices:  </p>
                <xmt:oList rend="arabic">      
                    <item> ‘Talents imitate, geniuses steal’ – Oscar Wilde (1854-1900?).<note>Routinely attributed to Wilde, but of uncertain origin, Wilde probably ‘borrowed’ this quip.</note></item>
                    <item>‘All ideas are second hand, consciously and unconsciously drawn from a
                        million outside sources’ – Mark Twain (1903).</item>
                    <item>‘The historical sense compels a man to write not merely with his own
                        generation in his bones, but with a feeling that the whole of the literature …
                        has a simultaneous existence’ – T. S. Eliot (1920).</item>
                    <item>‘The elements of which the artwork is created are external to the
                        author and independent of him …’ – Osip Brik (1929).</item>
                    <item><hi rend="italic">Anxiety of Influence </hi>– Harold Bloom (1973).</item>
                </xmt:oList>
                <p>Whether consciously influenced by a predecessor or not, it might be argued that
                    every book is in some sense a necessary descendant of, or necessarily <hi
                        rend="italic">‘</hi>connected to,<hi rend="italic"> ’</hi> those before it.
                    Influence may be direct, as when a writer models his or her writing on another
                        writer,<note>An extreme case may be Fielding’s <hi rend="italic"
                            >Shamela</hi>, which attempts to satirize Richardson’s <hi rend="italic"
                            >Pamela</hi>.</note> or influence may be indirect in the form of
                    unconscious borrowing. Influence may even be <hi rend="italic"
                        >‘</hi>oppositional<hi rend="italic">’</hi> as in the case of a writer who
                    wishes to make his or her writing intentionally different from that of a
                    predecessor. The aforementioned thinkers offer informed but anecdotal evidence
                    in support of their claims of influence. My research brings a complementary
                    quantitative and macroanalytic dimension to the discussion of influence. For
                    this, I employ the tools and techniques of stylometry, corpus linguistics,
                    machine learning, and network analysis to measure influence in a corpus of late
                    18th- and 19th-century novels.</p>
                </div>
            <div>
            
                <head>Method</head>
                <p>The 3,592 books in my corpus span from 1780 to 1900 and were written by authors
                    from Britain, Ireland, and America; the corpus is almost even in terms of gender
                    representation. From each of these books, I extracted stylistic information
                    using techniques similar to those employed in authorship attribution analysis:
                    the relative frequencies of every word and mark of punctuation are calculated
                    and the resulting data winnowed so as to exclude features not meeting a preset
                    relative frequency threshold.<note>Features with a corpus mean less than 0.10 were excluded.  This resulted in 92 features being retained. For more on feature selection practices see: Martindale and McKenzie (1995), Yang and Pedersen (1997), Hoover (2001), Zhao and Zobel (2005), Garcia and Martin (2007), Grieve (2007), Hoover (2008)</note> From each book I also
                    extracted thematic (or <hi rend="italic">‘</hi>topical<hi rend="italic">’</hi>)
                    information using Latent <hi rend="italic">Dirichlet</hi> Allocation (Blei, Ng
                    et al. 2003; Blei, Griffiths et al. 2004; Chang, Boyd-Graber et al. 2009). The
                    thematic data includes information about the percentages of each theme/topic
                    found in each text.<note>For this research, the topic model was set to extract 500 latent topics.</note> I combine these two categories of
                    data – stylistic and thematic – to create <hi rend="italic">‘</hi>book
                        signals<hi rend="italic">’</hi> composed of 592 unique feature measurements.
                    The <hi rend="italic">‘</hi>Euclidian” metric is then used to calculate every
                    book’s distance from every other book in the corpus. The result is a distance
                    matrix of dimension 3,592 x 3,592.<note>‘Distance’ here is a measure of stylistic and thematic similarity. Distances were calculated using the default settings of the ‘dist()’ function in the R statistics package.  See: Team (2011)</note></p>
                <p>While measuring and tracking <hi rend="italic">‘</hi>actual<hi rend="italic"
                        >’</hi> or <hi rend="italic">‘</hi>true<hi rend="italic">’</hi> influence –
                    conscious or unconscious – is impossible, it is possible to use the
                    stylistic-thematic distance/similarity measurements as a proxy for influence.<note>This is not simply a ‘proxy’ of convenience. It is, in fact, an ideal proxy, especially so when we consider that even plagiarism (the most obvious form of influence) can be accidental.</note> Network visualization software can then be used as a
                    way to organize, visualize, and study the presence of influence among of books
                    in my corpus.<note>I’m grateful to my colleague Elijah Meeks who sees the world through network analysis goggles and who aided me in visualizing and analyzing this data.</note> To prepare the data for use in a network
                    environment, I converted the distance matrix into a long-form table with
                    12,902,464 rows and three columns in which each row captures a distance
                    relationship between two books. The first cell contains a <hi rend="italic"
                        >‘</hi>source<hi rend="italic">’</hi> book, the second cell a <hi
                        rend="italic">‘</hi>target<hi rend="italic">’</hi> book, and a third cell
                    the measured distance between the two. After removing all of the records in
                    which the target book was published before, or in the same year as, the source
                    book,<note>Influence only works in one direction!</note> the data was reduced from 12,902,464 records
                    to 6,447,640. This data and a separate table of metadata were then imported into
                    the open source network analysis software package Gephi (2009) for analysis and
                    visualization.</p></div>
                <div>
               <head>Analysis</head>
                    <p>Networks are constructed out of nodes (books) and edges (distances). When plotted, nodes with less similarity (i.e. larger distances between them) will spread out further in the network. Figure 1 offers a simplified example of three imaginary books.</p><p><figure><graphic url="img154-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 1: a sample network with edge numbers representing measured distances between nodes</head></figure></p>
                    <p>While it is not possible to show the details of the entire network here, it is possible to display several of the most obvious macro-structures. Figure 2, for example, presents a zoomed out view of the network with book nodes colored according to dates of publication.<note>All network layouts employ Gephi’s built-in Force Atlas 2 algorithm.</note></p><p><figure><graphic url="img154-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 2: The 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>-century novel network colored according to publication date</head></figure></p>
                    <p>The shading of nodes and edges according to publication date reveals the inherently chronological nature of stylistic and thematic change.  The progressive darkening of the nodes from east to west allows us to see, at the macro-scale, how style and theme are changing and evolving over time. <note>Remember that time is not a feature in the similarity calculations.  The arrangement of the nodes in a chronological fashion is a byproduct of the way in which the books signals change in a regular, chronological, manner.</note>Also seen in this image is a ‘satellite’ of books in the northwest.  This satellite represents a ‘community’ of novels that are highly self-similar but at the same time markedly different from the books in the main network cluster. <note>In the larger presentation of this work, I will offer an explanation for why the 499 books in this isolated cluster are split off from the main network. One unifying element is time; most are books from a similar time period, but the full explanation is more nuanced.</note>When the network is recolored according to gender (figure 3), a new axis can be seen splitting the network into northern and southern sectors along gender lines.</p><p><figure><graphic url="img154-3.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 3: The 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>-century novel network colored according to author-gender</head></figure></p>
                    <p>This visualization (Figure 3) reveals that works by female authors (colored
                    light gray) and male authors (black) are more stylistically and thematically
                    homogeneous within their respective gender classes. As a result of this
                    similarity in ‘signals,’ female-authored books cluster together on the south
                    side of the main network, while male-authored books are drawn together in the
                        north.<note>Even in the satellite community, sub clustering by gender is
                        apparent.</note> These two ‘views’ of the network allow us to begin
                    imagining the larger macro-history of thematic-stylistic change and influence in
                    the 19th-century novel. What is not obvious in this macro-view, however, is that
                    a great many of the individual books we have traditionally studied are in fact
                    ‘mutations’ or outliers from the general trends. Harriet Beecher Stowe’s <hi
                        rend="italic">Uncle Tom’s Cabin</hi>, for example, clusters closer to the
                    works of male authors, and Maria Edgeworth’s <hi rend="italic">Belinda</hi> has
                    a signal that does not become dominant for forty years after the date of
                    Belinda’s publication. Also absent from the macro-view are the individual
                    thematic-stylistic ‘legacies’. Using three measures of network significance
                    (weighted in-degree, weighted out-degree and Page-Rank), <note>Weighted
                        in-degree is a measure of influence coming into a node whereas weighted
                        out-degree provides a measure of the influence a given node exerts on
                        subsequent nodes. The Page-Rank algorithm can be used to gauge the
                        significance/power/importance of a book in the overall network.</note>I will
                    end my presentation with the argument that Jane Austen and Walter Scott are at
                    once the least influenced (i.e. most original) of the early writers in the
                    network and, at the same time, the most influential in terms of the longevity,
                    or ‘fitness,’ of their thematic-stylistic signals. The signals introduced by
                    Austen and Scott position them at the beginning of a stylistic-thematic
                    genealogy; they are, in this sense, the literary equivalent of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Homo erectus</hi> or, if you prefer, Adam and Eve. </p>
            </div>
            
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                    <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Bastian, M., S. Heymann, et al.</hi> (2009). <hi rend="italic"
                        >Gephi: An Open Source Software for Exploring and Manipulating
                    Networks</hi>.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Blei, D. M., T. L. Griffiths, et al. </hi>(2004).<hi rend="italic"> Hierarchical
                        topic models and the nested Chinese restaurant process</hi>. Cambridge, MA:
                    MIT Press.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Blei, D. M., A. Y. Ng, et al.</hi> (2003). Latent Dirichlet Allocation. <hi
                        rend="italic">Journal of Machine Learning Research</hi> 3: 993-1022. </p><p><hi rend="bold">Bloom, H</hi>. (1973).
                            <hi rend="italic">The anxiety of influence; a theory of poetry</hi>. New
                        York: Oxford UP.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Bloom, H</hi>. (2011). <hi rend="italic">The anatomy of influence: literature as
                        a way of life</hi>. New Haven, Conn.: Yale UP.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Brik, O.
                            M</hi>. (1929). Teaching Writers.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Chang, J., J. Boyd-Graber, et al.</hi> (2009). <hi rend="italic">Reading Tea
                        Leaves: How Humans Interpret Topic Models</hi>Advances in Neural Information
                    Processing Systems 22.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Eliot, T. S.</hi>
                        (1920). <hi rend="italic">The sacred wood; essays on poetry and
                            criticism</hi>. London: Methuen.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Garcia, M., and C. Martin</hi> (2007). Function Words in Authorship Attribution
                    Studies. <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing: Journal of the
                        Association for Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi>
                    <hi rend="bold">2</hi>2(1): 49-66.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Grieve, J.</hi>
                        (2007). Quantitative Authorship Attribution: An Evaluation of Techniques.
                            <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing: Journal of the
                            Association for Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi> 22(3):
                        251-270.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Hoover, D. L.</hi> (2001). Statistical
                        Stylistics and Authorship Attribution: An Empirical Investigation. <hi
                            rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing: Journal of the
                            Association for Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi> 16(4):
                        421-444.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Hoover, D. L.</hi> (2008). <hi rend="italic"
                            >Quantitative Analysis and Literary Studies. A Companion to Digital
                            Literary Studies</hi>. Oxford: Blackwell.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Martindale, C., and D. McKenzie</hi> (1995). On the Utility of Content Analysis
                    in Author Attribution: The Federalist. <hi rend="italic">Computers and the
                        Humanities</hi> 29(4): 259-270.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Team, R.
                            D. C.</hi> (2011). <hi rend="italic">R: A Language and Environment for
                            Statistical Computing</hi>. Vienna: Austria, R Foundation for
                        Statistical Computing.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Twain, M., and A. B. Paine</hi> (1975). <hi rend="italic">Mark Twain’s
                        letters</hi>. New York: AMS Press.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Yang, Y., and J. Pedersen</hi> (1997). <hi rend="italic">A comparative study on
                        feature selection in text categorization</hi>. Proceedings of the 14th
                    International Conference on Machine Learning (ICML ’97), Nashville,
                    Tennessee.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Zhao, Y., and J. Zobel</hi> (2005). Effective and scalable authorship attribution
                    using function words. <hi rend="italic">Lecture Notes in Computer Science</hi>.
                    Berlin: Springer, pp.<hi rend="bold"> </hi>174-189.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>