<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-106">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Programming Historian 2: A Participatory Textbook</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Crymble, Adam H.</name>
                    <affiliation>Network in Canadian History &amp; Environment, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>acrymbl@uwo.ca</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>MacEachern, Alan</name>
                    <affiliation>Network in Canadian History &amp; Environment, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>amaceach@uwo.ca</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Turkel, William J.</name>
                    <affiliation>Network in Canadian History &amp; Environment, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>wturkel@uwo.ca</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>The second edition of <hi rend="italic">The Programming Historian (PH2)</hi> is an
                open access and open source introductory text designed to teach the fundamentals of
                programming to humanists. The first edition (Turkel &amp; MacEachern 2007), while
                popular, is basically a traditional text presented online. It was limited to the
                lessons that we provided and followed a single narrative arc. The second edition,
                also online, has been restructured to invite ongoing community participation and
                authorship.</p>
            
                
                <p>The project is designed with a core sequence of lessons that get readers up to
                    speed with basic programming concepts. These show how to programmatically
                    download sources from the Internet, process them for keywords, and visualize
                    some textual attributes. Contributors can introduce new lessons at any point by
                    branching off from a previous lesson. They might, for example, introduce a
                    related technique, or show how to implement something in another programming
                    language, on another platform, or using different kinds of sources. The
                    branching structure allows members of the digital humanities community to add
                    lessons based on their own specialties, or to create new sequences for use in
                    the classroom, while still guaranteeing that readers will have the background
                    required to understand a particular branch if their study of <hi rend="italic"
                        >PH2</hi> has taken them to that point. Each lesson is intended to take two
                    hours or less to complete.</p>
        
                <p>For contributors, <hi rend="italic">PH2</hi> provides a peer-reviewed platform
                    for methodology. Both literary and technical reviewers vet all submissions with
                    quality emphasized over quantity. Lessons are presented in a custom WordPress
                    installation and code snippets are stored in GitHub for easy maintenance and
                    sharing. To make the site as easy as possible to use, code snippets are pulled
                    directly into the WordPress posts making GitHub essentially invisible for both
                    authors and readers not familiar with or interested in its features. Individual
                    lessons are attributed to their authors, and reviewers and other contributors
                    receive public credit for their labour. For learners, <hi rend="italic">PH2</hi>
                    focuses on the use of programming to solve problems common to academic research,
                    such as obtaining, analyzing, processing, and mashing up sources. While there
                    are hundreds of programming books on the market, very few teach these kinds of
                    hands-on tasks that are crucial to the practice of the digital humanities. </p>
                
                <p>With the first edition of the <hi rend="italic">Programming Historian</hi>, we
                    showed that there is a great demand for programming introduction that focuses on
                    the day-to-day work of digital humanists both historians and otherwise. We have
                    commissioned a number of new lessons from guest authors for the second edition
                    and hope to open our submission process to the wider community shortly. From our
                    past experience we know that people well beyond our target audience of digital
                    humanists can and will use the project as a way to delve into programming. When
                        <hi rend="italic">PH2</hi> launches publicly, we believe that the digital
                    humanities community will embrace and expand it and we look forward to working
                    with them.</p>
            <div><p><hi rend="bold">Funding</hi></p>
            
            
        </div></body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <p>This work was supported by <hi rend="italic">The Network in Canadian History
                        &amp; Environment, </hi>and the <hi rend="italic">Roy Rosenzweig Center for
                        History and New Media.</hi></p></div>
                <div>
                    <head>References</head>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Github</hi><hi rend="italic">.</hi><ref
                        target="http://github.com" type="external">http://github.com (accessed 1
                        March 2012).</ref>
                </p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Wordpress.</hi><ref target="http://wordpress.org"
                        type="external">http://wordpress.org</ref> (accessed 1 March 2012).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Turkel, W. J. and A. MacEachern</hi> (2007). <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Programming Historian 1st Edition. </hi><ref
                        target="http://niche-canada.org/programming-historian" type="external"
                        >http://niche-canada.org/programming-historian</ref> (accessed 1 March
                        2012).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Turkel, W. J., A. Crymble, J. Boggs, M. Posner, et al., eds.</hi>
                    (2012). <hi rend="italic">The Programming Historian 2. </hi><ref
                        target="http://chnm.gmu.edu/press/programminghistorian/"
                        >http://chnm.gmu.edu/press/programminghistorian/</ref> (accessed 1 March
                        2012).</p>
                
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>