<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-207">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>A Computer-Based Approach for Predicting the Translation Time Period of Early Chinese Buddhism Translation</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Hung, Jen-Jou</name>
                    <affiliation>Dharma Drum Buddhist College, Taiwan</affiliation>
                    <email>jenjou.hung@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Bingenheimer, Marcus</name>
                    <affiliation>Temple University, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>m.bingenheimer@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Kwok, Jieli</name>
                    <affiliation>Dharma Drum Buddhist College, Taiwan</affiliation>
                    <email>guo.jieli@ddbc.edu.tw</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
            <p>Buddhism is a world-religion which has managed to take roots in cultures vastly
                different from that of its origin. Its transmission from India to China between the
                2nd and the 10th centuries happened against all odds. The ‘Buddhist conquest of
                China’ can be partly attributed to the successful translation of a great number of
                texts translated into Chinese from Indian languages. The current standard edition of
                the Chinese Buddhist canon (<hi rend="italic">Taishō shinshū daizōkyō</hi> (Abbr.:
                T.) <foreign>大正新修大蔵經</foreign>, edited 1924-1934) contains 3053 works in 85 volumes, including about
                1000 texts of Indian (or alleged Indian) provenance. However, ca. 150 of these texts
                are marked as <hi rend="italic">shiyi</hi> <foreign>失譯</foreign>, indicating that the name(s) of the
                translator(s) are unknown. Furthermore, for the texts that were translated between
                the 2nd and the late 6th century, many attributions are uncertain, problematic or
                simply incorrect. The issue of doubtful and wrong attributions has been debated in
                the field of Buddhist studies over the last few decades, e.g., Zürcher (1991),
                Harrison (1993), (and) Nattier (2008).</p>
            <p>Over the years Buddhist scholars have leveraged traditional text-critical methods to
                    corroborate or dispute traditional attributions yet like every method philology
                    has its limits. Faced with a large number of texts in ‘Buddhist Hybrid Chinese’
                    of unknown provenance/origin, the long-established note-taking on the usage of
                    characters and words quickly runs into problems. As with European languages,
                    computational linguistics might offer new avenues of data collection and
                    verification. The corpus of Buddhist Hybrid Chinese is available in a reliable
                    digital format (XML/TEI) since the first 55 volumes of the Taishō edition were
                    published freely by the Chinese Buddhist Electronic Texts Association
                    (CBETA).</p>
            <p>We are now able to apply statistical methods and artificial intelligence algorithms
                to the analysis of this corpus. This enables us to obtain new evidence bearing on
                translatorship attribution problems. The major advantage of quantitative methods for
                translatorship attribution is being able to analyze large amounts of data and to
                discover patterns which are not evident to the human reader.</p>
            <p>Quantitative translatorship attribution is often considered to be a classification
                problem, that is, a text with uncertain or problematic authorship will be analyzed
                and compared with a corpus of texts by possible authors and then attributed to the
                author which whose works the texts shares most ‘characteristics.’ Recent years have
                seen renewed interest in many issues involved in optimizing quantitative authorship
                attribution. One of them is the effect of the size of possible candidate authors. As
                Luyckx and Daelemans (2010) have shown the accuracy of authorship analysis will
                decrease as the number of possible authors increases. It is therefore advisable to
                limit the number of possible authors in order to get a high accuracy analysis
                result. In our case, however, many of the early Chinese Buddhist translations are
                only rarely mentioned in historical records and canonical catalogues, and few have
                attracted the attention of philologists. For these translations, it is difficult to
                reduce the range of possible translators.</p>
            <p>Therefore, as part of our attempt to establish a foundation for quantitative
                translatorship attribution for early Chinese Buddhist translations, we propose a
                classification mechanism based on predicting the translation time or period of a
                text. The advantage of this mechanism is twofold. First, within a given time bracket
                for the translation, the number of possible authors is limited, thereby improving
                the performance of the translatorship attribution. Second, by examining the result
                classification mechanism, we are able to identify possible and probable stylistic
                features of translations for different periods.</p>
            <p>The time periods we focus on in the present study include three early Chinese
                dynasties: the Eastern Han (C.E. 25-220), the Three Kingdoms (C.E. 220-280) and the
                Western Jin (C.E. 266-316). These three dynasties constitute the earliest phase of
                Buddhist translation history and most of the translations from these periods present
                attribution problems. In this research, we build up classification mechanisms for
                each of the three dynasties. These can be used to test whether the translation style
                of a text is similar to the one <hi rend="italic">prevalent</hi> during a certain
                period. We are aware of the fact that within Buddhist Hybrid Chinese translation
                styles within a given period can vary greatly.</p>
            <p>For the Eastern Han (C.E. 25-220) and the Three Kingdoms periods we build on recent
                philological scholarship (Nattier 2008), which has ascertained a number of
                attributions for this period. For the Western Jin textual corpus, we rely on
                contemporary research on traditional Buddhist sūtra catalogs, from which we exclude
                those texts for which current scholarship has not reached a consensus (Lancaster
                2008; Lü 1981; Ren 1985; Yu 1993; Xu 1987). We then adopt the Variant Length N-gram
                algorithm (Hung et. al. 2009) to extract the stylometric features from the three
                corpora of ascertained texts. Variant Length N-gram is an extended form of the
                traditional n-gram algorithm. In the traditional n-gram algorithm, the length of
                grams <hi rend="italic">n</hi> is fixed. Although the exploitation of n-gram
                algorithm has great impact on the performance of following analysis, deciding the
                best value of <hi rend="italic">n</hi> is not straightforward. The Variant Length
                N-gram algorithm generates grams of all possible lengths, then removes those which
                are not significant. Thus, the importance of stylometric features is measured across
                grams of different length. This is crucial as there are no word boundaries in
                Buddhist Hybrid Chinese: gram-based analysis must therefore include grams of any
                length.</p>
            <p>In the final stage, we use Fisher Linear Discriminant Analysis (FLDA) to analyze the
                stylometric features that have been extracted from the translations and to build up
                the classification mechanisms. The FLDA is a well-known dimension reducing and
                classification algorithm. It returns a linear function that transfers the high
                dimension source data of different groups into one-dimension points such that the
                ratio of total variances of projected points to the variances between groups of
                projected points is maximized. Since the FLDA’s transformation is based on assigning
                weight to n-grams, the analysis is capable of yielding distinctive features, i.e.
                strings of Chinese characters, that are characteristic of the dynasties in
                question.</p>
            <p>According to our experiments, the classification mechanisms for the three dynasties
                have all reached an accuracy rate higher than 90%. Moreover, when the three
                classification mechanisms are combined and usedto predict the translation time of an
                unknown translation, we can achieve an accuracy rate and a recall rate both above
                80%. Besides, we are able to identify characteristic translation terms for different
                time periods.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <head>References</head>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Harrison, P.</hi> (1993). The Earliest Chinese Translations
                    of Mahāyāna Buddhist Sūtras: Some Notes on the Works of Lokaksema. <hi
                        rend="italic">Buddhist Studies Review</hi> 10(2): 135-177.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Hung, J., M. Bingenheimer, and S. Wiles</hi> (2009).
                        Quantitative evidence for a hypothesis regarding the attribution of early
                        Buddhist translations.<hi rend="italic"> Literary and Linguistic
                            Computing</hi> 25(1): 119-134.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Lancaster, L.</hi> (2008). <hi rend="italic">Catalogues in
                            the Electronic Era: CBETA and The Korean Buddhist Canon: A Descriptive
                            Catalogue</hi>. CBETA, Taipei, 2008 (electronic publication). Retrieved
                    from <ref target="http://jinglu.cbeta.org/lancaster.htm" type="external">http://jinglu.cbeta.org/lancaster.htm</ref>.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Lu, </hi><hi rend="bold">Cheng </hi><hi rend="bold"><foreign>呂澂</foreign></hi>
                        (1981). <hi rend="italic">Xinbian hanwen dazangjing mulu</hi>  <foreign>新編漢文大藏經目錄</foreign>.
                        Jinan: Jilu shushe  <foreign>齊魯書社</foreign>.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Luyckx, K., and W. Daelemans</hi> (2010). The effect of
                        author set size and data size in authorship attribution. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Literary and Linguistic Computing.</hi> 26(1): 35-55.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Nattier, J.</hi> (2008). <hi rend="italic">A Guide to the
                            Earliest Chinese Buddhist Translations: Texts from the Eastern Han
                            </hi><foreign>東漢</foreign><hi rend="italic"> and Three Kingdoms </hi><foreign>三國</foreign> <hi rend="italic"
                            >Periods</hi>. Tokyo: The International Research Institute for Advanced
                        Buddhology, Soka University.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Ren Jiyu </hi><hi rend="bold"><foreign>任繼愈</foreign></hi> (1985). <hi
                            rend="italic">Zhongguo fojiao shi</hi> <foreign>中國佛教史</foreign>. Vol 1. Beijing: Zhongguo
                        shehui kexue <foreign>中国社会科学出版社</foreign>.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Xu Lihe</hi>
                    <hi rend="bold"><foreign>許理和</foreign></hi> (1987). Zui zao de fojing yiwen zhong de donghan kouyu
                    chengfen <foreign>最早的佛經譯文中的東漢口語成分</foreign>, Yu yan xue lun cong <foreign>語言學論叢</foreign>, Vol. 14. Beijing: Shangwu
                    yinshuguan <foreign>商務印書館</foreign>, pp. 197-225. </p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Yu Liming</hi>
                    <hi rend="bold"><foreign>俞理明</foreign></hi> (1993). <hi rend="italic">Fojing wenxian
                    yuyan</hi><foreign>佛経文献語言</foreign> [The Language of the Buddhist Scriptures]. Chengdu: Bashu
                    shushe<foreign>巴蜀書社</foreign>, p. 206.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Zürcher, E.</hi> (1991). A New Look at the Earliest Chinese
                    Buddhist Texts. In K. Shinohara et al. (eds.), <hi rend="italic">From Benares to
                        Beijing: Essays on Buddhism and Chinese Religion in Honour of Prof. Jan
                        Yün-hua.</hi>Oakville, Ontario: Mosaic Press, pp. 277-304.</p>
             </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>