<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-293">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>On the Internet, nobody knows you’re a historian: exploring resistance to
                    crowdsourced resources among historians</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Ridge, Mia</name>
                    <affiliation>Open University, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>m.ridge@open.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>Crowdsourcing, the act of taking work once performed within an organisation and
                outsourcing it to the general public in an open call (Howe 2006), is increasingly
                popular in memory institutions as a tool for digitising or computing vast amounts of
                data, as projects such as Galaxy Zoo and Old Weather (Romeo &amp; Blaser 2011),
                Transcribe Bentham (Terras 2010) and the Australian Newspapers Digitisation Program
                (Holley 2010) have shown. However, the very openness that allows large numbers of
                experts and amateurs to participate in the process of building crowdsourced
                resources also raises issues of authority, reliability and trust in those resources.
                Can we rely on content created by pseudonymous peers or members of the public? And
                why do academics often feel that they can’t? This paper explores some of the causes
                and forms of resistance to creating and using crowdsourced resources among
                historians.</p>
            <p>‘Participant digitisation’ is a specialised form of crowdsourcing in which the
                digital records and knowledge generated when researchers access primary materials
                are captured at the point of creation and potentially made available for future
                re-use. Through interviews with academic and family/local historians, this paper
                examines the following: the commonalities and differences in how these two groups
                assess the provenance, reliability and probable accuracy of digital resources; how
                crowdsourcing tools might support their working practices with historical materials;
                the motivations of historians for sharing their transcriptions and images in a
                public repository; the barriers that would prevent them from participating in a
                project that required them to share their personally-digitised archives; and the
                circumstances under which they would selectively restrict content sharing. From this
                preliminary investigation, the paper will go on to consider implications for the
                creation of digital humanities resources for academic and amateur users.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Holley, R.</hi> (2010). Crowdsourcing: How and Why Should
                    Libraries Do It? <hi rend="italic">D-Lib Magazine</hi> 16(3/4).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Howe, J.</hi> (2006). The Rise of Crowdsourcing. <hi
                        rend="italic">Wired</hi> 14.06. [Online] Available from: <ref
                        target="http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/14.06/crowds.html" type="external">
                    http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/14.06/crowds.html</ref></p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Romeo, F., and L. Blaser</hi> (2011). Bringing Citizen Scientists
                    and Historians Together. In J. Trant and D. Bearman (eds), <hi rend="italic"
                        >Museums and the Web 2011: Proceedings</hi>. Toronto: Archives &amp; Museum
                    Informatics.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Terras, M.</hi> (2010). Digital curiosities: resource creation
                    via amateur digitization. <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic
                        Computing</hi> 25(4), 425-438.</p>
                
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>