<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-232">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Opportunity and accountability in the ‘eResearch push’</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Bellamy, Craig</name>
                    <affiliation>Victorian eResearch Strategic Initiative (VeRSI), Australia</affiliation>
                    <email>txt@craigbellamy.net</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            
            <p>In this paper I will present an examination of the institutional and epistemological
                tensions between particular national ‘eResearch’ infrastructure agendas (or
                ‘eScience’, ‘cyber-infrastructure’) and particular aspects of the digital
                humanities. Whilst much of the digital humanities positions itself within the
                research ‘infrastructures’ of the humanities (journals, academic departments,
                conferences, libraries, and sober ethics committees) – and is partly responsible for
                building the ‘human capital’ to work in the humanities – eResearch has largely
                emerged outside of the perspectives and training of the digital humanities,
                primarily driven by a ‘big science’ agenda (ie. an emphasis on mass data storage and
                infrastructures that largely support scientific methods and ways of collaborating).
                This has created numerous complexities for the digital humanities, particularly in
                the UK and Australia where it may, for better or worse, be emerging as a competing
                set of discourses and practices to the digital humanities (Examples will be given in
                the presentation).</p>
            <p>Admittedly, the eResearch agenda <hi rend="italic">has</hi> created many
                opportunities for research in the humanities, however, the way in which this agenda
                has been institutionalised in a number of countries means that it doesn’t always
                serve the needs of the humanities. This is because eResearch largely exists <hi
                    rend="italic">outside</hi> of humanities research structures and is principally
                measured and driven by different accountability metrics. Its technical development
                also sits within rarefied institutional hierarchies between ‘service staff and
                researcher’, and biases a mistaken industrial utility; neither of which seem
                particularly useful for the contemporary challenges of digital humanities nor
                humanities research. As Geoffrey Rockwell states:</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">[there are] dangers in general and especially the issue of the turn
                    from research to research infrastructure [...] we need to be careful about
                    defining the difference and avoid moving into the realm of infrastructure [...]
                    those things we are still studying</hi> (Rockwell 2010: 5).</p>
            <p>Through presenting key examples, in this presentation I will broadly explore the
                institutionalisation of eResearch-infrastructures in the humanities over the past
                decade, and in particular, reference the countries in which I have the most
                experience, Australia and the UK. The landscape in Australia is particularly
                problematic as unlike other countries, the eResearch agenda is still at its height
                whilst the digital humanities is still developing its own institutional addenda.</p>
            <p>The main tension appears to be a ‘two cultures’ one; it is the misunderstandings
                between applied computing, largely focused upon meeting the many practical needs of
                large-scale scientific endeavours, and the digital humanities that has its own
                particular understandings of the efficacy of computing within its heterogeneous
                research endeavours. Many infrastructure investors unavoidably claim a ‘research
                enabling’ or even a research pedigree for their work, but the exact nature of this
                research and how it helps us understand humans society and culture is, on occasions,
                yet to be determined (and this is far from an easy task and is largely an
                experimental practice; rarely a utilitarian one). Plus the institutional positioning
                of eResearch infrastructure in university service divisions, remote national
                services, and monolithic government and science-led programmes, means that the
                tradition of critique, and synthesis of eResearch infrastructure within contemporary
                digital humanities scholarship, is barely possible.</p>

                <div>
            <head>What can be done?</head>
            <p>As a trained historian and long-time digital humanities advocate who has benefited
                from investments in eResearch – and indeed, I am employed by a particularly flexible
                strategic eResearch programme in the State of Victoria in Australia – I caution
                against retreating too eagerly from the ‘infrastructure turn’ as there are still
                healthy opportunities in many countries between the cracks of otherwise clumsy
                agendas. However these opportunities need to be positioned within a research-led
                digital humanities agenda and not a science led-agenda (and there is a perhaps a
                dark side to the <hi rend="bold">#alt-ac</hi> movement in the United States if new
                digital outputs are not well supported within a humanities research setting)
                (Nowviskie 2011). </p>
            <p>Perhaps a better approach for the humanities than cambering to a science led
                ‘e-infrastructure’ funding model, along with its often abrasive tectonic plates of
                incongruous collaborations, would be to lobby for the funding model to strengthen
                digital humanities research. The digital humanities has a sophisticated
                international network of centres, undergraduate and graduate degrees, associations,
                conferences, journals, and research accountability structures that are largely <hi
                    rend="italic">internal</hi> to the humanities and is thus much better equipped
                to lead computing in the humanities than eResearch (and there are some positive
                institutional developments in this direction). And if led by the digital humanities,
                new research infrastructures such as data and text centres, virtual environments,
                and digital libraries would be more relevant to humanities research, thus insuring
                their long term sustainability. But this would require ‘e-infrastructure’ to be
                institutionalised in a much more responsive way; in a way that isn’t unequally
                coupled with the needs of science. Again Geoffrey Rockwell states:</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Perhaps things like the Text Encoding Initiative Guidelines are the
                        real infrastructure of humanities computing, and the consortia like the TEI
                        are the future of light and shared infrastructure maintenance</hi> (Rockwell
                    2010: 5).</p>
            <p>I would like to think that this is because the TEI and derivatives such as EpiDoc
                exist within a deeply scholarly and vibrant international research culture that is
                both embedded within and accountable to humanities research; this is not always the
                case with eResearch infrastructure. However, for the digital humanities to take a
                greater lead in terms of guiding the implementation of eResearch infrastructure, in
                its various institutional settings, would require the digital humanities to be
                strengthened institutionally to rise to the challenge, especially in countries where
                ‘eResearch’ is much stronger than the digital humanities. All infrastructure,
                despite its veneer of utilitarian simplicity, is ‘among the complex and expensive
                things that society creates’ (Hauser 2011). ‘e-Infrastructure’ for the humanities
                may provide opportunities, but aspects of the present model in various countries
                lacks a complex humanities research environment and is wedded to an empirical,
                engineering, and industrial instrumentalism that is often at odds or even hostile to
                the humanities. It is not that eResearch does not do some things very well, it is
                the promise of research that it doesn’t do particularly well. The goals of eResearch
                infrastructures are often so monumental; that they should perhaps be a set of
                research questions in themselves rather than practical goals. Based on my experience
                within eResearch and the digital humanities I will propose a number of alternative
                directions in this presentation and seek insight from others in the audience from
                various national and institutional contexts.</p>
                </div> 
               
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
                
                    
                            <p><hi rend="bold">Barjak, F., J. Lane, M. Poschen, R. Proctor, S.
                        Robinson, and G. Weigand </hi>(2010). e-Infrastructure adoption in the
                    social sciences and humanities: cross-national evidence from the AVROSS survey.
                        Info<hi rend="italic">rmation, Communication and Society</hi> 13(5):
                    635-651.</p>
                        
                            <p><hi rend="bold">Capshew, J. H., and K. A. Rader </hi>(1992). Big
                    science: price to the present. <hi rend="italic">Osiris</hi> 7: 2-25, <ref
                        target="http://www.jstor.org/stable/301765" type="external"
                        >http://www.jstor.org/stable/301765.</ref></p>
                        
                            <p><hi rend="bold">Edwards, P., S. Jackson, J. Bowker, and K.
                        Knobel</hi> (January, 2007). Understanding infrastructure: dynamics,
                    tension, design. <hi rend="italic">Report of a Workshop on History &amp; Theory
                        of Infrastructure: Lessons for New Scientific Cyberinfrastructures, Rice
                        University</hi>,<ref
                        target="http://cohesion.rice.edu/Conferences/Hewlett/emplibrary/UI_Final_Report.pdf"
                        type="external">
                        http://cohesion.rice.edu/Conferences/Hewlett/emplibrary/UI_Final_Report.pdf.</ref></p>
                       
                            <p><hi rend="bold">Hauser, Th. </hi>(2011). Cyberinfrastructure and data
                    management (presentation). Research Computing, University of Bolder, Colorado,
                        <ref
                        target="http://www.stonesoup.org/meetings/1106/work3.pres/2b-CI-DM-TH.htm"
                        type="external"
                        >http://www.stonesoup.org/meetings/1106/work3.pres/2b-CI-DM-TH.htm.</ref></p>
                        
                            <p><hi rend="bold">Katz, R. N. </hi>(2008). The tower and the cloud:
                    higher education in the age of cloud computing educause, <ref
                        target="http://net.educause.edu/ir/library/pdf/PUB7202.pdf" type="external"
                        >http://net.educause.edu/ir/library/pdf/PUB7202.pdf.</ref></p>
                        
                            <p><hi rend="bold">Nowviskie, B. </hi>(2011). #alt-ac Alternative
                    academic careers for humanities scholars, <ref
                        target="http://nowviskie.org/2010/alt-ac/" type="external"
                        >http://nowviskie.org/2010/alt-ac/ (accessed, 30 October, 2011).</ref></p>
                        
                            <p><hi rend="bold">Rockwell, G. </hi>(14 May 2010 <hi rend="bold"
                    >)</hi>. As Transparent as Infrastructure: On the research of
                    cyberinfrastructure in the humanities’. <hi rend="italic">Connexions</hi>, <ref
                        target="http://cnx.org/content/m34315/1.2/" type="external"
                        >http://cnx.org/content/m34315/1.2/</ref></p>
                <p><ref target="http://www.acls.org/cyberinfrastructure/ourculturalcommonwealth.pdf" type="external">http://www.acls.org/cyberinfrastructure/ourculturalcommonwealth.pdf.</ref></p>
                        
                            <p><hi rend="bold">Svennsson, P.</hi> (2011). From optical fibre to
                    conceptual cyberinfrastucture. <hi rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities
                        Quarterly</hi> 5(1), <ref
                        target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000090/000090.html"
                        type="external"
                        >http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000090/000090.html.</ref></p>
                        <p><hi rend="bold">Turner, G.</hi> (September, 2008), Report from the HASS
                    capability workshop, Old Canberra House, Australian National University, 15
                    August 2008 (unpublished report).</p><p><hi rend="bold">Turner, G.</hi> (2009). Towards and Australian Humanities Digital Archive. A
                    report of a scoping study of the establishment of a national digital research
                    resource for the humanities, Australian Academy of the Humanities, <ref
                        target="http://www.humanities.org.au/Portals/0/documents/Policy/Research/Towards_An_Australian_Digital_Humanities_Archive.pdf"
                        type="external"
                        >http://www.humanities.org.au/Portals/0/documents/Policy/Research/Towards_An_Australian_Digital_Humanities_Archive.pdf</ref></p><p><hi rend="bold">Unsworth, J.,</hi> Chair (2006) ‘Our cultural commonwealth: The report of the
                    American Council of Learned Societies Commission on Cyberinfrastructure for the
                    Humanities and Social Sciences, American council of learned societies. </p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>