<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-257">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Engaging the Museum Space: Mobilising Visitor Engagement with Digital Content Creation</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Ross, Claire Stephanie</name>
                    <affiliation>University College London, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>claire.ross@ucl.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Gray, Steven</name>
                    <affiliation>University College London, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>steven.gray@ucl.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Warwick, Claire</name>
                    <affiliation>University College London, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>c.warwick@ucl.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Hudson Smith, Andrew</name>
                    <affiliation>University College London, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>a.hudson-smith@ucl.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Terras, Melissa</name>
                    <affiliation>University College London, UK</affiliation>
                    <email>m.terras@ucl.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>The following paper presents the results of the QRator research project which aims to
                understand how digital technologies, such as interactive labels and smart phones,
                create new ways for users to engage with museum objects; investigate the value and
                constraints of digital sources and methods involving cultural content; and
                demonstrate how crowdsourced digital interpretation may be utilised as a research
                source. </p>
            <p>Museum exhibitions have been transformed by the addition of digital technology to
                enhance the visitor experience. Ubiquitous mobile technologies offer museum
                professionals new ways of personally engaging visitors with content, creating new
                relationships between museums and their users. Museums and other cultural
                institutions have made significant investments in developing and disseminating
                digital content in the physical museum space to reach and engage users, marking a
                shift in how museums communicate publicly their role as custodians of cultural
                content and their attitude towards cultural authority. Despite recent technical
                advances in collections access and interpretation, a number of key issues still
                remain. Does the rapidly changing technological environment provide a more engaging
                and participatory visitor experience?</p>
            <p>The QRator project explores how mobile devices and interactive digital labels can
                create new models for public engagement, visitor meaning-making and the construction
                of multiple interpretations inside museum spaces. This project is located within the
                emerging technological and cultural phenomenon known as ‘The Internet of Things’;
                the technical and social shift that is anticipated as society moves to a ubiquitous
                form of computing in which every device is ‘on’, and connected to the Internet.
                QRator is based on ‘Tales of things’ (<ref target="http://www.talesofthings.com"
                type="external">http://www.talesofthings.com</ref>) which has developed a ‘method for cataloguing
                physical objects online which could make museums and galleries a more interactive
                experience’ (Giles 2010). QRator takes the technology a step further, allowing users
                to take part in content creation on digital interactive labels- static iPads and
                their own mobile phones: a sustainable model for two-way public interaction in
                museum spaces. The QRator project uses iPads installed in the UCL Grant Museum of
                Zoology to provide a fully interactive experience where visitors respond to
                questions posed by the curators, contribute to discussions, and leave comments about
                individual exhibits. Visitors’ comments are synchronised with the QRator website
                (<ref target="http://www.qrator.org" type="external">http://www.qrator.org</ref>) to allow them to
                contribute to the continuing discussion away from a museum setting. The application
                provides each exhibit with a QR code, a matrix barcode that embeds information such
                as text or an URL within a graphic that users can read using mobile devices, which
                links the physical exhibit with the associated conversations. When scanned these
                codes allow users to discover information about an object and join the conversation
                from their own mobile device. The unpredictable, multiple forms of interpretation
                produced by the use of mobile devices and interactive labels make us to reconsider
                ways in which museums provide information about objects and collections and should
                also allow museums to become more engaging for visitors.</p>
            <div>
                <head>Methodology</head>
                <p>Data from the ten QRator iPads was collected by archiving contributions from
                    March to July 2011; each individual visitor contribution is simultaneously
                    uploaded to the master database on the Tales of Things website, followed by the
                    QRator website pulling the data about each case label (current question) from
                    the master database and integrates these comments within QRator online. These
                    comments are then aggregated together based on the current questions originally
                    asked by the museum. This resulted in a corpus of 1463 visitor contributions,
                    totalling 13,308 words and 2,708 unique tokens, providing a rich dataset for the
                    analysis of visitor experience.</p>
                <p>Visitor contributions were categorized qualitatively using open coded content
                    analysis where each comment was read and categorized. Contributions were divided
                    into three basic categories; about the current question or topic, about the
                    museum, or noise. Despite the apparently simplistic categorisation it is
                    possible to discover patterns of use and begin to understand how visitors are
                    relating to and interpreting the exhibitions, and making meaning from their
                    experience. </p>
                <p>For the purpose of this study, various quantitative measures were used such as
                    analysing the frequency of comments according to date and time, comparing
                    comment rate between the ten iPad’s and suitable text analysis tools were used
                    to interrogate the corpus. One of these purpose built tools emulates the popular
                    Wordle<note><ref target="http://www.wordle.net/" type="external">http://www.wordle.net/</ref></note> visualisation where the frequency of words
                    within the whole corpus is sized in relation to the words font size. This tool
                    provided more stylistic control over the visualisation than other web-based
                    services like Wordle. In addition, the corpus was analysed using a Sentiment
                    analysis tool, SentiStrength<note><ref target="http://sentistrength.wlv.ac.uk/"
                    >http://sentistrength.wlv.ac.uk/</ref></note> developed by Thelwall et
                    al, (forthcoming), in order to automatically measure emotion in the visitor
                    comments, which provides an indication of a positive or negative museum
                    experience. </p>
                
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Findings</head>
                
                    <p>The largest proportion of the comments in the corpus fell into the category
                        of topic (42%), triggered predominately by the QRator interface and
                        questions posed by the museum curators, suggesting that visitors are
                        inspired to share their own experiences, thus co-constructing a public
                        multiple interpretation of museum objects. This is very pleasing, since this
                        was exactly what the museum professionals had hoped might happen.</p>
                    <p>The lack of spam and inappropriate commenting is surprising (22%). Many
                        museums have been hesitant to open up commu­nication to greater
                        participation by visitors. There is an ingrained fear in the museum
                        profession that visitors will leave inappropriate comments when there is no
                        moderation or intervention by the museum (Russo et al. 2008) despite
                        research showing that museum visitors want to engage with complex,
                        controversial topics by making comments or talking to staff and other
                        visitors (Kelly 2006). The QRator project and the Grant Museum have,
                        however, adopted the concept of ‘radical trust’ in the visitor
                        community:</p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">‘Radical trust is about trusting the community. We know
                            that abuse can happen, but we trust (radically) that the community and
                            participation will work. In the real world, we know that vandalism
                            happens but we still put art and sculpture up in our parks. As an online
                            community we come up with safeguards or mechanisms that help keep open
                            contribution and participation working</hi><hi rend="italic">’</hi>
                        (Fichter 2006). </p>
                    <p>Inherent in the term is the suggestion of a previous lack of trust shown by
                        museums towards visitors, but also the admission that such trust is regarded
                        as new and perhaps dangerous. Nevertheless, the QRator data suggests that
                        ‘radical trust’ in visitors does indeed work: spamming and inappropriate
                        commenting does not appear to have happened to a significant extent in the
                        Grant Museum. </p>
                    <p>Interestingly, many of the visitor comments focused on opinions of the museum
                        as a whole (36%). This raises the question of whether a digital technology
                        used in this way promotes of an opportunity for visitors to make meaning
                        from their whole experience, rather than engage with the exhibit specific
                        content and interpret the exhibitions themselves.  </p>
                    <p>The length of comment may also be used as an indicator of engagement- if we
                        assume that those who are interested in an issue or topic may wish to write
                        at greater length. Indeed the average length of comment increased
                        significantly between categories. The noise category had an average of
                        4.071429 words, comments on the museum had 7.431599 words and visitor
                        contributions on topic had an average of 15.36672 words. This is pleasing,
                        since it suggests that visitors were inspired by the questions to engage
                        with topics in a relatively complex fashion. Additionally when compared to
                        the SentiStrength results, which classifies for positive and negative
                        sentiment on a scale of 1 (no sentiment) to 5 (very strong positive/negative
                        sentiment), highlights that the comments on the museum were in average more
                        positive in sentiment (2.04 positive) whereas the comments on topic had an
                        equal positive to negative response (1.52 positive; 1.55 negative).
                        Suggesting more engaged texts often contain a mix of positive and negative
                        sentiment, in contrast to less engagement which is more likely to produce a
                        single sentiment result. </p></div>
                
                <div>
                    <head>Conclusion</head>
                    <p>Digital technologies are becoming more embedded, ubiquitous and
                    networked, with enhanced capabilities for rich social interactions, context
                    awareness and connectivity. This has led to unprecedented changes in the
                    provision of digital museum resources, which are beginning to transform the
                    experience of visiting museums. The QRator project represents a shift in how
                    cultural organisations act as trusted and authoritarian institutions;
                    communicate knowledge to the community; and integrate their role as keepers of
                    cultural content with their responsibility to facilitate access to content. It
                    also suggests that users are willing to take part in a dialogue, and express
                    their views about their visit and individual object via digital technologies. It
                    further suggests that in most cases they can be trusted to do so in a
                    thoughtful, serious fashion. The challenges that digital technology and
                    participatory media bring to museums demonstrate a change from a one to many
                    transmission to a many to many interaction, in which museums use their own voice
                    and au­thority to encourage participatory communication and content creation
                    with visitors. The growing emphasis on the interactional and informal nature of
                    learning in museums provides the perfect opportunity to showcase digital
                    interactive technologies as important resources for engaging visitors in
                    exhibits and more generally in museums as a whole (Thomas &amp; Mintz 1998;
                    Marty &amp; Burton Jones 2007; Heath &amp; vom Lehm 2010). </p></div>
                
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Acknowledgments</hi></p>
                <p>The authors of this paper would like to acknowledge the other members of the
                    QRator team: Jack Ashby and March Carnall (UCL Grant Museum of Zoology), Sally
                    MacDonald (UCL Museums and Public Engagement), Sussanah Chan (UCL) and
                    Emma-Louise Nicholls (UCL Grant Museum of Zoology). QRator was funded through
                    Beacons for Public Engagement Innovation Seed funding and we would like to thank
                    Hilary Jackson (UCL Public Engagement) for her support and advice throughout the
                    project.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Fichter, D.</hi> (2006). Web 2.0, library 2.0 and radical trust:
                    A first take. April 2. Accessed 27th October 2011 at <ref
                        target="http://library2.usask.ca/~fichter/blog_on_the_side/2006/04/web-2.html" type="external"
                    >http://library2.usask.ca/~fichter/blog_on_the_side/2006/04/web-2.html.</ref></p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Giles, J.</hi> (2010). Barcodes help objects tell their stories.
                        <hi rend="italic">New Scientist</hi> (17th April, 2010).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Heath, C., and D. vom Lehn</hi> (2010). Interactivity and
                    Collaboration: new forms of participation in museums, galleries and science
                    centres. In R. Parry (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Museums in a Digital Age</hi>.
                    Abingdon: Routledge, pp. 266-280.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Kelly, L.</hi> (2006). Museums as sources of information and
                    learning: The decision-making process. <hi rend="italic">Open Museum
                        Journal</hi> 8, accessed at <ref
                        target="http://archive.amol.org.au/omj/volume8/volume8_index.asp" type="external"
                    >http://archive.amol.org.au/omj/volume8/volume8_index.asp.</ref></p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Marty, P., and K. Burton Jones</hi> (2007). <hi rend="italic"
                        >Museum Informatics: People, Information, and Technology in Museums</hi>.
                    New York: Routledge.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Russo, A., J. Watkins,L. Kelly, and S. Chan</hi> (2008).
                    Participatory communication with social media. <hi rend="italic">Curator</hi>
                    51(1): 21-31.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Thelwall, M., K. Buckley, G. Paltoglou, D. Cai, and A.
                        Kappas</hi> (forthcoming). Sentiment strength detection in short informal
                    text. <hi rend="italic">Journal of the American Society for Information Science
                        and Technology</hi>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Thomas, S., and A. Mintz, eds</hi>. (1998). <hi rend="italic">The
                        Virtual and the Real: Media in the Museum</hi>. Washington, DC: American
                    Association of Museums.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>