<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-268">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Using the Google Ngram Corpus to Measure Cultural Complexity</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Juola, Patrick</name>
                    <affiliation>Duquesne University, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>juola@mathcs.duq.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>It is common to hear assertions that culture is complex, that language is
                    complex, and that while the complexity of language is a universal constant, the
                    complexity of culture is increasing as technology and the increased pace of
                    modern life creates new complexities. These statements are usually based on
                    subjective assessments, often tinged by nostalgia for the ‘good old days.’ Can
                    questions of cultural complexity be addressed quantitatively?</p>
                <p>Previous
                    work (e.g. Juola 1997, 2008) has been able to use information theory to address
                    this question. The basic idea is that a sample of language is ‘complex’ if it
                    contains a lot of information, defined formally as the size of the computer
                    program that would be necessary to (re)create the sample from scratch, a measure
                    more formally known as Kolmogorov complexity. This can be approximated by
                    compressing the text sample and looking at the size of the resulting file – the
                    larger the resulting file, the more complex the original. Alternatively, one can
                    compute complexity directly using Shannon’s (1948) famous formula for
                    information entropy based on a concept of the underlying linguistic ‘events.’ In
                    any case, linguistic complexity can be measured observing discourse-controlled
                    samples of language, essentially by comparing several (linguistic) versions of
                    the same text, such as translations of the Bible or of a specific novel, and
                    observing whether one language yields systematically larger measurements than
                    another. Previous work suggests that no such systematic pattern exists, and that
                    all languages are indeed roughly equal in complexity.</p>
                <p>Key to this
                    approach is the idea of discourse control; we are measuring how difficult it is
                    to express a specific fixed concept in a given language and comparing it to the
                    same concept expressed in an another language. Culture, however, can be treated
                    as the set of concepts that people choose to express. By eliminating the
                    restriction of discourse control and instead investigating language chosen
                    freely by the cultural participants, we may be able to tease apart the
                    interaction between cultural and linguistic complexity. In particular, we can
                    distinguish between linguistic and cultural complexity as follows: a language is
                    complex if there is a lot of information contained in a topic-controlled
                    discourse. A culture is complex if there is a large range of topics for
                    discourse, or alternatively a lot of information contained in topical choice.
                    Therefore, if we compare the complexity (however measured) of two language
                    samples that are not topic-controlled, but instead are in some sense
                    representative of the breadth of discourse present in a culture, we can
                    calculate the differences attributable to discourse variation, and hence to
                    cultural complexity.</p>
                <p>As an illustrative example, we follow the approach
                    of Spenser (1900; cited by Denton 2004), in that ‘complex’ means ‘containing
                    many different interdependent parts.’ A complex political system has many
                    parties and power groups, many different roles and offices, and many
                    relationships among them. In a political discourse, many if not most of these
                    parties and power groups would need to be explicitly named and distinguished
                    from each other. By contrast, an autocratic monarchy is relatively simple: there
                    is the monarch and then everyone else. A game is complex if it has many rules
                    and strategies. A culture is complex if it contains many heterogeneous aspects
                    such as technological specifications, social stratification, multilevel
                    administrative hierarchies, or a large amount of object or object-types.
                    Continuing this line of reasoning, a complex culture is one with lots of ‘stuff’
                    and where people do lots of things to or with ‘stuff,’ where ‘stuff’ here refers
                    not only to physical objects but also to people, groups, activities,
                    abstractions, and so forth – anything that can be discussed among the group.</p>
                <p>We therefore apply the previous methodology to a different sort of corpus; an
                    uncontrolled corpus that represents the breadth of cultural experience. If the
                    information contained in such a corpus is high, then we can say the culture is
                    complex. Several corpora may be suitable for this purpose; we have chosen to
                    study the Google Books Ngram Corpus (Michel et al. 2010). This contains all of
                    the n-grams from the millions of books in the Google Books database, something
                    like 20 million books, or approximately 4% of all books ever printed. While not
                    strictly speaking representative (for example, ‘publishing was a relatively rare
                    event in the 16th and 17th centuries,’ and ‘many more books are published in
                    modern years’), and of course typically only the literate can write or publish
                    books, this nevertheless gives us a time-stamped window into the scope of
                    culture. Furthermore, by focusing on n-grams (and specifically on 2-grams, word
                    pairs), we can observe not only the distribution of ‘stuff,’ but also some of
                    the relationships between ‘stuff’ – for example, the number and range of word
                    pairs beginning with ‘expensive’ will inform us about changing opinions
                    regarding money and the types of goods considered luxurious and pricey.</p>
                <p>We therefore used the Google Books American 2-Gram Corpus to measure changes
                    in the complexity of American culture at ten-year intervals between 1900 and
                    2000. This corpus simply contains a frequency list of all two word phrases used
                    in American-published books in any given year. For example, the phrase
                    ‘hamburgers with’ appeared only 8 times in print in 1940, compared to 45 in the
                    year 2000. Focusing strictly on the US during the 20th century avoids many of
                    the problems with mass culture, as publishing was a well-established industry
                    and literacy was widespread. However, the number of books published in this time
                    of course tended to increase. Our first observation, then, is that culture may
                    be increasing simply from the number of different things to talk about. The
                    number of different word pair types per year increased dramatically, nearly
                    doubling from 1900 to 2000, as given in table 1.</p>
                
                <table>
                    <head>Table 1</head>
                    
                    <row>
                        <cell> Year </cell>
                        <cell> # types </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1900 </cell>
                        <cell> 17,769,755 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1910 </cell>
                        <cell> 22,834,741 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1920 </cell>
                        <cell> 22,409,426 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1930 </cell>
                        <cell> 19,745,549 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1940 </cell>
                        <cell> 20,369,679 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1950 </cell>
                        <cell> 23,632,749 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1960 </cell>
                        <cell> 27,379,411 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1970 </cell>
                        <cell> 34,218,686 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1980 </cell>
                        <cell> 34,458,083 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1990 </cell>
                        <cell> 37,796,626 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 2000 </cell>
                        <cell> 41,654,264 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                
                <p>This alone indicates an increase in the complexity of written culture,
                    although this process is not continuous and some years during the Depression
                    show a loss. To confirm the overall upward trend, we have also calculated the
                    Shannon-entropy of the 2-gram distributions, attached as table 2.</p>
                
                <table>
                    <head>Table 2</head>
                    
                    <row>
                        <cell> Year </cell>
                        <cell> Entropy (bits) </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1900 </cell>
                        <cell> 17.942357 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1910 </cell>
                        <cell> 18.072880 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1920 </cell>
                        <cell> 18.072325 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1930 </cell>
                        <cell> 18.133058 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1940 </cell>
                        <cell> 18.241048 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1950 </cell>
                        <cell> 18.336162 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1960 </cell>
                        <cell> 18.391872 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1970 </cell>
                        <cell> 18.473447 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1980 </cell>
                        <cell> 18.692278 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 1990 </cell>
                        <cell> 18.729807 </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell> 2000 </cell>
                        <cell> 18.742085 </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                
                <p>This further analysis illustrates that a more sophisticated measure of
                    complexity shows a continuous process of increasing complexity, even in times
                    when (for example due to economic downturn) the actual volume of words published
                    decreases. Even when people are writing less, they still have more ‘stuff’ about
                    which to write, showing the cumulative nature of culture (today’s current events
                    are tomorrow’s history, but still suitable material for discussion and analysis
                    – part of culture).</p>
                <p>We acknowledge that this is a preliminary study
                    only. Google Books offers cultural snapshots at much greater frequency than
                    ten-year intervals. Google Books also offers corpora in other languages
                    (including German, French, Spanish, Russian, and Hebrew) as well as another
                    English-speaking culture. Use of a more balanced corpus (such as the Google
                    Books English Million corpus, a corpus balanced at about 1 million words/year to
                    offset increased publication), or the BYU Corpus of Historical American English
                    might help clarify the effects of publication volume. Analysis of n-grams at
                    sizes other than 2 would illustrate other types of complexity -- in particular,
                    1-grams (words) would show changes in lexical but not syntactic complexity and
                    hence an analysis of ‘stuff’ but not what people do with ‘stuff.’ Despite these
                    weaknesses, we still feel this paper illustrates that culture-wide analysis of
                    abstractions like ‘increasing complexity’ is both practical and fruitful.</p>
               </div>
            
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <head>References</head>
                   
            <p><hi rend="bold">Denton, T.</hi> (2004). Cultural Complexity Revisited. <hi
                    rend="italic">Cross-Cultural Research</hi> 38(1): 3-26.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold"
                    >Juola, P.</hi> (1998). Measuring Linguistic Complexity : The Morphological
                Tier. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Quantitative Linguistics</hi> 5(3): 206-213.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Juola, P..</hi> (2008). Assessing Linguistic Complexity. In M.
                Miestamo, K. Sinnemaki, and F. Karlsson (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Language
                    Complexity: Typology, Contact, Change</hi>. Amsterdam: John Benjamins.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Michel, Jean-Baptiste, Y. Kui Shen, A. Presser Aiden, A.
                    Veres, M. K. Gray, W. Brockman, The Google Books Team, J. P. Pickett, D.
                    Hoiberg, D. Clancy, P. Norvig, J. Orwant, St. Pinker, M. A. Nowak, and E.
                    Lieberman Aiden</hi> (2010). Quantitative Analysis of Culture Using Millions of
                Digitized Books. <hi rend="italic">Science</hi> (Published online ahead of print:
                12/16/2010).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Spencer, H.</hi> (1900). <hi rend="italic">First principles</hi> (6th ed.). Akron, OH: Werner.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>