<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-313">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>May Humanists Learn from Artists a New Way to Interact with Digital Technology?</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Franchi, Stefano</name>
                    <affiliation>Texas A&amp;M University, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>stefano@tamu.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Takeovers</head>
                <p>The two best-known interactions between computational technologies and
                    traditional Humanist pursuits are represented by the Artificial
                    Intelligence/Cognitive science movement and the roughly contemporary Digital
                    Humanities approach (although the label became popular only recently). Classic
                    Artificial Intelligence saw itself as ‘anti-philosophy’ (Dupuy 2000; Agre 2005;
                    Franchi 2006): it was the discipline that could take over philosophy’s
                    traditional questions about rationality, the mind/body problem, creative
                    thinking, perception, and so on, and solve them with the help of a set of
                    radically new synthetic, experimentally based techniques. The true meaning of
                    the ‘computational turn in philosophy’ lies in its methodology, which allowed it
                    to associate engineering techniques with age-old philosophical questions. This
                    ‘imperialist’ tendency of cognitive science (Dupuy 2000) was present from the
                    very beginning, even before the formalization of the field into well – defined
                    theoretical approaches (McCulloch 1989 [1948]; Simon 1994). </p>
                <p>The Digital Humanities represent the reverse modality of the encounter just
                    described. The most common approach (Kirschenbau 2010) uses tools, techniques,
                    and algorithms developed by computer scientists to address traditional questions
                    about the meaning of texts, their accessibility and interpretation, and so on.
                    Other approaches turn technology into the scholar’s preferred object of study
                    (Svensson 2010). The recent approach pioneered by the ‘Philosophy of
                    Information’ (Floridi 1999, 2011) follows this pattern. Its focus on the much
                    broader category of ‘information’ substantially increases the scope of its
                    inquiries, while firmly keeping it within philosophy’s standard reflective mode. </p>
                <p>The common feature of these two classic encounters between the Humanities and
                    computational theory and technology is their one-sidedness. In either case, one
                    of the two partners took over some relevant aspects from the other participant
                    and fit it within its own field of inquiry (mostly questions, in AI’s case;
                    mostly tools, for the Digital Humanities). The appropriation, however, did not
                    alter the theoretical features of either camp. For instance, AI and Cognitive
                    Science researchers maintained that philosophy pre-scientific methodology had
                    only produced mere speculation that made those problems unsolvable. Therefore,
                    philosophy’s accumulated wealth of reflection about the mind, rationality,
                    perception, memory, emotions, and so forth could not be used by the
                    computational approach. In McCulloch’s famous phrase, the ‘den of the
                    metaphysician is strewn with the bones of researchers past.’ In the Digital
                    Humanities’ case, the takeover happens at the level of tools. In most cases,
                    however, this appropriation does not become an opportunity for a critical
                    reflection on the role of the canon on liberal education, or for a reappraisal
                    of the role of the text and the social, political, and moral roles it plays in
                    society at large. </p>
                <p>
                    <lb/>
                    <lb/>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> Artistic Digital Practices</head>
                
                    <p>Meetings between artists and computational technology show the possibility of
                        a different paradigm. In many cases, making music, painting, producing
                        installations, and writing with a computer changes the concepts artists work
                        with, and, at the same time, forces computer sciences to change theirs as
                        well. There are many examples in the rich history of ‘digital art,’ broadly
                        understood (OuLiPo 1973; <hi rend="italic">ALAMO (Atelier de Littérature
                            Assistée par la Mathématique et les Ordinateurs)</hi>; Schaeffer 1952).
                        I will illustrate their general features with reference to two more recent
                        projects: the ‘microsound’ approach to musical composition (Roads 2004) and
                        the T-Garden approach to agency (Sha 2002). </p>
                    <p>‘Microsounds’ are sonic objects whose timescale lies between that of <hi
                        rend="italic">notes </hi><hi rend="italic">–</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>the
                    smallest traditional music objects, whose duration is measured in seconds or
                    fractions thereof – and <hi rend="italic">samples </hi><hi rend="italic"
                        >–</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi>the smallest bit, measured in microseconds
                        (10<hi rend="sup">-6</hi>). The manipulation of microsounds broadens substantially the composer’s
                    palette, but it is impossible without the help of technological devices of
                    various kinds, from granular synthesis software to high-level mixing interfaces.
                    Composers wishing to ‘sculpt’ sounds at the microlevel face a double challenge
                    that translates into a mutual collaboration between compositional and
                    algorithmic techniques. On the one hand, they need to broaden the syntax an
                    grammar of music’s language to allow the manipulation and aesthetic assessment
                    of previously unheard of objects (Vaggione 2001). On the other hand, they need
                    computer scientists and mathematicians to develop alternative analytic and
                    synthetic models of sound (in addition to Fourier-transforms and similar
                    methods) capable of capturing the features of sonic events lasting only a few
                    milliseconds (Vaggione 1996). </p>
                    <p>The T-Garden environment produced at the Topological Media Lab follows a
                        structurally similar paradigm. It is a closed room within which people
                        wearing wireless sensors on their chest and limbs can project images and
                        sounds on the room’s walls and ceiling. As the participants move around,
                        their gestures across the floor perturb the preexisting sonic and visual
                        fields, thereby modifying it and introducing new aural and visual patterns.
                        As Sha describes it: </p>
                    <p><hi rend="italic">[The environment] was built to explore how people can
                        improvise gestures out of dense, evolving fields of media. In ordinary
                        informal conversation, you can spontaneously drag or pitch your speech to
                        express irony, sympathy, and so forth. Similarly, in a T-Garden, by waving
                        your arm you write video or leave a trace in sound, and by moving about the
                        space, solo or in concert with other people, you construct a voice for
                        yourself out of a sound field that is summed from all the instrumental
                        voices in the room. […] as you play, your continuous motions create an aural
                        and visual ‘voice’ for yourself out of the ambient perceptual field</hi>
                    (Sha 2002: 441-442).  </p>
                    <p>Whereas Roads explored a new sonic object lying between samples and notes,
                        Sha investigated a segment of human agency that is neither fully free nor
                        fully constrained. He took human gestures as a proxy for agency in general
                        and conceived a project that demanded theoretical and technical work on two
                        fronts. On the artistic side, it mandated the translation of a theoretical
                        reflection upon the status of semiotic structures into a concrete
                        installation. It required the construction of an event that forced the
                        participants to reassess their conception of communication and ‘freedom of
                        speech.’ On the technical sides, it forced the computer scientists to
                        develop real-time systems capable of interpreting human gestures and
                        translating them into sonic and visual equivalents the participants could
                        reintegrate into their communicative actions. </p>
                    <p>These two examples points to a pattern of cooperation between work in
                        computational and non-computational disciplines that is deeply at odds with
                        the AI/CogSci and DigHum patterns discussed above. Instead of a takeover,
                        the artistic model produces a true encounter that changes both partners’
                        technical and theoretical apparatus. </p></div>
                
                <div>
                    <head>
                    <hi rend="bold">Digital Theoretical <hi rend="italic">Poiesis</hi></hi>
                </head>
                <p>Could the interaction pattern most favored by artists be generalized to the
                    Humanities? With the help of Aristotle’s classification of human activity as <hi
                        rend="italic">poiesis</hi>, <hi rend="italic">praxis</hi>, and <hi
                        rend="italic">theoria</hi> (Aristotle 1984, 1025b19-30, p. 1619), it could
                    be objected that artistic practices are examples of <hi rend="italic"
                        >poiesis</hi>. They produce objects on the basis of materials and
                    manipulating tools. Anything (including digital tools) that provides new
                    materials (material substrate) or new ways of organizing them will necessarily
                    change artistic practices. And artists have always been extremely keen on
                    expanding their material and formal palettes, long before the advent of digital
                    techniques. The daily work of Humanists, it could be claimed, is essentially <hi
                        rend="italic">theoretical</hi>, since their task is to critically reflect
                    upon a previously produced reality. </p>
                <p>Paradoxically, however, a serious critical engagement with contemporary reality
                    shows that the Aristotelian tripartite distinction is untenable in the current
                    landscape. How can Humanities’ traditional inquiries about human nature and
                    human cultural production still be relevant in a landscape in which some of the
                    communicating agents may not be human, partially or entirely? Can they go on in
                    the same way? And <hi rend="italic">vice versa</hi>: are science and technology
                    fully aware that the new digital artifacts they are shepherding into the world
                    may change its landscape and transform worldly action at the pragmatic as well
                    as at the theoretical level? Or are they still relying upon a pre-digital
                    universe in which technological artifacts were always to be used as mere tools
                    deployed by humans, an assumption that seems increasingly questionable? The
                    genuine challenge Humanists face when confronting the ‘computational turn’
                    demands a truly poietic effort. Humanists will have to engage in the
                    constructions of new concepts in a close peer-to-peer interaction with the
                    ‘sciences of the artificial’ (Cordeschi 2002) that may result in a form of
                    ‘digital theoretical <hi rend="italic">poiesis</hi>’ much closer to artistic
                    practice than to their traditional forms of inquiry. </p>
                <p>This suggestion does not pretend to exhaust the theoretical options we have at
                    our disposal when reflecting upon the computational turn. There are certainly
                    other views that may legitimately claim to be seeking the same goal. My
                    contention, however, is that artistic practices in all forms of ‘digital art’
                    can serve as an inspiration to all of the Humanities disciplines. We can follow
                    their path toward a new mode of digital encounter that does not fall into the
                    well-worn path of hostile takeovers by either partner. </p>
                </div>
            
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Agre, P. E.</hi> (2005). The Soul Gained and Lost: Artificial
                    Intelligence as Philosophical Project. In S. Franchi and G. Güzeldere (eds.),
                        <hi rend="italic">Mechanical Bodies, Computational Minds</hi>. Cambridge,
                    Mass.: MIT Press.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">ALAMO (Atelier de Littérature Assistée par la Mathématique et les
                        Ordinateurs).</hi>
                    <ref target="http://alamo.mshparisnord.org/index.html" type="external"
                        >http://alamo.mshparisnord.org/index.html</ref> (accessed 24 March
                    2012).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Aristotle</hi> (1984). <hi rend="italic">The complete works of
                        Aristotle</hi>. Ed. by J. Barnes. Princeton, NJ: Princeton UP. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Cordeschi, R.</hi> (2002). <hi rend="italic">Discovery of the
                        Artificial: Behavior, Mind, and Machines Before and Beyond Cybernetics</hi>.
                    Dordrecht: Kluwer. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Dupuy, J.-P.</hi> (2000). <hi rend="italic">The Mechanization of
                        the Mind: On the Origins of Cognitive Science</hi>. Princeton, N.J.:
                    Princeton UP. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Floridi, L.</hi> (1999). <hi rend="italic">Philosophy and
                        Computing: An Introduction</hi>. London, New York: Routledge. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Floridi, L. </hi>(2011). <hi rend="italic">The Philosophy of
                        Information</hi>. Oxford: Oxford UP.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Franchi, S.</hi> (2006). Herbert Simon, Anti-Philosopher. In L.
                    Magnani (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Computing and Philosophy, </hi>Pavia:
                    Associated International Academic Publishers, pp. 27-40. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Kirschenbau, M. G.</hi> (2010). What Is Digital humanities and
                    What’s It Doing in English Departments? <hi rend="italic">ADE Bullettin</hi>
                    150: 1-7. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">McCulloch, W. S.</hi> (1989[1948]). Through the Den of the
                    Metaphysician. In W. S.  McCulloch, <hi rend="italic">Embodiments of Mind</hi>.
                    Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press, pp. 142-156. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">OuLiPo</hi> (1973). <hi rend="italic">La littérature
                        potentielle</hi>. Paris: Gallimard. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Roads, C.</hi> (2004). <hi rend="italic">Microsound</hi>.
                    Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Schaeffer, P.</hi> (1952). <hi rend="italic">À la recherche d’une
                        musique concrète</hi>. Paris: Seuil. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Sha, X.</hi> (2002). Resistance Is Fertile: Gesture and Agency in
                    the Field of Responsive Media. <hi rend="italic">Configurations</hi> 10(3):
                    439-472. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Simon, H.</hi> (1994). Literary Criticism: a Cognitive Approach.
                    In S. Franchi and G. Güzeldere (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Bridging the Gap,</hi>
                    Vol. 4. 1. <hi rend="italic">Stanford Humanities Review</hi>, Special
                    Supplement, pp. 1-26. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Svensson, P.</hi> (Summer 2010). The Landscape of Digital
                    Humanities. <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</hi> 4(1). </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Vaggione, H.</hi> (1996). Articulating Microtime <hi
                        rend="italic">Computer Music Journal</hi> 20(2): 33-38. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Vaggione, H.</hi> (2001). Some Ontological Remarks about Music
                    Composition Processes. <hi rend="italic">Computer Music Journal</hi> 25(1):
                    54-61.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>