<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-372">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Contours of the Past: Computationally Exploring Civil Rights Histories</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Shaw, Ryan Benjamin</name>
                    <affiliation>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>ryanshaw@unc.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Historical insight is only achieved when the contours of our
                        view of the past are as clear as possible.</hi></p>
            <p>(Frank Ankersmit)</p>
            <p>Each history provides a unique view of the past by picking out a path through the
                field of possible events (Veyne 1984: 36). And because histories respond to earlier
                histories, their paths intersect. At these intersections lie events which become
                taken for granted as ‘sites to be visited’ on ‘a pre-arranged itinerary marking out
                the recommended scenic route (and the beaten track) from one major point of interest
                to the next’ (Rigney 1990: 37). Some of these itineraries are then reified as
                periods. </p><p>If we accept these itineraries too readily, we risk missing opportunities for new insights.
                Historical insight results not just from the accumulation of new facts about the
                past, but from the development of new views upon the facts we already know. The more
                stories we have about some piece of the past, ‘the deeper our insight into it will
                be […] because only the presence of other stories enables us to draw the contours
                and to recognize the specificity of the view of the past presented in each one’
                (Ankersmit 1983: 219).</p><p>In 1983, Frank Ankersmit theorized a
                    procedure for drawing these contours by clustering stories that contain
                    overlapping sets of propositions. By taking a set of stories about a person,
                    place, or period, transforming each story into a list of propositions, and
                    aligning them in such a way that the lists could be compared, Ankersmit posited
                    that ‘certain classificatory patterns [would] automatically appear’ (Ankersmit,
                    1983: 145).</p><p>The <hi rend="italic">Contours of the Past</hi> project is
                    testing Ankersmit’s theory by building tools for comparing and contrasting
                    histories of the civil rights movement. The historiography of the civil rights
                    movement exemplifies how periods coalesce around dominant stories. The first
                    generation of civil rights scholars ‘conceived of the civil rights struggle as
                    primarily a political movement that secured legislative and judicial triumphs’
                    (Lawson 1991). The chronology of this movement began with <hi rend="italic"
                        >Brown v. Board of Education of Topeka</hi> in 1954 and ended with the
                    Voting Rights Act of 1965. Due in part to intense media coverage, by the end of
                    the twentieth century this chronology had become a well-beaten path not only
                    among scholars but also in popular understanding.</p><p>In the past decade, a
                    new generation of scholars has sought to broaden this itinerary, telling ‘the
                    story of a ‘long civil rights movement’ that took root in the liberal and
                    radical milieu of the late 1930s, was intimately tied to the ‘rise and fall of
                    the New Deal Order,’ accelerated during World War II, [and] stretched far beyond
                    the South’ (Hall 2005). The concept of the Long Civil Rights Movement (LCRM) is
                    about more than simply replacing one story with a new one. By widening the scope
                    of the civil rights movement, the LCRM opens space for a greater diversity of
                    stories, enabling greater insight but making it more difficult to grasp the
                    movement as whole. We<hi rend="italic"> </hi>aim to show how computational
                    analysis might complement the work of scholars evolving new periodizations and
                    perspectives, by providing tools for comprehending narrative patterns in a more
                    complex whole.</p><p>We are applying cutting-edge text analysis techniques to
                    two corpuses: eighty-seven books made available by the UNC Press through their
                    Publishing the LCRM project, and transcripts of approximately 350 interviews
                    conducted by the Southern Oral History Program as part of their LCRM
                    initiative.<note>See the Publishing the LCRM project at <ref
                        target="https://lcrm.lib.unc.edu/blog/">https://lcrm.lib.unc.edu/blog/</ref>
                        and the LCRM Initiative at <ref
                            target="http://www.sohp.org/content/our_research/the_long_civil_rights_movement_initiative/"
                            type="external">http://www.sohp.org/content/our_research/the_long_civil_rights_movement_initiative/.</ref></note> The specific techniques we are
                    applying are<hi rend="italic"> event parsing </hi>and <hi rend="italic"
                        >narrative clustering. </hi></p><p>Event parsing involves identifying
                    sentences that communicate some event, for example a strike, a protest, a
                    bombing, or a legislative act. Specifically, it involves identifying <hi
                        rend="italic">frames</hi>, conceptual structures that describe particular
                            events along with their participants and settings.<note>More specifically, it involves two tasks: first
                                identifying the frames invoked by particular words in a text (a form of <hi
                                    rend="italic">word sense disambiguation</hi>) and then assigning
                                entities to the various roles in each frame, known as semantic role
                                labeling. For an overview of the former, see Agirre and Edmonds (2006). For
                                the latter, see Gildea &amp; Jurafsky (2002).</note>
                    Typically event parsing has been used for detection and tracking of topics in
                    news media, automated question answering, text summarization, and the production
                    of structured data from unstructured text. </p><p>We apply event parsing to
                    different ends. We do not treat events as ‘facts’ that can be consumed
                    independently of the histories from which they were ‘extracted.’ Historical
                    knowledge inheres within the narrative form, so the ‘extraction’ metaphor is a
                    poor fit for tools that aim to enhance access to historical knowledge (Shaw
                    2010). Instead, we use the results of event parsing as features for comparing
                    stories though narrative clustering: treating stories as ‘bags of events’ and
                    applying statistical techniques for grouping together similar ‘bags.’ </p><p>We
                    envision two forms of comparison. First, along the lines of Ankersmit’s original
                    proposal, we can highlight the specificity of a given history by showing which
                    events it recounts that are not recounted by similar histories. In conjunction
                    with information about the history such as when, where, and by whom it was
                    produced, such comparisons could provide a powerful means of assessing the depth
                    and scope of a given collection of histories.</p><p>Second, given a group of
                    histories recounting overlapping sets of events, we can compare their ‘speeds.’
                    Roland Barthes noted that an event that takes up dozens of pages in one history
                    may be covered by just one in another – a phenomenon he called <hi rend="italic"
                        >acceleration</hi>.<note>Barthes (1981: 9) hypothesized that ‘the nearer we
                            are to the historian’s own time […] the slower the history becomes.’</note> Because we propose to bring
                    together histories that recount the same events, and because those events are
                    parsed from the actual texts of those histories, we can potentially compare how
                    different histories speed up and slow down time.</p><p><hi rend="italic"
                        >Contours of the Past</hi> is comparable to recent projects applying topic
                    modeling to historical sources such as diaries and newspaper archives (Blevins
                    2011; Nelson). Topic modeling is a statistical technique for discovering
                    independent topics in some collection of documents, where a ‘topic’ is defined
                    as a group of words that tend to appear in the same documents (Blei, Ng and
                    Jordan 2003). Topic modeling has found favor among digital humanists for quickly
                    identifying themes in a large collection of documents without having to specify
                    some set of themes ahead of time. </p><p>However, topic modeling as it is
                    usually applied directly to the words used in historical documents will mainly
                    reflect patterns of word usage. This is exactly what is desired for
                    investigations of diction and style, but for identifying common patterns of
                    historical narration, this may not be the best approach. An oral history
                    containing a firsthand account may use language that is very different from that
                    found in a scholarly monograph, even if both sources are describing the ‘same’
                    event. Yet two sentences may evoke the same semantic frame even if they do not
                    have any words in common. Thus we can potentially find common patterns of
                    historical narration across different kinds of narrative source by applying
                    clustering techniques, not at the surface level of language (the specific words
                    used), but at the level of frame-semantic representation.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
               
                    <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Agirre, E., and P. G. Edmonds</hi> (2006). <hi rend="italic">Word
                        Sense Disambiguation: Algorithms and Applications.</hi> Dordrecht: Springer <ref target="http://www.wsdbook.org/" type="external">http://www.wsdbook.org/</ref>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Ankersmit, F. R.</hi> (1983). <hi rend="italic">Narrative Logic:
                        A Semantic Analysis of the Historian’s Language.</hi> The Hague: M.
                    Nijhoff.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Barthes, R.</hi> (1981). The Discourse of History. Translated by
                    S. Bann. In E. S. Shaffer (ed.), <hi rend="italic">Comparative Criticism: A
                        Yearbook</hi> 3. Cambridge: Cambridge UP.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Blei, D. M., A. Y. Ng, and M. I. Jordan</hi> (2003). Latent
                    Dirichlet Allocation <hi rend="italic">The Journal of Machine Learning
                        Research</hi>  3: 993 <ref
                        target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1162/jmlr.2003.3.4-5.993"
                        type="external">http://dx.doi.org/10.1162/jmlr.2003.3.4-5.993</ref>. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Blevins, C.</hi> (2011). Topic Modeling Historical Sources:
                    Analyzing the Diary of Martha Ballard. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of Digital
                        Humanities 2011.</hi> Stanford, CA, 19-22 June 2011. <ref
                        target="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-173.xml"
                        type="external">http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-173.xml</ref>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Gildea, D., and D. Jurafsky</hi> (2002). Automatic Labeling of
                    Semantic Roles. <hi rend="italic">Computational Linguistics</hi> 28(3): 245
                         <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1162/089120102760275983"
                            type="external">http://dx.doi.org/10.1162/089120102760275983</ref>. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Hall, J. D.</hi> (2005). The Long Civil Rights Movement and the
                    Political Uses of the Past. <hi rend="italic">Journal of American History
                    </hi> 91(4): 1235 <ref target="http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.2307/3660172"
                        type="external"> http://www.jstor.org/stable/10.2307/3660172</ref>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Lawson, S. F.</hi> (1991). Freedom Then, Freedom Now: The
                    Historiography of the Civil Rights Movement.<hi rend="italic"> The American
                        Historical Review </hi> 96(2): 456 <ref
                        target="http://www.jstor.org/stable/2163219"
                        type="external">http://www.jstor.org/stable/2163219</ref>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Nelson, R. K.</hi> Mining the <hi rend="italic">Dispatch</hi>.
                    Digital Scholarship Lab, University of Richmond <ref
                        target="http://dsl.richmond.edu/dispatch/"
                        type="external">http://dsl.richmond.edu/dispatch/</ref>. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Rigney, A.</hi> (1990). <hi rend="italic">The Rhetoric of
                        Historical Representation: Three Narrative Histories of the French
                        Revolution</hi>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Shaw, R.</hi> (2010). From Facts to Judgments: Theorizing History
                    for Information Science. <hi rend="italic">Bulletin of the American Society for
                        Information Science and Technology</hi> 36(2): 13 <ref
                        target="http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/bult.2010.1720360207"
                        type="external">http://dx.doi.org/10.1002/bult.2010.1720360207</ref>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Veyne, P.</hi> (1984). <hi rend="italic">Writing History: Essay
                        on Epistemology</hi>. Translated by M. Moore-Rinvolucri. Middletown,
                    Connecticut: Wesleyan UP.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>