<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-395">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>On the dual nature of written texts and its implications for the encoding of genetic manuscripts</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Brüning, Gerrit</name>
                    <affiliation>Freies Deutsches Hochstift, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>bruening@faustedition.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Henzel, Katrin</name>
                    <affiliation>Klassik Stiftung Weimar, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>henzel@faustedition.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Pravida, Dietmar</name>
                    <affiliation>Johann-Wolfgang-Goethe-Universität Frankfurt am Main, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>pravida@faustedition.de</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Discussions about a markup language for the genetic encoding of manuscripts have
                    reached a crucial point. The endeavours undertaken by a couple of notable
                    projects over the last years promise to yield a new encoding standard for the
                    description of the genesis of texts. In our talk we will survey the past and
                    current states of affairs and outline some problems of genetic encoding within
                    and without the framework of the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI). </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Crucial issues in genetic encoding</head>
                <p> Early conceptions of a computer-aided genetic edition trace back to the 1970s
                    (Gabler 1998). The absence of any established standard for projects that aim to
                    record revised manuscripts and genetic relations across numerous witnesses was
                    still felt at the end of the 20th century. Through the 1990s and early 2000s,
                    the then available TEI guidelines did not meet the requirements of genetic
                    textual criticism, for genetic manuscripts often lack textual structure in a
                    more conventional sense and show complicated series of revisions. This
                    incompletenesses gave rise to the construction of the HyperNietzsche Markup
                    Language (Saller 2003, esp. note 3) which was a kind of spin-off, but no
                    sustainable alternative.<note>‘HyperNietzsche’ nowadays operates under the name
                        of ‘Nietzsche Source’, where the HNML based contents are regrettably cut
                        off. They are still available by the following address: <ref
                            target="http://www.hypernietzsche.org/surf_page.php?type=scholarly"
                            type="external"
                            >http://www.hypernietzsche.org/surf_page.php?type=scholarly</ref>. To
                        become affiliated with the group of ‘Source’ projects, the ‘Bergen Text
                        Edition’ of the Wittgenstein papers was converted from the specifically
                        developed MECS to XML-TEI (P5) (<ref
                            target="http://www.wittgensteinsource.org/" type="external"
                            >http://www.wittgensteinsource.org/</ref>; Huitfeldt 1998). There are
                        other ways to mark up transcriptions of modern manuscripts (see ‘Les
                        manuscrits de Madame Bovary’, <ref target="http://www.bovary.fr/"
                            type="external">http://www.bovary.fr/</ref>; ‘Les Manuscrits de
                        Stendhal’, <ref target="http://manuscrits-de-stendhal.org/" type="external"
                            >http://manuscrits-de-stendhal.org/</ref>). But the set of tools
                        provided by the TEI is clearly the one that is likely to become
                        standard.</note>Some of the problems that led to HNML resolved themselves
                    with the previous version of the Guidelines (Burnard et al. 2008: 72-78,
                    335-374). Other expectations, however (Vanhoutte 2002; Pierazzo 2009), remained
                    unfulfilled:</p><xmt:uList>
                    <item>A documentary or ‘diplomatic’ transcription
                        which focuses less on the as yet privileged textual structure of the
                        examined material.</item>
                    <item>The possibility to record the temporal course of the genesis of
                        texts.</item></xmt:uList>
                    <p>The ‘Encoding Model for Genetic Editions’ (Workgroup on Genetic Editions, 2010) was to satisfy both requests. Now that it has been
                        largely incorporated in chapter 11 of the second version of ‘Proposal 5’
                        (Burnard et al. 2011), successes and shortcomings can be discussed. As for
                        the documentary transcription, a way of encoding has been made possible
                        which could not be thought of in former versions of the TEI Guidelines up to
                        the first version of P5 (Burnard et al. 2008). However, the suggested
                        approach to transcribe texts, taking into account the spatial distribution
                        of the inscription falls short of completion (Brüning et al., forthcoming).
                        The conceptual tension between the documentary and the textual perspective
                        which gave rise to the proposed encoding model has become even more
                        pronounced. As for the markup of textual alterations, it is not always clear
                        how the newly introduced elements relate to well-established practice.<note>See esp. sect. 11.3.4.4 of the second version of
                            P5 (Burnard et al. 367 sq.).</note> The former stringency of chapter 11 of the
                        Guidelines corresponded to the limited goal of providing ‘methods for
                        encoding as broad a variety of textual features as the consensus of the
                        community permits’ (Sperberg-McQueen et al. 1993). This consensus came to be
                        known under the name of an ‘agnostic’ view on the issue of textuality.
                        However, when chapter 11 was revised for the actual version, this consensus
                        was tacitly and perhaps unawares abandoned. for the sake of much specific
                        needs that parts of the new version of the chapter try to fulfill. Many of
                        the needs which the newly introduced parts of the chapter try to fulfill are
                        not covered by a broad consensus, but are based on very specific aims.
                        Therefore the conceptional problems inherent in the genetic module cannot
                        any longer be solved with reference to an alleged ‘agnostic’ basis. A
                        discussion on the nature of text is not only of theoretical interest but
                        also inevitable for practical reasons.
                    
                </p></div>
            
                <div>
                    <head>The dual nature of written texts</head>
                <p>We would like to submit as a basic principle that any written text is, by virtue
                    of being a linguistic entity, of a double-sided nature: First, it is by virtue
                    of being a <hi rend="italic">written</hi> text, a physical object that can be
                    identified in space and time as a document or an inscription (the material or
                    documentary dimension). Second, it is – by virtue of being a written <hi
                        rend="italic">text – </hi>an abstract object (the textual dimension), which
                    has to be materialized in some way, not necessarily in one specific material
                    form (Goodman 1977; Genette 1997).  As can be learned from the epistemology of
                    general linguistics (Saussure 1916: introduction, ch. 3; cf. Bouquet 1997), it
                    is imperative for sound methodology to keep irreducible points of view distinct,
                    each of which allows a coherent strategy of inquiry. Any attempt to collapse two
                    entirely different dimensions into one, will ultimately run up on a reef of
                    methodological incoherence. Within the digital humanities, the use of the word
                    ‘text’ is often inspired by the way texts are <hi rend="italic">represented</hi>
                    in the digital code: as an ordered hierarchy of content objects (Renear et al.
                    1996) or as a strictly linear sequence of characters (cf. Buzzetti &amp; McGann
                    2006: 60). But the hierarchical and/or linear <hi rend="italic"
                        >representation</hi> of a text in a computer file is not and cannot by
                    principle be a text in a linguistically respectable sense of the word
                    (Sperberg-McQueen 1991: 34).</p>
                </div>
            <div>
                <head>Consequences</head>
                <p>
                    Adherence to our basic principle will lead to some important consequences for
                        encoding written texts and to some proposals for the application and further
                        development of the available TEI Guidelines.</p>
               
                
                <xmt:oList rend="arabic">
                    <item>The documentary perspective (1) takes the inscriptional point of view and focuses on the <hi
                            rend="italic">materialization</hi> of the text. The basic elements of
                        this perspective are written letters and other inscriptional phenomena, such
                        as cancellations and other sediments of the writing process. Inscriptional
                        analyses can be focussed on units smaller than letters (e.g. allographic
                        forms or elements below the niveau of the letter, see Feigs 1979). But due
                        to the specific aims of our project, units smaller than letters are ignored.
                        Letters can as well be regarded as linguistic units, and a linguistic
                        understanding of what is written is a precondition for any manuscript to be
                        deciphered. However, it is possible to disregard from this understanding for
                        the purpose of a documentary edition. – The textual perspective (2) focuses
                        on linguistic entities. Its basic elements are linguistic units. Depending
                        on the perspective chosen, the following example has to be treated in two
                        different ways:
                    <p><figure>
                                <graphic url="img395-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                                    mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                            </figure></p>
                    
                    <xmt:oList rend="arabic">
                <item>From the documentary perspective, one letter
                        (B) is changed into another (L). As said, even the fact that only a <hi
                            rend="italic">part</hi> of the original letter has been modified, might
                        be of interest. But for the above reason, a replacement of letters is
                        recorded. Therefore a documentary oriented encoding will usually look like
                        this:<note>In fact, we do not use &lt;subst&gt; to record
                            overwritings. Especially in the case of discarded starts overwriting
                            letters do not positively substitute their predecessors. But we will not
                            address this issue here.</note>
                    <p><figure>
                                        <graphic url="img395-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px"
                                            width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                                    </figure></p></item>
                        
                        <item>From the textual
                        perspective, a whole word is substituted by another, ‘Band’ (ligament) by
                        ‘Land’ (land):
                            <p><figure>
                                        <graphic url="img395-3.jpg" rend="left" height="256px"
                                            width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                                    </figure></p>
                        <p>This way of encoding focuses on the textual
                        impact of the overwriting of (a part of) one letter: the substitution of a
                        whole word. It does not mean that the textual perspective is <hi
                            rend="italic">confined</hi> to the level of word forms. In fact,
                        sometimes only the spelling is corrected, and the alteration can very well
                        be recorded on the level of graphemic units alone – no matter how many
                        letters of the word have been replaced, no matter if the complete word is
                        rewritten for the sake of clarity in the manuscript. However, in the given
                        case the substitution does <hi rend="italic">not</hi> concern only single
                        letters but the linguistic unit of the next level (the word), although the
                        scribe carefully avoided to deface the manuscript more than was
                        necessary.</p></item>
                    
                    </xmt:oList>
                        
                        <p>How can the sediments of the writing process and the
                        textual genesis be given their equal due? </p><p>As is clear from the
                        above example, not only the markup is concerned by the difference of the two
                        perspectives but also the marked up content (‘BLand’ vs. ‘BandLand’). This
                        is one of the reasons why a split-up of the encoding which we tried to avoid
                        for a long time finally proved inevitable. We decided to introduce two
                        separate transcripts: a documentary and a textual one (Bohnenkamp et al.,
                        forthcoming). The separate transcripts are the source for different parts of
                        the edition: the documentary for the diplomatic rendering and the textual
                        for the reading text and the apparatuses. The disadvantages of the split-up
                        will be dealt with by help of automatic collation (Brüning et al.,
                        forthcoming). Logically, it is possible to integrate both perspectives in a
                        single transcript, under the only condition that the markup is dominated by
                        one of the two perspectives (Renear et al. 1996). Practically, however, it
                        is very difficult to give adequate information on the writing process and on
                        the text with equal regard to both sides. Detailed information of one of
                        both will inevitably get lost. Furthermore, the intermingling of both
                        perspectives complicates the subsequent data processing.</p></item>
                    
                    <item>Thanks to the split-up, the documentary transcript is kept free from the limitations inherent
                        to the markup of the textual structure, so that all the information that is
                        needed to generate a satisfying diplomatic rendering can be placed.
                        Likewise, the textual transcript is kept free from descriptive information
                        about the record. In turn, an aspect of the linguistic structure can be
                        taken into account the importance of which for genetic encoding has not yet
                        found sufficient perception. As a concatenation of linguistic entities is
                        not a mere sequence but a structure, it is necessary to distinguish between
                        syntagmatically defined positions and paradigmatically selected items
                        occupying them.<note>he terminology of position-in-structure and of
                            items-occupying-positions are very common in various schools of
                            linguistics (cf. Owens 1988: 31-35) and in the computer sciences as
                            well.</note> In the above example, a position is initially occupied by
                        the word ‘Band’, and subsequently by the word ‘Land’. The surrounding
                        &lt;subst&gt;-tag indicates the paradigmatic relation between both items,
                        although this is not explicit in the definition (Burnard et al. 2011:
                            1348).<note>It is doubtful, therefore, if items which occupy ‘different
                            positions’ (ibid., 352) can enter such a relation, as is, perhaps
                            inadvertently, implied in the name of the newly introduced
                            &lt;substJoin&gt; (ibid., 351 sq.).</note> Problems arise in cases which
                        deviate from the normal one-to-one-correspondence of items to positions, for
                        example where the wording of the passage is held in abeyance as a
                        consequence of an unfinished alteration.<note>For an example of the further,
                            see sect. 11.3.4.6 of the TEI Guidelines (Burnard et al. 2011: 369). The
                            suggested encoding (ibid., 370) neglects the symmetrical relation
                            between the items ‘before’ and ‘beside’. From a textual point of view,
                            the latter can be considered <hi rend="italic">added</hi> only insofar
                            as the former is considered <hi rend="italic">deleted</hi>.</note>
                        Introducing the differentiation between positions and items into genetic
                        encoding might help to spot, clarify, and solve these problems.</item></xmt:oList>
                
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Bohnenkamp, A., G. Brüning, S. Henke, K. Henzel, F. Jannidis, G.
                        Middell, D. Pravida, and M. Wissenbach</hi> (forthcoming). Perspektiven auf
                    Goethes <hi rend="italic">Faust</hi>. Zur historisch-kritischen Hybridedition
                    des <hi rend="italic">Faust.</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Jahrbuch des Freien Deutschen Hochstifts 2011</hi>.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Bouquet, S.</hi> (1997). <hi rend="italic">Introduction à la
                        lecture de Saussure. </hi>Paris: Payot &amp; Rivages.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Brüning, G., K. Henzel, D. Pravida</hi> (forthcoming). Rationale
                    of multiple encoding in the Genetic Faust Edition. <hi rend="italic">Journal of
                        the Text Encoding Initiative</hi> (submitted).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Burnard, L., and S. Bauman, eds</hi>. (2004). <hi rend="italic"
                        >TEI P4. Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange.
                        XML-compatible edition</hi>. Oxford, Providence, Charlottesville and Bergen:
                    The TEI Consortium.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Burnard, L., and S. Bauman, eds.</hi> (2008). <hi rend="italic"
                        >TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange by the TEI
                        Consortium</hi>. Oxford, Providence, Charlottesville, Nancy: Tei
                    Consortium.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Burnard, L., and S. Bauman, eds.</hi> (2011). <hi rend="italic"
                        >TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange by the TEI
                        Consortium</hi>. Charlottesville: Text Encoding Initiative Consortium.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Buzzetti, D., and J. McGann</hi> (2006). Electronic Textual
                    Editing: Critical Editing in a Digital Horizon. In L. Burnard, K. O’Brien
                    O’Keeffe, and J. Unsworth (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Electronic Textual
                        Editing</hi>. New York: MLA, pp. 51-71.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Feigs, W.</hi> (1979). <hi rend="italic">Deskriptive Edition auf
                        Allograph-. Wort- und Satzniveau, demonstriert an handschriftlich
                        überlieferten, deutschsprachigen Briefen von H. Steffens.</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Teil 1: Methode. </hi>Bern: Peter Lang.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Gabler, H. W.</hi> (1998). Computergestütztes Edieren und
                    Computer-Edition. In H. Zeller and G. Martens (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                        >Textgenetische Edition</hi>. Tübingen: Niemeyer, pp. 315-328.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Genette, G.</hi> (1997). <hi rend="italic">The Work of Art.
                        Immanence and Transcendence</hi>. Ithaca, NY: Cornell UP.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Goodman, N.</hi> (1977). <hi rend="italic">Languages of Art. An
                        Approach to a Theory of Symbols. </hi>2nd ed. Indianapolis, IN: Hackett.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Huitfeldt, C.</hi> (1998). MECS – a Multi-Element Code System
                    (Version October 1998), <hi rend="italic">Working Papers from the Wittgenstein
                        Archives at the University of Bergen</hi>, 3. <ref
                        target="http://www.hit.uib.no/claus/mecs/mecs.htm" type="external">http://www.hit.uib.no/claus/mecs/mecs.htm</ref> (accessed 9 March
                    2012).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Owens, J.</hi> (1988). <hi rend="italic">The Foundations of
                        Grammar. An Introduction to Medieval Arabic Grammatical Theory</hi>.
                    Amsterdam, Philadelphia: Benjamins.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Pierazzo, E.</hi> (2009). Digital Genetic Editions: The Encoding
                    of Time in Manuscript Transcription, In M. Deegan and K. Sutherland (eds.), <hi
                        rend="italic">Text Editing, Print and the Digital World</hi>. Farnham and
                    Burlington, VT: Ashgate, pp. 169-186.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Renear, A., E. Mylonas, and D. Durand</hi> (1996). Refining our
                    Notion of What Text Really Is: The Problem of Overlapping Hierarchies. <hi
                        rend="italic">Research in Humanities Computing</hi> 4: 263-280. <ref
                        target="http://www.stg.brown.edu/resources/stg/monographs/ohco.html"
                        type="external">http://www.stg.brown.edu/resources/stg/monographs/ohco.html</ref>
                    (accessed 9 March 2012). </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Saller, H.</hi> (2003). HNML – HyperNietzsche Markup Language.
                        <hi rend="italic">Jahrbuch für Computerphilologie </hi>5: 185-192. <ref
                        target="http://computerphilologie.uni-muenchen.de/jg03/saller.html"
                        type="external">http://computerphilologie.uni-muenchen.de/jg03/saller.html</ref>
                    (accessed 9 March 2012).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Saussure, F. de </hi>(1916). <hi rend="italic">Cours de
                        linguistique générale. </hi>Lausanne: Payot. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.</hi> (1991). Text in the Electronic Age:
                    Textual Study and Text Encoding with Examples from Medieval Texts.<hi
                        rend="italic"> Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi> 6: 34-46.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Sperberg-McQueen, C. M., and L. Burnard, eds.</hi> (1993). <hi
                        rend="italic">Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</hi>
                    (P2). Chicago, Oxford: Text Encoding Initiative. <ref
                        target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/Vault-GL.html" type="external">http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/Vault-GL.html</ref>(accessed 9 March
                    2012).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Sperberg-McQueen, C. M., and L. Burnard, eds.</hi> (1999). <hi
                        rend="italic">Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</hi>.
                    1994. Revised Reprint. Chicago, Oxford: Text Encoding Initiative.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Vanhoutte, E.</hi> (2002). <hi rend="italic">Putting Time back in
                        Manuscripts: Textual Study and Text Encoding, with Examples from Modern
                        Manuscripts</hi>, paper presented at the ALLC/ACH 2002, Tübingen, 25 July
                    2002. <ref target="http://www.edwardvanhoutte.org/pub/2002/allc02abstr.htm"
                        type="external">http://www.edwardvanhoutte.org/pub/2002/allc02abstr.htm</ref>
                    (accessed 9 March 2012).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Workgroup on Genetic Editions 2010</hi>. <hi rend="italic">An
                        Encoding Model for Genetic Editions</hi>. <ref
                        target="http://www.tei-c.org/Activities/Council/Working/tcw19.html"
                        type="external">http://www.tei-c.org/Activities/Council/Working/tcw19.html</ref>
                    (accessed 9 March 2012).</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>