<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-338">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Benefits of tools and applications for a digitized analysis of Chinese Buddhist inscriptions</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Wenzel, Claudia</name>
                    <affiliation>Heidelberger Akademie der Wissenschaften, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>claudiawen@googlemail.com</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>
                The research project ‘Buddhist stone scriptures in China’ hosted at the
                    Heidelberg Academy of Sciences and Humanities and headed by Prof. Lothar
                    Ledderose is devoted to the documentation of holy Buddhist scriptures that were
                    carved onto rocks, boulders and stones from the sixth to the eighth century in
                    China. The digital processing and presentation of these stone carved texts
                    offers remarkable benefits with regard to facilitation of the workflow,
                    incorporation of spatial relations, and transparency.</p>
            
            <div>
                <head>Application of digital tools for enhancing the workflow of transcribing and
                    editing the texts to establish the corpus of carved stone sutras</head>
                <p>Traditionally, pre-modern Chinese texts engraved on durable materials like metal
                    or stone were first ‘copied’ by brushing a moistened sheet of paper into the
                    cavities of the carved surface, and applying black ink on all outstanding parts,
                    leaving the traces of the chisel in white on the paper. These transportable
                    rubbings were collected from the eighteenth century on by Chinese epigraphers,
                    who studied their ancient scripts and transcribed them for further publication.
                    However, the rubbings are in no way a faithful copy of what was originally
                    written into stone. The very process of taking them from the stone cut
                    characters already involves a reading and interpretation of less well preserved
                    glyphs. </p>
                <p>To avoid such flaws and short-comings of the traditional Chinese procedure of
                    text documentation, our project relies solely on the carved text to provide the
                    lemmas for the corpus of stone sutras. The original stone is documented either
                    by photographs alone, or by both scans and photographs. Then it is collated with
                    several text witnesses, including different versions of rubbings, and different
                    versions of the text extant either in manuscripts, or printed editions of the
                    Buddhist canon, as well as the digital edition of the Buddhist canon, edited by
                    the Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association (CBETA). As a result, the
                    original stone text can be transcribed by reconstructing lost or damaged
                    characters, and can be discussed in text critical annotations. </p>
                <p>Digital research and publication helps making this editing process more
                    transparent and replicable. The web application documents each inscription on
                    five levels by providing (1) a scan or photograph of the original stone, (2) one
                    or several paper rubbings of the stone, (3) a transcription in Unicode
                    characters reflecting the original layout of characters in vertical columns on
                    the stone, (4) a transcription in Unicode characters with modern punctuation and
                    reading direction in horizontal lines from left to right, and (5) an English
                    translation of the text including text critical annotations. In this way, text
                    editing is significantly enhanced in terms of correctness as well as
                    transparency, since the user can follow the transcribing of each stone character
                    step by step. </p>
                <p>The basis for the transcription process is the documentation of the original
                    stone, which is done ideally by 3D laser scans. After processing, the
                    inscriptions can be viewed either in 2 D or 3 D view by means of an applet
                    developed for the project by the i3 Mainz (University of Applied Sciences,
                        Mainz).<note>Schmidt et al. 2010b: 3-9; Schmidt et al. 2010a: 2-5.</note>
                    This applet was already implemented in the workflow of reading and transcribing
                    the text in modern Unicode characters, but it is also available online. It
                    provides various options like zooming, adjusting the light position, or applying
                    colors for better legibility of the carved characters, thereby empowering users
                    to not only better comprehend the editing process, but also to continue research
                    by themselves. The use of this digital tool exceeds by far the possibilities of
                    traditional print media.</p>
                <p>Another main challenge of the edition of the medieval stone sutras is their
                    transcription in modern Unicode characters. Many of the ancient carved texts use
                    glyphs not yet encoded in the Unicode standard. Although more Chinese ideographs
                    are being added currently to the Unihan database, the problems of mapping
                    ancient glyphs to Unicode characters are complex, and cannot be solved
                    completely by encoding more glyphs. By programming and implementing a ‘snippet
                    tool’ that is able to search and line up images of the same character connected
                    to a certain Unicode character, we not only provide a tool for an analysis of
                    writing styles, but also bring to light the complexity of the issue of mapping
                    glyphs to unified characters. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Incorporation of spatial relations </head>
                <p>
                   For a comprehensive understanding of the historical background behind the
                        creation of stone carved sutras in China, each inscription site has to be
                        seen in its particular topography in which it is embedded. The choice of the
                        site is of religious importance, and infers particular ritual uses.
                        Inter-spatial relations between multiple sites are also of interest.
                        <note>Tsai &amp; Wenzel 2009: 24.</note> For this reason, all inscriptions and sites were
                        GIS documented and can now be addressed on interactive maps.<note>Auer et al. 2011: 2-5; Lanig et al. 2011 b:
                            3-4.</note> In cooperation with the Institute of Geography of
                        Heidelberg University, more tools for a GIS based analysis have been
                        developed to clarify the spatial history of the creation of inscription
                        sites, the related spreading of Buddhist sutras, and the migration movements
                        of the monks responsible for it.<note>Lanig et al. 2011a: 4-5; Lanig et al. 2011b:
                            7-8.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Right from the start, the project has generated 3D models of larger
                        inscription sites that have been integrated into the project’s
                        web-application. At first, we made use of these models to provide map-like
                        views of the general layout of inscriptions at particular sites. In one
                        case, the course of a pilgrim’s path was simulated in a flash animation.
                        More recently, the visualization with 3D models has become even more
                        rewarding for a particular type of inscription sites, namely those hosting
                        stone sutras inside caves. Now the user can find the inscription site on a
                        map, zoom in, select a particular cave, and by means of a panoramic view,
                        approach the inscriptions inside the digital cave and read them herself by
                        means of high-resolution photographs. In this respect, digital space is not
                        only a synthesis of traditional documentation with rubbings, photographs,
                        and printing, but offers a new level of close-to- reality documentation.<note>Ledderose 2012.</note>
                    </p></div>
            <div><head>(Future<note>According to the agreement of the Chinese-German
                co-operation project, a print publication has first priority; the
                digital publication has to follow afterwards. For this reason, the
                project’s web-application at <ref target="http://www.stonesutras.org"
                type="external">www.stonesutras.org</ref> is to date still password protected. Access will
                be granted by request; please contact Claudia.Wenzel@urz.uni-heidelberg.de. </note>)
                            digital publication of research results and their transparency for the
                            community</head>
                    
                            
                        <p>All data of the project are stored in an open
                        source XML database called eXist (exist-db.org); the mark-up of texts
                        follows <hi rend="bold">TEI</hi> (Text Encoding Initiative) standards. On
                        the basis of the same set of data, a web application as well as a print
                        publication is generated. For the latter, the data is being transformed by
                        XSLT. The digital as well as the print publication are set up similarly. The
                        scheme of documenting each inscription on the aforementioned five levels
                        pervades the digital and the print publication. While the purpose of this
                        structure is to provide maximum transparency about the editing process for
                        the reader/user, the electronic publication is in this respect even more
                        efficient. By integrating the aforementioned digital tools (Mainz applet,
                        snippet-tool, GIS analysis tools) into the project’s web-application, the
                        (future) user is enabled to replicate the editing of stone scriptures, and
                        to continue research herself.</p></div>
                    
                <div>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Funding</hi></p>
                <p>This work was supported by the Heidelberg Academy of Sciences and Humanities
                    (Heidelberger Akademie der Wissenschaften), Germany. The development of digital
                    tools mentioned was supported by the German Ministry of Education and
                        Research<hi rend="italic"> </hi>(BMBF) within a program on interdisciplinary
                    research between natural and social sciences, namely the research project
                    ‘3D-Sutras: A web based atlas of laser scanned Buddhist stone inscriptions in
                    China,’ co-operated by the Heidelberg Academy of Sciences, the Department of
                    Geography of Heidelberg University, and the Institute for Spatial Information
                    and Surveying Technology, i3mainz, of the University of Applied Sciences in
                    Mainz.</p>
                </div>
            
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Auer, M., B. Höfle, S. Lanig, A. Schilling, and A. Zipf</hi>
                    (2011). 3D-Sutras: A web based atlas of laser scanned Buddhist stone
                    inscriptions in China. <hi rend="italic">14th AGILE International Conference on
                        Geographic Information Science</hi>, Utrecht, The Netherlands 18-21 April
                    2011.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Lanig, S., A. Schilling, M. Auer, B. Höfle, N. Billen, and A.
                        Zipf</hi> (2011a). Interoperable integration of high precision 3D laser data
                    and large scale geoanalysis in a SDI for Sutra inscriptions in Sichuan
                        (China).<hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Geoinformatik 2011–</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Geochange</hi>, Münster, Germany.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Lanig, S., B. Höfle, M. Auer, A. Schilling, H. Deierling, and A.
                        Zipf</hi> (2011b). Geodateninfrastrukturen im historisch-geographischen
                    Kontext – Buddhistische Steinschriften in der Provinz Sichuan/China. AGIT
                        2011.<hi rend="italic"> Symposium Angewandte Geoinformatik</hi>, Salzburg,
                    Österreich. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Ledderose, L.</hi> (2012, in print) Fünf Perspektiven auf
                    Steinerne Sutren. In I. Reichle and V. Lepper (eds.), <hi rend="italic"
                        >Perspektiven. </hi>Berlin: Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der
                    Wissenschaften 2012.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Schmidt, N., R. Schütze, and F. Boochs</hi> (2010a). 3D-Sutra –
                    Interactive Analysis Tool for a Web-Atlas of Scanned Sutra Inscriptions in
                        China.<hi rend="italic"> Proceedings of the ISPRS Commissi</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">on V Mid-Term Symposium Close Range Image Measurement
                        Techniques</hi>, Newcastle upon Tyne, United Kingdom.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Schmidt, N., F. Boochs, and R. Schütze</hi> (2010b). Capture and
                    Processing of High Resolution 3D-Data of Sutra Inscriptions in China. <ref
                        target="http://www.springerlink.com/content/978-3-642-16872-7/" type="external">http://www.springerlink.com/content/978-3-642-16872-7/</ref>Digital
                    Heritage, <ref target="http://www.springerlink.com/content/0302-9743/" type="external">http://www.springerlink.com/content/0302-9743/</ref>Lecture
                    Notes in Computer Science 6436: 125-139, DOI: 10.1007/978-3-642-16873-4_10,
                    Limassol, Zypern</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Tsai, S., and C. Wenzel</hi> (2009). The Stone Inscriptions of
                    the Six Mountains of Zoucheng. Die Steinschriften der Sechs Berge von Zoucheng.
                    In Museum für Ostasiatische Kunst Köln und Forschungsstelle der Heidelberger
                    Akademie der Wissenschaften, Buddhistische Steinschriften in Nord-China (eds),
                        <hi rend="italic">The Centenary of the Museum of East Asian Art in Cologne.
                        The Heart of Enlightenment. Buddhist Art in China 550-600. 100 Jahre Museum
                        für Ostasiatische Kunst in Köln. Das Herz der Erleuchtung. Buddhistische
                        Kunst in China 550-600. </hi>Köln, pp. 24-37.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>