<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-391">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Corpus Coranicum: A digital landscape for the study of the Qu’ran</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Schnöpf, Markus</name>
                    <affiliation>Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Sciences and Humanities,
                        Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>schnoepf@bbaw.de</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introductiom</head>
                <p>In 2007 begun the project Corpus Coranicum located at the Berlin-Brandenburg
                    Academy of Science and Humanities with an estimated duration of twelve years. A
                    goal of the project is a holistic documentation of the holy text. The project
                    consists of different modules: Collection of early manuscripts, documentation of
                    environmental texts to the Quran, documentation of alternate writings and
                    finally a commentary on each sura of the Quran. In the last years the
                    technological infrastructure has been set up and data was collected in a SQL
                    database. The commentary of the  was realised in XML and is stored in a
                    XML-database. The website of the project thus combines SQL and XML in an
                    integrated information system. Lately, a bibliography consisting of 8000
                    references was added to the system. Further investigations are directed more on
                    a scientific dating, analysing the materiality of early written documents. They
                    are scheduled for 2012/13 within a French-German joint research project. Another
                    new module is a glossary of the  and early Arabic literature. For overcoming
                    troubles in the presentation of early Arabic script a special font has been
                    developed: The Coranica. </p>
                <p>The project Corpus Coranicum began at the Berlin-Brandenburg Academy of Science
                    and Humanities in 2007 with a planned duration of 12 years. The project aims at
                    both a holistic edition of the Quran and also an extensive commentary. In
                    addition to the Al-Azhar Quran edition from 1923/1924, this project will provide
                    the reader with early written testimonies as well as oral reading variants that
                    are manifested in early islamic literature.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                        <head>Manuscripta</head>
                        
                    <p>The project sees the module Manuscripta Coranica as following the tradition
                        of G. Bergsträßers planned Apparatus Criticus, which due to Bergsträßers
                        early death could never be realised. Thus the project aims at a new approach
                        to the text of the Quran. Bergsträßer collected the oldest Quran manuscripts
                        by travelling the Arabic world in the 1920s with a 35-mm camera.</p>
                <p><figure>
                        <graphic url="img391-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>Figure 1: A page from the Kodex Meknes from the collection of
                            Bergsträßer</head>
                    </figure></p>
                <p>These
                        photographs remained lost until members of the Corpus Coranicum found the
                        filmstrips in 2008 (Higgins 2008). Immediately we began to digitize the
                        images in levels of grey. The project can therefore present digitizations
                        from Quran manuscripts in the module Manuscripta Coranica that are lost
                        today. A database containing metadata that includes the range of verses in
                        one image has been developed and filled. The early manuscripts have a high
                        degree of ambiguity, as vocals and diacritics were used irregularly and
                        different from today. Thus these manuscripts document the continuity as well
                        as the development of the Arabic writing system.</p>
                <p><figure>
                        <graphic url="img391-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>Figure 2: Same page in the module Manuscripta Coranica</head>
                    </figure></p>
                <p>The Quran was
                    revealed to Mohammed from God via the angel Gabriel beginning in 610 (western
                    dating). Until 632, the year of Mohammed’s death, the divine revelations were
                    mainly orally memorized and written on palm leaves. The Quran consists of 114
                    chapters that are called suras. Each sura consists of a different number of
                    verses with a total number of 6326 verses. The length of the verses degrees from
                    sura one to 114. The Corpus Coranicum aims at documenting the double string of
                    the quranic textual history, as it was handwritten and orally (which was
                    codified in later islamic sources) passed on next generations. So, beneath the
                    module Manuscripta Coranica, which documents the handwritten tradition of text,
                    the oral reading tradition of the Quran has to be documented as well.</p>
               
                    </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>Lectiones</head>
                <p>This is the module Lectiones Coranicae, in which we present the different
                    readings of the Quran. In this module only these variants that have phonetic
                    effects, are collected. Each variant is assigned to one or more reader or the
                    bequeathing person. A synoptical view on these variants looks like a score of
                    the Quran.</p>
            <p><figure>
                        <graphic url="img391-3.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>Figure 3: Lectiones Coranicae</head>
                    </figure></p>
                </div><div>
                    <head>Commentary</head>
                <p>The commentary on each sura contains different parts. First, texts from the
                    environment of the Quran like the bible, Talmud and early Arabic inscriptions,
                    papyri and others have to be mentioned. We call these texts intertexts. Here one
                    encounters a high diversity of different writing systems, such as Greek, Syrian,
                    Pahlawi and others. Sources are therefore found in many different languages.
                    With this collection of heterogeneous texts connected to each verse of the Quran
                    the user will be able to draw a map of traditions that were mentioned in the
                    holy text.</p>
                    <p><figure>
                        <graphic url="img391-4.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>Figure 4: The module commentary on the Quran</head>
                    </figure></p>
                <p>The grammar in the suras is the theme of the second part of the commentary. A
                    word can be explained through comparisons with other manifestations of the word
                    in the Quran. In addition, the identification of Quranic loan words must be
                    mentioned. In order to facilitate this work, a database Glossarium Coranicum has
                    been developed. The formal structure of each sura is the subject of another part
                    of the commentary. The literal appearance of oaths, revelations and other
                    structural phenomena are recorded in this section, thus documenting the formal
                    history of Quranic speech. After having captured the lexical, grammatical and
                    literal characteristics of the sura, it is possible to identify insertions, in
                    so far as they can be proofed following the interpolation hypothesis. The
                    interpretation is the last part of the commentary for each sura. On the one hand
                    each text can be assembled in different ways, reflecting the chronology of the
                    sura’s formation. On the other hand the differences to the intertexts can be
                    used to show the uniqueness of the sura.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The digital landscape</head>
                <p>Coming to the digital environment of the project, we try to organize the
                    information in different databases that provide the backbone of the Corpus
                    Coranicum:</p><xmt:uList>
                <item>Manuscripta Coranica</item>
                <item>Lectiones Coranicae</item>
                <item>Bibliographia Coranica</item>
                <item>Glossarium Coranicum</item>
                <item>Intertexts</item>
                <item>Quran itself</item></xmt:uList>
                    <p><figure>
                        <graphic url="img391-5.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>Figure 5: The module intertexts</head>
                    </figure></p>
                <p>The connection between these databases is the sura and the verse. It is thus
                    possible to show all connected information for one verse: the manuscripts
                    showing the verse, the intertexts of the verse and the loan words used in the
                    verse. The commentary for each sura is stored in XML, following and extending
                    the transcription rules of the Text Encoding Initiative. We therefore, have a
                    heterogeneous digital information landscape, where different and yet separated
                    information systems are bundled under one umbrella. Generally stated, the
                    different cultures the project deals with are combined within this information
                    system. The usage of different writing systems and languages are thus another
                    challenge in the project. As available fonts were unable to represent ancient
                    Arabic writings (the vocalisation points are orientated on modern Arabic writing
                    systems) a special font had to be developed within the project, called Coranica,
                    which we offer as well for download as open source. </p>
                <p>Arabic digital philology is a young and emerging field in the digital humanities.
                    Speech technologies like the Hopper of the Perseus project or the Buckwalter
                    ensive arabic dictionary, remain unfulfilled. However, freshly published
                    resources like the Lane dictionary can be used to broaden the perception of
                    Arabic texts. In my presentation I will demonstrate the techniques and
                    web-contents of the Corpus Coranicum, as the first results of the project goals
                    are published in the first half of 2012. Thus the Quran will be presented for
                    the first time as a digital reference system not only for the Quran itself, but
                    as well integrating other sources from the early Arabic and old Ancient world.
                    Thus, philology must make sense to the text itself (Pollock 2009).</p>
                   </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Bergsträsser, G.</hi> (1993). <hi rend="italic">Nichtkanonische
                        Koranlesarten im Muhtasab des Ibn-Ginnī / von G. Bergsträsser</hi>.
                    Egelsbach: Hänsel-Hohenhausen.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Higgins, A.</hi> (2008). The Lost Archive. <hi rend="italic">Wall
                        Street Journal</hi>. Available at:
                    <ref target="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB120008793352784631.html" type="external">http://online.wsj.com/article/SB120008793352784631.html</ref> (accessed  25 March
                    2012).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Pollock, S.</hi> (2009). Future philology? The fate of a soft
                    science in a hard world. <hi rend="italic">Critical Inquiry</hi>. 35(4):
                    931-961.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Spitaler, A.</hi> (1935). <hi rend="italic">Die Verszählung des
                        Koran nach islamischer Überlieferung.</hi> München: Bayer. Akad. d.
                    Wissenschaften.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Wansbrough, J.</hi> (2004). <hi rend="italic">Quranic Studies:
                        Sources and Methods of Scriptural Interpretation</hi>. London: Prometheus
                    Books.</p>
                
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>