<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-452">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Multilingual and Semantic Extension of Folk Tale Catalogues</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Declerck, Thierry</name>
                    <affiliation>DFKI GmbH, Germany, ICLTT, Austrian Academy of Sciences,
                        Austria</affiliation>
                    <email>declerck@dfki.de</email>
                </author>
                
                <author>
                    <name>Lendvai, Piroska</name>
                    <affiliation>Research Institute for Linguistics, Hungary</affiliation>
                    <email>lendvai.piroska@nytud.hu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Darányi, Sándor</name>
                    <affiliation>Swedish School of Library and Information Science, Sweden</affiliation>
                    <email>sandor.daranyi@hb.se</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>The modelling of phenomena related to higher-order knowledge mechanisms poses
                    significant challenges to research in any domain, this being also valid for
                    narratives, which ‘are an important form of knowledge representation’, as
                    (Tuffield et al. 2006) state. In the context of the AMICUS network<note>AMICUS (Automated Motif Discovery in Cultural
                        Heritage and Scientific Communication Texts), <ref target="http://ilk.uvt.nl/amicus" type="external">
                            http://ilk.uvt.nl/amicus/</ref>.</note> we are more specifically interested in the
                    representation of motifs in narratives. Motifs are recurring conceptual,
                    textual, audio or visual units appearing in artefacts – in folk tales, they can
                    be seen as cognitively complex notions (e.g. ‘Rescue of princess’, ‘Helpful
                    animal’, ‘Cruel stepmother’, etc.), expressed by lexically and syntactically
                    variable narrative structures. The modelling of such motifs, including their
                    typical realizations in natural language form, can help in supporting the
                    automatic motif detection in large (multilingual) text collections<note>The
                        interconnection of Knowledge Representation systems and automated textual
                        analysis is being successfully applied to various domains. One of our goal
                        is to adapt and apply such technologies to the automated analysis of folk
                        narratives, using for example the approach presented in (Declerck &amp;
                        Koleva 2012), to be extended among others by ontology elements described in
                        (Zöllner-Weber 2008).</note>. But this kind of formal representation of motifs is
                    so far unresolved, and thus a large amount of cultural heritage collections of
                    which motifs are typical constructive units can still only be manually indexed,
                    which significantly limits access to these resources and to this type of
                    knowledge. Recently, we started to investigate the utility of linguistic and
                    semantic analysis and mark-up of motifs (Lendvai et al. 2010), which we would
                    like to extend and apply to studies on motif sequencing (Darányi, Wittek &amp;
                        Forró<hi rend="italic"> </hi>2012).</p>
                <p>In the current study, we address two priorities of the Digital Humanities
                    discipline: devising procedures that integrate semantic enhancement of legacy
                    folk tale indexes, classification systems and taxonomies (Declerck &amp; Lendvai
                    2011) and their automatized translation (Mörth et al. 2011). For this study we
                    are dealing with two extended catalogues that hold conceptual schemes of
                    narrative elements from folktales, ballads, myths, and related genres: the <hi
                        rend="italic">Thompson’s Motif-Index of Folk-Literature</hi>, TMI (Thompson
                    1955) and <hi rend="italic">The Types of International Folktales</hi>, ATU
                    (Uther 2004). TMI has an available on-line version<note>See <ref
                            target="http://www.ruthenia.ru/folklore/thompson/index.htm"
                            type="external">
                            http://www.ruthenia.ru/folklore/thompson/index.htm</ref>.</note>, only
                    in English language, but the digitized ATU is not yet available on-line in its
                    entirety, only some of its subsections are reproduced in Wikipedia, in various
                        languages<note>See <ref
                            target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aarne%E2%80%93Thompson_classification_system"
                            type="external"
                            >http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aarne%E2%80%93Thompson_classification_system</ref>
                        for the English version, <ref
                            target="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aarne-Thompson-Index"
                            type="external">http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aarne-Thompson-Index</ref>
                        for the German version, and for the French version <ref
                            target="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classification_Aarne-Thompson"
                            type="external"
                            >http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classification_Aarne-Thompson</ref>. Note
                        that the online ATU data do not reflect the layout of the original
                        catalogue, as was the case for TMI.</note>.</p>
                <p>TMI indexes and ATU types are both combined with extensive labels, and a novel
                    approach to those resources is that this combination can be linguistically
                    processed (Declerck &amp; Lendvai 2011), semantically represented, and,
                    ultimately, turned into domain-specific ontology classes that can be
                    interlinked. The upgrade leads to semantically enriched catalogues that qualify
                    as interoperable language technology resources that can be harnessed to assign
                    text units to the folktale domain classes, creating in an automatized way
                    indexed folktale corpora. As part of such a normalization process, catalogues
                    have to be made interoperable with each other, and stored in a semantically
                    harmonized representation, like the SKOS<note>SKOS stands for ‘Simple
                        Knowledge Organization System’. See for more details:
                        <ref target="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/" type="external">http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/</ref>.</note> standard,
                    which is using RDF<note> RDF
                        stands for ‘Resource Description Framework’. See <ref target="http://www.w3.org/RDF" type="external">http://www.w3.org/RDF</ref>.</note> as its formal representation
                    language. </p>
               
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Towards Semantic and Multilingual Extensions of TMI </head>
                
                    <p>The Thompson’s Motif-Index of Folktale-Literature is organized by
                        alphanumeric indexes, which resembles a taxonomy structure of motifs, but
                        does not express hierarchy or inheritance properties. i.e. it is not made
                        explicit that some elements of the taxonomy introduce mere classification
                        information over a span of labels <hi rend="italic">(‘A0-A99. Creator’</hi>,
                        split into finer-grained subclasses, e.g. <hi rend="italic">‘A20. Origin of
                            the creator.’)</hi>, that some elements are abstractions of motifs <hi
                            rend="italic">(‘A21. /Creator from above./’)</hi>, and that some
                        elements are summaries of a concrete motif, supplying source information as
                        well <hi rend="italic">(‘A21.1. /Woman who fell from the sky./--Daughter of
                            the sky-chief falls from the sky, is caught by birds, and lowered to the
                            surface of the water. She becomes the creator.--*Iroquois: Thompson
                            Tales n.27.--Cf. Finnish: Kalevala rune 1.’)</hi>.</p>
                    <p>We prepared a program that converts TMI to an XML representation and marks
                        such properties explicitly by designated tags, as exemplified below:</p>
                    <p>&lt;label class="TMI_A0" span="A0-A99" type="<hi rend="italic">abstract</hi>"
                        lang="en"&gt;Creator&lt;/label&gt;</p>
                    <p>&lt;label class="TMI_A20" span="A21-A27" type="<hi rend="italic"
                            >abstract</hi>" Property_Of="A0" lang="en"&gt;Origin of the
                        Creator&lt;/label&gt;</p>
                    <p>&lt;label class="TMI_A21" span="A21.1-A21.2" type="<hi rend="italic"
                            >abstract</hi>" SubClassOf="A20" lang="en"&gt;Creator from
                        Above&lt;/label&gt;</p>
                    <p>&lt;label class="TMI_A21.1" span="A21.1-A21.1" type="<hi rend="italic"
                            >concrete</hi>" SubClassOf="A21" lang="en"&gt;Woman who fell from the
                        sky&lt;/label&gt;</p>
                    <p>This representation makes explicit the fact that the natural language
                        expressions (like ‘Creator from Above’) are labels of classes that we
                        explicitly organise in a class hierarchy. The feature ‘type’ can take two
                        values: ‘abstract’ or ‘concrete’. The latter is indicating that the index
                        (for example: A21.1) is pointing to concrete examples in selected tales. The
                        ‘span’ feature is indicating the number (from 1 to many) of subsumed
                        indexes. We noticed that indexes (‘classes’ in our terminology), which are
                        in fact leaves (spanning only over their own number) point all to concrete
                        tales, and can thus be considered as first level motifs, whereas the other
                        classes have more a classification role. </p>
                    <p>Ongoing work is dedicated to upgrading the XML representation to SKOS-RDF, to
                        provide adequate means for differentiating between hierarchical realizations
                        and properties associated with classes, and the possibility to compute
                        inheritance properties o  of the class hierarchy. SKOS-RDF is also
                        appropriated for publishing the enriched TMI resource on the LOD. We display
                        below a simplified example (where ‘TMI_A*’ are shortcuts for URIs):</p>
                    
                    <p>                &lt;TMI_A0&gt; rdf:type skos:Concept ; </p>
                    <p>                 skos:prefLabel "Creator"@en.</p>
                    <p>            &lt;TMI_A20&gt; rdf:type skos:Concept ; </p>
                    <p>                 skos:prefLabel "Origin of the Creator"@en</p>
                    <p>                 skos:related &lt;TMI_A0&gt;.</p>
                    <p>            &lt;TMI_A21&gt; rdf:type skos:Concept ; </p>
                    <p>                 skos:prefLabel "Creator from Above"@en.</p>
                    <p>            &lt;TMI_A21.1&gt; rdf:type skos:Concept ;</p>
                    <p>                 skos:prefLabel "Woman who fell from the sky"@en ;</p>
                    <p>                 skos:broader &lt;TMI_A21&gt;</p>
                    <p>In parallel, we target the extension of motifs listed in TMI in English into
                        a multilingual version. This is carried out by accessing the <hi
                            rend="italic">Wiktionary</hi> lexicon<note>See <ref
                                target="http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/Wiktionary:Main_Page"
                                type="external">http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/Wiktionary:Main_Page.</ref></note>, via the
                        LOD-compliant <hi rend="italic">lexvo</hi><note>‘Lexvo.org brings information about languages,
                            words, characters, and other human language-related entities to the
                            Linked Data Web and Semantic Web.’ See <ref target="http://www.lexvo.org" type="external">http://www.lexvo.org</ref>.</note>
                        service. Actual work (Declerck et al. 2012) is aiming at extracting from
                        Wiktionary a multilingual lexical semantics network for the labels included
                        in TMI.</p></div>
                    
                       
                <div>
                    <head> Towards the Harmonization of Multilingual ATU On-line Data </head>
                    <p>
                    As we mentioned above, only segments of ATU are available on-line, in the
                        context of Wikipedia articles, in different languages. We note the following
                        discrepancies in these:</p>
                            <xmt:uList>
                                <item>(EN) 310 Rapunzel (Italian,Italian, Greek, Italian)</item>
                                <item>(DE) AaTh 310 Jungfrau im Turm KHM 12</item>
                                <item>(FR) AT 310: ‘La Fille dans la tour’(<hi rend="italic">The Maiden in the Tower</hi>): version allemande</item>
                            </xmt:uList>
                            <p>The English Wikipedia links <hi rend="italic">Rapunzel</hi> to four Wikipedia pages on tales belonging to the same
                        ATU type. Rhe Wikipedia page for the original Rapunzel tale is reached if
                        the reader clicks on ‘Rapunzel’. The German page links additionally to the
                        German classification KHM (<hi rend="italic">Kinder- und Hausmärchen</hi>).
                        The French Wikipedia page gives an English translation of the French naming,
                        while the French title of the Rapunzel tale is accessible only if the user
                        clicks on the link ‘version allemande’, leading to the French Wikipedia page
                        ‘Raiponce’). There is a clear need to structure this disparate information
                        in one representation format. We turned the basic information from the
                        Wikipedia pages into an integrated SKOS representation: </p>
                    <p>&lt;ATU_310&gt; rdf:type skos:Concept;</p>
                    <p>skos:prefLabel "Rapunzel"@en;</p>
                    <p>skos:altLabel "The Maiden in the Tower"@en;</p>
                    <p>skos:prefLabel "Jungfrau im Turm"@de;</p>
                    <p>skos:altLabel "Rapunzel"@de;</p>
                    <p>skos:prefLabel "La Fille dans la Tour"@fr;</p>
                    <p>skos:altLabel "Raiponce"@fr.</p>
                    
                    <p>On the basis of a small fragment of such aligned information from Wikipedia
                        pages, a representative multilingual terminology of ATU terms can be
                        aggregated, and this terminology can be re-used for supporting the
                        translation of other labels of ATU or of TMI. We investigate for this
                        terminology alignment techniques used in the Machine Translation field,
                        adapting them to the short terms that are employed in the catalogues.
                </p>
                </div>
            <div>
                <head> Relating the Upgraded Representations of TMI and ATU </head>
                <p>The SKOS vocabulary allows to establish matching relations between the upgraded
                    TMI and ATU catalogues, so that for example the motif TMI_A2223.1. ‘Cat helps
                    man build house: may occupy chimney corner.’ can be linked to ATU_545 ‘The Cat
                    as Helper’:</p>
                <p>            &lt;TMI_A2223.1&gt; rdf:type skos:Concept ; </p>
                <p>                 skos:prefLabel "Cat helps man build house: may occupy chimney
                    corner"@en.</p>
                <p>            &lt;ATU_545&gt; rdf:type skos:Concept;</p>
                <p>              skos:prefLabel "The Cat as Helper"@en.</p>
                <p>            &lt;TMI_AA2223.1&gt; skos:relatedMatch &lt;ATU_545&gt;</p>
                <p/>
                <p>Whereas we still do not take decisions on the type of matching relation, which
                    could be ‘broader’, ‘narrower’ or ‘close’. Additionally we currently investigate
                    the concrete linguistic and semantic markup of the tokens used in labels, using
                    another RDF-based formalism: the <hi rend="italic">lemon</hi><note>‘lemon
                        (LExicon Model for ONtologies) is an RDF model that allows to specify lexica
                        for ontologies and allows to publish these lexica on the Web’ (see McCrae et
                        al. 2012)). This model was developed within the European R&amp;D project
                        “Monnet” (see <ref target=" www.monnet-project.eu" type="external"
                            >www.monnet-project.eu</ref></note> representation scheme. Precise
                    linguistic mark-up allows establishing in an automated way this kind of SKOS
                    matching, since the noun ‘Helper’ can be marked as a derivation of the verb
                    ‘help’. This work also supports the building of a lexical semantics network for
                    folktales, based on the labels used in TMI and ATU.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> Towards the Automated Analysis of Motif Sequences in Folktale Plots </head>
                <p>The semantically upgraded TMI and ATU resources incorporate information about
                    class hierarchy, which allows potential users to query for motifs that are
                    connected on the same or on different levels of the taxonomy. This is feature
                    that could be exploited for the analysis or generation of storytelling
                    scenarios, since plot graphs of folktales are like watersheds, progressing by
                    connecting motifs at different hierarchical levels as points at various heights.
                    Thus the semantically upgraded TMI could help to learn about the concatenation
                    patterns of motif categories used in tales In turn, one could use such category
                    information as a source of probabilities for network construction. Such
                    probabilistic networks, prominently Hidden Markov Models, are a highly
                    significant research topic in bioinformatics, a field as much utilizing the
                    concept of motifs as narratology, therefore methodological cross-pollination is
                    a totally realistic option. Darányi et al. (2012) have recently shown that ATU
                    tale types as motif strings exemplify the basic recombination patterns of
                    chromosome mutations already on a limited sample of types, and more new findings
                    can be expected by an extension of the quest for ‘narrative DNA’. Further, the
                    manual tagging of tale types by motifs in ATU is known to be incomplete, so to
                    repeat this tagging by automatic means by annealing motif definitions and
                    NLP-based term or phrase extraction is an ultimately fruitful endeavour. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> Conclusion </head>
                <p>In this study, we focus on converting TMI and ATU into adequate semantic
                    resources, compliant with linguistic and terminological requirements, to enable
                    multilingual, content-level indexing of folktale texts. TMI and ATU in their
                    paper form have mainly been used for manual assignment of English-language
                    metadata. To upgrade these established classification systems of folk
                    narratives, we specify a development program that enhances and links them using
                    language processing and semantic technologies. Recent work was dedicated to
                    establish terminological relationships between both catalogues, using for this
                    the SKOS framework establishing semantic links between specific labels of both
                    semantically enriched catalogues. Our work will lead to the deployment of such
                    resources in the LOD framework, complementing the work of national libraries
                    that already ported their bibliographic data to the LOD. This may not only
                    facilitate automated text indexing, but also allow for more detailed analysis of
                    motif sequencing.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Acknowledgements</hi></p>
                <p>The contribution of DFKI to the  work reported in this paper has been partly
                    supported by the R&amp;D project ‘Monnet’, which is co-funded by the European
                    Union under Grant No. 248458.</p></div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Darányi, S., P. Wittek, and L. Forró</hi> (2012). Toward
                        Sequencing ‘Narrative DNA’: Tale Types, Motif Strings and Memetic
                            Pathways<hi rend="italic">.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the </hi><hi rend="italic">Workshop on
                            Computational Models of Narrative</hi>, Istanbul, May 2012.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Declerck, T., and P. Lendvai</hi> (2011)<hi rend="italic">. </hi>Linguistic and
                    Semantic Representation of the Thompson’s Motif-Index of Folk-Literature<hi
                        rend="italic">. Proceedings of the International Conference on Theory and
                        Practice of Digital Libraries</hi>, Berlin, Germany, Springer, 9/2011.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Declerck, T., and N.
                            Koleva</hi> (2012). An Iterative Ontology-Based Text Processing Strategy
                        for Detecting and Recognizing Characters in Folktales<hi rend="italic"
                            >.</hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of Digital Humanities -2012</hi>.</p><p><hi
                            rend="bold">Declerck, T., K. Mörth, and P. Lendvai</hi> (2012).
                        Accessing and standardizing Wiktionary Lexical Entries for supporting the
                        Translation of Labels in Taxonomies for Digital Humanities. <hi
                            rend="italic">Proceedings of LREC-2012</hi>.</p><p><hi rend="bold"
                            >Lendvai, P., T. Declerck, S. Darányi, P. Gervás, R. Hervás, S. Malec,
                            and F. Peinado </hi>(2010). Integration of Linguistic Markup into
                        Semantic Models of Folk Narratives: The Fairy Tale Use Case. <hi
                            rend="italic">Proceedings of the Seventh International conference on
                            Language Resources and Evaluation</hi>, Pages 1996-2001, Valetta, Malta,
                        European Language Resources Association (ELRA).</p><p><hi rend="bold"
                            >McCrae, J., E. Montiel-Ponsoda, and P. Cimiano</hi> (2012).<hi
                            rend="italic"> </hi><hi rend="italic">Integrating WordNet and Wiktionary
                            with lemon</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of  LDL 2012</hi>.
                            </p><p><hi rend="bold">Mörth, K., T. Declerck, P. Lendvai, and T.
                            Váradi</hi> (2011). Accessing Multilingual Data on the Web for the
                        Semantic Annotation of Cultural Heritage Texts. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Proceedings of the 2nd International Workshop on the Multilingual
                            Semantic Web</hi><hi rend="italic">, Bonn, Germany, Springer,
                            10/2011.</hi></p><p><hi rend="bold">Thompson, S.</hi> (1955). <hi
                            rend="italic">Motif-index of folk-literature: A classification of
                            narrative elements in folktales, ballads, myths, fables, medieval
                            romances, exempla, fabliaux, jest-books, and local legends</hi><hi
                            rend="italic">. Revised and enlarged edition</hi>. Bloomington: Indiana
                        UP, 1955-58.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Tuffield, M. M., D. E. Millard, and N. R.
                            Shadbolt</hi> (2006) Ontological Approaches to Modelling Narrative. In:
                            <hi rend="italic">2nd AKT DTA Symposium</hi>, January 2006, AKT,
                        Aberdeen University.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Uther, H.-J</hi>. (2004). <hi
                            rend="italic">The Types of International Folktales: A Classification and
                            Bibliography. Based on the system of Antti Aarne and Stith
                        Thompson</hi>. FF Communications no. 284–286. Helsinki: Suomalainen
                        Tiedeakatemia.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Zöllner-Weber, A. </hi>(2008). <hi
                            rend="italic">Noctua literaria : a computer-aided approach for the
                            formal description of literary characters using an ontology</hi>. Ph.D.
                        Thesis, Bielefeld University.</p>
                
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>