<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="ab-490">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Approaching Dickens’ Style through Random Forests</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Tabata, Tomoji</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Osaka, Japan</affiliation>
                    <email>tabata@lang.osaka-u.ac.jp</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Outline of this study </head>
                <p>This paper describes a new approach to Dickens’ style, applying a state-of-art
                    machine-learning classification technique in an effort to distinguish Dickens’
                    texts from a reference corpus of texts. This study makes use of Breiman’s (2001)
                    ‘Random Forests’ in order to spotlight lexical items Dickens consistently used
                    or avoided in his texts in comparison with the control set.</p>
                <p>By demonstrating how we can identify Dickensian stylistic markers, this study
                    also proposes Random Forests as a more powerful alternative for traditional ‘key
                    word’ analysis, a popular method in corpus linguistics for extracting a set of
                    words that characterize a particular text, a particular register/(sub)corpus, or
                    a particular diachronic set of texts, etc. from others.</p>
                <p>In a typical key word analysis, the significance of difference between two sets of
                    texts in the frequency of a word is calculated based on log-likelihood ratio
                    (LLR, henceforward; Tun- ning 1993; Rayson &amp; Garside 2000). However, LLR
                    alone provides little information about proportion of difference between the
                    sets, not to mention whether or not a particular word is distributed evenly
                    throughout each set of texts. LLR tells us only about the ‘significance’ (NOT the
                    ‘degree’ of) of discrepancy between two sets of texts with respect to frequency
                    of a partic- ular lexical variable. Thus, a potential drawback of the method is
                    seen in a case where a word occurring with exceptionally high frequency in a
                    single text can over-represent the entire set it belongs to. Using Random
                    Forests, this study will address such an issue and provide means to identify a
                    more reliable set of markers of Dickens’ style.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The drawbacks of traditional ‘key’ word analysis</head>
                <p>Textual analysis often begins with identifying key words of a text on the
                    assumption that key words reﬂect what the text is really about and that they are
                    likely to reﬂect stylistic features of the text as well. Key words as a corpus
                    linguistic terminology are defined as words that ‘appear in a text or a part of a
                    text with a frequency greater than chance occurrence alone would suggest’ (Henry
                    &amp; Roseberry 2001: 110). A popular method to measure ‘keyness’ is to
                    calculate an LLR to assess the significance of difference between the expected
                    frequency and the observed frequency of a word in a text.  However, one drawback
                    of this approach emerges when we compare Dickens’ texts with, for example, a set
                    of texts by his contemporary Wilkie Collins.</p>
                
                <p><figure><graphic url="tabl490-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Table 1: 40 most significant key words of Dickens compared with Wilkie Collins (sorted according to log-likelihood ratio (LLR))</head></figure></p>
                 
                 
                   
                <p>Although proper names such as <hi rend="italic">Dombey</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Pecksniff</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Boffin</hi> are ranked among the top
                    40 Dickensian ‘key’ words, none of these would normally be counted as important
                    at least from a stylistic perspective, apart from the fact these represent a few
                    peculiar Dickensian characters, who appear only in a single text. As we go down
                    the list, it turns out that 19 out of the top 100 are those which occur only in
                    a single text. As we turn our eyes to words listed as Collins’s key words, we
                    see 35 out of the top 100 are from a single text. If we include words that occur
                    only in a very small number of texts, the proportion becomes even greater.</p>
                <p>Another (though less obvious) drawback comes from the mathematical fact that LLR
                    em- phasizes high-frequency items: in fact, high-frequency words tend to
                    predominate towards the top of the list in Table 1, with words in lower
                    frequency-strata not tending to be highlighted easily. A better alternative is
                    needed.</p>
            </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Random Forests as a stylometric tool </head>
                    <p>Random Forests (henceforth, RF) are a very efficient classification algorithm
                    based on ensemble learning from a large number of classification trees (thus
                    ‘forests’) randomly generated from the dataset. As RF builds a classification
                    tree from a set of bootstrap samples, about one-third of the cases are left out
                    for running an internal unbiased estimate of the classification error each time.
                    The process is iterated until <hi rend="italic">n</hi>-th (500th by default)
                    tree is added to the forests, there being no need for cross-validation or a
                    separate test (Breiman and Cutler, ND). One of the most prominent features of RF
                    is its high accuracy in respect to classification of data sets. In the
                    experiments reported by Jin and Murakami (2007), RF was unexcelled in accuracy
                    among other high-performance classifiers, such as <hi rend="italic">k
                    </hi>Nearest Neighbor, Support Vector Machine, Learning Vector Quantification,
                    Bagging and AdaBoosting, in distinguishing between 200 pieces of texts written
                    by 10 modern Japanese novelists. In my own experiments, RF constantly achieved
                    accuracy rates as high as 96–100% in distinguishing Dickens’s texts from the
                    control set of texts.</p>
                    
                    <p>RF is capable of handling thousands of input variables and of running
                    efficiently on large database.<note>Breiman, L., and A. Cutler, <hi
                            rend="italic">Random Forests. </hi>Online resource. (Last accessed 20
                        October 2011.) <ref
                            target="http://stat-
                                www.berkeley.edu/users/breiman/RandomForests/cc_home.htm"
                            type="external">http://stat-
                            www.berkeley.edu/users/breiman/RandomForests/cc_home.htm</ref></note>
                    The first series of experiments with RF in this study were on a set of 24
                    Dickens’s texts versus a comparable set of 24 Wilkie Collins’ texts with from
                    more than five thousand to as few as fifty word-variables. The results were fairly
                    consistent with over 96% accuracy. The best of the results was seen when 300
                    input variables are used (Table 2). The out-of-bag (OOB) estimate of error rate
                    was 0%, or 100% accuracy in distinguishing between Dickens’s and Collins’s
                    texts.</p>
                    
                    <p><figure><graphic url="tabl490-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Table 2: A result of running Random Forests</head></figure></p>
                    
                    <p><figure><graphic url="img490-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 1: A multi-dimensional scaling diagram based on the proximity matrix generated by RF: Dickens versus Collins</head></figure></p>
                    
                    
                    
                                      
                    <p>RF computes proximities between pairs of cases that can be visualized in a
                    multidimensional scaling diagram as in Figure 1. Dickens’s texts and Collins’s
                    texts, respectively, form distinct clusters, with two unusual pieces by Collins
                    shown as outliers: <hi rend="italic">Antonina</hi> (1850), which has its setting
                    in ancient Rome, and the travel book <hi rend="italic">Rambles beyond
                        Railways</hi> (1851).</p>
                    
                    <p>Of further merit is the ability to
                        highlight the lexical items that contribute most strongly to authorial
                        classifications. RF shows the importance of variables in two measures:
                        Mean-DecreaseAccuracy and MeanDecreaseGini. The former indicates the mean of
                        decrease in the accuracy of classification when a particular variable is
                        excluded from analysis. The latter shows the mean of decrease in Gini index,
                        an index of uneven distribution of a particular variable between the groups,
                        when the variable in question is excluded from analysis. The two indices are
                        comparable to each other. Table 3 list marker words of Dickens and Collins,
                        respectively, in the order of importance (sorted according to the mean
                        decrease in Gini index).</p>
                    
    
                    
                    <p><figure><graphic url="tabl490-3.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Table 3: Import variables: Dickens markers and Collins markers (in the ordner of importance)</head></figure></p>
                    
                    <p>A close comparison of Table 3 with Table 1will show how RF helps identify
                    words with high discriminatory power. Proper nouns and words distributed
                    unevenly in each set now have effectively made way for words which are
                    consistently more frequent in one author than the other. Although Table 3 in
                    itself is worth scrutiny in that it reveals how Dickens markers are contrasted
                    with Collins markers, it is necessary to compare Dickens texts with a larger and
                    more representative corpus of writings in order to spotlight Dickens’s stylistic
                    features in a wider perspective.</p>
                 
                </div>
            <div>
                <head>Comparing and contrasting Dickens with a reference corpus of 18th-and
                    19th-Century authors</head>
                <p>In the following analysis, the set of 24 Dickens’
                    texts was compared with a reference corpus consisting of 24 eighteenth-century
                    texts and 31 nineteenth-century texts.</p>
                <p>When 300 input variables were used,
                    the OOB estimate of error rate fell down to 1.28%, or 98.72% of runs correctly
                    distinguishing Dickens from the reference set of texts.  Fig.  2 distinguishes
                    between the Dickens cluster and the control cluster. One seeming anomaly is the
                    position of <hi rend="italic">A Child’s History of England </hi>(1851), which
                    finds itself as an outlier. This history book for children is considerably
                    different in style from other Dickensian works. Therefore, it is not unexpected
                    for this piece to be found least Dickensian, a phenomenon in consistent with
                    previous multivariate studies based on other linguistic variables, such as
                    collocates of <hi rend="italic">gentleman </hi>(Tabata 2009: 272), <hi
                        rend="italic">–ly </hi>adverbs (Tabata 2005: 231) and part-of-speech
                    distribution (Tabata 2002: 173).</p>
                
                <p><figure><graphic url="img490-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 2: A multi-dimensional scaling diagram based on the proximity
                            matrix generated by RF: Dickens versus reference corpus</head></figure></p>
                
                <p><figure><graphic url="img490-6.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Table 4: Important variables: Dickens versus the reference corpus (in order of importance)</head></figure></p>
                        
                <p>Table 4 arrays major Dickens markers. Although relationships among these
                    words are com- plex enough to defy straightforward generalization, one could see
                    the predominance of words related to description of actions – typically bodily
                    actions – or postures of characters rather than words denoting abstract ideas.
                     Words like <hi rend="italic">eyes, hands, saw, looked, back </hi>in particular
                    have caught eyes of critics such as Hori (2004) and Mahlberg (2007a, 2007b),
                    which suggests the present methodology is well-grounded. Stubbs (2005)
                    states:</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">[E]ven if quantification only confirms what we have already know, this is not a
                        bad thing. Indeed , in developing a new method, it is perhaps better not to
                        find anything too new, but to confirm findings from many years of traditional
                        study, since tis gives confidence that the method can be relied on (Stubbs
                        2005: 6).</hi></p>
                <p>In order to determine local textual functions
                    (Mahlberg 2007a, 2007b) each of these words performs, it is of course necessary
                    to go back to texts and examine the words in local contexts with the help of
                    other tools such as concordance, collocation, and <hi rend="italic"
                    >n</hi>-grams. However, the present method opens up a promising pathway to
                    deeper textual analysis. The results of this study will also point to the
                    effectiveness of this approach in cases of disputed authorship.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Appendix</head>
                
                <p><figure><graphic url="tabl490-5.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Table 5: Dickens component of ORCHIDS</head></figure></p>
                <p><figure><graphic url="tabl490-6.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Table 6: 18th Century component of ORCHIDS</head></figure></p>
                <p><figure><graphic url="tabl490-7.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Table 7: 19th Century component of ORCHIDS</head></figure></p>
                
            </div>
           
        </body>
        <back>
            <div><head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Breiman, L.</hi> (2001). Random forests. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Machine Learning</hi> 45: 5-23.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Dunning, T.</hi>
                    (1993). Accurate methods for the statistics of surprise and coincidence. <hi
                        rend="italic">Computational Linguistics</hi> 19(1): 61-74.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Henry.
                         A., and R. L. Rooseberry</hi> (2001). Using a small corpus to obtain data
                    for teaching genre. In M. Ghadessy, A. Henry and R. L. Roseberry (eds.), <hi
                        rend="italic">Small Corpus and ELT</hi>. Amsterdam,Philadelphia, Pa.: John
                    Benjamins, pp. 93-133.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Hori, M.</hi> (2004). <hi
                        rend="italic">Investigating Dickens’ Style: A Collocational Analysis</hi>.
                    New York: Palgrave Macmillan.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Jin, M., and M. Murakami</hi> (2007). Random
                    forest hou ni yoru bunshou no kakite no doutei (Authorship Identification Using
                    Random Forests), <hi rend="italic">Toukei Suuri </hi>(<hi rend="italic"
                        >Proceedings of the Institute of Statistical Mathematics</hi>) 55(2):
                    255-268.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Mahlberg, M.</hi> (2007a). Corpus stylistics: bridging the gap between linguistic
                    and literary studies. In M. Hoey et al. (eds.), <hi rend="italic">Text,
                        discourse and corpora. Theory and analysis</hi>. London: Continuum, pp.
                    217-246.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Mahlberg, M.</hi> (2007b). Clusters, key clusters and local textual functions in
                    Dickens. <hi rend="italic">Corpora</hi> 2(1): 1-31.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Rayson, P., and R. Garside</hi> (2000).
                     Comparing Corpora Using Frequency Profiling. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of
                        the Workshop on Comparing Corpora, Held in Conjunction with the 38th Annual
                        Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics </hi>(ACL 2000),
                    1-8 October 2000, Hong Kong, 1-6. Available online at <ref
                        target="http://www.comp.lancs.ac.uk/computing/users/paul/phd/phd2003.pdf"
                    type="external">http://www.comp.lancs.ac.uk/computing/users/paul/phd/phd2003.pdf</ref>.</p><p><hi
                        rend="bold">Stubbs, M.</hi> (2005). Conrad in the computer: examples of
                    quantitative stylistic methods. <hi rend="italic">Language and Literature</hi>
                    14(1): 5-24.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Tabata, T.</hi> (2002). Investigating Stylistic Variation in Dickens through
                    Correspondence Analysis of Word-Class Distribution. In T. Saito, J. Nakamura and
                    S. Yamasaki (eds.), <hi rend="italic">English Corpus Lin- guistics in
                    Japan</hi>. Amsterdam: Rodopi, pp. 165-182.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Tabata, T.</hi> (2005). Profiling stylistic variations in Dickens and Smollett
                    through correspondence analy- sis of low frequency words. <hi rend="italic"
                        >ACH</hi>/<hi rend="italic">ALLC</hi><hi rend="italic"> </hi><hi
                        rend="italic">2005 Conference Abstracts</hi>, Humanities Computing and Media
                    Centre, University of Victoria, Canada, pp. 229-232.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Tabata, T.</hi> (2009). More about gentleman in Dickens. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Digital Humanities 2009 Conference Abstracts, University of Maryland,
                        College Park, June 22–25, 2009</hi>, The Association for Literary and Lin-
                    guistic Computing, the Association for Computers and the Humanities, and the
                    Society for Digital Humanities – Société pour l’étude des médias interactifs,
                    pp. 270-275.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>