<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-413">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Focus on Users in the Open Development of the National Digital Library of Finland</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Hirvonen, Ville</name>
                    <affiliation>The National Library of Finland, Finland</affiliation>
                    <email>ville.z.hirvonen@helsinki.fi</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Kautonen, Heli Johanna</name>
                    <affiliation>The National Library of Finland, Finland</affiliation>
                    <email>heli.kautonen@helsinki.fi</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>The Public Interface of the National Digital Library of Finland</head>
                <p>The tools for discovering cultural heritage material are changing. For more than
                    a decade there has been a demand for better services for acquiring and working
                    with the ever increasing amount of digitized collections of archives, libraries,
                    and museums. Almost quarterly we hear about new electronic search and research
                    services, which promise better assistance to academic workers. These tools are
                    brought out by software vendors, academic research and development projects, or
                    publishers. Looking at these news we can estimate that the research
                    infrastructure for scholars in the humanities, currently concentrating on
                    resource databases, will be replaced by integrated, modular services, which
                    utilize the potential of social metadata.</p>
                <p>As a response to the increasing demand for novel research infrastructure
                    services, we in Finland have started building our National Digital Library
                    (NDL). The NDL project covers the digitization of Finnish archives, libraries,
                    and museums; the long term preservation system; and a next generation search
                    application called the Public Interface, which harvests the metadata from
                    various data repositories and provides it for the end users. The NDL will also
                    serve as the national aggregator to the European Digital Library, Europeana. The
                    development project is funded by the Finnish Ministry of Education and Culture
                    until 2014, after which there should be permanent funding for maintenance and
                    support. The project started in 2008 and will reach the publication of the first
                    end-user interfaces displaying the first set of material by the end of the year
                    2012. (Further information:  www.kdk.fi/en/public-interface.)</p>
                <p>The Public Interface facilitates access to the diverse digital repositories of
                    Finnish libraries, archives and museums. The users can use it to find physical
                    items, digital objects, and licensed electronic materials. The metadata for
                    these are harvested from the organizations’ back-end systems via an OAI-PMH
                    interface. Access to restricted and licensed materials will be provided by
                    integrating user authentication from the corresponding back-end system.</p>
                <p>Within the service there will be one common user interface for all free contents
                    within the system, called the National View. It will serve as the basis for
                    those organizations who will not need specific system integrations and
                    modifications. Organizations who wish to integrate external services, such as an
                    online payment system or an ontology, to the core service can set their own
                    interface instances and thus create so called Local Views to the NDL. All will
                    still have the entire set of data available for their customers, via whichever
                    user interface, if desired.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>A Technically Challenging Project</head>
                <p>
                    From the technical point of view, the scope of the project is very ambitious.
                        So far there has been a lot of hard work choosing and testing the
                        satisfactory software for the Public Interface and defining various system
                        interfaces. Potentially all Finnish archives, libraries, and museums are
                        entitled to join the project and get their services within the NDL. While
                        some of them will follow given standards and some have similar back-end
                        systems, there will be those who will require completely individual
                        solutions for systems’ integration.</p>
                    <p>Scalability and additional service integrations also require thorough
                        planning and good management. The amount of material in a country like
                        Finland is not enormous and the number of possible service integrations can
                        be controlled.  However, the number of organizations and user interfaces is
                        easily in the hundreds. If not compensated, these can have some effect on
                        server loads and delays, which in turn will have impact on the end-user
                        experience.</p>
                    <p>The greatest technical challenge so far has been the choice of the core
                        software for constructing the Public Interface. When the available software
                        solutions were initially compared, the information discovery and delivery
                        system Primo by the Ex Libris Group was considered as the most suitable for
                        the needs of the NDL. During the pilot testing, which took almost sixteen
                        months, it became apparent that the customizations needed in Primo would
                        require much more time and resources than was reserved for the project.
                        Although the software procurement contract between the National Library of
                        Finland and Ex Libris was cancelled in January 2012, the partnership between
                        these organizations continues. The National Library still examines
                        possibilities to provide access from the NDL Public Interface to the Primo
                        Central Index.</p>
                    <p>In order to stay in the schedule of the project, a new solution was needed
                        quickly. After a speedy market analysis, the National Library decided to
                        turn to use an open source software solution. Having some experience of open
                        source development, and avoiding a tedious start from the scratch, the
                        National Library studied some alternatives to be used as the basis for the
                        software development. The library resource portal VuFind was selected to
                        serve as the starting point.
                </p>
                </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Focus on Usability</head>
                        <p>From the very beginning of the NDL project the importance of
                        end-users and their expectations has been seriously regarded. As a means to
                        realize the aim of good usability, a Usability Working Group and a
                        reasonable budget has been assigned to meeting the goals and coordinating
                        the needed tasks. The group has established the usability requirements and
                        defined target users for the Public Interface service, and gradually
                        completed a Usability Plan for the project and its outcome. Applicable
                        design approaches (e.g. Meroni &amp; Sangiori 2011) and best practices (<hi
                            rend="italic">e.g.</hi> Clark et al<hi rend="italic">.</hi> 2010) have
                        been consulted all along the process. The plan covers all project phases
                        from planning to maintenance, but is still flexible enough to adjust to
                        changes in technical solutions  or the scope of the project. </p><p>Years
                        2010 and 2011 were mostly spent on testing the Primo software, but also on
                        testing the service concept among prospect users. Eight organizations among
                        Finnish archives, libraries, and museums volunteered, and started
                        integrating their back-end systems to Primo. The concept testing was
                        conducted by the University of Tampere in summer 2010 (Lavikainen 2010).
                        Some months later a user study was conducted by an usability consultant
                        company Adage on the first end-user interface layouts of the National View
                        (Hirvonen 2011). The results of both studies indicated that some features of
                        the future service might be difficult for end-users to comprehend, and
                        therefore the final design of the end-user interfaces will be crucially
                        important. However, the results gave no reason to change the scope of the
                        service or the system requirements. These studies, on their part, supported
                        the demand to chance the software solution.</p>
                
                        </div>
                            <div>
                                <head>Several Local Views, One National View </head>
                                
                <p>Although the core software had to be changed after a reasonably long period of
                    work, the efforts put on testing one solution could be immediately utilized with
                    the other option. Especially the concept of different views was considered
                    applicable on VuFind, too.</p>
                <p>During the year 2011 some Local Views were implemented with Primo and exposed to
                    technical and functional tests. The first in line was the Turku City Library,
                    which integrated Primo to their web content management and publication system.
                    In their solution the main objective was to merge the  Digital Library into a
                    dynamic and locally oriented customer service. On the second track there was the
                    National Board of Antiquities of Finland, which has invested considerable
                    resources on establishing common technological solutions for Finnish museums.
                    They implemented some varying user interface instances that displayed the museum
                    repositories and utilized the features offered by Primo. Their focus was on
                    experimentation of data visualization and service integration, since they intend
                    to offer one Local View for all museums. The third track of the Local View
                    testing concentrated on a portal-like application that leaves the external
                    services to be run on the back-end system. The National Archives of Finland
                    worked on mapping and normalizing aggregation levels of archival data. They also
                    aim at producing solutions and standards for all archives in Finland. Such
                    applications of Local Views will later provide excellent field for usage
                    studies, since they reveal three entirely different viewpoints to the same
                    service.</p>
                <p>The National View, which will serve as the user interface for compiling all free
                    material within the NDL, could not be thoroughly implemented and tested with
                    Primo. Therefore there are now great expectations to the implementation of those
                    features that support effective discovery and display of different types of
                    content, i.e. content from archives, libraries, and museums at the same time.
                    (See Fig. 1.) According to the recently updated Usability Plan the National View
                    will be exposed to several usage tests. Before the summer 2013 there will be a
                    comprehensive log analysis, some customer surveys, and other usability studies,
                    which aim at further analyzing the service concept and giving input to the user
                    interface design.</p>
                <p>Along with the new software solution, the software development methods, the
                    collaboration practices, and the user testing processes have been renewed. The
                    usability tests planned for the implementation and production phases will still
                    be valid and executed in time. In addition, a constant row of end-users will be
                    involved in the agile development process to test freshly developed features
                    immediately after they have been published.</p>
                                <p><figure>
                                    <graphic url="img413-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                                        mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                                    <head>Figure 1: The layout of the National View exposed to end-user tests
                                        in March 2012</head>
                                </figure></p>
                                </div><div>
                    <head>More Challenges Ahead</head>
                    <p>With the exception of certain back-end a <hi rend="italic">pplication
                        programming interfaces (APIs)</hi>, the NDL Public Interface service will be
                    mainly developed by the staff of the National Library. It will be crucially
                    important to share knowledge and results with the open source community involved
                    in VuFind. The national open source development community will also be
                    communicated with. This sets extra demands on project management and
                    collaboration management.  </p>
                    <p>In future years the Public Interface of the NDL will replace several research
                        services currently used by humanities’ scholars. Within the National Library
                        of Finland alone the user interface of the national bibliographic database,
                        the portal of electronic publications in Finnish libraries, and the
                        interface of digital material repository will be ‘powered by’ the Public
                        Interface of NDL. It is difficult yet to foresee how the actual research
                        activities will change due to the new tools. At least  scholars themselves
                        should be more involved in systems’ and services’ development than today
                        (see <hi rend="italic">e.g.</hi> Jeffreys 2010).  Nevertheless, the
                        Usability Working Group has already made preliminary plans for examining the
                        scholarly use of the NDL service.</p>
                    <p>As soon as a sufficient number of organizations have gone live, and there is
                        a critical mass of coherent data within the service, we can start proper
                        tracking and evaluation of the system as a research infrastructure. It is to
                        be noticed, that the service is not just a library in a digital environment,
                        since it can offer and recommend content from archives and museums on single
                        search request.  It will be particularly interesting to study how students
                        and scholars will be able to utilize such diverse and multifaceted
                        information, and how that information can best be represented and laid out
                        to the user. Therefore, it is yet to be seen, how well the National Digital
                        Library of Finland will meet the great expectations.</p>
                                    
                                    
                
                </div>
            
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                
                    <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Clark, D. J., D. Nicholas, and I. Rowlands</hi> (2011).<hi
                        rend="italic"> Europeana Log Analysis Report 1. </hi>Europeana Connect.
                    <ref target="http://ciber-research.eu/download/20110821-M3.1.2_eConnect_LogAnalysis.pdf" type="external">http://ciber-research.eu/download/20110821-M3.1.2_eConnect_LogAnalysis.pdf</ref>
                    (accessed 14 March 2012).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Hirvonen, V.</hi> (2011). <hi rend="italic">Kansallisen näkymän
                        käytettävyystesti.</hi> Project report, The National Library of Finland..
                    <ref target="http://kdk.fi/wiki/images/4/45/KDK-k%C3%A4ytett%C3%A4vyystesti_2011_01.pdf" type="external">http://kdk.fi/wiki/images/4/45/KDK-k%C3%A4ytett%C3%A4vyystesti_2011_01.pdf</ref>
                    (accessed 14 March 2012).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Jeffreys, P.</hi> (2010). The Developing Conception of
                        e-Research<hi rend="italic">.</hi> In W. H. Dutton and P. W. Jeffreys
                    (eds.), <hi rend="italic">World Wide Research. Reshaping the Sciences and
                        Humanities. </hi>Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press,  pp. 51-66.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Lavikainen, V.</hi> (2012). <hi rend="italic">Kansallisen
                        digitaalisen kirjaston palvelukonseptin testaaminen.</hi> Project report,
                    University of Tampere. 
                    <ref target="http://kdk.fi/wiki/images/9/96/KDKn_palvelukonseptin_testaaminen.pdf" type="external">http://kdk.fi/wiki/images/9/96/KDKn_palvelukonseptin_testaaminen.pdf</ref>  (accessed
                    14 March 2012).</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Meroni, A., and D. Sangiori</hi> (2011). <hi rend="italic">Design
                        for Services. </hi>Surrey, UK: Gower.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>