<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-431">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Texts in Motion – Rethinking Reader Annotations in Online Literary
                    Texts</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Fendt, Kurt E.</name>
                    <affiliation>Massachusetts Institute of Technology, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>fendt@mit.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Kelley, Wyn</name>
                    <affiliation>Massachusetts Institute of Technology, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>wkelley@mit.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Zhang, Jia</name>
                    <affiliation>Massachusetts Institute of Technology, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>zhangjia@mit.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Della Costa, Dave</name>
                    <affiliation>Massachusetts Institute of Technology, USA</affiliation>
                    <email>dfd@mit.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>
               Taking Reader’s Response Theory as the basis, this short paper discusses
                    approaches to enhancing reader interaction with literary texts through social
                    annotation and visualization tools. The integration of multimedia repositories,
                    collaborative annotation mechanisms, and advanced visualization techniques
                    creates a digital environment for students and scholars alike and provides
                    readers with rich tools for both interpreting literary texts and visualizing
                    reader interactions with these texts. Examples will be drawn from Mary Shelley’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Frankenstein</hi> and Herman Melville’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Moby-Dick</hi>.</p>
                <p>Notes in margins of books fulfill several functions for the individual reader:
                recording thoughts and associations while reading, marking important passages or
                references to other parts within the same text, noting possible links to other texts
                and documents, or simply creating a reference point to come back to in a subsequent
                reading. From a cognitive point of view, marginalia offer insights into the
                interaction of a reader with a given text and offer hints towards understanding the
                process of reading and sense making. Reading a book that already contains notes by
                another reader can be both enlightening or distracting, yet it allows us to
                encounter another person’s reading experience, forming another layer of meaning that
                might influence our own interpretation. It’s this interactive nature of the reading
                experience, the constant interaction between the text itself and the reader’s
                response to it that, according to Wolfgang Iser in the <hi rend="italic">Implied
                    Reader</hi> (1974)<note> Iser, W. (1974). <hi rend="italic">The Implied
                        Reader; Patterns of Communication in Prose Fiction from Bunyan to
                        Beckett</hi>. Baltimore: John Hopkins UP.</note>, allows us to interpret a
                literary text. The result is a ‘virtual text’ that is formed by a text and the
                reader‘s interaction with it.</p>
                <p>For centuries, marginalia have served as instantiations of a rich reader
                    engagement with a text, often providing hints to interpretations from different
                    times, languages, and cultures thus forming critical insights into texts that
                    would otherwise be lost. With more and more texts being digitized or already
                    born digital texts available online or on electronic readers, the notion of
                    marginalia in a digital space poses a number of interesting questions. How can
                    we preserve, enhance, and expand this critical interaction especially with
                    literary texts, particularly when we consider the social dimension offered
                    through digital media? How can we make use of large digital text, image, video,
                    and audio repositories to help us represent a text as a ‘multi-dimensional
                    space,’ as a ‘tissue of quotations drawn from innumerable centers of culture’
                    (Roland Barthes)<note>Barthes, R. (1997). The Death of the Author. In <hi
                        rend="italic">Image – Music–
                      Text</hi>. New York: Hill &amp; Wang, pp. 142-148.</note>? What if we had digital tools that
                    allowed us to even visualize how readers experience a text by following their
                    interactions, for example by graphically representing their annotations across
                    the whole text? How do readers discover connections within a text, across
                    different texts, to source texts, to adaptations in other media, or derivative
                    texts? What if we could finally visualize the ‘act of reading’ (Iser) and
                    analyze a literary text from the perspective of both the author and the
                    readers?</p>
                <p>A multidisciplinary research team at HyperStudio, the Massachusetts Institute of
                    Technology’s Digital Humanities Lab within Comparative Media Studies, has been
                    exploring these questions, developing digital tools that allow readers to create
                    multimedia annotations to literary texts, and testing them in the literature
                    classroom. HyperStudio has created specific visualization tools that allow for a
                    visual representation of the structural features of a text and, more
                    importantly, offer graphs that show the reader interactions with a given text
                    both on page and whole book levels. At the same time, these visualizations also
                    serve as navigational mechanisms through the texts and annotations, both
                    fine-grained and on a whole-text basis.</p>
                <p>Pedagogically this work is informed by a wide range of theoretical and practical
                    approaches: concepts of media literacy, work on interactive and collaborative
                    text editing, a pedagogy of close reading and critical writing devised to place
                    literary texts in relation to their multimedia sources and adaptations; and new
                    Digital Humanities tools for visualization, data mining, and social
                    networking.</p>
                <p>At the heart of these different approaches lie theories and technologies for
                    understanding the mix as a central feature of new media ‘literacies’ or
                    ‘competencies,’ in Henry Jenkins’ terminology<note>Jenkins, J., et al. (2006). <hi rend="italic"
                        >Confronting the Challenges of Participatory Culture: Media Education
                        for the 21st Century</hi>. Chicago: The John D. and Catherine T.
                        MacArthur Foundation. <ref
                            target="http://digitallearning.macfound.org/atf/cf/%7B7E45C7E0-A3E0-4B89-AC9C-E807E1B0AE4E%7D/JENKINS_WHITE_PAPER.PDF"
                            type="external">http://digitallearning.macfound.org/atf/cf/%7B7E45C7E0-A3E0-4B89-AC9C-E807E1B0AE4E%7D/JENKINS_WHITE_PAPER.PDF
                        </ref>accessed 25 March 2012.</note>. The
                    notion of remix borrowed from popular musical forms has come to define new modes
                    of artistic production and consumption that inspire active creators. Similarly
                    in academic scholarship and pedagogy, an appreciation for how artists borrow and
                    rework cultural materials has energized the study of creative processes. In a
                    literature classroom, traditional methods of close reading, source study, and
                    literary analysis can merge with newer interpretive models to view texts in
                    creative flux: as fluid vessels for recombining older forms of inspiration and
                    engendering new ones in different media adaptations. Reading literary works as
                    textual remixes reinforces strong close reading and critical skills while
                    rejuvenating source study. We see text annotation at the center of this notion
                    of remix.  </p>
                <p>The visualization approaches have been informed by a range of current online
                tools for visualizing texts but also by artistic representations of text corpora
                such as David Small’s work<note>Small, D. (1999). <hi rend="italic">Talmud
                        Project</hi>. <ref
                        target="http://www.davidsmall.com/portfolio/talmud-project/" type="external"
                        >http://www.davidsmall.com/portfolio/talmud-project/</ref> accessed 25 March
                    2012</note>, timeline tools such as HyperStudio’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Chronos</hi><note>MIT HyperStudio (2011). <hi rend="italic">Chronos
                        Timeline</hi>. <ref
                        target="http://hyperstudio.mit.edu/software/chronos-timeline/"
                        type="external">http://hyperstudio.mit.edu/software/chronos-timeline/</ref>
                    accessed 25 March 2012.</note>, and playful approaches such as the ones by John
                        Maeda<note><ref target="http://www.maedastudio.com/index.php"
                        type="external"> http://www.maedastudio.com/index.php accessed 25 March
                        2012.</ref></note>. Existing visualization concepts such as word clouds,
                word trees, phrase nets are only a few of the online visual tools that help us graph
                occurrences of single words or the relationship between words within texts. Popular
                visualization tools such as the ones available for experimentation at IBM‘s Many Eyes<note>
                    <ref target="http://www-958.ibm.com/software/data/cognos/manyeyes/"
                        type="external">http://www-958.ibm.com/software/data/cognos/manyeyes/</ref>
                    accessed 25 March 2012.</note> or scholarly tools such as Voyeur<note>
                    <ref target="http://hermeneuti.ca/voyeur/" type="external"
                        >http://hermeneuti.ca/voyeur/</ref> accessed 25 March 2012.</note> help us
                quickly discover word frequencies and usage patterns. Google’s Ngram
                        Viewer<note><ref target="http://books.google.com/ngrams" type="external"
                        >http://books.google.com/ngrams</ref> accessed 25 March 2012.</note> makes
                the leap beyond the single text and searches across ‘millions’ of books and displays
                occurrences of single or multiple words as line graphs along a timeline that spans
                decades or even centuries. While these tools help us greatly analyze a range of
                linguistic aspects of the work of an author, they tell us little about how readers
                interact with literary texts. The tools that HyperStudio is developing allow us to
                visualize how readers interact with a text, how they discover connections within a
                text, across texts, to source texts, to adaptations in other media, or derivative
                texts. In the end, they aim at visualizing the ‘act of reading’ (Iser) and helping
                to analyze a literary text from the perspective of both the author and the readers. </p>
                <p>From a software development point of view, we are using principles of agile
                    development and co-design, involving students, faculty, designers, and
                    assessment specialists from the outset. Building on HyperStudio’s
                    Ruby-on-Rails-based platform Repertoire, the text annotation tools feature
                    shareable text repositories, easy role and group management, filtering of
                    annotations via tags and search, and display of overlapping annotations from
                    different users/groups. The visualization tools will allow a seamless transition
                    from fine-grained display of annotations to a global view of annotations within
                    a whole literary text.</p>
                <p>We recognize that there are a number of text annotation tools available, both
                    open source and commercial, that include some of the features we are describing
                    here.  However, the approach to annotating texts with multimedia materials,
                    annotation across texts, a deep integration of visualization tools for both
                    textual features and reader interaction, combined with a strong educational
                    focus, is unique in the field.   </p>
                <p>Early feedback from students using a prototype of the annotation tools in two
                    literature classes at MIT has shown a deeper engagement by students not only in
                    processes of close reading and creating references to external sources but also
                    in students’ requests for private workspaces where they could upload their
                    selection of literary texts and annotate them in the same way for their own
                    research, not even related to any class assignments. In addition, the
                    HyperStudio team has also received a number of feature requests from students.
                    One feature in particular was in great demand (on our schedule for later
                    implementation): the flexible comparison and joint annotation of two texts
                    side-by-side. Each text can be independently defined as source, version, base,
                    or adaptation, allowing for the display of referenced annotations even when the
                    related text is not present. Additional features such as annotation of
                    non-contiguous portions of text and the creation of multimedia essays based on
                    reader annotations will be implemented in a next phase.  By the time of DH2012,
                    HyperStudio will have tested the annotation tools and visualizations in half a
                    dozen courses and conducted extensive assessment.</p>
                
               
           
            <p><hi rend="bold">Funding</hi></p>
            <p>This work was supported by the MIT Class Fund and the MIT SHASS Teaching and Learning
                Fund.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>