<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-436">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Reasoning about Genesis or The Mechanical Philologist</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Wissenbach, Moritz</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Würzburg, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>moritz.wissenbach@uni-wuerzburg.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Pravida, Dietmar</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Frankfurt, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>dpravida@goethehaus-frankfurt.de</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Middell, Gregor</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Würzburg, Germany</affiliation>
                    <email>gregor@middell.net</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>Dating manuscripts is one of the most demanding tasks of textual scholarship (see
                    e.g. Bockelkamp 1982; Tyson 1987). While there is a vast body of literature on
                    dating and constituting witness stemmata for ancient and medieval codices (West
                    1973; Bischoff 2009), there seems to be hardly any systematic discussion on the
                    issue of dating modern manuscripts. There have been successful approaches to
                    date older material by computational phylogenetics (Robinson et al. 1998) with
                    the consecutive import of quantitative methods and tools into the field, but to
                    our knowledge, there is no approach that uses formal logics.<note>Our purpose of mechanizing the operation of
                        manuscript dating has obvious parallels in various approaches (e.g. Quentin
                        1922; Greg 1927) of charting relationships between different manuscript
                        readings by means of a formula system or a decision procedure (conveniently
                        summarized in Birdsall 1992: 153sq). Dom Quentin, Greg and their followers
                        could build on a highly sophisticated tradition of theoretical reflection on
                        establishing manuscript genealogies without the intervention of subjective
                        interpretation (Lachmann 1842: v) for which there is no analogue in our 
                        particular field of interest.</note>
                </p>
                
                <p>Usually, the tools at the modern philologist’s disposal are very basic: A pencil
                    or marker pen and a maximal writing surface (<hi rend="italic">Figure 1</hi>:
                    Reconstruction of the genesis of Faust manuscript  VH2). In this paper, we
                    examine the use of a formal knowledge representation to facilitate the dating of
                    a large corpus of inscriptions on manuscripts. The knowledge representation is
                    to be a</p><xmt:uList>
                <item>point where diverse and possibly conflicting research sources can be
                    integrated</item>
                <item>working tool for the philologist to be queried and modified during
                    research</item>
                <item>basis of facts for a formal reasoning calculus </item>
                <item>database for users.</item></xmt:uList>
                <p>The quality of the results of automatic reasoning will be of special interest.
                    Will they be incorrect or correct, and in case of the latter, will they be
                    largely expected or to some degree unexpected?</p>
                
                <p><figure><graphic url="img436-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 1</head></figure></p>
                
                <div><head>Relativedating of modern
                            manuscripts</head>
                        <p>By <hi rend="italic">inscription</hi> we understand any portion of
                            written text on a manuscript in one specific phase of writing. If there
                            is no<hi rend="italic"> absolute chronology</hi> at hand, the only
                            possibility left is to try to give a <hi rend="italic">relative
                                chronology</hi>. We believe that a considerable part of conventional
                            dating procedures can be reduced to a combination of more elementary
                            steps that allow a more explicit and even formal approach.</p>
                    </div><div>
                        <head>Inductive vs. deductive reasoning</head>
                        <p>Relations between inscriptions can be used as predicates in a formal
                            logic and reasoned upon by a suitable calculus. In order to reason
                            deductively, a general rule or a set of rules is required. It is
                            imaginable for this set to be induced automatically by a machine
                            learning algorithm. In this study, however, the set of rules is manually
                            defined. Thus, the presented approach is purely deductive.</p>
                    </div><div>
                        <head>Dealing with contradictions</head>
                        <p>Some assertions are taken from various sources of research, others are
                            calculated automatically from existing data and even others are
                            established manually. There will inevitably be contradictions. Possible
                            solutions are:</p>
                        <xmt:oList rend="arabic">
                            <item>
                                Do not try to resolve and thus conceal the contradictions.
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                Try to specify explicit rules that prioritize one class of
                                    assertion over the other.
                            </item>
                            <item>
                                <p>Use a method of approximate reasoning.</p>
                            </item>
                        </xmt:oList>
                        <p>We have decided for the second approach, as it preserves the advantages
                            of the first while still enabling a very unambiguous specification and
                            interpretation.</p>
                    </div></div>
              
            
            <div>
                <head>Reasoning rules for relative dating</head>
                <p>
                        To our knowledge there is no extensive list of typical modes of
                            philological reasoning available, so we will try to give some elementary
                            suggestions (following Pravida 2005:58f.). </p>
                        <div>
                            <head>Relations between inscriptions</head>
                            
                                <p><hi rend="bold">Chronological anteriority</hi></p>
                                <p>The relation that we are interested in as a result is a temporal
                                    one: Which inscriptions <hi rend="italic">predate</hi> other
                                    inscriptions:</p>
                            <p><figure><graphic url="tabl436-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
                            
                            
                                <p><hi rend="bold">Syntagmatic precedence</hi></p>
                                <p>Inscription I <hi rend="italic">syntagmatically precedes</hi> a
                                    second inscription J if the text of J follows the text of I with
                                    respect to a larger text that contains them both: </p>
                            
                            <p><figure><graphic url="tabl436-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
                            
                            
                                <p><hi rend="bold">Paradigmatic relationship</hi></p>
                                <p>Inscription I <hi rend="italic">is paradigmatically related</hi>
                                    to a second inscription J if they share text: </p>
                           
                            <p><figure><graphic url="tabl436-3.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
                            
                                <p><hi rend="bold">Text-genetic anteriority</hi></p>
                                <p>Inscription I <hi rend="italic">text-genetically precedes</hi> an
                                    inscription J, if I contains an earlier stage of a text
                                    contained by J:</p>
                              
                            <p><figure><graphic url="tabl436-4.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
                            
                                <p>Text-genetic anteriority by definition implies chronological
                                    anteriority.</p>
                            
                                <p><hi rend="bold">Exclusive containment</hi></p>
                                <p>The overall syntagmatic interval of one inscription, I, is said
                                    to be exclusively contained by the overall syntagmatic interval
                                    of another inscription J, if some part of the text of
                                    inscription I lies within the overall syntagmatic interval of
                                    inscription J, where they have a larger coherent textual
                                    neighbourhood than in inscription I:</p>
                            
                            <p><figure><graphic url="tabl436-5.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
                            
                                <p>The notion of exclusive containment captures the case of
                                    additional amplification of a passage. Exclusive containment is
                                    some special case of text-genetic posteriority with regard to
                                    some portion of an inscription. (Exclusive containment is very
                                    common in the working manuscripts of Brentano; we take it as a
                                    matter of course that it will be necessary to refine our set of
                                    relations as soon as we will extend our approach to other
                                    authors.)</p>
                            </div>
                        
                        <div>
                            <head>Rules</head>
                            <p>Rules or axioms can be defined as a basis for deduction. The language
                                we use is that of predicate logic. The transitivity of the <hi
                                    rend="italic">predates</hi> relation, e.g., can be expressed
                                as</p>
                            
                            <p><figure><graphic url="tabl436-6.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
                            
                            <p>Other properties of relations can be modelled for the respective
                                relations accordingly.</p>
                            
                                <p><hi rend="bold">Precedence</hi></p>
                                <p>Rules that might potentially lead to contradictions need to be
                                    ordered, so that it is clear which rule has precedence over
                                    another. Consider the two rules</p>
                               
                            <p><figure><graphic url="tabl436-7.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
                            
                                <p>In order to subordinate rule b under rule a, we add a conjugation
                                    of the negated antecedent of the first rule:</p>

                            <p><figure><graphic url="tabl436-8.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
                            
                                <p>In this way, all rules can be ordered and thus the set of rules
                                    be made logically consistent. In the following, we will list the
                                    rules ordered by priority from lowest to highest. The term pi 
                                     is used to designate priority.</p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <p><hi rend="bold">Syntagmatic precedence</hi></p>
                                
                                <p><figure><graphic url="tabl436-8a.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
                                
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <p><hi rend="bold">Paradigmatic relations</hi></p>
                                <p>The paradigmatic relation is symmetric. For dating, another hint
                                    (term c) must be considered (material, elementary genetic
                                    classification, textual):</p>
                                <p><figure><graphic url="tabl436-9.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <p><hi rend="bold">Containment</hi></p>
                                <p><figure><graphic url="tabl436-10.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
                            </div>
                            <div>
                                <p><hi rend="bold">Text-genetic anteriority</hi></p>
                                <p><figure><graphic url="tabl436-11.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
                            </div>
            </div>
 
            
            <div>
                <head> An Example from Clemens Brentano’s <hi rend="italic">Romances of the
                        Rosary</hi></head>
                <p>
                    The twelfth canto of the <hi rend="italic">Romances of the Rosary</hi> serves
                        as an example that our default assumptions and their formalisation do in
                        fact yield adequate results (cf. Pravida 2005; Brentano 2006). We consider
                        the drafts (inscriptions) J1-6.</p><p>From the data which can be obtained
                        from manuscript descriptions, we gather the relations shown in <hi
                            rend="italic">Figure 2</hi>:</p>
                
                
                <p><figure><graphic url="img436-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 2</head></figure></p>
                
                <p>From textual evidence we know that:</p>
                
                <p><figure><graphic url="tabl436-12.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
                
                
                <p><figure><graphic url="tabl436-13.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
                
                   
                    <p>(**)</p><p>Our reasoning machine concludes:</p>
               
                <p><figure><graphic url="tabl436-14.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure></p>
                
                <p>Which establishes a total order (<hi rend="italic">Figure 3</hi>):</p>
                
                <p><figure><graphic url="img436-3.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/><head>Figure 3</head></figure></p>
                
              
            </div>
            <div>
                <head> Application to the Faust edition / Outlook</head>
                <p>
                    The above example is well suited for our purpose, perhaps exceptionally so.
                        Other texts may prove to be more difficult. Goethe’s habits of composing,
                        for example, are much less linear. Yet, we can show that the genesis of the
                        last act of <hi rend="italic">Faust II</hi> can be captured in a way that
                        resembles our example (Pravida, forthcoming). We expect that the genesis of
                        the whole work will permit an analysis closely following these lines. As
                        there is much more electronically encoded material, a computer-assisted
                        approach seems very promising to us. </p>
                    <p>We used first-order logic and a theorem prover (Schulz 2002). The required
                        expressivity of the logical formalism is probably lower than first-order
                        logic (e.g. it will not need quantification), but more expressive than
                        commonly used Semantic Web logics (e.g. OWL/SWRL) for the purpose of rule
                        prioritisation. The adequacy of a non-monotonic logic, such as default
                        reasoning (Reiter 1980; Delgrande &amp; Schaub 1997), or multi-valued logics
                        and approximate reasoning is to be evaluated. As many facts as possible
                        should be automatically extracted or calculated from existing data, e.g. by
                        means of automatic collation (Stolz &amp; Dimpel 2006), etc.</p>
                
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
              
                    <head>References</head>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Birdsall, J.N.</hi> (1992). The Recent History of New Testament
                    Textual Criticism (from Westcott and Hort, 1881, to the present). In  <hi
                        rend="italic">Aufstieg und Niedergang der römischen Welt. Geschichte und
                        Kultur Roms im Spiegel der neueren Forschung</hi>. Vol. II,26,1. Berlin: de
                    Gruyter, pp. 99-197.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Bischoff, B.</hi> (2009). <hi rend="italic">Paläographie des
                        römischen Altertums und des abendländischen Mittelalters</hi>. 4th ed.
                    Berlin: Erich Schmidt.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Bockelkamp, M.</hi> (1982). <hi rend="italic">Analytische
                        Forschungen zu Handschriften des 19. Jahrhunderts. </hi>Hamburg:
                    Hauswedell.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Brentano, C.</hi> (2006). <hi rend="italic">Romanzen vom
                        Rosenkranz. Frühe Fassungen</hi>. Ed. by Dietmar Pravida. Stuttgart:
                    Kohlhammer 2006.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Delgrande, J. P., and T. Schaub</hi> (1997). Compiling Reasoning
                    with and about Preferences into Default Logic. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of
                        the International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence</hi> 1, pp.
                    168-175. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Greg, W. W.</hi> (1927). <hi rend="italic">The Calculus of
                        Variants. An Essay on Textual Criticism</hi>. Oxford: Clarendon.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Lachmann, C.</hi> (1842). <hi rend="italic">Testamentum Novum
                        Graece et Latine. </hi>Vol. 1. Berlin: Reimer.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Pravida, D.</hi> (2005). <hi rend="italic">Die Erfindung des
                        Rosenkranzes. Untersuchungen zu Clemens Brentanos Versepos</hi>. Frankfurt:
                    Peter Lang.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Pravida, D.</hi> (forthcoming). Die Entstehung von <hi
                        rend="italic">Faust II</hi>, 5. Akt (1. Fassung). To appear in <hi
                        rend="italic">Jahrbuch des Freien Deutschen Hochstifts (2012)</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Quentin, H.</hi> (1922). <hi rend="italic">Mémoire sur l</hi><hi
                        rend="italic">’établissement du texte de la Vulgate. 1re partie:
                        Octateuque</hi>. Paris: Gabalda.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Reiter, R.</hi> (1980). A Logic for Default Reasoning. <hi
                        rend="italic">Artificial Intelligence</hi> 13: 81-132. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Robinson, P., A. Barbrook, N. Blake, and C. Howe</hi> (1998). The
                    Phylogeny of ‘The Canterbury Tales’. <hi rend="italic">Nature</hi> 394: 839-840. </p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Schulz, S.</hi> (2002). E – A Brainiac Theorem Prover<hi
                        rend="italic">.</hi>
                    <hi rend="italic">Journal of AI Communications</hi> 15(2/3): 111-126.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Stolz, M.. and F. M. Dimpel</hi> (2006). Computergestütztes
                    Kollationieren und dynamische Textpräsentation – Ein Werkstattbericht aus dem
                    Parzival-Projekt. <ref
                        target="http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:kobv:b4360-1004567"
                        type="external"
                    >http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:kobv:b4360-1004567</ref></p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Tyson, A.</hi> (1987). <hi rend="italic">Mozart: Studies of the
                        autograph scores</hi>. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard UP.</p>
                <p><hi rend="bold">West, M. L.</hi> (1973). <hi rend="italic">Textual criticism and
                        editorial technique, applicable to Greek and Latin texts</hi>. Stuttgart:
                    Teubner.</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>