<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" 
     xml:id="ab-407">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>A flexible model for the collaborative annotation of digitized literary works</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Gayoso-Cabada, Joaquin</name>
                    <affiliation>Universidad Complutense de Madrid, Spain</affiliation>
                    <email>gayoxo@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Ruiz, Cesar</name>
                    <affiliation>Universidad Complutense de Madrid, Spain</affiliation>
                    <email>cruiz85@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Pablo-Nuñez, Luis</name>
                    <affiliation>Universidad Complutense de Madrid, Spain</affiliation>
                    <email>lpnunez@filol.ucm.es</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Sarasa-Cabezuelo, Antonio</name>
                    <affiliation>Universidad Complutense de Madrid, Spain</affiliation>
                    <email>asarasa@fdi.ucm.es</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Goicoechea-de-Jorge, Maria</name>
                    <affiliation>Universidad Complutense de Madrid, Spain</affiliation>
                    <email>mgoico@filol.ucm.es</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Sanz-Cabrerizo, Amelia</name>
                    <affiliation>Universidad Complutense de Madrid, Spain</affiliation>
                    <email>amsanz@filol.ucm.es</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Sierra-Rodriguez, Jose-Luis</name>
                    <affiliation>Universidad Complutense de Madrid, Spain</affiliation>
                    <email>jlsierra@fdi.ucm.es</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Jan Christoph Meister, Universität Hamburg</publisher>
                <address>
                   <addrLine>Von-Melle-Park 6, 20146 Hamburg, Tel. +4940 428 38 2972</addrLine>
                   <addrLine>www.dh2012.uni-hamburg.de</addrLine>
              </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-15</date>
                <name>DH</name>
                <desc>generate TEI-template with data from ConfTool-Export</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2012-04-13</date>
                <name>LS</name>
                <desc>provide metadata for publicationStmt</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>The Complutense University has been one of the first European universities that
                    has collaborated with Google’s  project<note><ref target="http://www.ucm.es/BUCM/atencion/25403.php" type="external">http://www.ucm.es/BUCM/atencion/25403.php</ref></note> by putting on
                    the Web 100,000 volumes from its ancient fund. However scholars notice that
                    these digitized texts are often of no much use to
                    professors-researchers-students in literature unless additional tools are
                    provided, to enhance the educational and research value of this material. In
                    particular, the ability of making annotations on these texts has been largely
                    recognized as a basic mean of adding value to this kind of digitized resources
                    (Rios da Rocha et al. 2009). In this paper we present the annotation model used
                    in @Note 1.0, a system developed at UCM funded by the Google’s 2010 Digital
                    Humanities Award program.</p>
                <p>@Note 1.0 allows us to retrieve digitized works from Google Books collection and
                    add annotations to enrich the texts with research and learning purposes:
                    critical editions, reading activities, e-learning tasks, etc. One of the main
                    features of @Note annotation model, which distinguishes it from similar
                    approaches (Azouaou &amp; Desmoulins 2006; Bechhofer at al. 2002; Koivunen 2005;
                    Rios da Rocha et al. 2009; Schroeter et al. 2006; Tazi et al. 2003), is to
                    promote the collaborative creation of annotation schemas by communities of
                    researchers, teachers and students, and the use of these schemas in the
                    definition of annotation activities on literary works. It results in a very
                    flexible and adaptive model, able to be used by many different communities of
                    experts in literature defending different critical literary theories and for
                    different annotation tasks. In this paper we present this annotation model.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The @Note Annotation Model</head>
            
            <div>   
                <head>Structure of the model</head>
                <p>The structure of the @Note annotation model is summarized in the UML class
                    diagram (Booch et al. 2005) of Fig. 1. In this model:</p>
                <xmt:uList>
                <item><hi rend="italic">Annotation management communities </hi>are groups of
                        <hi rend="italic">annotation managers</hi>, experts in literature (teachers,
                    researchers, etc) who act as administrators to create activities, to select
                    works and to organize activity groups.</item>
                <item><hi rend="italic">Annotation communities</hi>, in their turn, are
                    groups of <hi rend="italic">annotators</hi>, students / pupils interested in
                    literature who perform proposed annotation activities.</item>
                <item>Each a<hi rend="italic">nnotation activity</hi> comprises (i) a <hi
                        rend="italic">digitized work</hi>, (ii) a <hi rend="italic"
                        >metalevel-oriented annotation schema</hi>, (iii) a <hi rend="italic"
                        >work-oriented annotation schema</hi>.</item>
                <item>In this context, the <hi rend="italic">works</hi> are the literary texts that
                            can be annotated during the annotation activities. <hi rend="italic"
                                >Annotations</hi>, in their turn, are characterized by: (i) an <hi
                                rend="italic">annotation anchor </hi>(the region of the work to
                            which the annotation refers), (ii) an <hi rend="italic">annotation
                                content </hi>(a free rich-text piece that actually configure the
                            annotation), (iii) a set of <hi rend="italic">annotation types</hi>
                            (semantic qualifiers for annotations) chosen from the annotation schemas
                            attached to the annotation activity (at least one from the
                            metalevel-oriented annotation schema).</item>
             
                </xmt:uList>
                
                    <p><figure>
                            <graphic url="img407-1.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                                mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                            <head>Figure 1: @Note information model</head>
                        </figure></p>
                 
                
                <xmt:uList>
                <item>The <hi rend="italic">annotation schemas</hi> are explicit formalization
                            of the types of annotations that can be carried out on works. In @Note,
                            annotation schemas are hierarchies formed by annotation types and <hi
                                rend="italic">annotation categories</hi> (sets of annotation types
                            and/or others, more specifically, annotation categories). In their turn,
                            they can be <hi rend="italic">metalevel-oriented annotation schemas</hi>
                            (schemas which usually comprise concepts concerning particular literary
                            theories around which the annotation activities are articulated), or <hi
                                rend="italic">work-oriented annotation schemas</hi> (schemas that
                            capture aspects relative to the relationships between annotations and
                            their anchors). While schemas of the first type are created by
                            annotation managers, schemas of the second type are usually created by
                            annotators.</item>
                    
                </xmt:uList>   
                
                <p><figure>
                            <graphic url="img407-2.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                                mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                            <head>Figure 2: Example of rules governing the annotation process
                                (informally described using natural language)</head>
                        </figure></p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>The annotation process</head>
                <p>The @Note annotation process governs how to create the different types of
                    information elements envisioned in the annotation model. For this purpose, @Note
                    introduces a set of rules governing aspects like information visibility,
                    creation and modification privileges of annotations and annotation schemas,
                    etc.  Although, by lack of space, these rules will not be detailed here, in Fig.
                    2 we include an example concerning an informal description of some of the rules
                    governing the management of annotation schemas.</p>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>Annotation browsing and recovering</head>
                <p>Annotation schemas in @Note are seen as T-<hi rend="italic">boxes</hi> of
                    description logic theories (Brachman &amp; Levesque 2004). For instance, Fig 3a
                    shows, edited in @Note, a fragment of the annotation schema used at UCM in an
                    English Literature introductory course, while  Fig 3b despites the description
                    logic’s counterpart. This simple interpretation is still powerful-enough to
                    enable powerful <hi rend="italic">annotation browsing</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >annotation recovering</hi> behavior. Indeed:</p>
                
                <p><figure>
                            <graphic url="img407-3.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                                mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                            <head>Figure 3: (a) A fragment of annotation schema (b) description
                                logic counterpart</head>
                        </figure></p>
                
                <xmt:uList>
                <item>Annotations can be browsed using annotation
                    schemas, in a similar way to a folder explorer in a filesystem. In each step,
                    there is a category or a type selected, and the user will <hi rend="italic"
                        >see</hi> all the annotations entailed by such a selected element.</item>
                <item>Queries consist of arbitrary Boolean formulae involving annotation
                    types and categories, being the outcomes the annotations entailed by such
                    formulae.</item>
                </xmt:uList>
                
                <p>In both cases, since entailment will be performed according to the description
                    logic principles, the process will take into account the<hi rend="italic"> is-a
                    </hi>relationship made explicit by the annotation schema.</p>
                
            </div>
            
            <div>
                <head>Some technical details</head>
                <p>The system has been entirely developed using Google technologies for the
                    development of Rich-Internet Applications (RIAs) (Fraternali et al. 2010): GWT
                    in the client side and the Google App Engine’s facilities in the server side
                    (Unruh 2010). Fig. 4 shows some snapshots of the system. The current version
                    runs on the fully free-access books integrated in Google Books, and, in
                    particular, on the UCM-Google collection. The works retrieval is achieved by the
                    use of the Google Books API through REST (Richardson &amp; Ruby 2007), and then
                    presented to clients in an asynchronous way to keep them responsive to their
                    events.</p>
                
                <p><figure>
                            <graphic url="img407-4.jpg" rend="left" height="256px" width="341px"
                                mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                            <head>Figure 4: Some snapshots of @Note</head>
                        </figure></p>
            </div>
            </div>
            
            <div>
                
                <head>Conclusions and Future Works</head>
                <p>@Note promotes a fully collaborative annotation process, in which not only
                    literary works are collaboratively annotated, but also annotation schemas are
                    collaboratively created. The @Note system has been evaluated at UCM by several
                    researchers and students in literature. They highlighted the flexibility of the
                    annotation model, and, in particular, the ability to create and share annotation
                    schemas tailored according to different critical perspectives and annotation
                    activities. Additionally, they appreciate a sufficient expressive power from a
                    browsing and recovering point of view. They also remarked the educational
                    potential of the tool, although some advanced features could add some conceptual
                    difficulties for students. </p>
                <p>Currently we are working to adapt the annotation tool in order to facilitate its
                    connection to a repository of learning objects, so as to allow the storage of
                    literary texts’ annotations as learning objects (Polsani 2003), and to make
                    possible the recovery of those annotations and move about them according to the
                    associated metadata. Thus, we are developing a communal working space for the
                    creation of written compositions in different traditions and languages. We are
                    also experimenting with the students’ capability for developing their own
                    catalogues, annotating the literary texts according to them and reusing their
                    annotations in the production of critical essays. Additionally, we are working
                    on connecting our system with other digital libraries (in particular, with Hathi
                    Trust<note><ref target="http://www.hathitrust.org/" type="external">http://www.hathitrust.org/</ref></note>). Finally, we are planning to address
                    interoperability issues, in order to enable the interchange of annotations
                    according to some of the emerging standards proposed by the digital humanities
                    community (e.g., OAC<note><ref target="http://www.openannotation.org/" type="external">http://www.openannotation.org/</ref></note>).</p>
                <p/>
                <p/>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">Acknowledgements</hi></p>
            <p>This work has been funded by Google with a grant of the
                Google’s 2010 Digital Humanities award program entitled <hi rend="italic"
                    >Collaborative annotation of digitalized literary texts</hi>. Additionally, this
                work has been performed in the context of the project grants of the Spanish Ministry
                for Research and Innovation (FF12008-06924-C02-01 and TIN2010-21288-C02-01), UCM
                (PIMCDs 2010/177 and 2011/313) and Santander-UCM (GR 42/10 - 962022).</p>
                </div>
        </body>

        
        <back><div>
                <head>References</head>

            <p><hi rend="bold">Azouaou, F., and C. Desmoulins</hi> (2006). MemoNote, a context-aware
                    annotation tool for teachers. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 7th
                        International Conference on Information Technology Based Higher Education
                        and Training</hi> ITHET’06, Sidney, Australia, July 2006.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Bechhofer, S., L. Carr, C. Goble, S. Kampa,
                        and T. Miles-Board</hi> (2002). The Semantics of Semantic Annotation.
                    <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the First International Conference on
                    Ontologies, DataBases, and Applications of Semantics for Large Scale Information
                    Systems</hi> ODBASE’02, Irvine, CA, USA, October 2002.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Booch, G., J. Rumbaugh, and I.
                    Jacobson</hi> (2005). <hi rend="italic">The Unified Modeling Language User
                    Guide</hi> (<hi rend="italic">2nd Edition</hi>). Boston: Adisson-Wesley.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Brachman, R., and H. Levesque</hi>
                (2004). <hi rend="italic">Knowledge Representation and Reasoning</hi>. Amsterdam:
                Morgan-Kauffmann. </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Fraternali, P., R. Gustavo, and F.
                        Sánchez-Figueroa</hi> (2010). Rich Internet Applications. IEEE <hi
                    rend="italic">Internet Computing</hi> 14(3): 9-12. </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Koivunen, M.-R</hi>. (2005). Annotea and Semantic Web Supported
                    Collaboration. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the UserSWeb Workshop</hi> – <hi
                        rend="italic">2nd European Semantic Web Conference</hi>, Heraklion, Grece,
                    June 2005.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Polsani, P</hi>. (2003). Use and abuse of
                reusable learning objects. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Digital Information</hi>
                3(4). </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Richardson, L., and S. Ruby</hi> (2007).
                    <hi rend="italic">Restful web services</hi>. Beijing: O’Reilly. </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Rios da Rocha, T., R. Willrich, R. Fileto, and
                        S. Tazi</hi> (2009). Supporting Collaborative Learning Activities with
                a Digital Library and Annotations. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 9th IFIP
                    World Conference on Computers in Education</hi> WCCE’09, Bento Gonçalves,
                Brazil, July 2009.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Schroeter, R., J. Hunter, J. Guerin, I. Khan,
                        I., and M. A. Henderson</hi> (2006). Synchronous Multimedia Annotation
                System for Secure Collaboratories. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Second IEEE
                    International Conference on e-Science and Grid Computing</hi> e-Science ’06,
                Amsterdam, Netherlands, December 2006. </p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Tazi, S., Y. Al-Tawki, and K. Drira K.</hi> (2003). Editing
                    pedagogical intentions for document reuse. <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the
                        4th IEEE Technology Based Higher Education and Training</hi> ITHET’03,
                    Marrakesh, Morocco, July 7-9, 2003.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Unruh, A.</hi> (2010 ). <hi rend="italic">Google App Engine Java and
                        GWT Application Development</hi>. Birmingham: Packt Publishing.</p>
        </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>