<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="panel_219_schreibman"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Digital Representation and the Hyper Real</title><author><name reg="Lavagnino, John">John Lavagnino</name></author><author><name reg="McCarty, Willard">Willard McCarty</name></author><author><name reg="Schreibman, Susan">Susan Schreibman</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>panel</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>modeling</item><item>virtual reality</item><item>knowledge representation</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Susan Schreibman's doc <date value="2007-05"> May
                    2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Digital Representation and the Hyper Real"><titlePart type="main">Digital Representation and the Hyper Real</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Lavagnino, John">John Lavagnino</name><address><addrLine>John.Lavagnino@kcl.ac.uk</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">King's College London</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="McCarty, Willard">Willard McCarty</name><address><addrLine>willard.mccarty@kcl.ac.uk</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">King's College London</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Schreibman, Susan">Susan Schreibman</name><address><addrLine>sschreib@umd.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of Maryland Libraries</titlePart></front><body><div0><p>Art has never been a mere mirror up to nature, yet as in no other medium has it
                    been so easy to create a simulacra of reality as with digital technology: a
                    'heterocosm', both simulating the familiar while deconstructing it. This session
                    brings together three theoretical papers that explore how mimesis might be used
                    as a paradigm from which to explore the relationship between the digital world,
                    the analogue world, and the space between them; digital surrogates and their
                    analogue counterparts; how familiar terms like object, imitation, copy, original
                    function in the digital realm; and the notion that a digital representation may
                    be more appropriately termed a simulacral identity, reflecting, not the object
                    itself, but our beliefs and conventions about it. This session will explore
                    digital representation as conscious fashionings of hyper-reality, computational
                    zones or subspaces which employ the unreal and non-existent to recreate the
                    material world, pointing to the past, and the future, in unexpected, fresh, or
                    subversive ways</p></div0><div0 type="EmbeddedDoc"><div1><head><emph>Being Digital, or Analogue, or Neither</emph></head><p rend="Presenter">John Lavagnino</p><p>When I speak of something being digital or analogue, I draw on a connected
                        pair of terms that is often thought to cover all possibilities in a way
                        that's theoretically well grounded. But the origin of these two terms is not
                        theoretical, and the conventional opposition reflects a pragmatic view of
                        approaches to making computing machinery rather than deep and inherent
                        qualities of information. The two terms also do not exhaust the world: most
                        things are neither digital nor analogue, because those terms describe
                        information that has been carefully prepared for machine processing.
                        Nonmachines get by in the world without that restriction of input.</p><p>The separate ideas of digital and analogue representation come not from
                        theory but from engineering. Digital representation has its background prior
                        to the days of the digital computer, in the longer history of numerical
                        calculating machines, and in particular in the use of punch cards and
                        tabulating machinery, which could not only perform computations but provided
                        ways to manage large bodies of information. Analogue representation goes
                        back to a different tradition of calculating machinery, in which physical
                        operations that could be interpreted as performing computations mattered
                        much more than storage of information in any quantity. In the mid-twentieth
                        century, a moment came when both approaches had significant applications,
                        and two separate strands of technological development became a pair of
                        options, both sometimes applicable to the same tasks (Wiener; Mindell).
                        Today the two are commonly thought to exhaust all possibilities; but at the
                        same time there is a marked status hierarchy, as digital systems continue to
                        spread everywhere and analogue systems have a minor or nearly invisible
                        existence in unexciting devices like thermostats. On this view, the digital
                        has the prestige of being made by us, and the analogue has the consolation
                        of covering everything that isn't manmade and a few things that are. Or, in
                        one very common version of this opposition, thought is digital and reality
                        is analogue.</p><p>Although many people assume in this way that everything is either digital or
                        analogue, most things aren't actually either, because most things are not
                        information prepared for machine processing. All our machinery for
                        processing information, analogue or digital, has the common property of
                        ignoring all but a restricted slice of the world as we experience it, and
                        having no way to notice phenomena beyond that slice. We craft these machines
                        to work with particular inputs and sometimes learn to change our behavior so
                        that machines get the right sort of input. Representations made for other
                        purposes (art, in particular) are based on selections, too, but because they
                        are not created to serve as a basis for computation they don't present the
                        same kind of claim to be authoritative versions of reality. Nothing is
                        digital or analogue until we actually get it into a computational system;
                        these properties result from our choices about how to process reality, and
                        are not inherent in reality itself.</p><p>If reality is not by default analogue, thinking is not by its nature digital.
                        Much work in artificial intelligence has been based on the hypothesis that
                        the brain and mind work like digital computers: so that, while our current
                        systems might be crude, they are still on the right path of development
                        towards the real thing, and it's important that the real thing is digital.
                        The hypothesis has been highly productive as a basis for useful work, but is
                        at odds with the biological account of how the brain works; John von Neumann
                        argued that the brain's machinery was essentially different from that of
                        both digital and analogue computers. That difference is unsurprising, since
                        machines of other kinds work very differently from biological systems with
                        comparable functions. The natural form of technology “is typically tiny,
                        wet, nonmetallic, non-wheeled, and flexible; human technology is mainly the
                        opposite: large, dry, metallic, wheeled, and stiff” (Vogel 271).</p><p>In one classical line of discussion of the digital-and-analogue pairing,
                        Nelson Goodman's, written texts serve as an example of the digital mode: on
                        this view, written symbols are intended as discrete and unambiguous tokens
                        chosen from a fixed set (142). The way that texts lend themselves so
                        naturally to transformation into electronic form may seem to provide
                        evidence for this view: that they're not only readily made into usable
                        digital objects but that they inherently <emph>are</emph> such objects. But
                        in Goodman's account the digital nature of the alphabet is an idealization:
                        you are supposed to be able to tell your letters apart unambiguously, yet we
                        get by working with handwriting and bad print that fails in this regard.
                        Much more significantly, we notice other things than the choice of token; as
                        many accounts of communication point out (Roman Jakobson's, for example),
                        there are many functions of verbal messages besides the transmission of the
                        information. Digital representation in computers is different because they
                        are designed to recognize nothing but the choice of token; what is an
                        idealized account when applied to human use of the alphabet is a perfect
                        account of computing, because it describes how computers are built to work.</p><p>Conventional accounts of digital representation rarely mention how much of
                        the workings of a computer are there to keep the digital data digital, to
                        prevent it from being degraded by noise; works on electronic engineering
                        never omit the point. We miss a key feature of the digital and the analogue
                        when we think of them as static properties that happen to everything without
                        effort; they are instead deliberate creations. They have been highly
                        successful creations, representations of reality that lend themselves to
                        many uses; we ought to recognize them as our creations, and not mistake them
                        for natural phenomena.</p></div1><div1><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Goodman, Nelson">Nelson Goodman</name></author><title level="m">Languages of Art: An Approach to a Theory of
                                    Symbols</title><imprint><pubPlace>Indianapolis, IN</pubPlace><publisher>Bobbs-Merrill</publisher><date value="1968">1968</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Jakobson, Roman">Roman Jakobson</name></author><title level="a">Linguistics and Poetics</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Linguistics and Poetics</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Sebeok, Thomas A.">Thomas A. Sebeok</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace><publisher>MIT Press</publisher><date value="1960">1960</date><biblScope type="pages">350–377</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Mindell, David A.">David A. Mindell</name></author><title level="m">Between Human and Machine: Feedback, Control, and
                                    Computing before Cybernetics</title><imprint><pubPlace>Baltimore, MD</pubPlace><publisher>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Vogel, Steven">Steven Vogel</name></author><title level="m">Cat's Paws and Catapults: Mechanical Worlds of
                                    Nature and People</title><imprint><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>Norton</publisher><date value="1998">1998</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Von Neumann, John">John Von Neumann</name></author><title level="m">The Computer and the Brain</title><edition>2nd ed.</edition><imprint><pubPlace>New Haven, CT</pubPlace><publisher>Yale University Press</publisher><date value="2000">2000</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Wiener, Norbert">Norbert Wiener&gt;</name></author><title level="m">Cybernetics; or, Control and Communication in the
                                    Animal and the Machine</title><imprint><pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace><publisher>MIT Press</publisher><date value="1948">1948</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div1></div0><div0 type="EmbeddedDoc"><div1><head>Looking Backward, Figuring Forward:<lb/> Modelling, its Discontents and
                        the Future </head><p rend="Presenter">Willard McCarty </p><p>Alan Turing’s scheme has not been adequate to computing “in the wild” for
                        more than 50 years (Mahoney 1997: 621), but it does have two fundamental
                        implications for work in the humanities. Its first implication is that
                        intellectual gain from the computational analysis of a cultural artefact
                        comes primarily from comparing it to its digital representation as this is
                        improved through repeated trials and adjustments. Its second implication is
                        that in principle there can be no limit other than human ingenuity to the
                        forms computing can take. Hence computing’s basic tradeoff: on the one hand,
                        reduction of the artefact to computational form guarantees a permanent
                        though changing gap between its transcendent reality and its calculable
                        representation; on the other, the mutability of computing allows for no end
                        to the perfective attempt to reach the former with the latter. This attempt
                        I have called “modeling” (McCarty 2005).</p><p>The proposed paper takes the centrality of modeling for granted, but it
                        attempts to move beyond the inherent limitations of a process that by
                        definition only imitates. Modeling is directed to a pre-existing conception
                        of an artefact one wishes to study; its strength is in contesting that
                        conception in comparison against one’s best attempt at representing it
                        rigorously. The discrepancies it discovers may well be, in Jerome McGann’s
                        words, “the hem of a quantum garment” that trails into our future (2004:
                        201), but modeling gives us little help in imagining that future. Turing’s
                        scheme guarantees innumerable forms of computing, but how best are we to
                        work toward them? Although, as Edsger Dijkstra remarks in his contribution
                        to <title level="m">Beyond Calculation: The Next Fifty Years of
                        Computing</title>, it may seem “utterly preposterous” to predict this
                        future, as teachers we do it all the time in deciding what to teach, what to
                        ignore (1997: 59). As researchers we get hints of the future, or hopes for
                        it, when no existing data model, or way of using computers, will do – when
                        (to take an example from my own work) neither textual encoding nor
                        relational database design satisfies, and we are left with a hunger for
                        something other than what we have. Can we do better than such backward
                        looking glances into the future? Can we imagine it directly?</p><p>One answer is supplied by Empirical Modelling (EM), presented to the last
                        North American ACH/ALLC conference (Beynon, Russ and McCarty 2006) and
                        further articulated in a recent MSc dissertation (King 2006). EM focuses on
                        the present and presence of tacit experience, which is as close to the
                        future as we ever get. Another answer comes out of work in critical theory,
                        e.g. by N. Katherine Hayles, whose focus on writing, and cultural
                        productions generally, lifts the gaze to what is emerging – to “emergent”
                        phenomena, as they are known (1999). Taking clues from both, I propose to
                        explore and talk about a third answer arising from reflective work in the
                        history, philosophy and anthropology of the natural sciences. In the
                        philosophy of physics, for example, Ian Hacking has argued that rigorously
                        imagined entities are made real when we learn to manipulate them (1983). In
                        the history of technology, Peter Galison shows that the devices we invent
                        tend to pull us forward into conformity with them (2007) – an argument quite
                        close to one Northrop Frye made at the first joint ACH/ALLC conference,
                        citing such human inventions as the wheel and the book (1990). In the
                        history of chemistry, Mi Gyung Kim examines how 19th Century researchers
                        worked to establish the reality of their substances, suggesting a
                        surprisingly immediate interrelation of the imagined and the real (2000). In
                        biological anthropology, Terrence Deacon argues beyond the uncomfortable
                        limitations of a mechanical world-view and strict Darwinian evolution to a
                        new conception of teleology, “to identify a real and substantial sense of
                        the ‘pull’ of future possibilities in terms of ‘pushes’ from the past”
                        (2006).</p><p>In the proposed paper, I summarize this work in the natural sciences and use
                        it to construct a theory of emergence in humanities computing. I base my
                        exposition on the underlying argument that use of computing, with its
                        emphasis on “how we find out, not… what we find out” (Hacking 2002), brings
                        us into productive relation with the experimental sciences without in any
                        way compromising our orientation to the humanities (McCarty 2002, 2006,
                        2007). Sumarizing my earlier work, I suggest briefly at the beginning of the
                        paper how computing has allowed us to create within the humanities a
                        computational zone or subspace, within which practitioners may treat
                        cultural artefacts <emph>as if</emph> they were only data, and so apply to
                        them <emph>something like</emph> natural law. I argue that the conjectural,
                        as-if status of what may be done within this zone gives us a defensible way
                        of importing powerful scientific conceptions, such as Hacking’s
                        realization-by-manipulation or Deacon’s biological teleology, and apply them
                        to our artefacts of study, not in order to test what we think we know but to
                        imagine and realize what we do not know.</p><p>In earlier work I have used this conjectural relation with the natural
                        sciences to ground the practice of modelling in its scientific past (McCarty
                        2005). Here I use it as entry-point to speculations on how humanities
                        computing might lead the disciplines which it most immediately serves into a
                        fruitful relationship with the sciences and so to an end of the epistemic
                        wars foreseen by Richard Rorty (2000).</p></div1><div1><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Beynon, Meurig">Meurig Beynon</name></author><author><name reg="Russ, Steve">Steve Russ </name></author><author><name reg="McCarty, Willard">Willard McCarty</name></author><title level="a">Human Computing – Modelling with Meaning</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">21.2</biblScope><date value="2006">2006</date><biblScope type="pages">141-57</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Deacon, Terrence W.">Terrence W. Deacon</name></author><title level="a">Emergence: The Hole at the Wheel’s Hub</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Re-Emergence of Emergence: The Emergentist
                                    Hypothesis from Science to Religion</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Clayton, Philip">Philip Clayton </name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Davies, Paul">Paul Davies</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace><publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher><date value="2006">2006</date><biblScope>111-150</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Dijkstra, Edsger W.">Edsger W. Dijkstra</name></author><title level="a">The Tide, not the Waves</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Beyond Calculation: The Next Fifty Years of
                                    Computing</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Denning, Peter J.">Peter J. Denning </name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Metcalfe, Robert M.">Robert M. Metcalfe</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>Copernicus</publisher><date value="1997">1997</date><biblScope type="pages">59-64</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Frye, Northrop">Northrop Frye</name></author><title level="a">Literary and Mechanical Models</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Research in Humanities Computing 1: Selected Papers
                                    from the 1989 ACH-ALLC Conference</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Lancashire, Ian">Ian Lancashire</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace><publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher><date value="1991">1991</date><biblScope type="pages">3-12</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Galison, Peter">Peter Galison</name></author><title level="m">Building, Crashing, Thinking</title><imprint><date value="2007">Forthcoming</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Hacking, Ian">Ian Hacking</name></author><title level="m">Representing and Intervening: Introductory Topics
                                    in the Philosophy of Natural Science</title><imprint><pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace><publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher><date value="1983">1983</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Hacking, Ian">Ian Hacking</name></author><title level="m">Historical Ontology</title><imprint><pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace><publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Hales, N. Katherine">Katherine N. Hales</name></author><title level="m">How We Became Posthuman: Virtual Bodies in
                                    Cybernetics, Literature and Informatics</title><imprint><pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace><publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher><date value="1999">1999</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Kim, Mi Gyung">Mi Gyung Kim</name></author><title level="a">Chemical Analysis and the Domains of Reality:
                                    Wilhelm Homberg’s <emph>Essais De Chimie</emph>,
                                1702-1709</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Studies in the History and Philosophy of Science</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">31.1</biblScope><date value="2000">2000</date><biblScope type="pages">37-69</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="King, Karl George">Karl George King</name></author><title level="u">“Uncovering Empirical Modelling”</title><edition>Unpublished MSc dissertation</edition><imprint><publisher>Computer Science Department, Warwick University</publisher><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Mahoney, Michael S.">Michael S. Mahoney</name></author><title level="a">Computer Science: The Search for a Mathematical
                                    Theory</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Science in the Twentieth Century</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Krige, John">John Krige</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Pestre, Dominique">Dominique Pestre</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace><publisher>Harwood Academic Publishers</publisher><date value="1997">1997</date><biblScope type="pages">617-34</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="McCarty, Willard">Willard McCarty</name></author><title level="a">Humanities Computing: Essential Problems,
                                    Experimental Practice</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">17.1</biblScope><date value="2002">April 2002</date><biblScope type="pages">103-25</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="McCarty, Willard">Willard McCarty</name></author><title level="m">Humanities Computing</title><imprint><pubPlace>Basingstoke</pubPlace><publisher>Palgrave</publisher><date value="2005">2005</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="McCarty, Willard">Willard McCarty</name></author><title level="a">The Imaginations of Computing</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Richard W. Lyman Award lecture, National Humanities
                                    Center, Research Triangle Park, North Carolina, 6 November</title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="McCarty, Willard">Willard McCarty</name></author><title level="a">Being Reborn: The Humanities, Computing and Styles
                                    of Scientific Reasoning</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Renaissance Studies and New Technologies: A
                                    Collection</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Bowen, William R.">William R. Bowen </name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Siemens, Raymond G.">Raymond G. Siemens</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Tempe, AZ</pubPlace><publisher>Medieval and Renaissance Texts and Studies</publisher><date value="2007">Forthcoming</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Rorty, Richard">Richard Rorty</name></author><title level="a">Being That Can Be Understood Is Language</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Gadamer's Repurcussions: Reconsidering
                                    Philosophical Hermeneutics</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Krajewski, Bruce">Bruce Krajewski</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Berkeley</pubPlace><publisher>University of California Press</publisher><date value="2004">2004</date><biblScope>21-9</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div1></div0><div0 type="EmbeddedDoc"><div1><head><emph>Beautiful Untrue Things: The Digital Dilemma</emph></head><p rend="Presenter">Susan Schreibman</p><p>In Oscar Wilde's dialogue <title level="m">The Decay of Lying</title>, Vivian
                        and Cyril discuss the interdependence of Nature and Imagination, with
                        imagination, in that typically Wildean fashion, more faithfully representing
                        the real than the material world. For much of the dialogue, Vivian reads an
                        essay that he has authored to Cyril: his thesis is that there must be a
                        return to 'lying in art' (5): a return to the roots of art in the purely
                        imaginative abstract. This imaginative work, rooted in the 'unreal and
                        non-existent' takes as its rough material life, 'recreates it, and
                        refashions it in fresh forms, absolutely indifferent to fact', to what is
                        true or natural or real (20). </p><p>Wilde's theory of artistic process can also serve as a starting point in
                        articulating a theory of digital mimesis; of understanding the
                        relationship(s) between the original and its digital manifestation(s), as
                        well as the relationship between and amongst digital surrogates. Moreover,
                        it can be taken as a framework for exploring the complex and shifting
                        relationship between a digitally-presented hyper-reality and material
                        reality.</p><p>As has been argued elsewhere, art has never been a mere mirror up to nature,
                        but in no other medium has it been so easy to create a simulacra of reality;
                        a 'heterocosm', simultaneously simulating the familiar while deconstructing
                        it. While the mimetic effect of visualizations, simulations, and virtual
                        reality inherit a set of conventions between an audience and its
                        expectations of a work, these conventions are ultimately unstable, shifting
                        as the technology, and our expectations of it, change.</p><p>Digital representations of three dimensional objects, necessarily, lose their
                        corporeality, becoming two-dimensional artifacts<note n="1">This is true
                            even when the computer emulates three-dimensional space, such as
                            utilizing software to be able to view 380° of a sculpture, or using
                            virtual reality software to emulate perspective.</note> engaged with
                        through the mediating presence of an electronic viewing device (a computer
                        monitor, a mobile phone, an e-book). What we engage with, however, are only
                        representations of digital corporeality: what we see are manifestations of
                        the underlying code, much as the prisoners in Plato's allegory of the cave
                        saw only shadows cast on the wall. What we engage with is in fact, not the
                        digital object, but a representation of it. </p><p>Johanna Drucker in 'Digital Ontologies: The Ideality of Form in/and code
                        Storage – or – Can Graphesis Challenge Mathesis?' posits that although
                        throughout the Western history, images have been charged with being
                        essentially deceptive or illusionary, the algorithmically-generated code of
                        digital images may, in fact, be a perfect representation of an object; a
                        representation which is not tainted through display or representation. On
                        the other hand, without the representation of the code, the image exists
                        outside our ability to perceive it. In traditional discussions of mimesis
                        the thing being represented typically reflects, however distorted the lens,
                        the represented; the essence of the represented recognizable in the
                        simulacra. With digital media, however, paradoxically, to see beyond the
                        surface of the material world, objects are transmuted into a series of
                        electric currents represented to the computer as binary code. What is being
                        encoded is the object as it never existed, a simulation or
                        hyper-realization.</p><p>The intention of a simulation may be to represent an object as it never
                        existed in the material world reflecting our theories and beliefs about it.
                        Digital imagery may be used, for example, to make visible the characters of
                        a manuscript which are no longer perceptible to the human eye. What is
                        represented is not the manuscript as it existed before the damage occurred,
                        nor the manuscript as it exists today: it is not the shadows on the cave
                        wall, nor the reality which casts those shadows, but a hyper-reality which
                        exists between these worlds</p><p>As more of our cultural heritage is represented in digital form, the
                        artifacts that people engage with are the simulations without reference to
                        the originals. These disembodied objects exist outside time and space in a
                        way that material objects do not. Digital objects to not decay due to the
                        ravages of time or environment (although digital objects may be rendered
                        useless by our not having the proper hardware and software to read it). Our
                        display paradigms privilege certain readings of these objects; they are
                        surrounded by metadata, typically, if part of a library's holdings, Library
                        of Congress Subject Headings which categorize and group the known world
                        according to a Victorian perception of the universe. Images are not
                        represented to scale, so a map that is 3x2 feet appears the same size as one
                        that is 8x10 inches. Our search engines reduce hundreds, thousands, even
                        millions of objects to a text string displayed ten to a page, or a table
                        populated by 40 2x2 inch thumbnails. This homogenization of results further
                        decontextualize digital simulacra. These deconstructions of the object's
                        material existence reframe the relationship between the perceived and the
                        perceiver, refashioning it, as Wilde writes, 'absolutely indifferent to
                        fact' of what is true or natural or real (20).</p><p>This paper will thus explore mimesis from two distinct, but not unrelated
                        aspects of digital technology. The first part will explore the relationship
                        between digital surrogates and their analogue counterparts; how familiar
                        terms like object, imitation, copy, original function in the digital realm;
                        what is lost and gained in the transfer to the digital when the materiality
                        of a three-dimensional object is transmuted into a two-dimensional plane;
                        the concept of 'trusted digital objects': digital files that will live on
                        when we, and the objects they were created from, no longer exist; the notion
                        that a digital representation may be more appropriately termed a simulacral
                        identity, reflecting, not the object itself, but our beliefs and conventions
                        about it. The second part will explore mimesis from the viewpoint of digital
                        representations as conscious fashionings of hyper-reality or in Wildean
                        terms, employing the unreal and non-existent to recreate the material world
                        in unexpected, fresh, or subversive ways.</p></div1><div1><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Aarseth, Espen J.">Espen J. Aarseth</name></author><title level="m">Cybertext: Perspectives on Ergodic Literature</title><imprint><pubPlace>Baltimore, MD</pubPlace><publisher>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher><date value="1997">1997</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Baudrillard, Jean">Jean Baudrillard</name></author><title level="m">Simulations</title><imprint><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>Semiotext[e]</publisher><date value="1983">1983</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Davis, Michael">Michael Davis</name></author><title level="m">Poetry of Philosophy: On Aristotle's "Poetics"</title><imprint><pubPlace>South Bend, IN</pubPlace><publisher>St Augustine's Press</publisher><date value="1999">1999</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Drucker, Johanna">Johanna Drucker</name></author><title level="a">Digital Ontologies: The Ideality of Form in/and
                                    Code Storage – or –Can Graphesis Challenge Mathesis?</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Leonardo, the International Society for the Arts,
                                    Sciences and Technology</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">34.2</biblScope><date value="2001">2001</date><biblScope type="pages">141-145</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Hales, Katherine, N.">Katherine N. Hales</name></author><title level="m">Writing Machines</title><imprint><pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>MIT Press</publisher><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Levy, David M.">David M. Levy</name><title level="a">Where's Waldo? Reflections on Copies and
                                        Authenticity in a Digital Environment</title></author></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Authenticity in a Digital Environment</title><imprint><publisher>CLIR</publisher><date value="2000">2000</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.clir.org/pubs/reports/pub92/levy.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Halliwell, Stephen">Stephen Halliwell</name></author><title level="m">The Aesthetics of Mimesis: Ancient Texts and Modern
                                    Problems</title><imprint><pubPlace>Princeton</pubPlace><publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Potolsky, Matthew">Matthew Potolsky</name></author><title level="m">Mimesis: The New Critical Idiom</title><imprint><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>Routledge</publisher><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="San Segundo, Rosa">Rosa San Segundo</name></author><title level="a">A New Conception of Representation of
                                Knowledge</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Knowledge Organization</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">31.2</biblScope><date value="2004">2004</date><biblScope type="pages">106-111</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Wilde, Oscar">Oscar Wilde</name></author><title level="m">The Decay of Lying: An Observation</title><imprint><pubPlace>Cork</pubPlace><publisher>CELT: Corpus of Electronic Texts</publisher><date value="1999">1999</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-09-06" to="http://www.ucc.ie/celt/published/E800003-009/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct></listBibl></div1></div0></body></text></TEI.2>