<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="poster_153_furuta"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Ancient Technical Manuscripts: the Case of 17th-century Portuguese
                    Shipbuilding Treatises</title><author><name reg="Furuta, Richard">Richard Furuta</name></author><author><name reg="Monroy, Carlos">Carlos Monroy</name></author><author><name reg="Castro, Filipe">Filipe Castro</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Field, Hana S.">Hana S. Field</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>poster</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>nautical archaeology</item><item>shipbuilding treatises</item><item>digital libraries</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list><item>HSF: Created from Richard Furuta's doc<date value="2007-04">April
                2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Ancient Technical Manuscripts: the Case of 17th-century Portuguese Shipbuilding Treatises"><titlePart type="main">Ancient Technical Manuscripts: the Case of 17th-century
                    Portuguese Shipbuilding Treatises</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Furuta, Richard">Richard Furuta</name><address><addrLine>furuta@cs.tamu.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Center for the Study of Digital Libraries <lb/>Texas A&amp;M
                University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Castro, Filipe">Filipe Castro</name><address><addrLine>fvcastro@tamu.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Center for tMaritime Archaeology and Conservation<lb/>Texas
                A&amp;M University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Monroy, Carlos">Carlos Monroy</name><address><addrLine>cmonroy@cs.tamu.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Center for the Study of Digital Libraries <lb/>Texas A&amp;M
                University</titlePart></front><body><div0><p>During the 16th- and 17th-centuries European seafaring underwent an incredible
                    transformation driven mainly by the exploration of newly discovered lands, the
                    contact with previously unknown cultures, and the increase in maritime commerce.
                    The social changes that resulted from this cultural revolution affected the long
                    chain of events entailed by the construction of oceangoing ships and determined
                    a number of technical innovations in the construction of ships. From an original
                    oral tradition, where apprentices learned from masters the intricacies of
                    shipbuilding techniques; this process evolved into a more formal field as
                    masters began to follow guidelines, materials used, and construction sequences
                    in a more systematic way, forming a corpus of information that was soon compiled
                    in manuscripts known as shipbuilding treatises.</p><p>The first shipbuilding treatises, understandably, were written by mathematicians,
                    priests and other learned men, reflecting a reality where shipbuilders probably
                    were largely illiterate. Rich in technical descriptions, shipbuilding treatises
                    play a key role in Nautical Archaeology both for scholars and students. Scholars
                    access these manuscripts for several reasons. For example, working on the
                    reconstruction of sunken ships, they can provide vital information for
                    reassembling fragments and damaged timbers of ship remains recovered from
                    underwater excavations. Also, their contents often help our understanding of
                    shipbuilding techniques. In addition, they can be used to compare different
                    construction traditions both from geographical and chronological standpoints.
                    Moreover, they are great sources for understanding the evolution of shipbuilding
                    (Figure 2 shows our treatises browser).</p><p>Nautical Archaeology students—although not carrying out the complex tasks of ship
                    reconstruction—are exposed to treatises early in their studies. For them
                    treatises are a good source to understand the basic terminology and concepts
                    they will be using during the rest of their studies. Current teaching practices
                    are constrained to browse physical copies of the original sources; with obvious
                    restrictions such as limited number of copies and access, or unknown
                    language—depending of their provenance, they were written in different
                    languages, and difficult technical terminology. In fact, treatises inherit most
                    of the limitations of printed books.</p><p>Providing ways in which shipbuilding treatises can be used digitally by both
                    scholars and students is an attractive interdisciplinary effort for a number of
                    reasons. First, is the opportunity to investigate the variety of ways in which
                    manuscripts’ contents (both texts and illustrations) can be structured and
                    classified. Second, is the opportunity to make original-source material
                    available at the location of an excavation; the treatises description of the
                    construction of the physical objects can provide valuable information about
                    fragments of ship timbers that are recovered from an excavation site. This
                    effort clearly draws techniques from the earlier projects in the digital
                    humanities that examine the characteristics of digital representations of
                    paper-based texts. However the linkage to physical artifacts opens up additional
                    possibilities and considerations.</p><p>Digital humanities projects involving manuscripts or printed texts have been
                    related, for the most part, to literature and historical records; some Know:
                    Responding to the Computational Transformation of the well-known examples
                    include the Canterbury Tales Project.<note n="1"> The Canterbury Tales Project
                            <xptr crdate="2006-11-12" to="http://www.canterburytalesproject.org/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note>, the Rossetti Archive<note n="2"> The Rossetti Archive <xptr crdate="2006-11-12" to="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/rossetti/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note>, and the Perseus Digital Library <note n="3">The Perseus Digital Library
                            <xptr crdate="2006-11-12" to="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note>. We have been involved in creating collections of this form as well for
                        Cervantes<note n="4"> Eduardo Urbina, Electronic Variorum Edition of the
                            <emph rend="italics">Quixote</emph><xptr crdate="2006-11-12" to="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/rossetti/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note>,Donne,<note n="5"> Gary Stringer, Digital Donne. <xptr crdate="2006-11-12" to="http://www.csdl.tamu.edu/donne" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note> and Picasso<note n="6"> Enrique Mallen, The On-line Picasso Project
                            <xptr crdate="2006-11-12" to="http://picasso.tamu.edu/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note>. In the context of Nautical Archaeology, the manuscript of Michael of
                    Rhodes captures the knowledge obtained by this 15th century seaman during his 4-
                    decade-long career<note n="7"> Michael of Rhodes <xptr crdate="2006-11-12" to="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/rossetti/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note>. The presentation of the manuscript, oriented to a general audience,
                    hints at the value that such materials will have to the professional
                    archaeologist when representations and tools are provided that meet his
                    scholarly needs.</p><p>Until relatively recently, ships were the most advanced and complex
                    transportation means designed. Nautical treatises hold the key to understanding
                    their technical complexity. In essence, the collection of treatises represents
                    the technical manuals describing the components, their use, and the steps taken
                    in manufacturing of the ship. Several characteristics of treatises make
                    understanding them a very challenging task. Language is a major problem; in
                    order to better understand their contents, it is necessary to provide
                    translations and explanations of concepts, pieces, and sequences. Beyond the
                    multiple languages in which the treatises were written, they also come from
                    diverse geographical locations and span centuries, making terms, concepts, and
                    descriptions difficult to understand. Different units and standards of
                    measurement—a key aspect in technical descriptions—raise problems about not only
                    comparing treatises with different provenance, but also translating them into
                    modern scales; units of measurement used in the treatises are not necessarily
                    the ones used by archaeologists to measure recovered evidence. To tackle these
                    problems, we have developed a multilingual glossary, in which terms include
                    their corresponding translation and definition into ten languages (which can be
                    expanded as needed). The incorporation of “roles,” enables us to expand
                    characteristics related to the terms, for example spellings and synonyms. Our
                    framework allows multiple values per role as well the addition of more roles as
                    they are required (see figure 1).</p><p>However, despite common features shared by physical fragments and their
                    corresponding descriptions in the texts, fragments obtained from individual
                    ships have important differences because of the differing physical conditions
                    that they have been exposed to. Damaged and incomplete ship remains require the
                    adoption of an encoding scheme to describe and quantify uncertainty; textual
                    descriptions do not encompass “uncertainty.”</p><p>In the previous paragraphs we have briefly outlined the relationship between
                    physical archaeological evidence and written descriptions in the treatises.
                    However, treatises in themselves have properties that make them unique. For
                    example, an important question is how similar or different are treatises in
                    terms of the sequences, construction techniques, and materials used. An initial
                    approach would suggest that probably the encoding used in their description
                    could be used to quantify the degree of similarity.</p><p>Since treatises are “technical manuals,” illustrations are essential in their
                    understanding; therefore, we adopted a two-step process. First, illustrations
                    have to be segmented, an illustration <emph rend="bold">Ij</emph>, can be
                    composed of a set of components <emph rend="bold">C = {c1, c2,… ck}</emph>,
                    where a component <emph rend="bold">ci</emph> has a list of properties <emph rend="bold">P = {p1, p2 …pk}</emph>. Second, each component might have a
                    description within the text, thus a linkage between the two is required. To make
                    things more complex, a component <emph rend="bold">cj</emph> can be formed from a subset of components, a
                    step that resembles a recursive property, where the ship as a whole is formed by
                    small parts, which in turn are composed by smaller ones, and so on. Figure 3
                    depicts the interface for capturing coordinates in images linking them to terms
                    from the glossary.</p><p>Conversely, components can be mapped to other representations; a good example is
                    a model created in 3D rendering software such as Rhino. We have done preliminary
                    tests, exporting geometric data from Rhino models into XML and linking them to
                    both 2D slides of the model and their corresponding occurrences in the
                    treatises.</p><p>Although linking text and images has been extensively studied; the context of
                    treatises raises a series of complex issues. For example, the text of a treatise
                    could be segmented in a variety of ways based on different needs; assemblage
                    sequences, materials used, and section of the ship being described. This in turn
                    raises some interesting questions, for example: could the components being
                    included in part of the text give a hint of what that section is about, or what
                    section of the ship it describes? How could components in different treatises be
                    compared?</p><p> Our current collection includes digital images and transcriptions of three of
                    the most relevant late 16th and early 17th century Portuguese treatises: <note n="8">Special thanks to Academia de Marinha, Lisbon Portugal for providing
                        the facsimiles. <xptr crdate="2006-11-12" to="http://www.marinha.pt/Marinha/PT/Menu/DescobrirMarinha/Actividade/AreaCultural/academia/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note> Fernando Oliveira’s <emph>Livro da
                        Fabrica das Naos</emph> (dated to 1580), João Baptista Lavahna’s
                        <emph>Livro Primeiro da Architectura Naval</emph><note n="9">Lavahna, Joao
                        Baptista. <title level="m">Livro Primeiro da Architectura Naval,</title> c.
                        1610. Facsimile, transcription, and translation into English, Lisbon,
                        Academia de Marinha, 1996.</note> (dated between 1608 and 1615), and Manoel
                    Fernandez’s <emph>Livro de Tracas de Carpintaria</emph>(dated to 1616). We
                    expect to add more manuscripts as permissions from holders are granted.</p><p>The treatises’ dual role as historically-significant text and as formal
                    specification of elements of ship design affords an opportunity to investigate
                    the relationship of techniques developed within the context of textual studies
                    to applications with physical objects and virtual 3D models. Further, the
                    treatises provide the foundation for our development of the Nautical Archaeology
                    Digital Library (<xptr to="http://nadl.tamu.edu/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>),
                    which will center on providing resources in support of archaeologists’ work and
                    on dissemination of expedition artifacts<note n="10">Dissemination of
                        archaeological artifacts also has been the focus of other significant
                        efforts including ArchaeoML, used in OCHRE <xptr crdate="2006-11-12" to="http://ochre.lib.uchicago.edu/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>formerly
                        XSTAR, and ETANA<xptr crdate="2006-11-12" to="http://www.etana.org/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note>. The combination holds promise of
                    extending the reach of the digital humanities.</p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_153_furuta_1.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 1: The multilingual glossary interface depicting terms,
                        translations, and definitions in various languages.</figDesc></figure><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_153_furuta_2.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 2: Treatises browser allows navigation of the
                    treatises.</figDesc></figure><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_153_furuta_3.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 3: Treatises markup utility allows to mark certain areas of the
                        image and associate them with terms and categories in the
                    glossary.</figDesc></figure></div0></body></text></TEI.2>