<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="poster_240_rockwell"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Text Analysis Portal for Research, Using the Public Release</title><author><name reg="Rockwell, Geoffrey">Geoffrey Rockwell</name></author><author><name reg="Sinclair, Stéfan">Stéfan Sinclair</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Field, Hana S.">Hana S. Field</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>poster</classCode><keywords><list type="simple'"><item>text analysis</item><item>portal</item><item>research environment</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list><item>HSF: Created from Geoffrey Rockwell's text<date value="2007-04">April
                    2007</date></item><item>SAS: Revised <date value="2007-05">May 2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Text Analysis Portal for Research, Using the Public Release"><titlePart type="main">Text Analysis Portal for Research, Using the Public
                Release</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Rockwell, Geoffrey">Geoffrey Rockwell</name><address><addrLine>georock@mcmaster.ca</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">McMaster University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Sinclair, Stéfan">Stéfan Sinclair</name><address><addrLine>sgsinclair@gmail.com</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">McMaster University</titlePart></front><body><div0><head>Introduction</head><p>In April of 2007 the TAPoR project, after extended testing and two
                    public beta versions, released Version 1.0 of the Text Analysis
                    Portal for Research.<note n="1">For more about the
                        TAPoR project see <xptr to="http://www.tapor.ca" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note> This portal gathers text analysis tools
                    configured as web services into an environment where users can define the texts
                    they want to work with, select the tools that best work with different text
                    formats, and log their research. The portal is, on the one hand a broker for
                    piping electronic texts to tools and then managing the results, and on the other
                    hand is a study environment where projects can be managed over time. Our poster
                    will do three things:<list type="unordered"><item>Show an overview of how the portal works with annotated screen shots.</item><item>Show the life of the project including the user testing phases.</item><item>We will have a laptop in order to demonstrate a live version of the
                            portal to interested.</item></list></p></div0><div0><head>Demonstration</head><p>Provided we can have a live internet connection we will be prepared to
                        demonstrate:<list type="unordered"><item>How the portal can be used even without an account using the Try It
                            feature or myLinks pages where users can publish sets of texts for
                            analysis.</item><item>How to get a free account from TAPoR.</item><item>How to define texts that may be elsewhere on the internet or uploaded.
                            How to organize these texts using tags and how to publish a set of
                            searchable texts for students or colleagues.</item><item>How to use the Workbench to organize a set of texts and specific tools
                            for a project. How to run tools on texts and how to save results.</item><item>How to log the progress of a research project and share it through
                            TAPoR.</item></list></p><p>If a live connection is not available we will have a local version running based
                    on the TAPoR Live CD which is a bootable version of linux and the portal that
                    works locally.</p></div0><div0><head>User Testing and the Life Cycle of a Tool Project</head><p>Version 1.0 of the portal is the result of extensive user testing which will be
                    visually represented in the poster as will ways new users can provide us
                    feedback as we develop the priorities for further releases. <note n="2">TAPoR
                        interface at <xptr to="http://www.tapor.ca/interface" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/> details a persona oriented investigation conducted by
                        Audrey Carr and Joanna Dacko. Dr. Wendy Duff at the University of Toronto
                        also conducted extensive interviews that have not been published, but which
                        were absracted for the portal development team. Finally, we have a layered
                        testing process combined with the gathering of tool statistics that is being
                        conducted on the release.</note></p><p>For those familiar with earlier versions of the portal there are a number of
                    improvements including:<list type="unordered"><item>A new type of news channel called a Research Log. Users can save
                            results from tools to this log along with comments. They can also save
                            the text/tool configuration to run again.</item><item>A new feature called Analyze Text that will open a window with the
                            text on the right and suggested tools on the left for close study of one
                            text.</item><item>The myLinks feature has been adapted so users can publish their public
                            texts for others to search across and for other to analyze. This can be
                            used, for example, for providing students with a study set of texts.</item><item>The interface has been simplified to make it easy for users to get
                            projects going.</item></list></p></div0><div0><head>Background</head><p>The TAPor Portal is one of the outcomes of a 5 year project funded by the Canada
                    Foundation for Innovation (CFI) that involves 6 universities across Canada,
                    including the University of Victoria, the University of Alberta, McMaster
                    University, the University of Toronto, the Université de Montréal and the
                    University of New Brunswick. Provincial funding bodies and our respective
                    universities have also supported the TAPoR project. The portal was developed by
                    Open Sky Solutions with a team primarily at McMaster University. The poster will
                    recognize the supporting institutions but will focus on the portal and not
                    present the wealth of other projects that are part of TAPoR. <note n="3"><title level="m">Mind Technologies</title> edited by Raymond Siemens and
                        David Moorman (U of Calgary Press, 2006) includes a number of articles
                        about the variety of projects supported by TAPoR.</note></p><p>This poster will show the current version of a major text analysis tools
                    development effort that developed a model for sustainable and modular text
                    analysis for a broad community. This is a challenge that has concerned computing
                    humanists since the 1980s. As Susan Hockey put it in a post to HUMANIST in 1996
                    that reported on a meeting she convened at CETH, "For some time, those of us
                    active in humanities computing have felt the need for better and/or more widely
                    accessible text analysis software tools for the humanities. There have been
                    informal discussions about this at a number of meetings, but so far no
                    substantial long-term plan has emerged to clarify exactly what those needs are
                    and to identify what could to be done to ensure that humanities scholars have
                    readily-available text analysis tools to serve their computing needs into the
                    next century."<note n="4">Susan Hockey, <title level="j"> Humanist Discussion
                            Group</title> 10.54 (23 May 1996). See <xptr to="http://lists.village.virginia.edu/lists_archive/Humanist/v10/0054.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>. There is also a note from Michael
                        Sperberg-McQueen pointing to a trip report available at <xptr to="http://tigger.uic.edu/~cmsmcq/trips/ceth9505.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></p><p>The TAPoR model meets a number of the objectives described for text analysis
                    tools in the 1990s by Hockey and others.<note n="5">Geoffrey Rockwell and John
                        Bradley, <title level="a">Eye-ContTact: Towards a New Design for
                            Text-Analysis Tools</title>, CHWP
                        A.4. (1998). See <xptr to="http://www.chass.utoronto.ca/epc/chwp/rockwell/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note> It is
                    widely accessible. It provides a long-term model using web services to bring
                    tools together where they can be used in a study environment. It allows new
                    tools to be added and existing tools to be improved or replaced over time as new
                    needs emerge. It allows research to be recorded and shared.</p></div0><div0><head>Future Plans</head><p>The TAPoR Portal also has limitations. Depending on tools provided as web
                    services by others increases the chances of simple operations not working. Many
                    of the tools are not multi-lingual. The tool broker model where the portal gets
                    a remote text and passes it to a remote tool is not as efficient as an
                    all-in-one model where texts can be preindexed. And, as with any large software
                    project there are still inconsistencies, awkward interface panels, and bugs.</p><p>The poster will conclude by outlining future plans. TAPoR hopes to be funded for
                    a second phase through the CFI Leading Edge Fund in order to add large-scale
                    text datamining and aggregation tools. Currently the portal model does not
                    pre-index large collections (except in limited cases) and provides limited
                    aggregation or crawling tools. TAPoR 2, if funded, will continue improving the
                    interface and will add large-scale functionality by adapting crawling, scraping
                    and data mining tools to the study space.</p></div0></body></text></TEI.2>