<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="panel_131_rehm"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Digital Text Resources for the Humanities – Legal Issues</title><author><name reg="Rehm, Georg">Georg Rehm</name></author><author><name reg="Witt, Andreas">Andreas Witt</name></author><author><name reg="Hinrichs, Erhard">Erhard Hinrichs</name></author><author><name reg="Lehmberg, Timm">Timm Lehmberg</name></author><author><name reg="Chiarcos, Christian">Christian Chiarcos</name></author><author><name reg="Zimmermann, Felix">Felix Zimmermann</name></author><author><name reg="Zinsmeister, Heike">Heike Zinsmeister</name></author><author><name reg="Dellert, Johannes">Johannes Dellert</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>panel</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>sustainability</item><item>corpora</item><item>legal issues</item><item>preservation</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Georg Rehm's html<date value="2007-05">May
                2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Digital Text Resources for the Humanities – Legal Issues"><titlePart type="main">Digital Text Resources for the Humanities – Legal
                Issues</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Rehm, Georg">Georg Rehm</name><address><addrLine>georg.rehm@uni-tuebingen.de</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Tübingen University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Witt, Andreas">Andreas Witt</name><address><addrLine>andreas.witt@uni-tuebingen.de</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Tübingen University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Hinrichs">Erhard Hinrichs</name><address><addrLine>eh@sfs.uni-tuebingen.de</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Tübingen University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Lehmberg, Timm">Timm Lehmberg</name><address><addrLine>timm.lehmberg@uni-hamburg.de</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Hamburg University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Chiarcos, Christian">Christian Chiarcos</name><address><addrLine>chiarcos@ling.uni-potsdam.de</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Potsdam University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Zimmermann, Felix">Felix Zimmermann</name><address><addrLine>mail@felix-zimmermann.eu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Institute for Legal Informatics<lb/>Hannover University </titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Zinsmeister, Heike">Heike Zinsmeister</name><address><addrLine>heike.zinsmeister@uni-tuebingen.de</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Tübingen University </titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Dellert, Johannes">Johannes Dellert</name><address><addrLine>jdellert@sfs.uni-tuebingen.de</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Tübingen University </titlePart></front><body><div0><p>The session "Digital Text Resources for the Humanities – Legal Issues"
                        consists of three papers that address the legal aspects connected to several
                        crucial phases of handling text resources: collecting, compiling, curating,
                        analysing, distributing, and archiving text resources such as corpora, are
                        tasks carried out on a day-to-day basis by people involved in fields such
                        as, for example, humanities computing, computational and corpus linguistics,
                        information retrieval and text mining. Despite the ubiquity of document
                        collections, the legal issues that are intrinsically tied to virtually all
                        texts created and published by third parties (most importantly, their
                        copyright, as well as privacy issues), do not typically attract a lot of
                        interest. Though these issues are acknowledged, they are often regarded as
                        rather insignificant for the research question at hand, or a project does
                        not have any jurisprudential expertise to deal with legal issues in an
                        adequate way. As a consequence, distributing a corpus (for example, to other
                        interested researchers) whose provenance is unknown or questionable, or
                        publishing excerpts from a document collection on a website, may become next
                        to impossible from a legal point of view. This is why scholars often decide
                        not to publish their collections (or parts thereof) online at all, in order
                        to avoid any potential legal problems. The session aims to provide an
                        overview of the following legal aspects: <list type="unordered"><item>The first contribution, "Language Corpora – Copyright – Data
                                Protection: The Legal Point of View" (Timm Lehmberg, and Felix
                                Zimmermann), highlights the legal requirements that hold with regard
                                to the construction of digital text resources, special emphasis is
                                given to the aspect of copyright and data protection (for example,
                                potential reasons for the need to anonymise text corpora).</item><item>The second presentation, "Collecting Legally Relevant Metadata by
                                Means of a Decision-Tree-Based Questionnaire System" (Timm Lehmberg,
                                Christian Chiarcos, Erhard Hinrichs, Georg Rehm, and Andreas Witt),
                                consists of two parts: first, a web-based questionnaire is
                                introduced that was developed to capture the requirements research
                                projects have with regard to the archiving and distribution of their
                                corpora; second, initial results from a study that spans three large
                                research centres and more than 60 individual research projects are
                                reported.</item><item>The final paper, "Corpus Masking: Legally Bypassing Licensing
                                Restrictions for the Free Distribution of Text Collections" (Georg
                                Rehm, Andreas Witt, Heike Zinsmeister, and Johannes Dellert),
                                introduces the idea of masking an annotated text corpus whose
                                original source text collection is copyright-protected, so that the
                                masked version can be distributed without any restrictions;
                                furthermore, a fully working tool for masking an XML-annotated
                                corpus is presented.</item></list></p><p>The authors of the three papers are associated with a joint project situated
                        in three Collaborative Research Centres (SFB, Sonderforschungsbereich) that
                        are sponsored by the German Research Foundation (DFG, Deutsche
                        Forschungsgemeinschaft): SFB 441 (<emph>Linguistic Data Structures</emph>,
                        Tübingen University), SFB 538 (<emph>Multilingualism</emph>, Hamburg
                        University), and SFB 632 (<emph>Information Structure</emph>, Potsdam
                        University). Each of these three research centres consists of about 15 to 20
                        research projects. Most projects work with digital text collections, in
                        practically all cases these collections and corpora are constructed by the
                        respective researchers themselves. A problem people involved in the fields
                        of digital humanities or computational linguistics are often confronted with
                        concerns the fact that the sustainability and reusability of corpora is not
                        given too much attention – or that these aspects, in a worst case scenario,
                        are completely ignored. Corpora are often created for an application or for
                        a project that has a very specific research question, but when the project
                        is finished it becomes next to impossible (especially for third parties) to
                        gain access to the resource that took several months or maybe even years to
                        create. The joint project <emph>Sustainability of Linguistic Data</emph> was
                        therefore established to provide the conceptual, technical and
                        infrastructural basis for a solution to the problem of sustainably archiving
                        these digital text collections, addressing issues as diverse as, for
                        example, annotation and metadata frameworks, best practice guidelines, legal
                        issues of distributing text collections, and unifying diverse tag sets by
                        means of an ontology.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Session Chairs:</hi> Georg Rehm and Andreas Witt</p><div1><head>Language Corpora – Copyright – Data Protection: The Legal Point of View</head><p rend="Presenter">Felix Zimmermann and Timm Lehmberg</p><div2><head>1 Introduction</head><p>Creating comprehensive and sustainable archives of linguistic data and
                            making them (or parts of them) accessible to the research community
                            leads to a number of essential legal questions being raised by different
                            aspects of law. Like any discipline handling large amounts of data, the
                            digital humanities are confronted with a complex system of authorities
                            and restrictions. From acquisition, through storing and processing to
                            the annotation and finally publication of the data, there are a number
                            of rights as well as duties each participant in this process has to
                            consider. Additionally, some legal systems provide special rules for the
                            use of data for scientific purposes. On the one hand the opacity of the
                            legal position leads to the assumption that, in many cases, linguistic
                            data are used and transferred in a way that does not comply with legal
                            requirements. On the other hand there is a noticeable tendency not to
                            transfer linguistic data for fear of breaking the law (see Jüttner 2000,
                            and Patzelt 2003).</p></div2><div2><head>2 Relevant Areas of Law</head><p>Two different areas of law play an important role in the use of
                            linguistic data for research purposes: <list type="unordered"><item>"<emph>Intellectual Property Rights</emph>" provide legal
                                    protection of non-material goods which are any kind of
                                    intellectual property of a third party. This includes, amongst
                                    others, literary works as well as <emph>databases</emph>,
                                    software and utility patents. In terms of law language corpora
                                    are defined as databases.</item><item>"<emph>Privacy and Personal Data Protection Law</emph>"
                                    imposes restrictions for the processing of any personal data,
                                    i.e., any data that can be linked to an individual. In the face
                                    of linguistic data processing any audio and video recordings
                                    (and their transcriptions) as well as metadata that contain
                                    personal information on speakers are covered by this law.</item></list>Both areas are relevant to the complete process of data
                            processing and have to be considered from the initial step of the data
                            based work (normally the acquisition of the data) to the time of
                            publication.</p></div2><div2><head>3 Aspects of National and International Law</head><p>In everyday legal practice a particularly relevant role is played by
                            those legislative rulesets that are based on constitutional norms.
                            Within these, interests and entitlements of other involved individuals
                            and institutions, which are worthy of protection, are often outlined in
                            minute detail in relation to the procurement, processing, and transfer
                            of linguistic primary data.</p><p>Federal states, which contain individual member states with their own
                            legislative authority (such as the US, Germany, Switzerland, Austria,
                            Spain) may have enacted specific member state rules. This leads to the
                            possibility that there may be complex and potentially internally
                            conflicting legislation within a state in a federation.</p><p>It is not just, however, the original national legal situation which
                            regulates the use of linguistic data. International obligations may,
                            through direct or indirect applicability, have considerable impact. In
                            2007, 27 member states of the European Union adhere to European legal
                            instruments (such as directives and regulations) in relation to the
                            national and international use of data. Pursuant to the doctrine of
                            direct applicability enshrined in Article 10 of the Treaty establishing
                            the European Communities, these norms have priority in relation to
                            potentially conflicting national norms. What needs to be borne in mind
                            is that the individual member states have some leeway in the
                            implementation of the instruments, which may lead to minute differences
                            in the level of protection.</p><p>Finally, public international treaties which oblige their signatories to
                            adhere to certain minimal standards need to be taken into consideration.
                            In relation to linguistic data and the problem of copyright, the <title level="m">Copyright Treaty of the World Intellectual Property
                                Organisation</title> (<emph>WIPO</emph>, 1996) is to be considered
                            as particularly relevant. The question of personality rights with a view
                            to individuals whose data are processed is addressed in the <title level="m">Convention on Human Rights and Fundamental
                            Freedoms</title> (1950). Additionally, the <title level="m">Convention
                                for the Protection of Individuals with regard to Automatic
                                Processing of Personal Data</title> (1981) provides further
                            normative guidance for the member states of the European Union.</p></div2><div2><head>4 The Legal Impact of Intellectual Property</head><p>Copyright protection of language corpora is provided by different aspects
                            of applicable law. In order to simplify the presentation, there will be
                            a focus on the law of harmonised rules by the European Communities that
                            are placed within the framework of the World Intellectual Property
                            Organisation (WIPO).</p><div3><head>4.1 Directive 91/250/EC on the Legal Protection of Computer
                                Programs</head><p>The different tasks of linguistic data processing (transcription as
                                well as annotation etc.) require a considerable number of software
                                tools. For this purpose, apart from commercial development, software
                                is written by the research establishment's employees. The
                                participants in this process rarely bother with legal protection of
                                their work. By implementing the Directive 91/250/EC, computer
                                programs in all Member States of the European Community are
                                protected by copyright law. In accordance with Article 1.3 of the
                                Directive 91/250/EC, a computer program is protected, if it is
                                original in the sense that it is the author's own intellectual
                                creation. Ideas and principles of a computer program are not
                                protected by this Directive. The term of protection is the author's
                                lifetime plus a period of 50 years. The author owns the exclusive
                                rights to reproduce, translate, adapt and publicly distribute his
                                computer program.</p><p>If a computer program has been created by an employee, in accordance
                                with Article 2.3 of the Directive 91/250/EC, the employer is, unless
                                otherwise provided by contract, the copyright holder of the
                                resource. In the case of software being developed within a research
                                project, from this point of view the copyright is held by the
                                respective research establishment (University etc.).</p></div3><div3><head>4.2 Directive 96/9/EC on the Legal Protection of Databases</head><p>In accordance with Article 1.2 of the Directive 96/9/EC, a database
                                is defined as a "collection of independent works, data or other
                                materials arranged in a systematic or methodical way and
                                individually accessible by electronic or other means". Without
                                exception, linguistic corpus data come under this protection. This
                                Directive makes two significant stipulations. First, it offers
                                protection by copyright to databases which, by reason of the
                                selection or arrangement of their contents, constitute the author's
                                own intellectual creation. Thereby the author owns the exclusive
                                right to carry out or authorise the reproduction, alteration and
                                distribution. Secondly the Directive creates an exclusive right
                                protection <emph>sui generis</emph> for makers of databases,
                                independent of the degree of innovation. This protection of any
                                investment allows the makers of databases to prevent unauthorised
                                extraction and/or re-utilisation.</p></div3><div3><head>4.3 Copyright Directive 2001/29/EC</head><p>The Copyright Directive 2001/29/EC adapts legislation on copyright
                                and related rights to reflect technological developments into
                                European Community law. In this process, it discusses and harmonises
                                the property of reproduction, communication and distribution rights.
                                Concerning linguistic research data, attention should be paid to
                                Article 5.3(a) of the Copyright Directive. It gives freedom to
                                Member States in supporting non-commercial science by making
                                copyright less restrictive for academic use of copyrighted work.</p></div3></div2><div2><head>5 The Legal Impact of Data Protection</head><p>Directive 95/46/EC on the protection of individuals with regard to the
                            processing of personal data imposes strict restrictions for the
                            elevation and utilisation of personal data. Personal data are pieces of
                            information which can be linked to a specific person. The processing of
                            personal data only is permitted by law, if there is a clear and lawful
                            purpose at the time of data procurement, and if the respective person
                            has expressed his/her consent. Further restrictions are imposed, if the
                            racial, national or ethnical origin, political opinion, religious or
                            philosophical beliefs are apparent. The same applies to the disclosure
                            of health conditions or sexual life. If personal data are transferred to
                            countries outside of the European Union (Transborder Dataflow to third
                            countries), a level of protection has to be guaranteed that is
                            equivalent to the European level, for example by means of the
                                <emph>Safe-Harbour-Principles</emph>. The respective person may
                            enforce his/her rights by means such as disclosure and deletion of the
                            data. Article 6.2, Article 11.2 and Article 13.2 of the Data Protection
                            Directive contain privileges for academic research. An escape strategy
                            in respect of data protection law problems is complete anonymisation
                            (disguising by removing personal information by abbreviating names,
                            locations etc.) or pseudonymisation (disguising by aliasing individuals,
                            locations, etc.) of the personal data. However, it remains unsolved
                            which level of abstraction constitutes sufficient anonymisation,
                            particularly if it is possible to draw conclusions by joining the data
                            with other resources.</p><p>Figure 1 gives an overview about the different types of right holders to
                            a database.</p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">panel_131_rehm_1.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 1: The different types of right holders</figDesc></figure></div2><div2><head>Legal Competence by Trusted Third Parties</head><p>An additional option is given by the use of a trusted third party hosting
                            the information that has been disguised by anonymisation or
                            pseudonymisation. It may act as a trustee, passing the aliased or
                            anonymised data from its origin to a requesting research institution.
                            The trusted party is not required by law, but it has the ability to
                            provide a high level of data security, integrity and protection during
                            the whole data transaction process (Kilian et al 1995, p. 63).
                            Additionally a trusted party can provide specialist advice in technical
                            and copyright matters. Further, we suggest proceedings to increase legal
                            certainty in case of creating and using linguistic databases.</p></div2></div1><div1><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Jüttner, Irmtraud">Irmtraud Jüttner</name></author><title level="a">Mannheimer Korpus und Urheberrecht. Die
                                    Einbeziehung zeitgenössischer digitalisierter Texte in die
                                    computergespeicherten Korpora des IDS und ihre juristischen
                                    Grundlagen</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Sprachreport</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">3</biblScope><date value="2000">2000</date><biblScope>11-13</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Kilian, Wolfgang">Wolfgang Kilian</name></author><title level="a">Daten für die Forschung im Gesundheitswesen</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Gutachten II</title><imprint><publisher>Toeche-Mittler Verlag</publisher><date value="1995">1995</date><biblScope type="pages">57-76</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Patzelt, Johannes">Johannes Patzelt</name></author><title level="a">Unter juristischem Blickwinkel: Textkorpora und
                                    Urheberrecht</title></analytic><monogr><editor role="editor"><name reg="Wegstein, Werner">Werner Wegstein</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Schwitalla, Johannes">Johannes Schwitalla</name></editor><title level="m">Korpuslinguistik deutsch: synchron – diachron –
                                    kontrastiv: Würzburger Kolloqium 2003,</title><imprint><pubPlace>Würzburg</pubPlace><date value="2003">2003</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div1></div0><div0 type="EmbeddedDoc"><div1><head>Collecting Legally Relevant Metadata by Means of a Decision-Tree-Based
                        Questionnaire System</head><p rend="Presenter">Timm Lehmberg, Christian Chiarcos, Erhard Hinrichs, Georg
                        Rehm, and Andreas Witt</p><div2><head>1 Introduction and Overall Concept</head><p>Most metadata standards used for corpus linguistic purposes (TEI, OLAC,
                            IMDI etc., for a complete overview see Lehmberg and Wörner 2007) require
                            elements that contain legal information about the rights holder to the
                            particular resource and/or its accessibility. Normally these metadata
                            elements are kept very abstract and do neither distinguish between the
                            different types of personal rights nor do they consider the option of
                            multiple holders of copyright.</p><p>The legal situation upon which the evaluation of linguistic data to be
                            used for scientific purposes is based is clearly defined, but too
                            complex to be understood completely by non-experts. Furthermore, it
                            varies from one country to the other and is in a constant state of flux.</p><p>In the framework of our joint sustainability initiative (see the
                            introduction to this session), a large number of heterogeneous corpora
                            have been acquired from multiple sources and multiple projects, and
                            processed with regard to different individual requirements (Schmidt et
                            al. 2006). This heterogeneity is responsible for the problem that the
                            legal metadata that need to be collected strongly vary with regard to
                            the respective corpus and data situation. Only for a small number of
                            projects associated with our sustainability initiative are detailed sets
                            of legal metadata that inform a potential user of the corpus about, for
                            example, stipulations or copyright holders, readily available. For the
                            majority of projects and corpora, this task has to be performed
                            retroactively.</p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">panel_131_rehm_2.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 1: A concept map visualising the query
                            structure</figDesc></figure><p>Facing the complexity of the legal context (see Zimmermann and Lehmberg,
                            in this session), it is almost impossible for non-experts to evaluate
                            the situation of their language data and to extract the relevant
                            metadata without professional advice.</p><p>To reduce the complexity of this task, concept maps were created with the
                            goal of making the legal situation as well as the legal terminology
                            transparent and understandable to non-professionals. Unlike mindmaps
                            that are primarily used for the (often spontaneous and intuitive)
                            mapping of ideas and processes, the technique of concept mapping is
                            intended more for knowledge modelling: concepts are represented by
                            nodes, links represent the relations between them.</p><p>As a utility to create the concept maps modelling the legal situation
                            within our joint sustainability initiative we used
                            <emph>CmapTools</emph>, a program distributed by the Institute for Human
                            and Machine Cognition (IHMC). IHMC CmapTools provide a client/server
                            architecture that allows users at different locations to work
                            collectively on Concept Maps and to discuss their structure and content
                            online.</p><p>Based on these schemata and following the principles of decision-trees,
                            we built an additional concept map representing the query structure of a
                            questionnaire. Digressing from the original principles of concept
                            mapping mentioned above, in this map queries are represented as nodes
                            whereas responses are represented as links between them. The primary
                            query given in the centre node (see figure 1) corresponds to two central
                            aspects of law (data protection and copyright, see Zimmermann and
                            Lehmberg, in this session). Each response leads to a large number of
                            additional queries that again, depending on the users' response, have
                            subordinated queries. Further sections of the concept map deal with the
                            accessibility of the data as well as their respective principles and
                            standards of data processing.</p><p>In same manner we modelled the query structure that surveys the meta
                            information that ideally has been collected in connection with the
                            compilation process of corpora. Therefore it contains queries asking for
                            established metadata standards (TEI, DC, OLAC, IMDI etc.) that may have
                            been used, and if necessary asks for additional information.</p><p>Due to the fact that the IHMC CmapTools provide an export of concept maps
                            into an XML-based format, the content and structure of the concept map
                            can be processed automatically to create the web based questionnaire
                            that is described in the following section.</p><p>The complete concept map structures will be demonstrated in conjunction
                            with example scenarios in our presentation.</p></div2><div2><head>2 Implementation</head><p>As the questionnaire has to be accessible from different research project
                            locations, it has been implemented using a XAMP (any operating system,
                            Apache, MySQL and PHP) architecture to create a user-friendly, web-based
                            interface. The conceptual structure represented by the concept map is
                            transformed into a relational database model. Accordingly, it is
                            possible both to model the tree structure of the queries (Celko, 2004)
                            and to save responses to these questions within the database.
                            Additionally, the database includes user data (as well as user access
                            control data) and links them to the metadata sets of the resource being
                            acquired by the questionnaire.</p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">panel_131_rehm_3.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 2: A web-based wizard guides the user through the
                                questionnaire</figDesc></figure><p>The user interface is generated by a script that parses the database and
                            guides the user though the questionnaire tree with the help of a
                            web-based wizard (see figure 2). This architecture has several
                            advantages: <figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">panel_131_rehm_4.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 3: An overview page gives information about the data
                                    collection progress</figDesc></figure><list type="unordered"><item>Subordinate queries that refer to specific details of some
                                    legal aspects automatically can be skipped if they become
                                    superfluous. For instance, there is no need to query contractual
                                    agreements with subjects if there is no personal data contained
                                    in the corpus.</item><item>The data model provides users with the option of registering
                                    multiple corpora and running the questionnaire wizard
                                    individually. Furthermore, users can share the data they entered
                                    into the system with other registered users so that it is
                                    possible to edit the data across project locations (for example,
                                    queries can be skipped, answered later, or left to other users).</item><item>Should the structure or content of the questionnaire tree be
                                    changed, the database will be modified accordingly. If the
                                    change leads to unanswered queries, this will be indicated to
                                    the user in a status page. For this reason, every user account
                                    has an overview page that gives information about the state of
                                    progress of every registered resource (see figure 3).</item><item>The questionnaire includes queries about metadata content and
                                    standards that already have been applied to the registered
                                    corpora, so that users do not have to insert redundant
                                    information already contained in existing metadata sets.</item><item>Administrator users have unlimited access to all data in the
                                    database, so that users can be provided with support, if needed.</item></list></p><p>We are currently in the process of collecting legally relevant metadata
                            from about 60 different research projects with the aid of the
                            questionnaire system described in this paper. Content and structure of
                            the concept maps is available on our project homepage at <xptr to="http://www.sfb441.uni-tuebingen.de/c2/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>.</p></div2></div1><div1><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Celko, Joe">Joe Celko</name></author><title level="m">Trees and Hierarchies in SQL for Smarties</title><imprint><pubPlace>San Mateo</pubPlace><publisher>Morgan Kaufmann</publisher><date value="2004">2004</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Lehmberg, Timm">Timm Lehmberg</name></author><author><name reg="Wörner, Kai">Kai Wörner</name></author><title level="a">Annotation Standards</title></analytic><monogr><editor role="editor"><name reg="Lüdeling, Anke">Anke Lüdeling</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Kytö, Merja">Merja Kytö</name></editor><title level="m">Corpus Linguistics, Handbücher zur Sprach- und
                                    Kommunikationswissenschaft (HSK)</title><imprint><pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>de Gruyter</publisher><date value="2007">In press</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Schmidt, Thomas">Thomas Schmidt</name></author><author><name reg="Chiarcos, Christian">Christian Chiarcos</name></author><author><name reg="Lehmberg, Timm">Timm Lehmberg</name></author><author><name reg="Rehm, Georg">Georg Rehm</name></author><author><name reg="Witt, Andreas">Andreas Witt</name></author><author><name reg="Hinrichs, Erhard">Erhard Hinrichs</name></author><title level="a">Avoiding Data Graveyards: From Heterogeneous Data
                                    Collected in Multiple Research Projects to Sustainable
                                    Linguistic Resources</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Proceedings of the E-MELD 2006 Workshop on Digital
                                    Language Documentation: Tools and Standards – The State of the
                                    Art, East Lansing, Michigan, June 2006</title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div1></div0><div0 type="EmbeddedDoc"><div1><head>Corpus Masking: Legally Bypassing Licensing Restrictions for the Free
                        Distribution of Text Collections</head><p rend="Presenter">Georg Rehm, Andreas Witt, Heike Zinsmeister, and Johannes
                        Dellert</p><div2><head>1 Introduction</head><p>Though XML-annotated text collections are commonplace in humanities
                            computing, the value of the annotation is often underestimated, as
                            interesting applications can be realised by ignoring the content and
                            considering the annotation exclusively. At the same time, the
                            distribution of text collections (e. g., linguistic resources) is often
                            restricted by rigid licence agreements. Usually, a corpus consists of a
                            source text collection (STC) acquired from third parties such as web
                            sites or publishers, and annotation layers that refer to, for example,
                            structural or linguistic properties. In practically all cases the STC is
                            a copyrighted property, so that it is up to the copyright holder to
                            decide if, and under which conditions, the corpus - a crucial part of
                            which is the STC - can be made available to the public or to the
                            research community.</p><p>The example we use in this paper is TüBa-D/Z ("Tübingen Treebank of
                            Written German" (Telljohann et al, 2004 &amp; Telljohann et al,
                            2006)). This manually annotated treebank is based on a CD ROM that
                            contains an archive of the issues the newspaper <emph>die tageszeitung
                                (taz)</emph> has published since 1986. If a researcher (the
                            licencee) wants to obtain TüBa-D/Z, available for academic purposes free
                            of charge, he or she has to sign a licence agreement with Tübingen
                            University's Linguistics Department (the licencer) which states that the
                            licencer is the copyright holder of the annotation and that the STC, as
                            published on the <emph>taz</emph> CD ROM, is copyrighted by contrapress
                            media GmbH. The licencee has to certify that he, she or the institution
                            the person works for has a valid licence for this CD ROM.<note n="1">The
                                    <emph>taz</emph> CD ROM costs about 50 Euros. Licences for other
                                corpora are often more expensive.</note><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">panel_131_rehm_5.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 1: Masking linguistic corpora by example of the
                                    TüBa-D/Z treebank</figDesc></figure> We propose the notion of corpus masking, i. e., obfuscating
                            the STC, but not the annotation layer(s), the STC is "removed", so that
                            the original licensing restrictions no longer hold for the "new"
                            resource. The advantage is that the valuable annotation information can
                            be made available for free (see figure 1).<note n="2">The institution
                                that created the annotation holds its copyright and can decide the
                                distribution conditions. As modern corpora may comprise several
                                annotation layers created by more than one research group, each
                                group can be considered the creator of its annotation layer and can
                                decide its terms of distribution (as a consequence, every annotation
                                layer should potentially comprise a complete metadata record).
                                Commercially available software tools that were used in the
                                annotation process might restrict the terms of distribution of the
                                resulting data set as well.</note></p></div2><div2><head>2 Corpora – Licence Restrictions – Sustainability</head><p>When linguists have created a corpus it can become quite difficult to
                            gain access to the corpus once the project is finished. In an ideal
                            world, academics can turn to a sustainability initiative in order to
                            archive their datasets and to make them available to other researchers,
                            e. g., by means of a web-based corpus platform (Dipper et al, 2006
                            &amp; Schmidt et al 2006). Apart from issues such as providing
                            standardised markup languages and metadata sets (Chiarcos et al, 2006
                            &amp; Wörner et al, 2006), sustainability initiatives have to take
                            the copyright of the original data into account.</p><p>We developed a tool that is able to mask corpora on the fly. Should
                            someone who is interested in a corpus that is available under a rigid
                            licence model not have a valid STC licence, he or she can still receive
                            the corpus, albeit in masked form. A corpus potentially can be
                            associated with <emph>several</emph> accessibility regulations: full
                            access to TüBa-D/Z requires a licence for the <emph>taz</emph> CD ROM,
                            whereas masked versions can be placed under, say, the GNU Free
                            Documentation or a Creative Commons Licence. Therefore, a sustainability
                            initiative has to come up with a flexible system of representing the
                            relationships and dependencies between the STC and the different
                            annotation layers and their individual licence restrictions.</p></div2><div2><head>3 How to Mask Linguistic Resources</head><p>The easiest option to obfuscate an annotated corpus is to remove the
                            text. A less radical solution substitutes every STC character with, for
                            example, "x" and every digit with "0". In addition to preserving word
                            length, this process retains information on upper and lower case by
                            substituting these with "x" and "X" (Toms &amp; Campbell, 1999).</p><p>We developed <emph>CorpusMasker</emph>, a Java-based tool for the
                            parameterised masking of linguistic resources represented as XML
                            documents. The XML element(s) or attribute(s) that comprise the actual
                            words or tokens to be masked (in case of TüBa-D/Z, the <hi rend="code">&lt;orth&gt;</hi> element) can be specified to handle
                            arbitrary annotation schemes. CorpusMasker features a dictionary
                            approach: after collecting all word forms, every word is mapped onto a
                            randomly generated string and replaced by that string. Word length can
                            be retained, as well as information on the distribution and positioning
                            of vowels and consonants. If a word is usually written with an initial
                            lower case character and that word appears with an initial upper case
                            character, the same randomised word is used (e. g., "dort" -&gt; "kulp",
                            "Dort" -&gt; "Kulp"). CorpusMasker performs an affix analysis that is
                            similar to morphology induction. The algorithm analyses certain words,
                            masks the roots, but retains the affixes, so that the text is masked but
                            valuable linguistic information that in itself is insufficient to
                            reconstruct the source text or even to interpret the masked text, is
                            kept intact for further analysis. Parameterised masking can be performed
                            with several different degrees of retaining linguistic information, from
                            the complete removal of the STC to a rather light but sufficient masking
                            that keeps, e. g., closed word classes unchanged (see table 1; affixes
                            are marked in italics).<note n="3">After DH 2007, a downloadable version
                                of CorpusMasker will be available on our web site under an Open
                                Source licence (<xptr to="http://www.sfb441.uni-tuebingen.de/c2/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>).</note></p><p>Linguistic corpora often contain POS information so that the
                            randomisation process results in a list that could act as a key to
                            unlock the masked corpus, i. e., to reconstruct the STC. As publication
                            of this complete list would contradict the purpose of the tool, we will
                            only provide a reduced version of the file so that the randomly
                            generated words can be mapped onto POS tags.</p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">panel_131_rehm_6.jpg</xref></p><figDesc/></figure></div2><div2><head>4 Masked Corpora: What are They Good for?</head><p>Our original goal had been to give researchers interested in TüBa-D/Z the
                            option of examining the annotation without ordering the <emph>die
                                tageszeitung</emph> CD ROM first. As our sustainability platform
                            will give access to copyrighted corpora, we will implement the option of
                            masking a corpus archive before every single download to enhance
                            security. Furthermore, a password protected dictionary lookup could be
                            provided that enables researchers to retrieve a small amount of
                            translations from randomised strings back to original words. Following,
                            we sketch some application scenarios for masked corpora.</p><p><emph rend="bold">Unlexicalised parsing</emph> A masked corpus can be
                            used for all sorts of unlexicalised training. Charniak (1996) shows that
                            an unlexicalised PCFG trained on treebank annotations is compatible with
                            other unlexicalised parsers. In addition to the masked training data, a
                            minimal amount of testing data was required. In the case of TüBa-D/Z
                            this subcorpus could consist of randomly shuffled example sentences from
                            the treebank with unmasked text and full annotation. Hinrichs et al.
                            (2005) discuss experiments in memory-based learning of anaphora
                            resolution. Their tool is trained on the annotation of TüBa-D/Z and does
                            not take lexical information into account. The features refer to
                            morphological properties, parts-of-speech, syntactic boundaries and
                            grammatical functions, all of which are available in the annotation. In
                            this case even the test data could be generated directly from the masked
                            resource since the annotation includes marking of equivalence classes
                            comprising pronouns and noun phrases. The gold standard for testing
                            consists of these equivalence classes only in which the words are
                            represented by positional indices. The evaluation would then test
                            whether the relevant indices are grouped together correctly. A
                            comparable tool trained on masked corpus data could as well be applied
                            to `real' German texts.</p><p><emph rend="bold">Qualitative and quantitative analyses</emph> TüBa-D/Z's
                            annotation can be used for qualitative and quantitative analyses, it
                            includes both syntactic categories as well as grammatical functions. A
                            linguist can, for example, examine which categories occur as
                            predicatives (element <distinct>PRED</distinct>). In addition to this
                            qualitative investigation, the corpus also allows a quantitative
                            analysis: what percentage of predicatives is realised by a noun phrase,
                            what percentage is realised by an adjectival phrase or by a
                            prepositional phrase? To give a second example, coordinate structures
                            are marked with the label <distinct>KONJ</distinct>; even without
                            knowledge of the word level the treebank annotation gives sufficent
                            information to examine parallelism effects with respect to the structure
                            of the conjuncts: syntactic categories, grammatical functions,
                            modifiers, and length, see, e. g., Levy (2004), and Steiner (2006).</p><p><emph rend="bold">Teaching linguistics and computational
                            linguistics</emph> The masked version of TüBa-D/Z contains an unnatural
                            language that acts like German syntaxwise, but the lexicon of this
                            language contains, for the most part, random strings and associated POS
                            tags. This fact makes the masked treebank a valuable resource in the
                            context of teaching computational linguistics. If students have to work
                            with a language that has a known syntax and a rudimentary morphology but
                            lexical entries that bear no meaning whatsoever, they might be able to
                            concentrate better on the tasks of developing grammar rules or improving
                            parsing efficiency (e. g., with regard to unlexicalised parsing). This
                            approach of blanking out semantics is compatible with Chomsky's notion
                            of language as processing a set of symbols.<note n="4">For centuries,
                                typographers and graphic designers use the "Lorem ipsum dolor sit
                                amet" text fragment to evaluate new layouts without resorting to
                                writing actual text. The blind text gives the impression of a
                                natural distribution of characters and whitespace without
                                distracting the reader by conveying any meaning that could be
                                interpreted intuitively. This approach might be useful for
                                visualising masked corpora by means of XML to SVG transformations
                                (Piez, 2004).</note></p><p><emph rend="bold">Evaluating NLP software</emph> Another promising
                            application scenario is the evaluation of NLP software. Most tools use
                            n-gram language models, more sophisticated applications can be trained
                            on annotated corpora. With a masked resource it is possible to measure
                            the influence syntactic annotations have concerning precision and
                            recall, as the performance data of an NLP tool with regard to original,
                            as well as slightly and fully masked corpora can be compared. This
                            approach could result in substantial arguments in favour, or against the
                            use of treebanks for training NLP tools.</p></div2><div2><head>5 Related Work</head><p>Anonymisation methods remove proper nouns and other identity-revealing
                            phrases to protect the privacy of the people mentioned in a text (for
                            example, medical or legal records (Corti et al, 2006, Medlock, 2006,
                            Poesio et al, 2006, &amp; Rock, 2001)). A second application area is
                            concerned with the removal of cues that might reveal the identity of the
                            author of a text. A third area concerns the masking, or obfuscation of
                            texts, as described in the present paper; we are not aware of similar
                            approaches to the masking of linguistic resources.<note n="5">In a
                                message posted to Corpora-List on Aug 19th, 2006, Péter Halácsy
                                suggested an interesting method to distribute a copyrighted corpus
                                under "fair use" conditions. Part of the copyright notice Halácsy et
                                al. apply to the Creative Commons-based licence of the "Hunglish"
                                corpus (D. Varga et al, 2005) reads: "We prevented the illegal use
                                of copyrighted material by shuffling the texts at sentence level.
                                This form is still useful for research purposes, while it does not
                                infringe upon the rightholders' interests."</note></p></div2><div2><head>6 Concluding Remarks</head><p>We call our approach parameterised masking because the randomisation
                            process can be influenced with regard to several parameters, so that,
                            for example, certain word classes are not randomised. Typically, when
                            closed word classes such as determiners and prepositions are kept
                            intact, at least part of the original meaning of a sentence can be
                            guessed. This leads us to a crucial question: what happens if we choose
                            to mask only a small number of words (for example, only proper nouns)?
                            Do we have to mask a certain percentage of words, in order to bypass the
                            STC's licensing restrictions? When does a text that has been masked only
                            minimally become the original text again, so that the licence
                            restrictions <emph>prohibited</emph> the distribution of the
                            pseudo-masked linguistic resource?</p></div2><div2><head>Acknowledgements</head><p>The authors would like to thank Timm Lehmberg (Hamburg) and Felix
                            Zimmermann (Hannover) for valuable comments with regard to legal aspects
                            of the approach presented in this contribution. Furthermore, we would
                            like to thank our colleague Holger Wunsch for valuable discussions.</p></div2></div1><div1 type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Charniak, E.">E. Charniak</name></author><title level="a">Tree-bank Grammars</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Proceedings of the 13th National Conference on
                                    Artificial Intelligence (AAAI-96)</title><imprint><publisher>MIT Press</publisher><date value="1996">1996</date><biblScope type="pages">1031-1036</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Chiarcos, Christian">Christian Chiarcos</name></author><author><name reg="Lehmberg, Timm">Timm Lehmberg</name></author><author><name reg="Rehm, Georg">Georg Rehm</name></author><author><name reg="Witt, Andreas">Andreas Witt</name></author><title level="m">Regulating Access to the Sustainability Platform.
                                    Technical report</title><imprint><publisher>SFB 441 (Tübingen University)</publisher><publisher>SFB 538 (Hamburg University)</publisher><publisher>SFB 632 (Potsdam University, Humboldt-University
                                        Berlin)</publisher><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Corti, L.">L. Corti</name></author><author><name reg="Day, A.">A. Day</name></author><author><name reg="Backhouse, G.">G. Backhouse</name></author><title level="a">Confidentiality and Informed Consent: Issues for
                                    Consideration in the Preservation of and Provision of Access to
                                    Qualitative Data Archives</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Forum: Qualitative Social Research</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">1.3</biblScope><date value="2000">2000</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Dipper, S.">S. Dipper</name></author><author><name reg="Hinrichs, E.">E. Hinrichs</name></author><author><name reg="Schmidt, T.">T. Schmidt</name></author><author><name reg="Wagner, A.">A. Wagner</name></author><author><name reg="Witt, A."> A. Witt</name></author><title level="a">Sustainability of Linguistic Resources</title></analytic><monogr><editor role="editor"><name reg="Hinrichs, E.">E. Hinrichs</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Ide, N.">N. Ide</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Palmer, M.">M. Palmer</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Pustejovsky, J.">J. Pustejovsky</name></editor><title level="m">Proceedings of the LREC 2006 Workshop Merging and
                                    Layering Linguistic Information, Genoa, Italy</title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date><biblScope type="pages">48-54</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Hinrichs, E.">E. Hinrichs</name></author><author><name reg="Filippova, K.">K. Filippova</name></author><author><name reg="Wunsch, H.">H. Wunsch</name></author><title level="a">What Treebanks Can Do For You: Rule-based and
                                    Machine-learning Approaches to Anaphora Resolution in
                                German</title></analytic><monogr><editor role="editor"><name reg="Civit, M.">M. Civit</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Kübler, S.">S. Kübler</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Martí, Ma. Antònia">Ma. Antònia Martí</name></editor><title level="m">Proceedings of the 4th Workshop on Treebanks and
                                    Linguistic Theories (TLT 2005), Barcelona, Spain</title><imprint><date value="2005">2005</date><biblScope type="pages">77-88</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Levy, Roger">Roger Levy</name><title level="a">The Statistical Properties of Coordinate Noun
                                        Phrases</title></author></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Presented at the Department of Linguistics,
                                    University of Colorado-Boulder, March 11, 2004</title><imprint><date value="2004">2004</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Medlock, B.">B. Medlock</name></author><title level="a">An Introduction to NLP-based Textual
                                Anonymisation</title></analytic><monogr><editor role="editor"><name reg="Calzolari, N.">N. Calzolari</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Choukri, K.">K. Choukri</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Gangemi, A.">A. Gangemi</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Mariani, J.">J. Mariani</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Maegaard, B.">B. Maegaard</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Odjik, J.">J. Odjik</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Tapias, D.">D. Tapias</name></editor><title level="m">Proceedings of the 5th International Conference on
                                    Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC 2006), Genoa, Italy</title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date><biblScope type="pages">1051-1056</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Piez, Wendell">Wendell Piez</name></author><title level="a">Way Beyond Powerpoint: XML-driven SVG for
                                    Presentations</title></analytic><monogr><editor role="editor"><name reg="Wood, Lauren">Lauren Wood</name></editor><title level="m">Proceedings of XML 2004, Washington, November 2004.
                                    IDEA</title><imprint><date value="2004">2004</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Poesio, M.">M. Poesio</name></author><author><name reg="Kabadjov, M. A.">M. A. Kabadjov</name></author><author><name reg="Goux, P.">P. Goux</name></author><author><name reg="Kruschwitz, U.">U. Kruschwitz</name></author><author><name reg="Bishop, E.">E. Bishop</name></author><author><name reg="Corti, L.">L. Corti</name></author><title level="a">An Anaphora Resolution-Based Anonymization
                                Module</title></analytic><monogr><editor role="editor"><name reg="Calzolari, N.">N. Calzolari</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Choukri, K.">K. Choukri</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Gangemi, A.">A. Gangemi</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Mariani, J.">J. Mariani</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Maegaard, B.">B. Maegaard</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Odjik, J.">J. Odjik</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Tapias, D.">D. Tapias</name></editor><title level="m">Proceedings of the 5th International Conference on
                                    Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC 2006), Genoa, Italy</title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date><biblScope type="pages">1191-1193</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Rock, F.">F. Rock</name></author><title level="a">Policy and Practice in the Anonymisation of
                                    Linguistic Data</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">International Journal of Corpus Linguistics</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">6.1</biblScope><date value="2001">2001</date><biblScope type="pages">1-26</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Schmidt, Thomas">Thomas Schmidt</name></author><author><name reg="Chiarcos, Christian">Christian Chiarcos</name></author><author><name reg="Lehmberg, Timm">Timm Lehmberg</name></author><author><name reg="Rehm, Georg">Georg Rehm</name></author><author><name reg="Witt, Andreas">Andreas Witt</name></author><author><name reg="Hinrichs, Erhard">Erhard Hinrichs</name></author><title level="a">Avoiding Data Graveyards: From Heterogeneous Data
                                    Collected in Multiple Research Projects to Sustainable
                                    Linguistic Resources</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Proceedings of the E-MELD 2006 Workshop on Digital
                                    Language Documentation: Tools and Standards – The State of the
                                    Art, East Lansing, Michigan</title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Steiner, Ilona">Ilona Steiner</name></author><title level="a">Coordinate Structures: On the Relationship between
                                    Parsing Preferences and Corpus Frequencies</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Pre-Proceedings of the International Conference on
                                    Linguistic Evidence 2006, Tübingen, February 2006</title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Telljohann, Heinke">Heinke Telljohann</name></author><author><name reg="Hinrichs, Erhard">Erhard Hinrichs</name></author><author><name reg="Kübler, Sandra">Sandra Kübler</name></author><title level="a"> The TüBa-D/Z Treebank – Annotating German with a
                                    Context-Free Backbone</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Proceedings of the 4th International Conference on
                                    Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC 2004), Lisbon, Portugal,
                                    2004</title><imprint><date value="2004">2004</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Telljohann, Heike">Heike Telljohann</name></author><author><name reg="Hinrichs, Erhard">Erhard Hinrichs</name></author><author><name reg="Kübler, Sandra">Sandra Kübler</name></author><author><name reg="Zinsmeister, Heike">Heike Zinsmeister</name></author><title level="m">Stylebook for the Tübingen Treebank of Written
                                    German (TüBa-D/Z). Technical report</title><imprint><pubPlace>Tübingen</pubPlace><publisher>Seminar für Sprachwissenschaft, Universität Tübingen</publisher><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Toms, E. G.">E. G. Toms</name></author><author><name reg="Campbell, D. G.">D. G. Campbell</name></author><title level="a"> Genre as Interface Metaphor: Exploiting Form and
                                    Function in Digital Environments</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Proceedings of the 32nd Hawaii International
                                    Conference on Systems Sciences (HICSS-32)</title><imprint><publisher>IEEE Computer Society</publisher><date value="1999">1999</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Varga, D.">D. Varga</name></author><author><name reg="Halácsy, P.">P. Halácsy</name></author><author><name reg="Kornai, A.">A. Kornai</name></author><author><name reg="Nagy, V.">V. Nagy,</name></author><author><name reg="Németh, L.">L. Németh</name></author><author><name reg="Trón, V.">V. Trón</name></author><title level="a">Parallel Corpora for Medium Density
                                Languages</title></analytic><monogr><editor role="editor"><name reg="Angelova, G.">G. Angelova</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Bontcheva, K.">K. Bontcheva</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Mitkov, R.">R. Mitkov</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Nicolov, N.">N. Nicolov</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Nikolov, N.">N. Nikolov</name></editor><title level="m">International Conference on Recent Advances in
                                    Natural Language Processing, Borovets, Bulgaria, 2005</title><imprint><date value="2005">2005</date><biblScope type="pages">590-596</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Wörner, Kai">Kai Wörner</name></author><author><name reg="Witt, Andreas">Andreas Witt</name></author><author><name reg="Rehm, Georg">Georg Rehm</name></author><author><name reg="Dipper, Stefanie">Stefanie Dipper</name></author><title level="a">Modelling Linguistic Data Structures</title></analytic><monogr><editor role="editor"><name reg="Usdin, B. T.">B. T. Usdin</name></editor><title level="m">Proceedings of Extreme Markup Languages 2006,
                                    Montréal, Québec, August 2006</title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div1></div0></body></text></TEI.2>