<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="panel_236_sdhsemi"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>SDH/SEMI Panel: Explorations in a Variety of Interfaces for the Reading of a
                    Database</title><author><name reg="Vandendorpe, Christian">Christian Vandendorpe </name></author><author><name reg="Rueker, Stan">Stan Ruecker </name></author><author><name reg="Sinclair, Stéfan">Stéfan Sinclair</name></author><author><name reg="Forest, Dominic">Dominic Forest</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>panel</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>society panel</item><item>interfaces</item><item>databases</item><item>reading</item><item>reves</item><item>Mandala</item><item>semantic interfaces</item><item>text mining</item><item>computer-assisted text analysis tools</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Christian Vandendorpe's doc <date value="2007-05"> May 2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="SDH/SEMI Panel: Explorations in a Variety of Interfaces for the Reading of a                 Database"><titlePart type="main">SDH/SEMI Panel: Explorations in a Variety of Interfaces for
                    the Reading of a Database</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Vandendorpe, Christian">Christian Vandendorpe </name><address><addrLine>Christian.Vandendorpe@uottawa.ca</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Département de lettres françaises<lb/>Université d’Ottawa</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Ruecker, Stan">Stan Ruecker</name><address><addrLine>sruecker@ualberta.ca</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of Alberta</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Sinclair, Stéfan">Stéfan Sinclair</name><address><addrLine>sgsinclair@gmail.com</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">McMaster University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Forest, Dominic">Dominic Forest</name><address><addrLine>dominic.forest@umontreal.ca</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">École de bibliothéconomie et des sciences de
                l'information<lb/>Université de Montréal</titlePart></front><body><div0><div1><head>A Textual Database of Dreams and the New Context of Reading</head><p><emph rend="bold">Christian Vandendorpe </emph> (Département de letters françaises, Université d’Ottawa)</p><p>The advent of the web has fostered the development of specialised textual
                    databases, dedicated to tabular collections of snippets of our literary
                    heritage. Their purpose is to facilitate the study of a particular phenomenon
                    through the centuries. Henceforth, the act of reading tends to adopt a tabular
                    way of reading as the one advocated by Claude Levy Strauss for the study of
                    myths. In order to focus on a specific case, we shall examine the textual mysql
                    database <xptr to="http://www.reves.ca" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>, a
                    collection of some fifteen hundred dream narratives from various cultures since
                    Homer and the Bible, and discuss its goals and its initial interface. The
                    challenge is to design an interface that would be both efficient and exciting,
                    inducing in the reader the desire of reading and helping him or her to explore
                    the database and to make meaningful relations between the data.</p></div1><div1><head>The Mandala as an Interface to a Textual Database</head><p><emph rend="bold">Stan Ruecker </emph> (University of Alberta) and <emph rend="bold">Stéfan Sinclair </emph> (McMaster University) </p><p>The Mandala is a Java-xml application that makes visible the relations between
                    sets of data. Its playful interface is designed to elicit a meaningful reading
                    activity by the user in order to facilitate an in-depth exploration of the
                    contents. We shall examine how it works with <xptr to="http://www.reves.ca" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>, its potential and its pertinence in the new
                    context of reading.</p></div1><div1><head>Towards More Powerful Semantic Interfaces</head><p><emph rend="bold">Dominic Forest </emph> (École de bibliothéconomie et des sciences de l'information,
                    Université de Montréal)</p><p>In this presentation, I will discuss the preliminary results of a research
                    initiative where we explored the relevance of applying text mining techniques on
                    a literary corpus. The corpus used in this work is composed of short
                    thematically-related literary texts stored in a database. The main objective of
                    this project is twofold. First, we want to explore if traditional text mining
                    techniques can successfully be used to assist the extraction and analysis of
                    relevant information found in literary texts. Secondly, we also want to explore
                    if computer-assisted text analysis tools and text mining techniques can be
                    useful to help access to valuable literary information stored in a textual
                    database. This talk will be divided in three main parts. First, I will present
                    the fundamental text mining concepts and techniques. In the second part, I will
                    describe the computer-assisted text analysis processes that were applied on the
                    online textual database (<xptr to="http://www.reves.ca" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>).
                    Finally, I will discuss some of the results we obtained and give an overview of
                    the future work that will be done in this project. </p></div1></div0></body></text></TEI.2>