<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="paper_142_jessop"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Digital Visualization as a Scholarly Activity</title><author><name reg="Jessop, Martyn">Martyn Jessop</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>paper</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>visualization</item><item>images</item><item>humanities computing</item><item>digital humanities</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Martyn Jessop's doc <date value="2007-03">March
                2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Digital Visualization as a Scholarly Activity"><titlePart type="main">Digital Visualization as a Scholarly Activity</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Jessop, Martyn">Martyn Jessop</name><address><addrLine>martyn.jessop@kcl.ac.uk</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Centre for Computing in the Humanities<lb/>King's College
            London</titlePart></front><body><div0><head>Introduction</head><p>The numerous visual metaphors that describe cognitive processes hint at the nexus
                    of relationships between what we see and what we think. We say we ‘see’ when we
                    mean we understand, we try to organize and make our ideas ‘clear’ by bringing
                    them into ‘focus’, and so on. When faced with tasks that require substantial
                    thought or organization of ideas we will often reach for a pen and paper to
                    ‘sketch out’ (another visual metaphor) our thoughts. We have a deep
                    understanding that we can enhance our thought processes by finding ways of
                    linking external perception with our interior mental processes. Graphic aids to
                    thinking are not new but the development of computers has provided a new medium
                    with remarkable functionality. This in turn offers the potential for new
                    research methodologies that amplify cognition. These tools serve two distinct
                    purposes. One of these is often described by the hackneyed phrase “A picture is
                    worth ten thousand words”.<note n="1">This is commonly believed to be based on a
                        “Chinese proverb” however Paul Martin Lester believes that it was in fact
                        made up by the advert writer Federick R. Barnard. See <xptr to="http://www5.Fullerton.edu/les/ad.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>
                        and Printers’ Ink, March 10, 1927.</note> This misses the true point of
                    visualization as what is being described here is just a matter of transmission,
                    of having high bandwidth to transmit large volumes of information. Of far
                    greater importance is the ability of these tools to allow visual perception to
                    be used in the creation or discovery of new knowledge. Knowledge is not
                    transferred, revealed, or perceived, but is created through a dynamic process.
                    This raises epistemological issues concerning visualization and points the way
                    to an intellectual approach to the subject.</p><p>Computer visualization techniques began as a methodology for understanding the
                    meaning of large volumes of numeric data. Scientists needed a means of
                    visualizing the flood of data that can be collected by modern monitoring and
                    measuring instruments. The National Science Foundation initiative on Scientific
                    Visualization launched in 1985 led in a very short time to Scientific
                    Visualization becoming recognised as not just a methodology but a discipline in
                    its own right. A similar trend may now be developing in the Humanities. For
                    example the London Charter seeks to establish principles for the use of 3D
                    visualization in research and communication of cultural heritage that ensure the
                    intellectual integrity of the methods and outcomes derived from it. How is
                    visualization being used in the humanities at the moment? Is there a potential
                    counterpart to Scientific Visualization in the digital humanities – a field of
                    ‘humanistic visualization’? What issues does it raise? Where is the common
                    ground and what are the intellectual issues involved?</p></div0><div0><head>Visualization in the Digital Humanities</head><p>There are many ways of structuring an examination of the use of visualization in
                    the humanities; by discipline, by type of information structure and so on. To
                    set the context for this paper I have chosen to look at the type of data that is
                    being visualized. The boundaries of data types are sometimes blurred but a
                    starting point could be as follows <list type="unordered"><item>Numbers. Quantitative analysis and visualization has been an
                            established tool in many humanities disciplines for a long time. It is
                            found in generic statistical analysis software or embedded in
                            specialised applications such as text analysis. It is gradually
                            permeating into new areas of the humanities through work such as that of
                            Franco Moretti (2005) who has argued for a wider application of
                            quantitative methods in areas such as literary history.</item><item>Text: Visualization techniques using tables and graphs have been
                            commonplace in text analysis for many years. These visualizations are
                            sometimes variants of statistical visualizations of numeric data (as in
                            word frequencies) but in other cases they are specialised visual forms
                            of text analysis. Projects such as the TAPoR and NORA Projects are
                            developing imaginative new visual forms and applications. These new
                            methods apply not just to the visual representation of the results of
                            analysis but also to the visualization of the texts themselves. This
                            aims to support interpretive scholarship by allowing areas or
                            relationships of interest to be identified within large volumes of text.
                            Projects have explored specific texts in this way, for example Dante’s
                            Inferno , Hume’s Dialogues and The Shape of Shakespeare but there is
                            substantial scope for a tool that could be applied to any text. The use
                            of the word ‘tool’ here should not be taken to imply that this is a
                            computational problem, this is far from the truth, as what is being
                            grappled with here are conceptual problems. For example, what is a text?
                            How should it be displayed visually? Humanities computing provides a
                            medium with a myriad of possibilities of representation; uni-dimensional
                            or two dimensional physical objects, abstract objects showing relations
                            among words or between words and annotations, and animations. Further
                            questions arise from this work; is there a need for representational as
                            well as interpretive markup? What are the relationships between text
                            visualization and the interpretation of texts? The visualizing of texts
                            is also an area which links humanities computing work to the arts, for
                            example the interactive installation Text Rain by Camille Utterback and
                            Romy Achituv.</item><item>Narratives and relationships. These can be grouped and referred to as
                            diagrams . Edward Tufte has drawn public attention to this style of
                            diagram; famous examples include the work of Playfair and Charles
                            Minard’s narrative graphic of Napoleon’s ill-fated campaign against
                            Russia in 1812. In many respects this has been a neglected field since
                            the advent of digital tools because diagrams of this type are not easily
                            implemented in software. They are also potentially of enormous value to
                            the humanities as narratives and the study of relationships between
                            people, events and artefacts are studied by many disciplines.</item><item>Space. The study of spatial relationships and a sense of place occur
                            in many humanities disciplines. This area is dominated by Geographical
                            Information System (GIS) software but this was developed for scientific
                            data and is not ideally suited to the qualitative data used in the
                            humanities (Jessop, 2006). Digital dynamic maps are one of many
                            alternatives offering media that are better suited to humanists (Jessop,
                            2006). The Electronic Cultural Atlas Initiative (ECAI) with its
                            utilization of Timemap provides an indication of possible future
                            developments.</item><item>Time. Digital visualization provides a very powerful medium for
                            temporal visualisation. Tools such as timelines allow one to explore the
                            development of complex historical events and the inter-relationships
                            between precursor events. They are of obvious value in the study of
                            history where later events build upon earlier ones but they can also be
                            applied elsewhere. Historiography and literary criticism are both
                            histories of accumulated comments on a subject. Matt Jensen (2006) has
                            developed a number of timeline tools which are intended to answer the
                            styles of questions that are asked by humanists, for example in the case
                            of political scandals questions of the style ‘who knew what and when’ or
                            for exploring the response to an author’s writing over a period of many
                            years</item><item>3D Visualization. Much of this work has centred upon visualizations of
                            the built environment. It is of interest to not only historians and
                            archaeologists but also anyone who seeks to find out how the buildings
                            of the past worked in human terms, for example the Pompey Theatre and
                            Theatron projects are based on historical and archaeological data but
                            are primarily of interest to scholars of theatre studies. 3D
                            visualization is of especial interest in the context of this paper
                            because there is currently great deal of work focused on defining not
                            only good practice (see ICT Methods Network) but also principles for
                            maintaining the intellectual integrity of such work, for example the
                            London Charter. It may therefore provide pointers for similar work in
                            the development of a broader humanistic visualization as a whole.</item></list></p><p>Any demarcations between the applications of visualization between different
                    disciplines are misconceived. There is much common ground offering considerable
                    potential for humanities computing and the digital humanities. This is where we
                    need to focus our attention if digital visualization is to achieve recognition
                    as a rigorous intellectual activity in research and teaching.</p></div0><div0><head>Conclusion</head><p>We accept that texts and documents are produced as readings resulting from acts
                    of interpretation between the reader and the text; we now need to regard images
                    in the same way. Every representation, visual or otherwise, is an effort to
                    structure an argument and as such it is a rhetorical device. We need to
                    understand the relationship between what is being communicated and how it is
                    being communicated.</p><p>Information graphics, and indeed images generally, can be considered as
                    historical artefacts themselves, filled with interesting incidental and
                    substantive information embodied in their production, style, and graphical
                    properties. But perhaps more importantly, they are expressions of procedures for
                    generating knowledge through the act of visualization and ways of displaying
                    knowledge embodied in visual imagery (Drucker, 2003).</p><p>Visualization addresses epistemological and pedagogical issues that are common to
                    the digital humanities and are at the forefront of the developing discipline of
                    humanities computing. This is a vast topic the main aim here is to identify some
                    of the underlying intellectual issues arising from visualization and the use of
                    images in digital humanities scholarship.</p></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Barthes, Roland">Roland Barthes</name></author><title level="m">Elements of Semiology</title><imprint><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>Hill and Wang</publisher><date value="1968">1968</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Bertin, Jacques">Jacques Bertin</name></author><title level="m">The Semiology of Graphics: Diagrams, Networks and Maps</title><edition>1967</edition><respStmt><resp>Trans.</resp><name reg="Berg, William J.">William J. Berg</name></respStmt><imprint><pubPlace>Madison, WI</pubPlace><publisher>University of Wisconsin Press</publisher><date value="1983">1983</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><editor role="editor"><name reg="Card, Stuart K.">Stuart K. Card</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Mackinlay, Jock">Jock Mackinlay</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Shneiderman, Ben">Ben Shneiderman</name></editor><title level="m">Readings in Information Visualization: Using Vision to
                                Think</title><imprint><pubPlace>San Diego, CA</pubPlace><publisher>Academic Press</publisher><date value="1999">1999</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Drucker, Johanna">Johanna Drucker</name></author><title level="a">Graphesis: Visual Knowledge Production and
                                Representation </title></analytic><monogr><imprint><date value="2003">2003</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-10-20" to="http://www.noraproject.org/reading.php" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Gombrich, E. H.">E. H. Gombrich</name></author><title level="m">Art and Illusion</title><imprint><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>Bollingen</publisher><date value="1961">1961</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Ivins, William M., Jr.">William M. Ivins, Jr.</name></author><title level="m">Prints and Visual Communication</title><imprint><pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace><publisher>MIT Press</publisher><date value="1969">1969</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Jessop, Martyn">Martyn Jessop</name></author><title level="a">The Visualization of Spatial Data in the
                            Humanities</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">19.3</biblScope><date value="2004">2004</date><biblScope type="pages">335-350</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Jessop, Martyn">Martyn Jessop</name></author><title level="a">Dynamic Maps in Humanities Computing</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Human IT</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">8.3</biblScope><date value="2006">2006</date><biblScope type="pages">68–82</biblScope></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.hb.se/bhs/ith/3-8/mj.pdf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Keeler, Mary">Mary Keeler</name></author><title level="a">The Place of Images in a World of Text</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">36.1</biblScope><date value="2002">2002</date><biblScope type="pages">75-93</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="McCarty, Willard">Willard McCarty</name></author><title level="m">Humanities Computing</title><imprint><pubPlace>Basingstoke, UK</pubPlace><publisher>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher><date value="2005">2005</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="McCormick, B. H.">B. H. McCormick</name></author><author><name reg="DeFanti, T. H.">T. H. DeFanti</name></author><title level="a">Visualization in Scientific Computing</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Computer Graphics</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">21.6</biblScope><date value="1987">1987</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Moretti, Franco">Franco Moretti</name></author><title level="m">Graphs, Maps, Trees: Abstract Models for a Literary
                                Theory</title><imprint><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Verso</publisher><date value="2005">2005</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Norman, Donald A.">Donald A. Norman</name></author><title level="m">Things that Make Us Smart</title><imprint><pubPlace>Reading, MA</pubPlace><publisher>Addison-Wesley</publisher><date value="1993">1993</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Rockwell, Geoffrey">Geoffrey Rockwell</name></author><title level="a">What is Text Analysis, Really?</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">18.2</biblScope><date value="2003">2003</date><biblScope type="pages">209-219</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Rohrer, Randall">Randall Rohrer</name></author><author><name reg="Ebert, David">David Ebert</name></author><author><name reg="Sibert, John">John Sibert</name></author><title level="a">The Shape of Shakespeare: Visualizing Text Using Implicit Surfaces</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Proceedings of the IEEE Symposium on Information Visualization</title><imprint><date value="1998">1998</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Scaife, Mike">Mike Scaife</name></author><author><name reg="Rogers, Yvonne">Yvonne Rogers</name></author><title level="a">External Cognition: How do Graphical Representations
                                Work?</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">International Journal of Human-Computer Studies</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">45.2</biblScope><date value="1996">1996</date><biblScope type="pages">185-213</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Schreibman, Susan">Susan Schreibman</name></author><title level="a">Computer-mediated Texts and Textuality Theory and
                                Practice</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">36.3</biblScope><date value="2002">2002</date><biblScope type="pages">283-93</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Sinclair, Stéfan">Stéfan Sinclair</name></author><title level="a">Computer Assisted Reading: Reconceiving Text
                            Analysis</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">18.2</biblScope><date value="2003">2003</date><biblScope type="pages">175-184</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Tufte, Edward R.">Edward R. Tufte</name></author><title level="m">The Visual Display of Quantitative Information</title><imprint><pubPlace>Cheshire, CT</pubPlace><publisher>Graphic Press</publisher><date value="1983">1983</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Unsworth, John">John Unsworth</name></author><title level="a">Forms of Attention: Digital Humanities Beyond
                                Representation</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Paper presented at "The Face of Text: Computer-Assisted
                                Text Analysis in the Humanities," the third conference of the
                                Canadian Symposium on Text Analysis (CaSTA), McMaster University,
                                November 19-21, 2004</title><imprint><date value="2004">2004</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-10-20" to="http://www3.isrl.uiuc.edu/%7Eunsworth/FOA/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Unsworth, John">John Unsworth</name></author><title level="a">New Research Methods for the Humanities</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">The Lyman Award Lecture, National Humanities Center, November 11, 2005</title><imprint><date value="2005">2005</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-10-20" to="http://www3.isrl.uiuc.edu/~unsworth/lyman.htm" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Wurman, Richard Saul">Richard Saul Wurman</name></author><title level="m">Information Design</title><imprint><pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace><publisher>MIT Press</publisher><date value="1999">1999</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div><div type="Bibliography"><p><hi rend="bold">Web Resources</hi><list><item>A Visualization of Dante's Inferno <xptr to="http://urizen.village.virginia.edu/hell/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></item><item>Electronic Cultural Atlas Initiative (ECAI) <xptr to="http://ecai.org/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></item><item>ICT Methods Network <xptr to="http://www.methodsnetwork.ac.uk/index.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></item><item>King’s Visualization Lab <xptr to="http://www.kvl.cch.kcl.ac.uk/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></item><item>The London Charter <xptr to="http://public-repository.epoch-net.org/The                     LondonCharter_v1.pdf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></item><item>Nora Project <xptr to="http://www.noraproject.org/description.php" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></item><item>Pompey Theatre Project <xptr to="http://www.kvl.cch.kcl.ac.uk/pompey.htm" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></item><item>Text Analysis Portal for Research (TAPoR) Project <xptr to="http://www.tapor.ca/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></item><item>TimeMap <xptr to="http://www.timemap.net/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></item><item>Theatron <xptr to="http://www.theatron.org/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></item></list></p></div></back></text></TEI.2>