<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="poster_137_eder"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>How Rhythmical is Hexameter: A Statistical Approach to Ancient Epic Poetry</title><author><name reg="Eder, Maciej">Maciej Eder</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Field, Hana S.">Hana S. Field</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>poster</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>oral literature</item><item>versification</item><item>rhythm</item><item>hexameter</item><item>Greek and Latin languages</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list><item>HSF: Created from Maciej Eder's doc<date value="2007-04">April
                    2007</date></item><item>SAS: Revised <date value="2007-05">May 2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="How Rhythmical is Hexameter: A Statistical Approach to Ancient Epic Poetry"><titlePart type="main">How Rhythmical is Hexameter: A Statistical Approach to
                    Ancient Epic Poetry</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Eder, Maciej.">Maciej Eder</name><address><addrLine>maciejeder@poczta.ijp-pan.krakow.pl</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Polish Academy of Sciences</titlePart></front><body><div0><p>In this paper, I argue that the later a given specimen of hexamater is, the less
                    rhythmical it tends to be. A brief discussion of the background of ancient Greek
                    and Latin metrics and its connections to orality is followed by an account of
                    spectral density analysis as my chosen method. I then go on to comment on the
                    experimental data obtained by representing several samples of ancient poetry as
                    coded sequences of binary values. Hexameter’s decreasing rhythmicity is then
                    illustrated with reference to particular authors. In the last section, I suggest
                    how spectral density analysis may help to account for other features of ancient
                    meter.</p><p>The ancient epic poems, especially the most archaic Greek poetry attributed to
                    Homer, are usually referred as an extraordinary fact in the history of European
                    literature. For present-day readers educated in a culture of writing, it seems
                    unbelievable that such a large body of poetry should have been composed in a
                    culture based on oral transmission. In fact, despite of genuine singers' and
                    audience's memory, epic poems did not emerge at once as fixed texts, but they
                    were re-composed in each performance (Lord 2000, Foley 1993, Nagy 1996). The
                    surviving ancient epic poetry displays some features that reflect archaic
                    techniques of oral composition, formulaic structure being probably the most
                    characteristic (Parry 1971: 37-117).</p><p>Since formulaic diction prefers some fixed rhythmical patterns (Parry 1971:
                    8-21), we can ask some questions about the role of both versification and rhythm
                    in oral composition. Why was all of ancient epic poetry, both Greek and Latin,
                    composed in one particular type of meter called hexameter? Does the choice of
                    meter influence the rhythmicity of a text? Why does hexameter, in spite of its
                    relatively restricted possibilities of shaping rhythm, differ so much from one
                    writer to another some (cf. Duckworth 1969: 37-87)? And, last but not least,
                    what possible reasons are there for those wide differences between particular
                    authors?</p><p>It is commonly known that poetry is in general easier to memorize than prose,
                    because rhythm itself tends to facilitate memorization. In a culture without
                    writing, memorization is crucial, and much depends on the quality of oral
                    transmission. In epic poems from an oral culture rhythm is thus likely to be
                    particularly important for both singers and hearers, even though they need not
                    consciously perceive poetic texts as rhythmical to benefit from rhythm as an aid
                    to memory.</p><p>It may then be expected on theoretical grounds that non-oral poems, such as the
                    Latin epic poetry or the Greek hexameter of the Alexandrian age, will be largely
                    non-rhythmical, or at least display weaker rhythm effects than the archaic poems
                    of Homer and Hesiod. Although formulaic diction and other techniques of oral
                    composition are noticeable mostly in Homer’s epics (Parry 1971, Lord 2000, Foley
                    1993, etc.), the later hexameters, both Greek and Latin, also display some
                    features of oral diction (Parry 1971: 24-36). The metrical structure of
                    hexameter might be quite similar: strongly rhythmical in the oldest (or rather,
                    the most archaic) epic poems, and less conspicuous in poems composed in written
                    form a few centuries after Homer. The aim of the present study is to test the
                    hypothesis that the later a given specimen of hexameter is, the less rhythmical
                    it tends to be.</p><p>Because of its nature versification easily lends itself to statistical analysis.
                    A great deal of work has already been done in this field, including studies of
                    Greek and Latin hexameter (Jones &amp; Gray 1972, Duckworth 1969, Foley
                    1993, etc.). However, the main disadvantage of the methods applied in existing
                    research is that they describe a given meter as if it were a set of independent
                    elements, which is actually not true. In each versification system, the specific
                    sequence of elements plays a far more important role in establishing a
                    particular type of rhythm than the relations between those elements regardless
                    their linear order (language "in the mass" vs. language "in the line"; cf.
                    Pawlowski 1999).</p><p>Fortunately, there are a few methods of statistical analysis (both numeric and
                    probabilistic) that study verse by means of an ordered sequence of elements.
                    These methods include, for example, time series modeling, Fourier analysis, the
                    theory of Markov chains and Shannon's theory of information. In the present
                    study, spectral density analysis was used (Gottman 1999, Priestley 1981, etc.).
                    Spectral analysis seems to be a very suitable tool because it provides a
                    cross-section of a given time series: it allows us to detect waves, regularities
                    and cycles which are not otherwise manifest and open to inspection. In the case
                    of a coded poetry sample, the spectrogram shows not only simple repetitions of
                    metrical patterns, but also some subtle rhythmical relations, if any, between
                    distant lines or stanzas.</p><p>To verify the hypothesis of hexameter’s decreasing rhythmicity, 7 samples of
                    Greek and 3 samples of Latin epic poetry were chosen. The specific selection of
                    sample material was as follows: 3 samples from Homeric hexameter (books 18 and
                    22 from the Iliad, book 3 from the Odyssey), 1 sample from Hesiod (Theogony),
                    Apollonius (Argonautica, book 1), Aratos (Phainomena), Nonnos (Dionysiaca, book
                    1), Vergil (Aeneid, book 3), Horace (Ars poetica), and Ovid (Metamorphoses, book
                    1). In each sample, the first 500 lines were coded in such a way that each long
                    syllable was assigned value 1, and each short syllable value 0. Though it is
                    disputed whether ancient verse was purely quantitative or whether it also had
                    some prosodic features (Pawlowski &amp; Eder 2001), the quantity-based
                    nature of Greek and Roman meter was never questioned. It is possible that rhythm
                    was generated not only by quantity, but it is certain that quantity itself
                    played an essential role in ancient meter. Thus, in the coding procedure, all
                    prosodic features were left out except the quantity of syllables (cf. Jones
                    &amp; Gray 1972, Duckworth 1969, Foley 1993, etc.). A binary-coded series
                    was then obtained for each sample, e.g., book 22 of the Iliad begins as a series
                    of values:<lb/> 1110010010010011100100100100111001110010010011...</p><p>The coded samples were analyzed by means of the spectral density function. As
                    might be expected, on each spectogram there appeared a few peaks indicating the
                    existence of several rhythmical waves in the data. However, while the peaks
                    suggesting the existence of 2- and 3-syllable patterns it the text were very
                    similar for all the spectograms and quite obvious, the other peaks showed some
                    large differences between the samples. Perhaps the most surprising was the peak
                    echoing the wave with a 16-syllable period, which could be found in the samples
                    of early Greek poems by Homer, Hesiod, Apollonius, and Aratos. The same peak was
                    far less noticeable in the late Greek hexameter of Nonnos, and totally absent in
                    the samples of Latin writers. Other differences between the spectograms have
                    corroborated the observation: the rhythmical effects of the late poems were, in
                    general, weaker as compared with the rich rhythmical structure of the earliest,
                    orally composed epic poems.</p><p>Although the main hypothesis has been verified, the results also showed some
                    peculiarities. For example, the archaic poems by Homer and Hesiod did not differ
                    significantly from the poems of the Alexandrian age (Apollonius, Aratos), which
                    was rather unexpected. Again, the rhythm of the Latin hexameter turned out to
                    have a different underlying structure than that of all the Greek samples. There
                    are some possible explanations of those facts, such as that the weaker rhythm of
                    the Latin samples may relate to inherent differences between Latin and Greek.
                    More research, both in statistics and in philology, is needed, however, to make
                    such explanations more nuanced and more persuasive.</p></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Duckworth, George E.">George E. Duckworth</name></author><title level="m">Vergil and Classical Hexameter Poetry: A Study in
                                Metrical Variety</title><imprint><pubPlace>Ann Arbor</pubPlace><publisher>University of Michigan Press</publisher><date value="1969">1969</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Foley, John Miles">John Miles Foley</name></author><title level="m">Traditional Oral Epic: "The Odyssey", "Beowulf" and the
                                Serbo-Croatian Return Song</title><imprint><pubPlace>Berkeley</pubPlace><publisher>University of California Press</publisher><date value="1993">1993</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Gottman, John Mordechai">John Mordechai Gottman</name></author><author><name reg="Roy, Anup Kumar">Anup Kumar Roy</name></author><title level="m">Sequential Analysis: A Guide for Behavioral Researchers</title><imprint><pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace><publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher><date value="1990">1990</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Jones, Frank Pierce">Frank Pierce Jones</name></author><author><name reg="Gray, Florence E.">Florence E. Gray</name></author><title level="a">Hexameter Patterns, Statistical Inference, and the
                                Homeric Question: An Analysis of the La Roche Data</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Transactions and Proceedings of the American
                                Philological Association</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">103</biblScope><date value="1972">1972</date><biblScope type="pages">187-209</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Lord, Albert B.">Albert B. Lord</name></author><title level="m">The Singer of Tales</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Mitchell, Stephen">Stephen Mitchell</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Nagy, Gregory">Gregory Nagy</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace><publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher><date value="2000">2000</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Nagy, Gregory">Gregory Nagy</name></author><title level="m">Poetry as Performance: Homer and Beyond</title><imprint><pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace><publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher><date value="1996">1996</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Parry, Milman">Milman Parry</name></author><title level="m">The Making of Homeric Verse: The Collected Papers of
                                Milman Parry</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Parry, Adam">Adam Parry</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace><publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher><date value="1971">1971</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Pawlowski, Adam">Adam Pawlowski</name></author><title level="a">Language in the Line vs. Language in the Mass: On the
                                Efficiency of Sequential Modeling in the Analysis of Rhythm</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Journal of Quantitative Linguistics</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">6.1</biblScope><date value="1999">1999</date><biblScope type="pages">70-77</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Pawlowski, Adam">Adam Pawlowski</name></author><author><name reg="Eder, Maciej">Maciej Eder</name></author><title level="a">Quantity or Stress? Sequential Analysis of Latin
                                Prosody</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Journal of Quantitative Linguistics</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">8.1</biblScope><date value="2001">2001</date><biblScope type="pages">81-97</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Priestly, M. B.">M. B. Priestly</name></author><title level="m">Spectral Analysis and Time Series</title><imprint><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Academic Press</publisher><date value="1981">1981</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>