<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="paper_154_rybicki"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Twelve Hamlets: A Stylometric Analysis of Major Characters' Idiolects in
                    Three English Versions and Nine Translations</title><author><name reg="Rybicki, Jan">Jan Rybicki</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>paper</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>Shakespeare</item><item>Hamlet</item><item>multivariate analysis</item><item>stylometry</item><item>translation</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Jan Rybicki's rtf<date value="2007-03">March
                2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Twelve Hamlets: A Stylometric Analysis of Major Characters' Idiolects  in Three English Versions and Nine Translations"><titlePart type="main">Twelve Hamlets: A Stylometric Analysis of Major Characters'
                    Idiolects in Three English Versions and Nine Translations</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Rybicki, Jan">Jan Rybicki</name><address><addrLine>jrybicki@ap.krakow.pl</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Pedagogical University</titlePart></front><body><div0><p>Following my own comparative stylometric analyses of originals and translations
                    of literary works (Rybicki 2006, 2006a), I have decided to expand the scope of
                    this research to more than just two languages. This has been made possible by
                    the fact that Burrows’s well-established method, first used in his study of Jane
                    Austen (1987), and later developed, evaluated and applied by a number of
                    scholars, including Hoover (2002), can be applied to the most frequent words of
                    any text, also in a language unknown (or less-known) to the researcher. Quite
                    self-evidently, Shakespeare’s <title level="m">Hamlet</title> was chosen for its status of
                    a crucial work of English literature and its numerous translations. The fact
                    that the English <title level="m">Hamlet</title> exists in three primary versions (First
                    Quarto, Second Quarto, First Folio) was also a serious incentive.</p><p>Character parts were extracted from the three above-mentioned originals and nine
                    translations: Czech (by Josef Jirí Kolár, 1855), French (François-Victor Hugo,
                    1863), German (August Wilhelm Schlegel, 1798), Hungarian (János Arany, 1864),
                    Italian (Goffredo Raponi, 1999), Polish (ca. 1875), Portuguese (1966) Russian
                    (Mikhail Morozov, 1954), and Spanish (Leandro Fernandez de Moratin, 1798). The
                    selection of the translations was a compromise between their age (the older the
                    better) and availability in electronic form. The three originals were taken from
                    the collection of exemplary electronic texts on TACT CD (1996). Most frequent
                    words were identified in each version, basing on the rule that a given word was
                    allowed if it appeared in at least 5 of the major character parts: these
                    included Claudius, Gertrude, Hamlet, Horatio, Laertes, Ophelia and Polonius. As
                    a result, the number of the most frequent words included in the analysis varied
                    from 157 (First Quarto, obviously the shortest text) to 282 (the Italian
                    translation). Relative frequencies were then obtained for each character’s use
                    of each of the above-mentioned words; matrices of the relative frequencies were
                    then used to produce multidimensional scaling (MDS) graphs for each version of
                    the play. The same material was also treated with cluster analysis, usually with
                    good agreement with MDS.</p><p>The following observations have been made: <list type="ordered"><item>Graphs for each version of the play always included
                            at least two peripheral data points, invariably including the two female
                            characters, Gertrude and Ophelia;</item><item>Laertes and Horatio frequently joined Gertrude and
                            Ophelia in their peripheral orbits around the data point for Hamlet,
                            usually central in all graphs (with the notable exception of the Czech
                            translation);</item><item>In many translations, the idiolect of Hamlet was
                            more or less similar to those of some other characters: its closeness to
                            Polonius (or Corambis) in the First Quarto lessened in the Second, only
                            to be replaced by a much stronger similarity to Laertes. An even
                            stronger similitude was observed between Hamlet, Polonius and Claudius
                            in the Portuguese translation, or to Claudius alone in the Italian
                            version. In general, Polonius and Claudius were the idiolects most
                            consistently similar to that of the main character.</item><item>The closest similarity of pattern between entire
                            graphs was that between the First Quarto and Schlegel’s German
                            translation (Hamlet and Polonius surrounded by even-spaced peripheral
                            characters);</item><item>The general pattern was also quite similar between
                            the Second Quarto and the Folio (peripheral Gertrudes, Horatios and
                            Ophelias, central Hamlets, other characters in-between); it was also
                            roughly reproduced in the translations by Arany, Moratin and Paszkowski.</item><item>The clearest gender division was observed in the
                            Czech, Hungarian, and Russian translations.</item></list></p><p>This introductory study seems to offer several promising avenues for development.
                    The similarity of pattern between the Second Quarto and the Folio is not
                    surprising; even less so is its above-mentioned reproduction by three
                    translations, since their source material was usually a compilation of the two
                    original versions. On the other hand, Schlegel’s similarity to the First Quarto
                    seems pure coincidence, as the so-called “bad quarto” was discovered more than
                    twenty years after the early German translation. The peripheral position of
                    female characters in all graphs is perhaps the most consistent feature of most
                    of European writing so far analysed with MDS; this effect also travels very well
                    in translation.</p><p>Yet the greatest potential for expanding this study lies in the sheer number of
                        <title level="m">Hamlet</title> translations. In the languages included in this study,
                    they are at least five, and very often more than ten; cultures such as Polish,
                    German, or French, have produced almost twenty <title level="m">Hamlet</title>s each. The inclusion of at
                    least some of these would provide a fuller picture of patterns of stylistic
                    differences between Shakespeare’s fundamental play and its various realisations
                    in other languages.</p></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Burrows, J. F.">J. F. Burrows</name></author><title level="m">Computation into Criticism: A Study of Jane Austen’s
                                Novels and an Experiment in Method</title><imprint><pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace><publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher><date value="1987">1987</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Hoover, David">David Hoover</name></author><title level="a">New Directions in Statistical Stylistics and Authorship
                                Attribution</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2002 Conference Abstracts</title><imprint><pubPlace>Tübingen</pubPlace><publisher>Tübingen University</publisher><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Rybicki, Jan">Jan Rybicki</name></author><title level="a">Burrowing into Translation: Character Idiolects in
                                    Henryk Sienkiewicz's Trilogy and its Two English
                                Translations</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">21.1</biblScope><date value="2006">2006</date><biblScope type="pages">91-103</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Rybicki, Jan">Jan Rybicki</name></author><title level="a">Can I Write like John le Carré?</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Digital Humanities 2006 Conference Abstracts</title><imprint><pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace><publisher>CATI, Université Paris-Sorbonne</publisher><date value="2006">2006a</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>