<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="poster_259_tabata"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>A Statistical Study of Superlatives in Dickens and Smollett: A Case Study in
                    Corpus Stylistics</title><author><name reg="Tabata, Tomoji">Tomoji Tabata</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>poster</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>Dickens</item><item>Smollett</item><item>style</item><item>superlatives</item><item>corpus stylistics</item><item>correspondence analysis</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Tomoji Tabata's pdf <date value="2007-04">April
                2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="A Statistical Study of Superlatives in Dickens and Smollett:                  A Case Study in Corpus Stylistics"><titlePart type="main">A Statistical Study of Superlatives in Dickens and Smollett:
                    A Case Study in Corpus Stylistics</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="">Tomoji Tabata </name><address><addrLine>tabata@lang.osaka-u.ac.jp</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of Osaka</titlePart></front><body><div0><head><label>1.</label> Introduction</head><p>This study gives a quantitative overview of the use of superlatives in Dickens in
                    comparison with Smollett. The focus is laid on the differing distribution of
                    superlatives in the texts written by the two authors. By applying correspondence
                    analysis, this study tries to illustrate how sharply the two authors differ in
                    their uses of superlatives as well as how texts are clustered according to
                    chronology within authorial sets.</p><p>Despite a number of studies on Dickens’ style have noted a tendency for
                    overstatement in his fiction (Brook 1970; Sorensen 1985; Golding 1985; Hori
                    2004, etc.), surprisingly little attention has been paid to superlatives as a
                    whole. Apart from Dickens studies, however, Biber et al. (1999) gives an
                    interesting account of superlatives in four linguistic registers: conversation,
                    fiction, news, and academic prose. According to Biber et al., <emph>—est</emph>
                    superlative adjectives are most frequent in news reportage (c. 1400 times per
                    million words) while “the comparatively low frequency of superlatives in
                    academic writing (c. 800 per million) reflects a general reluctance to make
                    extreme claims” (Biber et al., 521), with fiction showing even lower frequency
                    for the word class (c. 700 per million). </p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head>Table 1: Set of twenty-three texts by Dickens and seven texts by
                        Smollett</head><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_259_tabata_1.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Table 1</figDesc></figure><p>Dickens and Smollett stand in contrast in the frequency of superlative forms. In
                    Dickens’ 23 texts used in this study, the number of tokens for superlatives
                    amounts to 4,960, whereas Smollett employs them 634 times in his seven works. In
                    the normalised frequency scale per million words, the frequency in Dickens is
                    nearly twice as high as in Smollett: 1,049 versus 568.</p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head>Table 2: Summary of descriptive statistics</head><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_259_tabata_2.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Table 2</figDesc></figure><p>With regard to the number of types, 423 different superlative forms are found in
                    total. Among those, a few types are highly frequent such as, <emph>most</emph>,
                        <emph>best</emph>, and <emph>least</emph>, occurring more than one thousand
                    times. Conversely, more than one third of the whole types occur only once. Such
                    hapax legomena include unique words, such as, <emph>superlativest</emph> and
                        <emph>unfortunatest</emph>. </p><p>This study deals with a corpus of texts comprising Dickens’ and Smollett’s major
                    works. Dickens’ set includes fifteen "serial fictions", six "sketches", one
                    "miscellany", and one "history". Smollett’s contains six "fictions" and one
                    "sketch". The total word-tokens in the corpus amount to 5.8 million, with the
                    Dickens component containing 4.7 million tokens and the Smollett component
                    totalling 1.1 million word-tokens. The present project was initiated as a study
                    based on a comprehensive collection, not a sample corpus, of texts by the
                    targeted authors. Therefore, the imbalance in the number of texts as well as
                    tokens is inevitable. However, due attention will be paid in the choice of
                    variables to minimize a potential effect of the differences in the population of
                    the two sets.</p></div0><div0><head><label>2.</label> Quantitative approaches to style/register variation</head><p>Milic (1967) is among the earliest successful specimens of a quantitative
                    description of style. He compared the style of Jonathan Swift with the writings
                    of his contemporaries, with special reference to the relative frequencies of
                    word-classes in the texts and to grammatical features such as seriation and
                    connection. Cluett (1971 &amp; 1976) adopted a similar approach to conduct a
                    diachronic study of prose style across 4 centuries: from 16th to 20th Centuries.
                    Brainerd’s works (1979 &amp; 1980) are ambitious attempts to apply
                    discriminant analysis to the question of genre and chronology in Shakespeare
                    plays. Takefuta’s (1981) approach to text typology, or register variation, is
                    among the first to successfully employ factor/cluster analysis to the lexical
                    differences between registers. His pioneering work, however, is not widely
                    acknowledged because it was written in Japanese.</p><p>Since Burrows (1987) and Biber (1988), it has become popular practice to employ
                    multivariate techniques in quantitative studies of texts. Biber carried out
                    factor analysis (FA) on 67 linguistic features to identify co-occurring
                    linguistic features that account for dimensions of register variation. A series
                    of research based on Biber’s Multi- Feature/Multi-Dimensional approach have been
                    successful in elucidating many interesting aspects of linguistic variation, such
                    as diachronic change of prose style, variation within a single author, and
                    differences between conversational styles in British and American English, to
                    give a few examples (Biber &amp; Finegan 1992; Opas-Hänninen 1996, Watson
                    1997, Conrad &amp; Bibereds. 2001)</p><p>The Biber model is one of the most sophisticated approaches by far. Yet it is not
                    without its critics. Nakamura (1995) raises a major objection. He argues that
                    Biber’s variables are “quite arbitrarily selected with no definite criterion and
                    mixed levels” (1995: 77-86). Further, Sigley (1997) notes that almost half of
                    Biber’s 67 linguistic features are too rare in texts of 2,000 words.</p><p>Burrows (1987), on the other hand, applied a Principal Component Analysis (PCA)
                    to the thirty most common words in the language of Jane Austen. The method
                    demonstrates that differing frequency patterns in these very common words show
                    significant differentiations among Austen’s characters, and that the statistical
                    analysis of literary style may lead not only to a deeper understanding of the
                    novel itself but may also contribute to our deeper appreciation of it. In this
                    use of a PCA, the frequencies of common words are used as variables. The Burrows
                    method seems to have higher replicability and feasibility; since it focuses on
                    common words, most of the variables are frequent enough to produce stable
                    statistical results. In addition, it does not require a multi-layered tagging
                    scheme optimised for Biber’s MF/MD approach.</p><p>A particular strength of the Burrows methodology is in testing cases of disputed
                    authorship and national differences in the English first-person retrospective
                    narrative, known as ‘history’. Among the most successful applications are
                    Burrows (1989, 1992 &amp; 1996), Craig (1999a, b, &amp; c). The Burrows
                    approach or similar methodology has been applied to Bible stylometry. Some
                    scholars like Linmans (1998), Merriam (1998), and Mealand (1999) use
                    Correspondence Analysis (CA) instead of PCA. In the context of text typology,
                    Nakamura (1993) applied CA to the frequency distribution of personal pronouns to
                    visualize association between personal pronouns and 15 text categories in the
                    LOB corpus.</p></div0><div0><head><label>3.</label> Methodology</head><p>The present study is different from the Biber and Burrows models in that it
                    extends the range of variables to include low-frequency words, or rare words, by
                    applying CA in the analysis of superlatives. CA is one of the techniques for
                    data-reduction alongside PCA and FA. CA allows examination of the complex
                    interrelationships between row cases (i.e., texts), interrelationships between
                    column variables (i.e., words), and association between the row cases and column
                    variables graphically in a multi-dimensional space. It computes the row
                    coordinates (word scores) and column coordinates (text scores) in a way that
                    permutes the original data matrix so that the correlation between the word
                    variables and text profiles are maximized. In a permuted data matrix, adverbs
                    with a similar pattern of distribution make the closest neighbours, and so do
                    texts of similar profile. When the row/column scores are projected in
                    multi-dimensional charts, relative distance between variable entries indicates
                    affinity, similarity, association, or otherwise between them. One advantage CA
                    has over PCA and FA is that PCA and FA cannot be computed on a rectangular
                    matrix where the number of columns exceeds the number of rows, a concern of the
                    present study. Yet CA can handle such types of a data table with, for example,
                    the row cases consisting of thirty texts and the column variables consisting of
                    hundreds of words.</p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_259_tabata_3.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Table 3: Frequency matrix for 242 types of superlatives across 30
                        texts: raw frequency scores</figDesc></figure></div0><div0><head><label>4.</label> Results</head><p>Figures 1 and 2 demonstrate a result of CA based on 242 superlative forms across
                    30 texts. The solution given as Dimension 1, the most powerful axis, allows
                    quite straightforward interpretation: the horizontal axis of Figure 1
                    distinguishes between the Dickens and the Smollett sets. It is also interesting
                    that the early Dickensian texts, such as <title type="m">Sketches by
                    Boz</title>, <title type="m">Pickwick Papers</title>, and <title type="m">Nicholas Nickleby</title>, are among the closest to Smollett’s texts along
                    the horizontal axis. </p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_259_tabata_4.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 1: Correspondence Analysis of superlatives in Dickens &amp;
                        Smollett based on 242 types that appear in two or more texts: Text-map
                        showing interrelationships between 30 texts</figDesc></figure><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_259_tabata_5.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 2: Correspondence Analysis of superlatives in Dickens &amp;
                        Smollett based on 242 types that appear in two or more texts: Word-map
                        showing interrelationships between 242 superlatives</figDesc></figure><p>The Dickens corpus is more than four times the size of the Smollett corpus, and
                    the number of types used by Dickens is nearly four times as many as those used
                    by Smollett (see Table 2). It is necessary to ensure that a size factor does not
                    come into play in the outcome of analysis. Figures 3 and 4 are derived from 105
                    superlatives common to both authors. Despite the decrease in the number of
                    variables from 242 to 105, the configuration of texts and words is remarkably
                    similar to that based on 242 items. Of further interest is that, in each of the
                    two authors’ sets, early works tend to have lower scores with later works
                    scoring higher along Dimension 2.</p><p>Such result seems to illustrate how the authorial difference and chronology are
                    reflected in the frequency pattern of superlatives in the texts written by
                    Dickens and Smollett. This study might suggest the effectiveness of the
                    stylo-statistical approach based on correspondence analysis of texts.</p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_259_tabata_6.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 3: Correspondence Analysis of superlatives in Dickens &amp;
                        Smollett based on the 105 types common to both authors: Text-map showing
                        interrelationships between 30 texts</figDesc></figure><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_259_tabata_7.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 4: Correspondence Analysis of superlatives in Dickens &amp;
                        Smollett based on the 105 types common to both authors: Word-map showing
                        interrelationships among  105 superlatives</figDesc></figure></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Biber, Douglas">Douglas Biber</name></author><title level="m">Variation Across Speech and Writing</title><imprint><pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace><publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher><date value="1988">1988</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Biber, Douglas">Douglas Biber</name></author><author><name reg="Finegan, Edward">Edward Finegan</name></author><title level="a">The Linguistic Evolution of Five Written and
                                Speech-Based English Genres from the 17th to the 20th
                            Centuries</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">History of Englishes: New Methods and Interpretation in
                                Historical Linguistics</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Rissanen, Matti">Matti Rissanen</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>Mouton de Gruyter</publisher><date value="1992">1992</date><biblScope type="pages">668–704</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Biber, Douglas">Douglas Biber</name></author><author><name reg="Johansson, Stig">Stig Johansson</name></author><author><name reg="Leech, Geoffrey">Geoffrey Leech</name></author><author><name reg="Conrad, Susan">Susan Conrad</name></author><author><name reg="Finegan, Edward">Edward Finegan</name></author><title level="m">Longman Grammar of Spoken and Written English</title><imprint><pubPlace>Harlow</pubPlace><publisher>Pearson Education Ltd</publisher><date value="1999">1999</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Brainerd, Barron">Barron Brainerd</name></author><title level="a">Pronouns and Genre in Shakespeare’s Drama</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">13.1</biblScope><date value="1999">1999</date><biblScope type="pages">3-16</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Brainerd, Barron">Barron Brainerd</name></author><title level="a">The Chronology of Shakespeare’s Plays: A Statistical
                                Study</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">14.4</biblScope><date value="1980">1980</date><biblScope type="pages">221-230</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Brook, G. L.">G. L. Brook</name></author><title level="m">The Language of Dickens</title><imprint><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Andre Deutsch</publisher><date value="1970">1970</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Burrows, John F.">John F. Burrows</name></author><title level="m">Computation into Criticism: A Study of Jane Austen’s
                                Novels and an Experiment in Method</title><imprint><pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace><publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher><date value="1987">1987</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Burrows, John F.">John F. Burrows</name></author><title level="a">“A Vision” as a Revision?</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Eighteenth-Century Studies</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">22.4</biblScope><date value="1989">1989</date><biblScope type="551-65"/></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Burrows, John F.">John F. Burrows</name></author><title level="a">Computers and the Study of Literature</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Computers and Written Texts</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Butler, Christopher S.">Christopher S. Butler</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace><publisher>Blackwell</publisher><date value="1992">1992</date><biblScope type="pages">167-204</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Burrows, John F.">John F. Burrows</name></author><title level="a">Tiptoeing into the Infinite: Testing for Evidence of
                                National Differences in the Language of English Narrative</title></analytic><monogr><title level="s">Research in Humanities Computing 4: Selected Papers
                                from the ALLC/ACH Conference, Christ Church, Oxford, April 1992</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Hockey, Susan">Susan Hockey</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Ide, Nancy">Nancy Ide</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher><date value="1996">1996</date><biblScope type="pages">1-33</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Cluett, Robert">Robert Cluett</name></author><title level="a">Style, Precept, Personality: A Test Case (Thomas Sprat,
                                1635-1713)</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">5.5</biblScope><date value="1971">1971</date><biblScope>257–274</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Cluett, Robert">Robert Cluett</name></author><title level="m">Prose Style and Critical Reading</title><imprint><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>Teachers College Press</publisher><date value="1976">1976</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><title level="m">Variation in English: Multi-Dimensional Studies</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Conrad, Susan">Susan Conrad</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Biber, Douglas">Douglas Biber</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Harlow</pubPlace><publisher>Pearson Education Ltd</publisher><date value="2001">2001</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Craig, D. H.">D. H. Craig</name></author><title level="a">Jonsonian Chronology and the Styles of A Tale of a
                            Tub</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Re-Presenting Ben Jonson: Text, History, Performance</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Butler, Martin">Martin Butler</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Macmillan</publisher><date value="1999">1999a</date><biblScope type="pages">210-32</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Craig, D. H.">D. H. Craig</name></author><title level="a">Authorial Attribution and Computational Stylistics: If
                                You Can Tell Authors Apart, Have You Learned Anything About
                            Them?</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">14.1</biblScope><date value="1999">1999b</date><biblScope type="pages">103-13</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Craig, D. H.">D. H. Craig</name></author><title level="a">Contrast and Change in the Idiolects of Ben Jonson
                                Characters</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">33.3</biblScope><date value="1999">1999c</date><biblScope type="pages">221-40</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Hori, Masahiro ">Masahiro Hori</name></author><title level="a">Collocational Patterns of Intensive Adverbs in
                                Dickens: A Tentative Approach</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">English Corpus Studies</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">6</biblScope><date value="1999">1999</date><biblScope type="pages">51–65</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Hori, Masahiro">Masahiro Hori</name></author><title level="a">Collocational Patterns of –ly Manner Adverbs in
                            Dickens</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">English Corpus Linguistics in Japan</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Saito, Toshio">Toshio Saito</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Nakamura, Junsaku">Junsaku Nakamura</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Yamazaki, Shunji">Shunji Yamazaki</name></editor><imprint><biblScope type="vol">15</biblScope><date value="2002">2002</date><biblScope type="pages">149–163</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Hori, Masahiro">Masahiro Hori</name></author><title level="m">Investigating Dickens’ Style: A Collocational Analysis</title><imprint><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>Palgrave Macmillan</publisher><date value="2004">2004</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Linmans, A. J. M.">A. J. M. Linmans</name></author><title level="a">Correspondence Analysis of the Synoptic Gospels</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">13.1</biblScope><date value="1998">1998</date><biblScope type="pages">1-13</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Mealand, D. L.">D. L. Mealand</name></author><title level="a">Style, Genre, and Authorship in Acts, the Septuagint,
                                and Hellenistic Historians</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">14.4</biblScope><date value="1999">1999</date><biblScope type="pages">479–505</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Merriam, Thomas">Thomad Merriam</name></author><title level="a">Heterogeneous Authorship in Early Shakespeare and the
                                Problem of Henry V</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">13.1</biblScope><date value="1998">1998</date><biblScope type="pages">15–28</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Milic, Louis Tonko">:Louis Tonko Milic</name></author><title level="m">A Quantitative Approach to the Style of Jonathan Swift</title><imprint><pubPlace>The Hague</pubPlace><publisher>Mouton</publisher><date value="1967">1967</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Nakamura, Junsaku">Junsaku Nakamura</name></author><title level="a">Statistical Methods and Large Corpora: A New Tool for
                                Describing Text Types</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Text and Technology: In Honour of John Sinclair</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Baker, Mona">Mona Baker</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Francis, Gill">Gill Francis </name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Tognini-Bonelli, Elena">Elena Tognini-Bonelli </name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace><publisher>John Benjamins</publisher><date value="1993">1993</date><biblScope type="pages">293–312</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Nakamura, Junsaku">Junsaku Nakamura</name></author><title level="a">Text Typology and Corpus: A Critical Review of Biber’s
                                Methodology</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">English Corpus Studies</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">2</biblScope><date value="1995">1995</date><biblScope type="pages">75-90</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Opas-Hänninen, Lisa Lena"> Lisa Lena
                                Opas-Hänninen</name></author><title level="a">A Multi-Dimensional Analysis of Style in Samuel
                                Beckett’s Prose Works</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Research in Humanities Computing 4: Selected Papers
                                from the ALLC/ACH Conference, Christ Church, Oxford, April 1992 </title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Hockey, Susan">Susan Hockey</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Ide, Nancy">Nacny Ide</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher><date value="1996">1996</date><biblScope type="pages">81-114</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Sigley, Robert">Robert Sigley</name></author><title level="a">Text Categories and Where You Can Stick Them: A Crude
                                Formality Index</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">International Journal of Corpus Linguistics</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">2.2</biblScope><date value="1997">1997</date><biblScope type="pages">199–237</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Sørensen, Knud">Knud Sørensen</name></author><title level="m">Charles Dickens: Linguistic Innovator</title><imprint><pubPlace>Aarhus</pubPlace><publisher>Aarhus Universitet</publisher><date value="1985">1985</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Takefuta, Y.">Y. Takefuta</name></author><title level="m">Kompyuta no mita gendai eigo: bokyaburari no kagaku
                                [The Computer Analysis of the Contemporary English Language: A
                                Quantitative Study of Vocabulary]</title><imprint><pubPlace>Tokyo</pubPlace><publisher>Educa</publisher><date value="1981">1981</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Watson, Greg">Greg Watson</name></author><title level="m">Doin' Mudrooroo: Elements of Style and Involvement in
                                the Early Prose Fiction of Mudrooroo</title><title level="s">Publications in the Humanities, No 19 </title><imprint><pubPlace>Joensuu, FI:</pubPlace><publisher>University of Joensuu</publisher><date value="1997">1997</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>