<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="paper_148_olsen"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Mining Eighteenth Century Ontologies: Machine Learning and Knowledge
                    Classification in the <emph>Encyclopédie</emph></title><author><name reg="Horton, Russell">Rusell Horton</name></author><author><name reg="Morrissey, Robert">Robert Morrissey</name></author><author><name reg="Olsen, Mark">Mark Olsen</name></author><author><name reg="Roe, Glenn">Glenn Roe</name></author><author><name reg="Voyer, Robert">Robert Voyer</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>paper</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item/><item/><item/></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Mark Olsen's HTML <date value="2007-05">May
                2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Mining Eighteenth Century Ontologies: Machine Learning and Knowledge                 Classification in the Encyclopédie"><titlePart type="main">Mining Eighteenth Century Ontologies: Machine Learning and
                    Knowledge Classification in the <emph>Encyclopédie</emph></titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Horton, Russell">Russell Horton</name><address><addrLine>russ@diderot.uchicago.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Digital Library Development Center<lb/>University of Chicago</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Morrissey, Robert">Robert Morrissey</name><address><addrLine/></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">ARTFL Project<lb/>University of Chicago</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Olsen, Mark">Mark Olsen</name><address><addrLine>mark@barkov.uchicago.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">ARTFL Project<lb/>University of Chicago</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Roe, Glenn">Glenn Roe</name><address><addrLine>glenn@diderot.uchicago.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">ARTFL Project<lb/>University of Chicago</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Voyer, Robert">Robert Voyer</name><address><addrLine>rlvoyer@diderot.uchicago.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">ARTFL Project<lb/>University of Chicago</titlePart></front><body><div0><p>One of the crowning achievements of the 18th century Enlightenment was the <title level="m">Encyclopédie ou Dictionnaire raisonné des sciences, des arts et
                  des métiers, par une Société de Gens de lettres</title>, edited by Diderot
                    and d'Alembert. Published in Paris between 1751 and 1772, in 17 volumes of text
                    and 11 volumes of plates, it contains 74,000 articles written by more than 140
                        contributors.<note n="1">The ARTFL implementation of the Encyclopédie is
                        discussed in Robert Morrissey, Jack Iverson and Mark Olsen, "Présentation:
                        L'Encyclopédie Electronique" Robert Morrissey and Philippe Roger, eds.,
                            <title level="m"> L'Encyclopédie de réseau au livre et du livre au
                            réseau</title>, (Paris: Champion, 2001): 17-27, and Leonid Andreev, Jack
                        Iverson and Mark Olsen, "Re-engineering a War Machine: ARTFL's Encyclopédie"
                            <title level="j"> Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title> 14.1
                        (1999): 11-28.</note>The <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title> was a massive
                    reference work for the arts and sciences, as well as a <emph>machine de
                    guerre</emph> which served to propagate Enlightenment ideas. The impact of the
                        <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title> was enormous. Through its attempt to
                    classify learning and to open all domains of human activity to its readers, the
                        <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title> gave expression to many of the most
                    important intellectual and social developments of its time.</p><p>The scale and ambition of the <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title> inspired its
                    editors to adopt three distinct modes of organization which, taken together,
                    Diderot described as encyclopedic: dictionary, hierarchical classification, and
                    the <emph>renvois</emph> (cross-references). The interaction of these three
                    modes has led modern commentators to describe the <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title> as an "ancestor of hypertext" and to depict Diderot as
                    "l'internaute d'hier"<note n="2">Eric Brian, "L'ancêtre de l'hypertexte", <title level="j">Les Cahiers de Science et Vie</title> 47 (Oct. 1998):
                    28-38.</note>. D'Alembert underscores the importance of the organization of
                    knowledge in the <emph>Discours Préliminaire</emph>: <cit rend="block"><q> As an <emph>Encyclopedia</emph>, it is to set forth the <emph rend="bold">order</emph> and <emph rend="bold">connection</emph> of
                            the parts of human knowledge. As a <emph>Reasoned Dictionary of the
                                Sciences, Arts, and Trades</emph>, it is to contain the general
                            principles that form the basis of each science and each art ... and the
                            most essential facts that make up the body and substance of each.<note n="3">English translation cited in Nelly Hoyt and Thomas Cassier's
                                "Introduction" to <emph>Encyclopedia</emph> (1965): xxiii (our
                                emphasis).</note></q></cit> Of the three modes of organization, the dictionary mode (organization of
                    entries in alphabetical order) is certainly the simplest and the most arbitrary.
                    The second mode of organization is classification, wherein each dictionary entry
                    is assigned to a "class of knowledge," placing it within the "order" of human
                    understanding, as depicted in the <emph>Système Figuré des connaissances
                        humaines</emph>. Modeled after Bacon's classification of knowledge and
                    Enlightenment theories of epistemology, all understanding is founded upon
                    memory, reason, or imagination, with numerous categories and sub-categories
                    branching out from these three faculties.<note n="4">For various representations
                        of the Système Figuré and the Editors' description, see <xptr to="http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/efts/ARTFL/projects/encyc/texts/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/> and <xptr to="http://artfl.uchicago.edu/cactus/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>.</note> However, simply placing an entry into this hierarchy of knowledge was
                    insufficient to indicate the interconnections of knowledge. Thus, Diderot
                    created an extensive system of renvois, the third mode of organization,
                    providing a lattice of interconnections between individual leaves of the tree as
                    well as between classes of knowledge.<note n="5">Blanchard and Olsen examined
                        the structure of the <emph>renvois</emph> generating a "mappemonde" of the
                        cross-references and node level classes of knowledge. See Gilles Blanchard
                        and Mark Olsen, "Le système de renvois dans l'<emph>Encyclopédie</emph>: une
                        cartographie de la structure des connaissances au XVIIIème siècle", <title level="j"> Recherches sur Diderot et sur l'Encyclopédie</title> 31-32
                        (April 2002): 45-70.</note></p><p>The central role of the classification system in the intellectual objectives of
                    the <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title> editors is indicated by the extent to
                    which it has been discussed and debated by both contemporaneous scholars and
                    later researchers. The editors were remarkably diligent in assigning classes of
                    knowledge to each article and sub-article. Of the 73,840 main and sub articles,
                    55,227 were assigned classes of knowledge. The editors were, however, somewhat
                    less diligent in maintaining a precisely controlled list. Thus the
                    classifications as found in the text are an amalgam of abbreviations,
                    conflations, and even entries that are not found on the <emph>Système
                    Figuré</emph>. We have recently completed orthographic normalization of the
                    classes of knowledge assigned to each article,<note n="6">This project was
                        accomplished in collaboration with Professor Dena Goodman at the University
                        of Michigan.</note>" resulting in some 54,289 articles with 2,600 normalized
                    classes of knowledge. The twenty most frequent classifications by number of
                    articles are:</p><lg><l>5513 Géographie</l><l>4794 Géographie moderne</l><l>3084 Géographie ancienne</l><l>2396 Jurisprudence</l><l>2304 Grammaire</l><l>1894 Marine</l><l>1483 Commerce</l><l>1277 Histoire naturelle. Botanique</l><l>1194 Histoire moderne</l><l>1115 Mythologie</l><l>1069 Histoire naturelle</l><l>889 Histoire ancienne</l><l>796 Medecine</l><l>730 Architecture</l><l>689 Jardinage</l><l>682 Littérature</l><l>627 Maréchallerie</l><l>614 Botanique</l><l>558 Histoire ecclésiastique</l><l>517 Théologie</l></lg><p>Like the <emph>Système Figuré</emph>, these classifications are a reflection of
                    how knowledge was ordered and classified in the 18th century. Given the
                    assumptions that ontologies are historically contingent and that the <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title> is by far the most consistent and coherent
                    representation of the structure of 18th century knowledge in French, this paper
                    reports the results of our current experiments using machine learning and data
                    mining techniques to understand and exploit this unique resource. Our initial
                    objectives are three-fold. First, we plan to examine the relationship of the
                    classifications to the content of the articles using machine learning techniques
                    to identify feature sets that characterize classes of knowledge in the 55,000
                    articles classified by the editors of the <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title>.
                    Secondly, we will apply these feature sets to the 19,500 articles for which we
                    do not have a class of knowledge and evaluate the accuracy of classification by
                    randomly selecting articles with known authors which scholars will then inspect.
                    Most contributors to the <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title> worked on fairly
                    specific domains -- Rousseau contributed exclusively on music, for example -- so
                    we can use authorship as one control for judging the accuracy of classification.
                    Similarly, the cross-references will also serve as an evaluation control, since
                    50% of the <emph>renvois</emph> link to articles within the same class of
                    knowledge. Finally, we plan to apply these feature sets to the unclassified
                    "plate legends" in an effort to determine accuracy by examining the degree to
                    which classification of the plate legends reflects the relationship of
                    particular plate legends to particular articles.</p><p>For our initial experiments, we have extracted the text from all articles that
                    are more than 100 words in length, and which are categorized within one of the
                    50 most frequent normalized classifications. Explicit markers of class of
                    knowledge, present at the beginnings of these articles, were removed to ensure
                    that they do not provide facile criteria for classification. The texts are
                    tokenized and lemmatized<note n="7"><xptr to="http://www.ims.uni-stuttgart.de/projekte/corplex/TreeTagger/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note>, and frequencies of words and lemmas are computed both globally and for
                    each article. Words and lemmas with more than 100 occurrences in the entire
                        <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title> were used as attributes, and vectors
                    for each article were generated from the number of occurrences of each attribute
                    in that article.</p><p>We are using the SMO implementation of a support vector machine in the Weka<note n="8">Ian H. Witten and Eibe Frank, <title level="m"> Data Mining: Practical
                            Machine Learning Tools and Techniques</title> 2nd ed. (Morgan Kaufmann,
                        2005) and <xptr to="http://www.cs.waikato.ac.nz/ml/weka/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note> data mining engine for initial experimentation on
                    smaller data samples, and an SVM-Light<note n="9">SVM-Light: <xptr to="http://svmlight.joachims.org/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/> See T.
                        Joachims, "Making large-Scale SVM Learning Practical", <title level="m">
                            Advances in Kernel Methods - Support Vector Learning</title>, B.
                        Schölkopf and C. Burges and A. Smola eds. (MIT-Press, 1999). Note that we
                        are using a parallel implementation. See <xptr to="http://www.dm.unife.it/gpdt/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>, G.
                        Zanghirati, L. Zanni, "A Parallel Solver for Large Quadratic Programs in
                        Training Support Vector Machines", <title level="j"> Parallel
                        Computing</title> 29 (2003): 535-551 and L. Zanni, T. Serafini, G.
                        Zanghirati, "Parallel Software for Training Large Scale Support Vector
                        Machines on Multiprocessor Systems", <title level="j"> JMLR</title> 7 (July
                        2006): 1467-1492.</note> classifier for larger datasets. While support
                    vector learning algorithms are very effective for classification problems<note n="10">S. Dumais, et. al., "Inductive learning algorithms and
                        representations for text categorization", <title level="m"> CIKM-98</title>,
                        1998.</note>, we are also evaluating several other data metrics and machine
                    learning techniques, including information gain statistics and J48 decision tree
                    classification as implemented in Weka, to examine the the most salient features
                    that are used in the classification process and to test the effectiveness of
                    various feature set selections.<note n="11">See the discussion conformity and
                        uniformity in Chih-Ming Chen, et. al. "A Hierarchical Neural Network
                        Document Classifier with Linguistic Feature Selection" <title level="j">
                            Applied Intelligence</title> 3 (December 2005).</note></p><p>Results from preliminary experimentation indicate that SVM classifiers applied to
                    the articles of the <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title> are very effective at
                    distinguishing articles from different classes. We examined 936 unlemmatized
                    articles in our sample dataset belonging to the classes <emph>Medecine</emph>
                    (499) and <emph>Mythologie</emph> (437). The Weka SMO classifier using default
                    options with 10-fold cross-validation correctly recognized 98.29% of the
                    articles (920/936). Under the same parameters, the Weka J48 tree classifier
                    achieved slightly lower performance (91.66% accuracy). The decision tree showed
                    a clear split on medical content words, such as <emph>maladie</emph>,
                        <emph>humeurs</emph>, <emph>inflammation</emph>, and so on. Such strong
                    performance may be due to the fact that one would not expect to find similar
                    vocabularies in articles dealing with medicine and mythology. We achieved
                    similar performance by classifying 2,448 articles equally divided between modern
                    and ancient geography. The SMO training achieved 100% accuracy with 92.2%
                    accuracy on cross-validation. Inspection of the most important features in both
                    J48 tree and InfoGain measures shows a strong preference for classical authors
                    (Pline, Ptolomée) and places (Gaule, Thrace), and the strings "l", "lib" and
                    "liv", which correspond to citations of classical authors (e.g. Pline, l. IV. c.
                        xvj.).<note n="12">We checked these using the PhiloLogic build of the <title level="m"> Encyclopédie</title> (<xptr to="http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/efts/ARTFL/projects/encyc/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>), suggesting the importance of checking text mining
                        results with full text analysis systems.</note> Distance and location terms
                        (<emph>lieues</emph>, <emph>long</emph>., <emph>latit</emph>.) are strongly
                    correlated with modern geography. Furthermore, the function words
                    "<emph>selon</emph>" and "<emph>dit</emph>", which are far more prevalent in
                    ancient geography articles as the authors were citing classical descriptions,
                    are given high InfoGain scores. </p><p>We anticipate assigning classes of knowledge to articles that were not originally
                    classified by the editors iteratively by comparing all unknown articles to
                    specific classes of knowledge rather than trying to classify all unknown
                    articles <emph>en masse</emph>. To test this approach, we assembled two sets of
                    articles each containing 1,209 instances. The first set contained articles
                    categorized by the editors as belonging to ancient geography, while the second
                    set was constituted by selecting, for each article in the first set, an article
                    as close as possible in length but belonging to a different class of knowledge.
                    Using SMO training, we achieved 97.8% accuracy with standard 10-fold
                    cross-validation. Again, the most heavily weighted features were terms denoting
                    classical authors and place names, along with a greater preponderance of more
                    general geographic terms, comporting nicely with a reasonable human's intuitive
                    understanding of what makes a document on ancient geography distinct from
                    another documents. We further validated our results by running another
                    experiment identical to the first except that each article was randomly labeled
                    as either ancient geography or not ancient geography, irrespective of its true
                    classification. The principle of Random Falsifiability states that if random
                    labels can be learned with the same ease (for SVM, 'ease' can be defined as
                    proportion of support vectors required <note n="13">A. Ruiz and P.E.
                        López-de-Teruel, "Random Falsifiability and Support Vector Machines"
                        (<xptr to="http://learn98.tsc.uc3m.es/~learn98/papers/abstracts/paper013/abstract.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>).</note>)
                    as true class labels, the method must be rejected as unreliable. After 10-fold
                    cross-validation, SMO achieved a mere 50.2895% accuracy on the classification,
                    barely surpassing random chance. That our method cannot learn the random labels
                    at all suggests that our success in discrimination is in fact based on inherent
                    differences between the two classes and not merely a greedy model's exploitation
                    of arbitrary patterns in the data distribution.</p><p>The SMO model derived from comparing ancient geography to a random selection of
                    articles in other classes allows us to test classification on a set of
                    unclassified articles. To do this, we assembled 5,000 randomly selected articles
                    containing more than 100 words for which classification was unknown and with
                    attributed authorship. We then applied the ancient geography SMO model to this
                    set in an effort to identify articles pertaining to this category. The recall of
                    this experiment was far too high. In the future we intend to implement a
                    classifier that reports a numeric score rather than a simple binary
                    categorization. There were, however, within the results a number of correctly
                    classified articles such as the river <emph>ASOPE</emph> and the articles
                        <emph>GARAMANTES</emph>and <emph>Ionique Transmigration</emph>. Many of the
                    misclassified articles, such as <emph>ADONIES, ou FESTES ADONIENNES</emph> and
                        <emph>Danse astronomique</emph>, pertain to classical history, mythology and
                    other related fields. In addition to implementing a ranking classifier, we will
                    also investigate moving up the tree of knowledge in order to use a coarser
                    classification scheme; e.g., rather than remaining at the leaves of "ancient"
                    and "modern" geography, we would use the branch of geography itself as a general
                    category. </p><p>The impressive performance of machine learning algorithms suggests that the
                    editors of the <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title> were quite judicious in
                    their assignments of classifications, a claim which will be tested further in
                    the full paper. Examination of the features most effective in classification
                    tasks will establish a sort of thesaurus which will give scholars a better
                    understanding of the organization of knowledge during the Englightenment.
                    Furthermore, we believe that the creation of well-verified training sets on this
                    large corpus will allow us to test the degree to which we may profitably apply
                    what the systems have learned to articles and plate legends which were not
                    classified at the time, using the contemporary ontologies. If this series of
                    experiments is successful, we would anticipate using the training sets from the
                    classifications in the <title level="m">Encyclopédie</title> to attempt to
                    classify passages in other 18th century French documents.</p></div0></body></text></TEI.2>