<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="poster_215_vanelsacker"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Complete Works of W.F. Hermans. Using Automatic Text
                    Comparison and XML for a Voluminous Edition</title><author><name reg="Van Elsacker, Bert">Bert Van Elsacker</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Field, Hana S.">Hana S. Field</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>poster</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>critical edition</item><item>variants</item><item>automated text comparison</item><item>web publication</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list><item>HSF: Created from Bert Van Elsacker's text<date value="2007-04">April
                    2007</date></item><item>SAS: Revised  <date value="2007-05">May 2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="The Complete Works of W.F. Hermans. Using Automatic Text Comparison and XML for a Voluminous Edition"><titlePart type="main">The Complete Works of W.F. Hermans. Using Automatic Text
                    Comparison and XML for a Voluminous Edition</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Van Elsacker, Bert">Bert Van Elsacker</name><address><addrLine>bertve@gmail.com</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Huygens Instituut<lb/>The Netherlands</titlePart></front><body><div0><head>Introduction</head><p>In November 2005 the first volume of the Volledige Werken (Complete Works) of
                    Willem Frederik Hermans appeared. This publication marked the official beginning
                    of the largest Dutch edition project ever undertaken in the field of modern
                    literature. There are two sides to the edition: a publication in print, aimed at
                    a general public, and a web site, where the reader can find the editorial
                    principles, a description of the textual history and listings of editorial
                    emendations. The project is exceptional not only because of its size, but also
                    because right from the beginning it has been set up as an experimental digital
                    research project.</p><p>The initial impetus came from the need for automated text comparison. An academic
                    edition cannot do without careful comparison of the different versions of a
                    text. In the case of Hermans, about one third of all print editions has been
                    revised, which brings the volume of research material to about 50,000 pages.
                    This implied manual collation was not feasible. We will give an overview of the
                    procedure to transform a large amount of print material into accurate digital
                    text, demonstrate a system which outputs XML-TEI-encoded collation results and
                    show an example of the possible uses of these documents.</p></div0><div0><head>The edition</head><p>Willem Frederik Hermans is widely regarded as the most important Dutch author of
                    the second half of the twentieth century. In addition to novels, Hermans
                    (1921-1995) wrote short stories, plays, poetry and essays; he also translated
                    several texts, including Ludwig Wittgenstein’s Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus.
                    His work is receiving more and more international attention; over the past few
                    years several novels have been translated into German, French and English.
                    Beyond Sleep (Nooit meer slapen) was hailed in the English press as a forgotten
                    masterpiece of post-war European literature, or in the words of the Times ‘a
                    welcome if belated introduction to an original and challenging voice in modern
                    European literature’. Hermans was a very prolific author. The edition will
                    consist of a total of 24 volumes, each with an average of about 800 pages. The
                    Huygens Institute (a research institute within the Royal Netherlands Academy of
                    Arts and Sciences) is responsible for the preparation of a reliable edition text
                    in accordance to scholarly standards. For each work, the last version Hermans
                    authorised is the point of departure for the critical edition. The editors
                    review this version in the light of the results of archival research and of a
                    comparison with selected other versions of the text.</p></div0><div0><head>Automatic text comparison</head><p>Traditionally the meticulous comparison of selected versions of a text has been
                    one of the most important tasks of an editor. Until a few decades ago manual
                    collation – which is extremely time-consuming – was the only possibility.
                    However, in computer science theoretical and practical research into automated
                    text comparison has been taking place since the 1970s. In computer science, the
                    general task of "text comparison" has to be expressed as a formal procedure in
                    order to make the development of an algorithm possible. More precisely, "text
                    comparison" has been understood as a procedure which results in a list of
                    changes between two versions of a text. The application of all changes to
                    version A transforms version A into version B. The algorithm should try to keep
                    the list as short as possible. This approach has led to a basic algorithm by
                    Eugene Myers, on which some variations have been developed, and various
                    implementations, of which the Unix/Linux tool ‘diff’ is the most widely used.
                    Source code implementing this algorithm is readily available for all major
                    programming languages.</p><p>Somewhat apart from these developments in computer science, in the world of
                    scholarly editing there have also been initiatives to use computers for text
                    comparison and, by extension, for the production of editions. The best-known
                    examples are Peter Robinson’s program Collate and Wilhelm Ott’s TUSTEP. Collate
                    is only available for the Macintosh Classic platform, an operating system which
                    has now been replaced by OS X. The program is particularly suitable for older
                    texts which have been divided into relatively short passages beforehand and in
                    which there are not too many long or complex variants. The algorithm used to
                    extract variants remains undocumented. Mr. Robinson has announced a successor to
                    Collate called EDITION. TUSTEP is actually a comprehensive environment for
                    textual research and the production of editions. It is a rather complex
                    instrument to work with and is more something like a programming language in
                    itself. Another impediment is the absence of a graphical user interface (GUI).
                    Recently, another interesting application, called Juxta, has become available.
                    Unfortunately, for now the program lacks the option to export the collation
                    results. According to the project web site, this will change with the next
                    release later this year.</p><p>On the one hand automatic text comparison has great advantages: the comparison is
                    based on a formally defined algorithm, free of errors and in principle
                    reproducible by others. Moreover, the use of computers saves a huge amount of
                    time, which may be of crucial importance as often resources are lacking to
                    collate texts manually. On the other hand, there is no ready-made solution for
                    the average user; whichever option is chosen, some extra training of the
                    prospective user is necessary, and experience with scripting will probably come
                    in handy. Of course this learning process also takes time and energy. For small
                    projects the effort may outweigh the advantages, but considering the size of the
                    Hermans project, in this case the investment did seem worthwhile. To date we
                    have made extensive use of Collate and software tools such as diff.</p><p>Automatic collation requires accurate digital sources. For a scholarly edition,
                    OCR-results aren't good enough. A checking system is necessary. Moreover, some
                    presentational markup like quotes, the use of bold, italic etc., and expressive
                    white space has to be captured as semantic markup, while other presentational
                    features (page width, fonts used...) have no importance, in any case for the
                    Hermans edition, and can be quietly disregarded. So a phase of checking and
                    automatic encoding before the actual collation is required. We will discuss this
                    operation in more detail in our poster presentation.</p></div0><div0><head>XML-encoded collation results</head><p>The result of these preparations are reliable and detailed overviews of all the
                    differences between sometimes a dozen versions of a text, encoded as a base text
                    with in-line apparatus conforming to the TEI Guidelines. This means that a
                    complex text history can be examined down to the tiniest detail in a manageable
                    way. The use of XML enables the editor to observe patterns in variants, to
                    categorize findings, and to examine them in greater detail. Due to systematic
                    encoding of the material the accumulated data can be searched accurately and
                    checked for correlations, and working hypotheses can be continually tested (for
                    example by using XML search languages such as XPath and XQuery) and if necessary
                    modified.</p><p>Currently, we are working on ways to present the multiple versions of the text
                    and the conclusions reached in research in a dynamic way, partly on the basis of
                    the digital research documentation and the findings of the analysis of De tranen
                    der acacia’s (a major novel which appeared in the first volume). During the
                    poster session, we will display the short story ‘Paranoia’. The digital
                    presentation of this story contains the reading text of the Hermans edition and
                    all the text versions which were of importance for the editorial research. We
                    intend to place a short introductory section before the full-text documentation
                    in which some important revisions in the short story are discussed, as a
                    reader’s guide. For example, in the version of this story in the first
                    publication in book form in 1953 Hermans puts more emphasis on the theme of the
                    housing shortage, which was a key concern in the Netherlands after the war,
                    especially in Amsterdam, where the story is set. Due to adjustments in substance
                    and narrative, the events in the book version of ‘Paranoia’ are described more
                    from the perspective of the character Cleever than in the magazine publication
                    of 1948, a significant revision in a story about someone who suffers from
                    persecution mania.</p><p>In the digital publication we will integrate observations and analyses into the
                    texts to which they refer, as a form of empirical evidence. Relevant text
                    passages will therefore be tagged in the online presentation so that they can be
                    seen separately and in context. We are also examining other presentation
                    options. There are analyses conceivable, such as a narratological study of
                    narrative structure, which in the form of hypertext can serve as a point of
                    access or a guide to Hermans’s work. Ideally, in future digital text
                    presentations text and research will constitute an integrated collection of data
                    which can constantly be consulted, modified and expanded. Or as Hermans himself
                    once put it: ‘...a collection, an enormous accumulation of movements and
                ideas.’</p></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Myers, Eugene W.">Eugene W. Myers</name></author><title level="a">An O(ND) Difference Algorithm and Its
                            Variations</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Algorithmica</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">1.2</biblScope><biblScope type="pages">251-266</biblScope><date value="1986">1986</date><biblScope>available online</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Ott, Wilhelm">Wilhelm Ott</name></author><title level="a">Strategies and Tools for Textual Scholarship: The
                                Tübingen System of Text Processing Programs (TUSTEP)</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing </title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">15.1</biblScope><biblScope type="pages">93-108</biblScope><date value="2000">2000</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Robinson, Peter">Peter Robinson</name></author><title level="m">Collate 2: A User Guide</title><imprint><pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace><publisher>The Computers and Variant Texts Project</publisher><date value="1994">1994</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><title level="m" type="WWW document"><name reg="Juxta">Juxta</name></title><imprint/></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.patacriticism.org/juxta/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>