<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="panel_194_walter"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Interoperability of Metadata for Thematic Research Collections: A Model Based
                    on the <emph>Walt Whitman Archive</emph></title><author><name reg="Walter, Katherine L.">Katherine L. Walter</name></author><author><name reg="Barney, Brett">Brett Barney</name></author><author><name reg="Flanders, Julia">Julia Flanders</name></author><author><name reg="Catapano, Terence">Terence Catapano</name></author><author><name reg="Pitti, Daniel">Daniel Pitti</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>panel</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>interoperability</item><item>metadata</item><item>METS</item><item>thematic research collections</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Katherine L. Walter's doc <date value="2007-05"> May
                    2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Interoperability of Metadata for Thematic Research Collections:  A Model Based on the Walt Whitman Archive"><titlePart type="main">Interoperability of Metadata for Thematic Research
                    Collections: A Model Based on the <emph>Walt Whitman Archive</emph></titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Walter, Katherine L.">Katherine L. Walter</name><address><addrLine>kwalter1@unl.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Center for Digital Research in the Humanities<lb/>University of
                Nebraska - Lincoln</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Barney, Brett">Brett Barney</name><address><addrLine>bbarney2@unl.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Walt Whitman Archive<lb/>University of Nebraska - Lincoln</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Flander, Julia"> Julia Flanders</name><address><addrLine>Julia_Flanders@brown.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Women Writer's Project<lb/>Brown University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Catapano, Terence">Terence Catapano</name><address><addrLine>thc4@columbia.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Columbia University Libraries Digital Program</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Pitti, Daniel">Daniel Pitti</name><address><addrLine>dpitti@Virginia.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Institute for Advanced Technology in the
                Humanities<lb/>University of Virginia</titlePart></front><body><div0><head>Topic:</head><p>Created by scholars in collaboration with librarians/archivists, thematic
                    research collections are directed primarily at other scholars, though they are
                    also used by students and by the general public. Their development and
                    preservation pose several challenges: 1) they require very detailed encoding and
                    metadata to serve their demanding audience; 2) they often involve materials
                    which are dispersed; and, 3) critically, they incorporate a variety of different
                    types of materials with different digitization and metadata requirements.
                    Digital thematic research collections often include texts, images, finding aids
                    to archival material, and administrative records. While standards have been
                    developed for each of these data and metadata types (e.g., TEI, TIFF, EAD, and
                    MODS), there has not yet been a disciplined effort to integrate the standards
                    and explore where overlap and commonalities are, and to document best practices
                    for recording appropriate metadata with a minimum of duplication.</p><p>These issues are crucial to creators of digital thematic research collections
                    because 1) the primary resources are held by the archives and libraries, and
                    many of the repositories are digitizing materials and making them available to
                    scholars, even though the digital representations frequently are not as richly
                    represented as those which the scholars will ultimately create; 2) archives and
                    libraries will ultimately be responsible for the collections that are created;
                    and 3) if publishers are to have a role in the publication of digital thematic
                    research collections, standards will be essential for portability, and these
                    standards will by and large come out of the library world.</p><p>That said, thematic collections are generally far more complex and dependent on
                    intricate metadata interrelations than digital objects created for most digital
                    libraries. This complexity is due in part to the interpretive aspects of
                    projects in which scholars are deeply engaged with the materials. For example,
                    the poetry manuscripts section of the <emph>Whitman Archive</emph> incorporates
                    images, transcriptions with scholarly annotations, copyright and administrative
                    information, and finding aids. All of these materials are encoded, presented
                    through XSLT stylesheets, and made available via various search options. The
                    Whitman Archive uses an array of data and metadata standards: TIFF, TEI, EAD,
                    and MODS. Because of its complexity, the<emph>Whitman Archive</emph> is a good
                    case study for investigating the use and adequacy of Metadata Encoding and
                    Transcription Standard (METS) as a bundling tool for coordination of the
                    standards found in digital thematic research collections. </p><p>In 2005, the Institute of Museum and Library Services awarded a two-year grant to
                    the University of Nebraska-Lincoln to explore interoperability of metadata for
                    thematic research collections and to demonstrate the power of METS as an
                    ingestion package. The current project builds on an earlier grant project to
                    create an integrated guide to dispersed manuscripts. One hypothesis of the
                    current project is that by standardizing the way metadata is encoded, creators
                    of digital thematic research collections can make their work more sustainable
                    and ingestible; in other words, digital scholarship will be collected in a form
                    that will allow libraries and other entities to incorporate into their holdings
                    digital thematic research collections created at diverse locations by a variety
                    of scholars. As the research team’s work has progressed, the group has naturally
                    experienced evolution in its thinking and approaches to metadata. Members of the
                    project team will report on project processes and findings.</p></div0><div0><head>Organization:</head><p>K<emph rend="bold">atherine L. Walter</emph>, Co-Director of the Center for Digital Research in the
                    Humanities (CDRH) and co-project director for the interoperability of metadata
                    project, will provide a brief introduction to the topic, including a description
                    of thematic research collections such as the <emph>Whitman Archive</emph>, the
                    varying types of metadata that may be involved, the impetus to study integration
                    of overlapping standards for such collections, and the project goals originally
                    set by the research team. Walter will introduce speakers, moderate the panel,
                    and invite questions from the audience at the end. </p><p><emph rend="bold">Brett Barney</emph>, Senior Associate Editor and Project Manager of the <emph>Walt
                        Whitman Archive</emph>, will describe the team’s approach to exploring what
                    constitutes redundancy in metadata and its exploration of questions such as what
                    is really redundancy and what is not? When is it desireable and when is it not?
                    Does redundancy stymie ingestion or aid it? His report will pose conclusions
                    regarding the value of redundancy and its drawbacks in the ingestion of thematic
                    research collections into open-source library catalogs. Barney will also
                    describe the thinking of the team in selecting different kinds of representative
                    digital objects in the Whitman Archive for the ingestion demonstration project.</p><p><emph rend="bold">Julia Flanders</emph>, Women Writers’ Project, Brown University, will describe issues
                    raised for scholars in contributing all or part of a thematic research
                    collection into library catalogs. Questions explored will include what
                    responsibility does an acquiring library have to preserve or honor a scholar’s
                    intentions in creating and shaping such a collection? Is a library in fact
                    ingesting a collection or simply objects in a collection? This will include
                    thoughts on preserving contextual aspects of thematic research collections,
                    navigational features, and interface. As a member of a standards board, she will
                    speak about the value of this kind of research for standards bodies. </p><p><emph rend="bold">Terence Catapano</emph>, Special Collections Analyst/Librarian, Libraries Digital
                    Program, Columbia University, will describe the importance and adequacy of METS
                    as a publication and ingestion package, or in OAIS terms, how a Submission
                    Information Package (SIP) is derived for ingestion into a Digital Library, and
                    the development of a METS Profile for Thematic Research Collections. Catapano
                    will briefly describe work of digital library projects that helped inform this
                    study, such as the DLF MODS Implementation Guidelines for Cultural Heritage
                    Materials, Descriptive Metadata Guidelines for RLG Cultural Materials, DLF
                    Aquifer, and others. </p><p><emph rend="bold">Daniel Pitti</emph>, Associate Director of the Institute for Advanced Technology in the
                    Humanities will discuss whether metadata should exist in different forms at
                    different stages; and describe ingestion of the <emph>Whitman Archive</emph>
                    into FEDORA, what this means for other thematic research collections, and
                    reflect on the thoughts the FEDORA group at the University of Virginia has with
                    respect to preservation of such collections.</p></div0></body></text></TEI.2>