<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="panel_231_smith"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Agora.Techno.Phobia.Philia: Gender, Knowledge Building, and Digital Media</title><author><name reg="Smith, Martha Nell">Martha Nell Smith</name></author><author><name reg="Guertin, Carolyn">Carolyn Guertin</name></author><author><name reg="Mandell, Laura C.">Laura C. Mandell </name></author><author><name reg="Harris, Katherine D.">Katherine D. Harris</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>panel</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>knowledge representation</item><item>gender studies</item><item>queer studies</item><item>knowledge production</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Martha Nell Smith's doc <date value="2007-05">May
                    2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Agora.Techno.Phobia.Philia: Gender, Knowledge Building, and Digital Media"><titlePart type="main">Agora.Techno.Phobia.Philia: Gender, Knowledge Building, and
                    Digital Media</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Smith, Martha Nell">Martha Nell Smith</name><address><addrLine>mnsmith@umd.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of Maryland (MITH)</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Guertin, Carolyn">Carolyn Guertin</name><address><addrLine>carolyn.guertin@gmail.com</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of Texas at Arlington<lb/>McLuhan Program in Culture
                and Technology</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Mandell, Laura C.">Laura C. Mandell</name><address><addrLine>mandellc@muohio.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Department of English<lb/>Miami University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Harris, Katherine D.">Katherine D. Harris</name><address><addrLine>kharris@email.sjsu.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">San Jose State University</titlePart></front><body><div0><p>The editors of a special issue of <title level="j">Signs: Journal of Women in
                        Culture and Society</title>, a prominent scholarly feminist journal, wrote
                    in 1990 that “the degree to which American society has embraced and absorbed
                    computer technologies is astonishing. The degree to which the changes provoked
                    by computers leave prevailing inequalities is troubling.”<note n="1">Jean F.
                        O’Barr, ed.,<title level="m"> From Hard Drive to Software: Gender,
                            Computers, and Difference</title>. Special Issue of <title level="j">
                            Signs: Journal of Women in Culture and Society</title> 16:1 (Autumn
                        1990).</note> This observation preceded the development of the World Wide
                    Web, which has enabled computational tools to suffuse much work of the
                    humanities. The questions that have informed our work as feminist theorists and
                    scholars—how do our items of knowledge come into being, who made them, for what
                    purposes, and how does gender play a role in knowledge making—inhere in our
                    digital humanities work. That the two fields are or should be inextricably
                    intertwined seems, therefore, an inevitable fact of life. But is this just
                    personal coincidence, a fact produced by the trajectory of our careers and
                    interests? What is humanities computing anyway, and why should it be important
                    for feminist cultural, social, and intellectual work? Concomitantly, can
                    feminism enhance and improve the world and work of computer science, of
                    humanities computing, of digital humanities? After all, “very early in life,
                    computing is claimed as a male territory. At each step from early childhood
                    through college, computing is both actively claimed as “guy stuff” by boys and
                    men and passively ceded by girls and women. The claiming is largely the work of
                    a culture and society that links interest and success with computers to boys and
                        men.”<note n="2"> Jane Margolis and Allan Fisher.<title level="m"> Unlocking
                            the Clubhouse: Women in Computing</title> (Cambridge, Massachusetts and
                        London England: The MIT Press, 2002), p. 4.</note></p><p>A culture that says to use computing tools expertly one must know how machines
                    work, or at least must be deft programmers, dominates much of the world of
                    humanities computing. It is as if those who have fretted over literary and other
                    humanities fields becoming feminized or soft have been rescued by a field that
                    is hard science. Thus through computing, humanities is being remasculinized.
                    Scientific matters of mathematics and computation, objective and hard, are not
                    subject to the concerns of gender, race, or sexuality. Either explicitly or
                    implicitly, concerns that had taken over so much academic work in literature—of
                    gender, race, class, sexuality—were assumed to be irrelevant to humanities
                    computing. 2 + 2, so the reasoning goes, always equals 4, whether you are black,
                    female, queer, or straight. The codes always work, whatever one’s personal
                    identity or social group, and, as matters of objective and hard science, are
                    best dealt with by those who have been most interested in being engineers and
                    computational scientists of critical inquiry. So surely those interested are
                    also folks who do not want to clutter sharp, disciplined, methodical philosophy
                    with considerations of the gender-, race-, and class-determined facts of life.
                    After all, in the wake of the sixties, the humanities in general and their
                    standings in particular had suffered, according to some, from being feminized by
                    these things. Humanities computing seemed to offer a space free from all this
                    messiness and a return to objective questions of representation.</p><p>Yet such dreams of a return to the “objective,” uncluttered by messy identity
                    questions, are nostalgic. That humanities disciplines were in fact
                    foundationally changed by feminist scholarship of the twentieth century is
                    obvious from project development within humanities computing itself, and each of
                    the panelists is deeply involved with a major digital humanities project
                    informed by feminist scholarship—the <emph>Dickinson Electronic Archives</emph>,
                        <emph>The Poetess Archive</emph>, <emph>The Forget-Me-Not Hypertextual
                        Archive</emph>, a <emph>cyberfeminist archive</emph>, <emph>The Assemblage
                        Gallery</emph>. Our work as feminists leads us to concur with social
                    scientist Jane Margolis and computer scientist Allan Fisher that “the goal is
                    not to fit women into computer science [digital humanities] as it is currently
                    taught and conceived. Rather, a cultural and curricular revolution is required
                    to change computer science [digital humanities] so that the valuable
                    contributions and perspectives of women are respected within the
                        discipline.”<note n="3"><title level="m">Unlocking the Clubhouse</title>, p.
                        6.</note> In other words, this panel will posit ways in which the methods of
                    feminist, queer, and race critical inquiry might benefit the work of digital
                    humanists across the board (or screen, as it were) rather than serving as a
                    special niche of interest (for example, the methods might benefit the
                    multi-institutional NORA project, <xptr to="http://noraproject.org" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>, and its second phase, MONK, tremendously). </p><p>Descriptions of the roundtable presenters are below and we trust will serve to
                    show the range of experience and expertise on which we will draw to pose our
                    questions, posit ways in which the messiness of such critical inquiry can
                    advance digital humanities, entertain questions and suggestions before, during,
                    and after our session in order to collaborate with audience members in knowledge
                    production.</p></div0><div0><p>Martha Nell Smith is Professor of English and Founding Director of the Maryland
                    Institute for Technology in the Humanities (MITH) at the University of Maryland.
                    Author of more than 40 articles, including “Electronic Scholarly Editing” in the
                        <title level="m">Blackwell Companion to Digital Humanities</title>, her
                    publications include <title level="m">Open Me Carefully: Emily Dickinson’s
                        Intimate Letters to Susan Dickinson</title>, with Ellen Louise Hart (1998);
                        <title level="m">Comic Power in Emily Dickinson</title>, with Cristanne
                    Miller and Suzanne Juhasz (1993); and <title level="m">Rowing in Eden: Rereading
                        Emily Dickinson</title> (1992). With Mary Loeffelholz, she is editing the
                        <title level="m">Blackwell Companion to Emily Dickinson</title> (forthcoming
                    in 2007). She is also Coordinator and Executive Editor of the <emph>Dickinson
                        Electronic Archives</emph> projects at the Institute for Advanced Technology
                    in the Humanities (IATH) at the University of Virginia. With Lara Vetter, she is
                    a general editor of <title level="m">Emily Dickinson’s Correspondence: A
                        Born-Digital Inquiry</title>, forthcoming from the Mellon-sponsored
                    University of Virginia Press Rotunda Electronic Imprint. Her digital humanities
                    work is an extension of her work as a feminist literary theorist and scholar.
                    Because her interest in the possibilities afforded by computers as powerful and
                    empowering tools of humanities scholarly work became so keen as the World Wide
                    Web was gaining precedence, her work in humanities computing has been powerfully
                    influenced by cyberculture and new media studies. As a digital humanities
                    specialist she has focused on the sociologies of knowledge production in our
                    technology-saturated world—what data is reproduced and made accessible, and to
                    whom, and what new knowledge has been produced by computational tools. Her
                    questions, suggestions, and models will be drawn from the multi-institutional
                    data mining and visualization NORA Project (<xptr to="http://noraproject.org" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>). </p></div0><div0><p>Carolyn Guertin is an Assistant Professor of Digital Media and Director of the
                    eCreate Lab in the Department of English at the University of Texas at
                    Arlington. During the 2004 to 2006 academic years, she was a Senior McLuhan
                    Fellow and SSHRC Postdoctoral Fellow in the McLuhan Program in Culture and
                    Technology at the University of Toronto ~ most recently giving the closing
                    keynote address at "Re-Reading McLuhan: An International Conference on Media and
                    Culture in the 21st Century" at the University of Bayreuth in Germany. She does
                    both theoretical and applied work in cyberfeminism, digital narrative, digital
                    design, media literacy (or postliteracy) and performance. She is a founding
                    editor of the online journal <title level="j">MediaTropes</title>, and a
                    literary advisor to the Electronic Literature Organization. She has written
                    textbooks on hypertext and literature and information aesthetics, and is
                    currently working on a new book project called <title level="m">Connective
                        Tissue: Queer Bodies, Postdramatic Performance and New Media
                    Aesthetics</title>. Guertin is best known as curator and founder of
                        <emph>Assemblage: The Women's New Media Gallery</emph><xptr to="http://tracearchive.ntu.ac.uk:80/traced/guertin/assemblage.htm" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>, the only site devoted exclusively to
                    born-digital art and lit by women on the Web ~ soon to be relaunched in a 2.0
                    version. She will be examining the trend toward personal media and participatory
                    culture that is a product (or fallout) of the politicizing of diversity, the
                    women’s movement, and queer issues. Where notions of interactivity focused on
                    the technology as the most important component, participatory or user-generated
                    culture—from wikis to podcasts to FaceBook to <emph>Second Life</emph>—puts the
                    backchannel into the foreground, and puts people of all genders back as active
                    users in the system.</p></div0><div0><p>Laura Mandell is Associate Professor in eighteenth-century and Romantic British
                    literature at Miami University. Her book, <title level="m">Misogynous Economies:
                        The Business of Literature in Eighteenth-Century Britain</title>, discusses
                    the feminist potential of anti-feminist writings produced during the long
                    eighteenth century. She has published essays in ELH, MLQ, European Romantic
                    Review, Studies in Romanticism, and Nineteenth-Century Prose. She has edited The
                    Castle of Otranto and <emph>The Poetess Archive Database</emph> (<xptr to="http://unixgen.muohio.edu/~poetess" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>), a
                    TEI-encoded bibliographic finding aid and full-text resource about the men and
                    women who wrote popular poetry in Britain and America between 1750 and 1900.
                    Within the next year, this resource will contain author and title information
                    from tables of contents of all the major anthologies and literary annuals.
                    Within the next few years, it will expand to periodicals.</p></div0><div0><p>Katherine D. Harris, Assistant Professor, San Jose State University, has created
                    an online hypertextual archive of the first literary annual, the Forget Me Not,
                    re-presenting various aspects of the book as well as the poetry, prose and
                    engravings: “Forget Me Not: A Hypertextual Archive of Ackermann’s 19th-Century
                    Literary Annual” <xptr to="http://www.orgs.muohio.edu/anthologies/FMN/Index.htm" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>. With Laura Mandell, she serves as an editor of
                        <emph>The Poetess Archive Database</emph>, which now contains a bibliography
                    of over 4,000 entries for works by and about writers working in and against the
                    “poetess tradition,” the extraordinarily popular, but much criticized, flowery
                    poetry written in Britain and America between 1750 and 1900. Their presentation
                    for this panel will not be a show-and-tell of these archives, but an in-depth
                    consideration of ways in which the feminist theories that have identified the
                    scholarly needs for this resource and informed their development can advance the
                    work of digital humanities at large. </p></div0></body></text></TEI.2>