<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="paper_136_esteva"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Bits and Pieces of Text: Appraisal of a Natural Electronic Archive</title><author><name reg="Esteva, Maria">Maria Esteva</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>paper</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>archive appraisal</item><item>digital archiving</item><item>text mining</item><item>social network analysis</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Maria Esteva's doc <date value="2007-04">April 2007</date></item><item>SAS: Revised incorporating Esteva's revisions<date value="2007-05">May
                    2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Bits and Pieces of Text: Appraisal of a Natural Electronic Archive"><titlePart type="main">Bits and Pieces of Text: Appraisal of a Natural Electronic
                    Archive</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Esteva, Maria">Maria Esteva</name><address><addrLine>mesteva@mail.utexas.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">School of Information<lb/>University of Texas at
            Austin</titlePart></front><body><div0><p>This paper presents the methods and tools designed to appraise a digital archive.
                    The attributes characterizing the archive at hand led to the development of the
                    concept of <emph>natural electronic archives</emph> that would allow
                    transforming the archive as a whole into a unit of analysis. The methodology for
                    appraising the archive combines traditional archival concepts while adding tools
                    –such as text mining and social network analysis– taken from other fields.</p><p>The digital archive belongs to a philanthropic agency whose activities in support
                    of the arts, sciences and social welfare in Argentina span from the mid 1980s
                    until its closure in December of 2005. In the early 1990s the institution
                    implemented a networked server to store, retrieve, and share electronic texts,
                    email, applications, and databases. In it, each employee had a virtual folder
                    with his or her initials to store the files that they created. To comply with
                    legal requirements the archive must be kept closed but accessible for the next
                    10 years. In parallel, appraisal needed to be undertaken to decide on the
                    archive’s long term destiny. An initial survey of the archive led to the
                    development of the natural archive concept and suggested an appraisal method to
                    establish archival evidence.</p><p>The natural electronic archive concept grew while I was surveying the server and
                    from the interviews conducted with staff members who had worked in the
                    organization since it opened. Based on my analysis, I concluded that the manner
                    in which records were generated and kept could not easily be ascribed to digital
                    archiving models currently discussed in the literature. These models focus more
                    on the creation of sound electronic records, the design of electronic
                    record-keeping systems, and on institutional repository archiving models than on
                    the way in which digital archives exist “in the wild” (Bearman &amp; Trant,
                    1997; Cox, 1997; Duranti et al., 2002; InterPARES Authenticity Task Force 2002;
                    Jones et al., 2006). The natural archive concept builds partly on that of
                    “natural collections” proposed by Phillip Cronenwett to describe collections of
                    literary manuscripts as they leave the hand of the creator (Cronnenwett, 1984,
                    p.106). I suggest that this concept is relevant both to the case study at hand,
                    as well as to archives of public or private persons and institutions showing
                    similar characteristics.</p><p>Creation of natural electronic archives involves a set of <emph>ad-hoc</emph>
                    practices developed as people adjust to and learn how to use information
                    technologies. A natural archive is not designed or managed by records managers
                    or archivists. Instead, it is what those working in institutions, in different
                    capacities, using different technologies, and making decisions, make of it. In a
                    natural archive, records are created, named, destroyed, or retained according to
                    individual work-practices. Each record creator decides on structure and naming
                    conventions for files and folders, spontaneously or consistently, according to
                    individual mnemonic rules or the spur of the moment. Within the virtual folders,
                    images, spreadsheets, texts, web sites, databases, back-ups, and applications
                    live together under the same roof, placed or misplaced, in organized or
                    disorganized fashion, in general without descriptive clues.</p><p>In a context without explicit recordkeeping rules, bits and pieces of text are
                    ubiquitous inhabitants. Either shared by different members of a network or used
                    repeatedly by their creators, they constitute the core of many records. This
                    repetition of fragments afforded by the cut and paste function of the text
                    editor, speaks as much of provenance, group collaboration and fair use, as of
                    hierarchies and corporate culture. As a consequence of all of these phenomena,
                    records within a natural archive are difficult to identify and lack formal
                    documentation. This creates doubts about their capacity to provide evidence.</p><p>An appraisal method that uses Text Mining and Social Network Analysis was
                    designed to determine what type of evidence of the organization that created it
                    is provided by a natural electronic archive. The method is rooted in concerns
                    expressed by Peter Boticelli in his study of networked organizations (Boticelli,
                    2000). It considers the need to document dynamics and changes in organizations
                    and it explores the meaning of evidence and archival bond –understood as the
                    “network of relationships between records” – in an ambiguous environment
                    (Duranti &amp; Guercio, 1997). Also, it highlights the importance of
                    preserving evidence of the archive’s formation process that will allow the study
                    of its technological history and social uses (Lubar, 1996; Parezo, 1996). Its
                    main departure from other appraisal methods is that it uses digital tools to
                    analyze a large corpus of records inductively.</p><p>Determining archival evidence implies being able to map the organization through
                    its records. Text Mining and Social Network Analysis use computing algorithms to
                    discover knowledge about the relations among electronic records. By measuring
                    the similarity between texts produced and co-produced by staff members within
                    frameworks of time and provenance, the strength of relationships between records
                    and between the staff members and/or functions that created them can be
                    established. In turn, by averaging the similarities between the records of all
                    pairs of staff members or functions across time, organizational structure and
                    functions as well as correspondent changes in dynamics emerge. To confirm the
                    validity of the findings, results are contrasted against the narratives of staff
                    members about who they collaborated with, when, and in what. In this way, the
                    evidence provided by the electronic records in this natural archive can be
                    attested</p><p>A proof of concept was conducted to determine the feasibility of the appraisal
                    method. For this, copies of electronic text records from the archive were used,
                    while the original archive, kept with its directory structure intact, remains as
                    guarantee of provenance and original order. Pre-processing documents involved
                    using file management software to sort files within directories and
                    sub-directories to construct sets belonging to a group of staff members that
                    worked in the organization during a one year period. After conversion to .txt
                    format, the sets were submitted to Rainbow, an open source text classification
                    and retrieval tool, to obtain a vector space model (McCallum, 1996). In this
                    phase, several trials were conducted to find the best way to narrow the
                    vocabulary without losing language subtleties. From this model, pair-wise
                    distances between documents where calculated using the cosine similarity formula
                    in MatLab on a UNIX server. The resultant matrix was submitted to the social
                    network analysis software UCINET to obtain a network drawing of the distances
                    between texts (Borgatti et al., 2002). In turn, the average of distances
                    corresponding to each staff member were calculated to obtain a matrix of
                    relationships between staff members during one year.</p><p>The experiment suggested that relationships between staff members do emerge from
                    the similarities and differences between the texts that they create. Testing
                    showed that staff members who were leaving the organization and wrote farewell
                    or personal records were less related to those cooperating in the preparation of
                    monthly or annual reports. Also, project proposals written by grant applicants
                    and stored in the shared server were barely related to reports or appropriation
                    requests written by members of the organization. These preliminary results
                    indicated that shifts in functions and consequent relationships between staff
                    members can emerge from electronic texts.</p><p>The proof of concept also examined the use of cluster analysis to explore the
                    concept of archival bond in natural electronic archives. Analyzing the content
                    of strongly and poorly related records can explain what characterizes
                    relationships between records –provenance, date, type of record, contents, topic
                    – and whether these features can be mapped onto theoretical conceptualizations
                    of archival bond. It will also explain the role of drafts, versions, and
                    non-records by finding the proportion in which they exist in the natural archive
                    and how close or not they are to complete records.</p><p>Before issuing the final appraisal protocol, changes had to be implemented and
                    concerns addressed. Since the archive contains formats as old as Microsoft Word
                    5.0 for DOS, a converter with broad file format support was found to transform
                    old files to ANSI text so they can be processed by Rainbow. Because there are
                    various pieces of software involved, processes need to be automated and
                    simplified as much as possible and issues related to the size of the text sets
                    and matrices vis a vis the power of the processing tools have to be considered.
                    Through a research grant from the University of Texas at Austin a programmer was
                    hired to modify existing applications and develop new ones. Rainbow’s tokenizer
                    was modified to recognize Spanish characters and to include the Oleander Spanish
                    stemmer (Oleander Solutions, 2006). The cosine similarity algorithm was coded in
                    C++ so that bigger matrices can be processed efficiently in a UNIX server. To
                    improve the ability to distinguish the characteristics of individual texts,
                    Tf-idf capabilities were added to the script. The program outputs both a matrix
                    of cosine similarities between every other document and a matrix of the averages
                    of cosine similarity distances between every other author in the sample. Current
                    testing involves processing sets with all the texts produced in one year by
                    every author to determine changes in collaboration dynamics. After processing
                    the matrices with UCINET, preliminary results for author’s yearly averages show
                    relationships that concur with their functions in the institution (See Fig. 1
                    and 2).</p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">paper_136_esteva_1.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 1. Network drawing of averages of cosine similarities between a
                        set of 544 records of different staff members during the year 1996. The
                        director is at the center of the network which corresponds with his
                        functions in the organization and the data gathered in the interviews. Most
                        of the records produced by the financial manager are non-textual and
                        remained within the database systems which explains the distance between him
                        and the director.</figDesc></figure><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">paper_136_esteva_2.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 2. Network drawing of averages of cosine similarities between
                        719 records of different staff members during the year 1997. As new staff
                        members added their records in the networked directory and started their own
                        relationships, the majority of the director’s previous relationships and his
                        status in the network remained stable.</figDesc></figure><p>The use of Text Mining and Social Network Analysis promises to allow archivists
                    to explore and define the meaning of evidence in natural electronic archives.
                    Instead of intuition and art, as appraisal has been characterized, the
                    opportunity exists to use inductive quantitative methods to make of appraisal a
                    research endeavor (Eastwood, 1992). Moreover, the use of these methods opens the
                    doors to the enormous potential of digital tools in the analysis and processing
                    of digital archives.</p></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Authenticity Task Force">Authenticity Task Force</name></author><title level="m">Requirements for Assessing and Maintaining the
                                Authenticity of Electronic Records</title><imprint><publisher>InterPARES</publisher><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2005-10-06" to="http://www.InterPARES.org/display_file.cfm?doc=ip1_authenticity_requirements.pdf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Bearman, David">David Bearman</name></author><author><name reg="Trant, Jennifer">Jennifer Trant</name></author><title level="a">Electronic Records Research Working Meeting May 28-30,
                                1997: A Report from the Archives Community</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">D-Lib</title><imprint><date value="1997"> July/August 1997</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2005-10-03" to="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/july97/07bearman.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Borgatti, Stephan P.">Stephan P. Borgatti</name></author><author><name reg="Everett, M.G."/></author><author><name reg="">Freeman, L.C.</name></author><title level="u">UCINET 6 Social Networks Analysis Software</title><imprint><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2005-04-01" to="http://www.analytictech.com/ucinet/ucinet.htm" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Boticelli, Peter">Peter Boticelli</name></author><title level="a">Records Appraisal in Network Organizations</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Archivaria </title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">49</biblScope><date value="2000">2000</date><biblScope type="pages">161-191</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Cox, Richard J.">Richard J. Cox</name></author><title level="a"> Electronic Systems and Records Management in the
                                Information Age: An Introduction</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">ASIS</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">23.5</biblScope><date value="1997">1997</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2005-10-03" to="http://www.asis.org/Bulletin/Jun-97/cox.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Cronenwett, Philip  N.">Philip N. Cronenwett</name></author><title level="a">Appraisal of Literary Manuscripts</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m"> Archival Choices: Managing the Historical Record in an
                                Age of Abundance</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Peace, Nancy E.">Nancy E. Peace</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Lexington, MA</pubPlace><publisher>Lexington Books</publisher><date value="1984">1984</date><biblScope type="pages">105-116</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Duranti, Luciana">Luciana Duranti</name></author><author><name reg="Eastwood, Terry">Terry Eastwood</name></author><author><name reg="McNeil, Heather">Heather McNeil</name></author><title level="m">Preservation of the Integrity of Electronic Records</title><imprint><pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace><publisher>Kluwer Academic</publisher><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Duranti, Luciana">Luciana Duranti</name></author><author><name reg="Guercio, Maria">Maria Guercio</name></author><title level="a">Research Issues in Archival Bond</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Electronic Records Meeting, Session I</title><imprint><date value="1997">1997</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-03-29" to="http://www.archimuse.com/erecs97/s1-ld-mg.HTM" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Eastwood, Terry">Terry Eastwood</name></author><title level="a">Towards a Social Theory of Appraisal</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Archival Imagination: Essays in Honor of Hugh A.
                                Taylor </title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Craig, Barbara L.">Barbara L. Craig</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace><publisher>Association of Canadian Archivists</publisher><date value="1992">1992</date><biblScope type="pages">71-89</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Jones, Richard">Richard Jones</name></author><author><name reg="Andrew, Theo">Theo Andrew</name></author><author><name reg="MacColl, John">John MacColl</name></author><title level="m">The Institutional Repository</title><imprint><pubPlace>Oxford, UK</pubPlace><publisher>Chandos Publishing Limited</publisher><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Lubar, Steven">Steven Lubar</name></author><title level="a">Learning from Technological Things</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Learning from Things</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Kingery, W. David">W. David Kingery</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Smithsonian Institution Press</publisher><date value="1996">1996</date><biblScope type="pages">31-34</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="McCallum, Andrew K.">Andrew K. McCallum</name></author><title level="u">Bow: A Toolkit for Statistical Language Modeling, Text
                                Retrieval, Classification and Clustering</title><imprint><date value="1996">1996</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2005-02-02" to="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~mccallum/bow" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Oleander Solutions">Oleander Solutions</name></author><title level="u">Oleander Stemming Library</title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-11-24" to="http://www.oleandersolutions.com/stemming.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Parezo, Nancy J.">Nancy J. Parezo</name></author><title level="a">The Formation of Anthropological Archival
                            Records</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Learning from Things</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Kingery, W. David">W. David Kingery</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Smithsonian Institution Press</publisher><date value="1996">1996</date><biblScope type="pages">145-174</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>