<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="paper_172_pierazzo"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>The Encoding of Time in Manuscripts Transcription: Toward Genetic Digital
                    Editions</title><author><name reg="Pierazzo, Elena">Elena Pierazzo</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>paper</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>genetic criticism</item><item>timing</item><item>XML</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Elena Pierazzo's doc<date value="2007-04">April and May
                2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="The Encoding of Time in Manuscripts Transcription: Toward Genetic Digital Editions"><titlePart type="main">The Encoding of Time in Manuscripts Transcription: Toward
                    Genetic Digital Editions</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Pierazzo, Elena">Elena Pierazzo</name><address><addrLine>elena.pierazzo@kcl.ac.uk</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">King's College London</titlePart></front><body><div0><p>Writing is a process that occurs in time. This simple and obvious consideration
                    involves many issues both from a theoretical and practical point of view. A
                    critical evaluation of timing is really crucial in the case of modern authors'
                    autograph draft manuscripts because different layers of corrections, deletions
                    and additions can give insight into an author’s way of working, key to the
                    interpretations of his/her works and the evolution of the author’s
                        <emph>Weltanschaung</emph>, as highlighted in genetic criticism over the
                    last few years.<note n="1">The question is too complex just to try to give some
                        basic references; anyway Gresillon 1994 will offer a good starting
                    point.</note> Medieval manuscripts copied by one ore more scribes are also, of
                    course, the result of a process that occurred in time, but the different kind of
                    authorship involved in such cases seems to involve a difference in the
                    evaluation of the cultural weight of recorded variants. </p><p>When a scholar inspects a written text, especially a manuscript, s/he has in
                    his/her hands the final result of that process and can choose whether to
                    approach it from a codicological/documentary point of view, “photographing” the
                    resulting product, or from a genetic point of view, trying to describe the
                    teleological flow of authoring. The first approach is more typical of scribes’
                    copies, the latter of autographic (draft) manuscripts.</p><p>Practically, time based editions are really difficult to represent in printed
                    works, because of the bi-dimensionality of paper sheets.</p><ab><cit rend="block"><q>On voudrait représenter dans la bidimensionalité des pages un processus
                            génétique dont on s’est pourtant appliqué à montrer que sa proprieté est
                            d’ajouter à l’écrit, qui est bidimensionel, une troisième dimension, qui
                            est celle du temps!</q><bibl>Gresillon 1994:121</bibl></cit></ab><p>In a digital framework bi-dimensionality can be overruled by a
                    hypertextual/multimedia approach that can allow the creation of a more flexible
                    context for the presentation of a genetic edition. The problem of a time based
                    encoding has been discussed in several circumstances (i.e. TEI Manuscripts SIG
                    Meeting Report 01, Vanhoutte 2002 that suggests the usage of the markup solution
                    employed in the transcription of speech for the purpose), but – up till now – a
                    coherent encoding model for such editions has not been proposed. And for a good
                    reasons: while it is possible to describe a relative-timed process, it is very
                    complicated, if not impossible, to draw a general absolute-timed framework.</p></div0><div0><head>Analysis and time-based encoding of authorial interventions</head><p>Let us consider a couple of examples taken from page 3595 of <title type="m">Zibaldone</title> of Giacomo Leopardi.</p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head>Ex. 1 line 6</head><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">paper_172_pierazzo_1.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Fig. 1</figDesc></figure><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">paper_172_pierazzo_2.jpg</xref></p><figDesc/></figure><p>In this line we can detect two corrections: 1) deletion of the line under “si”
                    and 2) deletion of “dotti” corrected into “denti”.</p><p>We can try to draw the timing of the creation of the segment as follow:</p><lg><l>Time 1: writing “che e’ si rechi a dotti”</l><l>Time 2: deletion of “dotti”; consequent writing of “denti”</l><l>Time 3: underlying of “si”</l><l>Time 4: deletion of the line under “si”</l><l>Time 5: underlying of “rechi” and “denti”</l><l>Time 6: writing of “l’un d’essi cibi”</l></lg><p>Other timetables are also possible, but let’s assume this is the more probable
                    one. The text can be encoded using a TEI-based mark-up with the help of a new
                    global attribute (<hi rend="code">@time</hi>), intending that it’s just an
                    example to help the conceptualization of the problem: <hi rend="code">
                        &lt;seg time="1"&gt;che e' &lt;del type="underline deletion"
                        time="4"&gt;<lb/> &lt;hi rend="underline"
                        time="3"&gt;si&lt;/hi&gt;<lb/>&gt; &lt;/del&gt;<lb/>
                        &lt;hi rend="underline" time="5"&gt;rechi a'&lt;/hi&gt;<lb/>
                        &lt;del type="overstrike" time="2"&gt;dotti&lt;/del&gt;<lb/>
                        &lt;/seg&gt;<lb/>&gt; &lt;seg time="2"&gt;<lb/> &lt;hi
                        rend="underline" time="5"&gt;denti&lt;/hi&gt;<lb/>
                        &lt;/seg&gt;<lb/> &lt;seg time="6"&gt;l'un d'essi
                        cibi&lt;/seg&gt;<lb/></hi></p><p>Such transcription tries to model the real flow of writing, but such a model may
                    not be workable. In fact, it will fragment the flow of the plain writing in
                    potentially infinite pieces. To simplify it, we can assume as Time 0 (default)
                    the time of the normal plain writing flow, timing just editorial interventions.</p><p>The schedule will then be modified as follows:</p><lg><l>Time 0: writing “che e’ si rechi a dotti”</l><l>Time 1: deletion of : “dotti”</l><l>Time 0: writing of “denti”</l><l>Time 2: underlying of “si”</l><l>Time 3: deletion of the underline under “si”</l><l>Time 4: underlying of “rechi” and “denti”</l><l>Time 0: writing of “l’un d’essi cibi”</l></lg><p>A further simplification is also possible: assuming that – in genetic criticism
                    terms – so-called “writing variant” (deletion of a single word substituted by
                    another that immediately follows on the same line) occurs during the normal
                    writing flow, the following model can be drawn:</p><lg><l>Time 0: writing “che si rechi a dotti”; deletion of : “dotti”; writing of
                        “denti”; writing of “l’un d’essi cibi”</l><l>Time 1: underlying of “si”</l><l>Time 2: deletion of the underline under “si”</l><l>Time 3: underlying of “rechi” and “denti”</l></lg><p>This will be the consequent new encoding: <hi rend="code">che e' &lt;del
                        type="underline deletion" time="2"&gt; &lt;hi rend="underline"
                        time="1"&gt;si&lt;/hi&gt;&lt;/del&gt; &lt;hi
                        rend="underline" time="3"&gt;rechi a'&lt;/hi&gt; &lt;del
                        type="overstrike"&gt;dotti&lt;/del&gt; &lt;hi
                        rend="underline" time="3"&gt;denti&lt;/hi&gt; l'un d'essi
                    cibi</hi></p><p>The last possibility should not imply that any inline correction is to be
                    considered as done in Time 0, but just the one followed by the correction. In
                    fact, in the case of a deletion of an adjective or of any other word not
                    essential from a syntactical point of view, the correction can occur in any
                    time.</p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head>Ex. 2 line 11</head><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">paper_172_pierazzo_3.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Fig. 2</figDesc></figure><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">paper_172_pierazzo_4.jpg</xref></p><figDesc/></figure><p>This passage can be timed as follow:</p><lg><l>Time 1: writing “che di due Eroi a”;</l><l>Time 2: deletion of “a”;</l><l>Time 3: writing of “quanto si voglia pari di”</l><l>Time 4: interlinear addition of “o più” after “Eroi”</l><l>Time 5: deletion of the addition</l><l>Time 6: interlinear addition of “o più” after “due”</l></lg><p>Or, in the simplified version, as follow:</p><lg><l>Time 0: writing of “che di due Eroi a”; deletion of “a”; writing of “quanto
                        si voglia pari di”</l><l>Time 1: interlinear addition of “o più” after “Eroi”</l><l>Time 2: deletion of the addition</l><l>Time 3: interlinear addition of “o più” after “due”</l></lg><p>The encoding model (simplified version): <hi rend="code">che di due &lt;add
                        place="intralinear" time="3"&gt;o più&lt;/add&gt; Eroi
                        &lt;del type="overstrike"&gt;a&lt;/del&gt; &lt;del
                        type="overstrike" time="2"&gt;&lt;add place="intralinear"
                        time="1"&gt;o più&lt;/add&gt;&lt;/del&gt; quanto si
                        voglia pari di </hi></p><p>By applying different stylesheets to the encoded texts, it will be possible to
                    show all the different stages and to give the user the possibility of browsing
                    among them.</p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">paper_172_pierazzo_5.jpg</xref></p><figDesc/></figure></div0><div0><head>Relative or absolute?</head><p>The two above examples occur on the same page: shall we then consider Time 1 of
                    the first example the same of Time 1 of the second example? The answer should
                    be: no; very little can be said about the timing of editorial/authorial
                    intervention in two different segments. The possibility of establishing an
                    absolute timing for correction is applicable only where we have strong
                    palaeographic evidences or authorial declarations dating or describing a
                    revision.</p><p>For instance, we can imagine an author used to typewrite his/her texts and then
                    to correct them by hand: in this case the assumption of an absolute time is
                    possible. But as different layers of hand corrections can also occur, there will
                    be, in this case also, the necessity of considering relative-timed
                    interventions. This situation can be represented in encoding distinguishing
                    absolute and relative timing for instance by the application of two different
                    attributes, i.e. <hi rend="code">@timeRel</hi> and <hi rend="code">@timeAbs</hi>
                    In a digital framework an incorrect consideration of time as absolute or
                    relative can bring to display texts that never existed. Let us imagine for a
                    moment that we build an XSLT based tool able to display at a time either Time 1,
                    Time 2 or Time 3 etc. variants: the results would be the display of variants
                    that might have lived in different moments. </p><p>I think that, in absence of explicit authorial declarations or of palaeographic
                    evidence, the only possible display would be to show timing of variants segment
                    by segment, i.e. to give evidence just of relative timed corrections.</p><p>In the presentation I will present some examples from different authors (Giacomo
                    Leopardi, Jane Austen, Virginia Woolf and some others) to examine the complexity
                    of representation of temporal factors in digital genetic editions.</p></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Grésillon, A.">A. Grésillon</name></author><title level="m">Eléments de critique génétique. Lire les manuscrits modernes</title><imprint><pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace><publisher>Presses Universitaires de France</publisher><date value="1994">1994</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><title level="m">TEI P4: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                                Interchange, XML Compatible Edition</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.">C. M. Sperberg-McQueen</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Burnard, Lou">Lou Burnard</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace><pubPlace>Providence, RI</pubPlace><pubPlace>Charlottesville, VA</pubPlace><pubPlace>Bergen, NO</pubPlace><publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/index.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="TEI Manuscripts SIG">TEI Manuscripts SIG</name></author><title level="m"> Meeting Report 01</title><imprint><pubPlace>Nancy</pubPlace><publisher>ATILF</publisher><date value="2003">November 8th 2003 </date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="at http://www.tei-c.org.uk/Activities/SIG/Manuscript/mssigr01.xml.ID=body.1_div.3" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Vanhoutte, Edward">Edward Vanhoutte</name></author><title level="a">Putting Time Back in Manuscripts. Text Ontology, Critique
                                Génétique and Modern Manuscript</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Paper presented at ALLC/ACH 2002 Tübingen: University of
                                Tübingen, 25 July 2002</title><imprint><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.uni-tuebingen.de/cgi-bin/abs/abs?propid=93" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>