<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="panel_134_fraistat"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Round Table: Coalition of Digital Humanities Centers</title><author><name reg="Fraistat, Neil">Neil Fraistat</name></author><author><name reg="Unsworth, John">John Unsworth</name></author><author><name reg="Walter, Katherine L.">Katherine L. Walter</name></author><author><name reg="Flanders, Julia">Julia Flanders</name></author><author><name reg="Kirschenbaum, Matthew">Matthew Kirschenbaum</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>panel</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>digital humanities</item><item>cyberinfrastructure</item><item>collaboration</item><item>cooperation</item><item>funding</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Neil Fraistat's doc <date value="2007-05"> May
                2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Round Table: Coalition of Digital Humanities Centers"><titlePart type="main">Round Table: Coalition of Digital Humanities Centers</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Fraistat, Neil">Neil Fraistat</name><address><addrLine>fraistat@umd.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of Maryland</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Unsworth, John">John Unsworth</name><address><addrLine>unsworth@uiuc.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Walter, Katherine L.">Katherine L. Walter</name><address><addrLine>kwalter1@unl.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of Nebraska - Lincoln</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Flanders, Julia">Julia Flanders</name><address><addrLine>Julia_Flanders@brown.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Brown University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Kirschenbaum, Matthew">Matthew Kirschenbaum</name><address><addrLine>mgk@umd.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of Maryland</titlePart></front><body><div0><p>The members of the panel will discuss with the audience the outcome of the
                    national summit meeting of American digital humanities centers and major funders
                    held at the National Endowment of Humanities headquarters on April 12-13,
                    co-sponsored by the NEH and the University of Maryland.</p><p>The purpose of the meeting was to take seriously the ACLS Cyberinfrastructure
                    Commission’s call for digital humanities centers to become key nodes of
                    cyberinfrastructure in the United States. To that end, the summit explored how
                    best to foster collaboration among national digital humanities centers, among
                    major funders of the digital humanities, and between centers and funders, along
                    with the possibility of creating a national coalition of digital humanities
                    centers.</p><p>Among the salient issues are the creation of mechanisms for promoting timely
                    exchange of information between centers and identifying opportunities for
                    collaboration among them; the articulation of mutual research goals as well as
                    particular areas of emphases so as to avoid duplication of effort among centers;
                    the development of joint policy agendas and successful strategies for pursuing
                    them; better articulating funding needs to funding agencies; methods for
                    optimizing collaborative opportunities between humanities content specialists
                    and the technological community; and advancing the place of the digital
                    humanities on campus, including such issues as infrastructure and the role of
                    the Digital Humanities in promotion and tenure.</p><p>This roundtable session will focus upon the initiatives begun at the summit
                    meeting and engage in a general discussion about them, with the hope of widening
                    the conversation to include other American centers not represented at the summit
                    meeting and centers in other countries.</p></div0></body></text></TEI.2>