<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="paper_196_ciula"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Expressing Complex Associations in Medieval Historical Documents: The Henry
                    III Fine Rolls Project</title><author><name reg="Ciula, Arianna">Arianna Ciula</name></author><author><name reg="Spence, Paul">Paul Spence</name></author><author><name reg="Vieira, José Miguel">José Miguel Vieira</name></author><author><name reg="Poupeau, Gautier"> Gautier Poupeau</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>paper</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>ontological representation</item><item>historical texts</item><item>text encoding</item><item>authorities</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Arianna Ciula's doc <date value="2007-04">April
                2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Expressing Complex Associations in Medieval Historical Documents: The Henry                 III Fine Rolls Project"><titlePart type="main">Expressing Complex Associations in Medieval Historical
                    Documents: The Henry III Fine Rolls Project</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Ciula, Arianna">Arianna Ciuala</name><address><addrLine>arianna.ciula@kcl.ac.uk</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Centre for Humanities Computing<lb/>King's College London</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Spence, Paul">Paul Spence</name><address><addrLine>paul.spence@kcl.ac.uk</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Centre for Humanities Computing<lb/>King's College London</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Vieira, José Miguel">José Miguel Vieira</name></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Centre for Humanities Computing<lb/>King's College London</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Poupeau, Gautier">Gautier Poupeau</name></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">École Nationale des Chartes<lb/>Université
            Paris-Sorbonne</titlePart></front><body><div0><p>This paper will focus on the use of technologies traditionally associated with
                    knowledge management and ontological representation to express complex
                    associations between entities in historical texts that have been marked up in
                    XML according to the Text Encoding Initiative guidelines.<note n="1"><xptr to="http://www.tei-c.org" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note> In particular, we will describe our exploration of the potential use of
                    RDF (Resource Description Framework)/OWL (Web Ontology Language) technologies
                    and will reflect on the role of an ontology in facilitating the interpretation
                    of implicit and hidden associations in the sources, examining its use and limits
                    in a digital humanities project in connection with editing tools and delivery
                    issues. </p><p>We will demonstrate our findings based on the Henry III Fine Rolls project,<note n="2"><xptr to="http://www.frh3.org.uk" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note> where an RDF ontology is being developed to make explicit information
                    about person, place and subject entities marked up as “instances” in the core
                    texts themselves.</p></div0><div0><head><emph>The Henry III Fine Rolls project and the need for authority lists</emph></head><p>The Henry III Fine Rolls is a three-year collaborative project between King's
                    College London and the National Archives (UK) that aims to represent the
                    complexity of a historical object known as the 'fine rolls' which chart offers
                    of money made to King Henry III of England in exchange for a wide range of
                    concessions and favours. A total of 64 rolls containing around 800 parchment
                    membranes, one for almost all of the fifty-six years of Henry III’s reign from
                    1216-72, survive in the UK National Archives.<note n="3"><xptr to="http://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note> Each fine roll was compiled in Latin by a handful of scribes and taken
                    as a body of documentary evidence, the rolls are of “prime importance in the
                    study of political, social, and economic history and of government and
                    administration at a local and national level.”<note n="4">Dryburgh, Paul. “Henry
                        III Fine Rolls Project” (paper presented at the Institute of Historical
                        Research, London , February, 9, 2006).</note></p><p>The project will cover the first thirty-two years of Henry III’s reign down to
                    1248 and will result in both print and digital editions of the rolls, using as a
                    model the format of the traditional printed 'calendar' (an English summary of
                    records, plus a set of indices) in connection with the digitised images of the
                    rolls themselves. The digital edition will have a sophisticated search interface
                    and both print and digital editions will provide a series of indices for people,
                    places and subjects that include complex associations between the various
                    entries.</p><p>The core texts were encoded in XML using the TEI guidelines and include mark-up
                    related to some aspects of the physical structure of the rolls as material
                        artefacts.<note n="5">For a more detailed presentation of the mark-up model
                        see Ciula, Arianna. “Searching the Fine Rolls: A Demonstration of the
                        Electronic Version” (paper presented at the International Medieval Congress,
                        University of Leeds, July 10-13, 2006).</note> Particular attention has been
                    given in the mark-up to the occurrences of names of persons, places and
                    institutions. Furthermore, the project researchers have identified and marked-up
                    relevant subjects in the fine rolls. Therefore, while the general mark-up in TEI
                    XML provides a framework for theoretical analysis and practical encoding of the
                    text of the calendar as it is being edited and summarised in English, the need
                    for additional modelling has emerged so as to: <list type="unordered"><item>associate textual instances of the same person, subject occurrence or
                            place to their correspondent logical authority —whether that be a
                            person (identified or anonymous), a subject class or a place;</item><item>express the mutual relationships between the relevant authorities
                            (e.g. individuals, locations, institutions and subjects).</item></list></p></div0><div0><head><emph>Why RDF/OWL?</emph></head><p>In previous work on projects requiring an expression of the associations between
                    sources in core texts marked up using TEI XML we have taken more traditional
                    approaches using XML structures or relational databases to solve the problem,
                    but have increasingly found these wanting. There has been some research in the
                    TEI community in this area lately, particularly around 'biographical and
                    prosopographical data'<note n="6"> See “Biographical and Prosopographical Data”.
                        In Sperberg-McQueen, C. M., and Burnard, Lou, eds. <title level="a">TEI P5
                            Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title>. <xptr to="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/html/ND.html#NDPERS" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/> (accessed 15 November 2006).</note>, but at
                    the time of writing this was not mature enough for us to make a commitment to
                    using it and in any case our attention was drawn to other standards whose main
                    objectives are closer to what we are trying to achieve.</p><p>After conducting a comparative evaluation of possible standards to create
                    authority lists structures that included research into RDF/OWL, Topic Maps and
                    MADS (Metadata Authority Description Schema), we opted for RDF/OWL.</p><p>The main reasons for this choice were the following:<note n="7">OWL is a language
                        developed on top of RDF by W3C to write ontologies. For W3C RDF
                        specifications on RDF see <xptr to="http://www.w3.org/RDF/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>. For an overview and further resources on OWL see <xptr to="http://www.w3.org/2001/sw/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note><list type="unordered"><item>RDF/OWL models provide a logical organisation of data together with
                            the possibility of a flexible manipulation of meanings (e.g. rich
                            expression of relationships among objects/entities mentioned in the
                            source text, where an object/entity might be a person, a place or a
                            subject);</item><item>RDF/OWL decreases ambiguity by identifying unique entities
                            independently from their instances in a decentralised way.</item></list></p><p>While the more practical advantages are that: <list type="unordered"><item>as a set of standards which are at the heart of the Semantic Web,
                            RDF/OWL is internationally recognised and supported - its models could
                            facilitate the interconnection between humanities computing projects in
                            general and between directly related data in particular;</item><item>there is a relatively good selection of tools for RDF/OWL compared
                            to the other technologies that we have explored;</item><item>RDF/OWL can be expressed in XML format, thus allowing the
                            re-purposing of data for web delivery (e.g. creation of indices through
                            the use of XSLT).</item></list></p></div0><div0><head><emph>Ontology: Structure, Tool and Delivery</emph></head><p>The RDF schema and OWL are used to define the knowledge domain around the core
                    materials on the project (the fine rolls) using classes and predicates. Already
                    existing predicates are used as extensively as possible (e.g. CIDOC-CRM, Dublin
                    Core, Friend of a Friend, Simple Knowledge Organization System).</p><p>The connection between the TEI source files and the ontology play an important
                    role in our model.<note n="8"> For a similar approach see Eide, Øyvind and Ore,
                        Christen-Emil. “TEI, CIDOC-CRM and a Possible Interface between the Two”
                        (paper presented at Digital Humanities 2006, Université Paris-Sorbonne, July
                        5-9, 2006) <xptr to="http://www.allc-ach2006.colloques.paris-sorbonne.fr/DHs.pdf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>.</note> Indeed the XML files not only feed
                    the ontology with some data (e.g. variants of a certain person name), but they
                    are themselves part of the ontological model. The fact that they exhibit names
                    and assert facts related to those names can be modelled in the ontology together
                    with the statement that a person name (proper name or in general reference
                    string) is associated to a specific person as an instance of the entity person
                    (e.g. that has a gender, a possible status etc.). Quoting Eide,<note n="9">Eide,
                        Øyvind. “The Exhibition Problem. A Real Life Example with a Suggested
                        Solution” (paper presented at Digital Humanities 2006, Université
                        Paris-Sorbonne, July 5-9, 2006) <xptr to="http://www.allc-ach2006.colloques.paris-sorbonne.fr/DHs.pdf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>.</note> we include “explicit statements of
                    the sources of the assertions exhibited in the text”: </p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">paper_196_ciula_1.jpg</xref></p><figDesc/></figure><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">paper_196_ciula_2.jpg</xref></p><figDesc/></figure><p>The concrete connection between the XML files and the ontology is maintained
                    through the use of identifiers, as in the example below:<lb/><hi rend="code">&lt;persName key="arsic_robert"&gt; Robert
                        Arsic &lt;/persName&gt; → &lt;frh3:Man
                        rdf:ID="arsic_robert"&gt; … &lt;/frh3:Man&gt;</hi></p><p>Evidently, the value and granularity of the ontology depends on various factors,
                    which include the richness of the source files themselves (e.g. how well do the
                    fine rolls express the reality of the roles/occupations in the thirteenth
                    century?), the specific interests of the researchers (e.g. in the types of fines
                    rather than in the amount of money they keep record of) and the definability of
                    the knowledge domain itself (as shown in the contrast between the identification
                    of individuals and the much more blurred identification of subjects).</p><p>In addition to expressing complex associations in an abstract intellectual sense,
                    it was also crucial to the project to create a system endowed with sophisticated
                    facilities for editing and final publication. We will describe our experience in
                    creating such tools, in particular taking into account such project requirements
                    as: <list type="unordered"><item>the facilities for managing/editing data: the addition of new
                            information, new classes/predicates/literal values; the definition of
                            relationships between entries, the possibility to merge instances of
                            classes or subclasses (e.g. while editing we may realise that person A
                            and B are actually the same);</item><item>the connection and synchronisation between the ontology structure
                            and data on the one hand, and the TEI source files on the other (e.g.
                            links from classes in authority list to actual references to those
                            classes as exhibited in the mark-up);</item><item>the facility to browse information alphabetically or categorised in
                            some way (e.g. by date, county, role, kind of relation) and to search
                            for particular associations as expressed in the ontology (e.g. all the
                            locations connected to the person called 'Robert Arsic' or all the
                            relatives of Robert Arsic).</item></list></p></div0><div0><head><emph>Conclusions</emph></head><p>In the case of the fine rolls (as is true of many projects involving complex
                    primary sources) it is not enough to mark-up an occurrence of a person name if
                    you wish to create complex indices or to create structured search functions.</p><p>Moreover, an authority-based approach is essential in order to make the resource
                    interoperable; external authority lists are needed to record information in a
                    systematic, comprehensive and possibly standardised way, so as to: <list type="unordered"><item>store additional information related to persons, places and subject
                            (exhibited and marked up as corresponding instances in the TEI XML
                            files);</item><item>make explicit the multiple connections between places, persons and
                            subjects;</item><item>merge or disambiguate identifications and eventually correct the
                            original mark-up of the rolls.</item></list></p><p>Our paper will describe how, for the Henry III Fine Rolls project, an RDF/OWL
                    ontology was used to model complex associations and how this has assisted the
                    project researchers in the interpretation of the material they are editing and
                    facilitated the production of a digital resource that will allow future users to
                    browse the material under different perspectives, to explore the relationships
                    among mentioned individuals, locations and subjects, and to foster new
                    understandings.</p></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><analytic><title level="a">Biographical and Prosopographical Data</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                                Interchange</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Sperberg-McQueen, C. M">C. M. Sperberg-McQueen</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Burnard, Lou">Lou Burnard</name></editor><imprint/></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-11-15" to="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/html/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Boot, Peter">Peter Boot</name></author><title level="a">Decoding Emblem Semantics</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">21(Supplement 1)</biblScope><date value="2006">2006</date><biblScope type="pages">15-27</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Ciula, Arianna">Arianna Ciula</name></author><title level="a">Searching the Fine Rolls: A Demonstration of the
                                Electronic Version</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Paper presented to the International Medieval Congress
                                2006, University of Leeds, July 10-13, 2003</title><imprint/></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Dryburgh, Paul">Paul Dryburgh</name></author><title level="a">Henry III Fine Rolls Project</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Paper presented to the Institute of Historical
                                Research, London , February 9, 2006</title><imprint/></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Poupeau, Gautier">Gautier Poupeau</name></author><title level="a">De l’index nominum à l’ontologie. Comment mettre en
                                lumière les réseaux sociaux dans les corpus historiques
                            numériques?</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Paper presented at Digital Humanities 2006, Université
                                Paris-Sorbonne, July 5-9, 2006</title><imprint/></monogr><note>Abstract available at <xptr to="http://www.allc-ach2006.colloques.paris-sorbonne.fr/DHs.pdf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>(accessed 15 November 2006).</note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Eide, Øyvind">Øyvind Eide</name></author><title level="a">The Exhibition Problem. A Real Life Example with a
                                Suggested Solution</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Paper presented at Digital Humanities 2006, Université
                                Paris-Sorbonne, July 5-9, 2006</title><imprint/></monogr><note>Abstract available at <xptr to="http://www.allc-ach2006.colloques.paris-sorbonne.fr/DHs.pdf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/> (accessed 15 November 2006).</note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Eide, Øyvind">Øyvind Eide</name></author><author><name reg="Ore, Christian-Emil">Christian-Emil Ore</name></author><title level="a">TEI, CIDOC-CRM and a Possible Interface between the
                            Two</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Paper presented at Digital Humanities 2006, Université
                                Paris-Sorbonne, July 5-9, 2006</title><imprint/></monogr><note>Abstract available at <xptr to="http://www.allc-ach2006.colloques.paris-sorbonne.fr/DHs.pdf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/> (accessed 15 November 2006).</note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Spence, Paul">Paul Spence</name></author><title level="a">The Henry III Fine Rolls Project</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Paper presented at Digital Humanities 2006, Université
                                Paris-Sorbonne, July 5-9, 2006</title><imprint/></monogr><note>Abstract available at <xptr to="http://www.allc-ach2006.colloques.paris-sorbonne.fr/DHs.pdf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/> (accessed 15 November 2006).</note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Tuohy, Conal">Conal Tuohy</name></author><title level="a">Using XML Topic Maps to Present TEI</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Paper presented at the 5th TEI Meeting, Sofia, Octobery 28-29, 2005</title><imprint/></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>