<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="poster_159_zafrin"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title><emph>RolandHT</emph> and Reconceiving the Notion of Corpus</title><author><name reg="Zafrin, Vika">Vika Zafrin</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>poster</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>corpus</item><item>encoding</item><item>RolandHT</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Vika Zafrin's rtf <date value="2007-04">April
                2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="RolandHT and Reconcieivng the Notion of Corpus"><titlePart type="main"><emph>RolandHT</emph> and Reconceiving the Notion of
                Corpus</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Zafrin, Vika">Vika Zafrin</name><address><addrLine>vika@wordsend.org</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Brown University</titlePart></front><body><div0><head><emph>RolandHT</emph></head><p>For the past several years I have been pursuing the study of a semi-fictional
                    character's manifestations in different art forms, throughout Europe and North
                    America, in the last thousand years. Roland is the protagonist of the French
                    epic <emph>Song of Roland</emph> and France's national hero. He first appeared
                    in written record at the end of the eleventh century, and hasn't left us since
                    then – although his character has undergone significant changes. He has easily
                    passed from one culture to another; but Roland is not merely borrowed – he is
                    mercurial. He has been used by writers and artists as a container for the
                    promotion of moral and political exigencies relevant to their circumstances.
                    Thus, in France he is a staunch protector of the Christian faith (<emph>Song of
                        Roland</emph>); in Germany, a religious martyr (Konrad); in Italy, a lover
                    and a comedic character (Boiardo, Ariosto); in England, a mystical traveler
                    (Browning); in the United States, a roadie (Silverstein) and a gunslinger
                    (King). </p><p>Nevertheless, the French Roland has easily identifiable personality traits, such
                    as his infamous pride (which cost him and twenty thousand of Charlemagne's best
                    men their lives) and his physical prowess. There are also artifacts, such as his
                    enchanted sword and his sounding horn that can be heard for miles. These
                    features have prompted me to make a case for the existence of a Roland corpus
                    that is held together by recurrent themes and imagery. In my dissertation titled
                        <emph>RolandHT</emph>I show these recurrences by encoding them in XML.<note n="1">The electronic part of the dissertation can be found at <xptr to="http://wordsend.org/rht/xml/index_2006.php"/>. N.B.: it is a work in
                        progress. New content is being added often. Please note also that the
                        project can only be viewed using Firefox/Mozilla or another XSLT-aware
                        browser.</note> This corpus has never been considered as a whole. An
                    examination of themes recurrent in it offers insight into the evolution of art
                    and the pace of intercultural transmission. This insight is relevant to the
                    study of literature at the dawn of Western secular writing; but it also sheds
                    light on our own literary present, in an age of widely accessible electronic
                    writing, when the processes of composition and transmission are changing again. </p><p>The Roland corpus consists of works in such diverse media as literature, live and
                    puppet theater, opera, sculpture and stone carvings, painting, film,
                    contemporary music, and comics. This presents a problem in my use of the word
                        <emph>corpus</emph>, which conforms to its theoretical definition but not to
                    any of its prior use in practice. I propose that the electronic medium, and
                    semantic encoding in particular, allow for the study of corpora bound not by
                    format or authorship, but by semantic content. </p><p><emph>RolandHT</emph> is a collection of excerpts from works that feature Roland,
                    encoded for recurring characters, imagery and themes. Some annotations are
                    present. Works span most of Europe and the United States, and date from between
                    the late 1090s to 1995. Most of the corpus objects are text-based – poems,
                    prose, drama, operatic lyrics. One particularly interesting corpus object – Greg
                    Roach's computer game <emph>The Madness of Roland</emph> – is a blend of text
                    and images. Other image-based corpus objects include comic-book panels and
                    photographs of medieval stonework found in France and Croatia. Included are also
                    excerpts from the 1999 film <emph>Beowulf</emph>, in QuickTime (.mov) format.
                    Other objects will be added as time and copyright restrictions allow.</p></div0><div0><head>Technical Details</head><p>The project is processed for web presentation using XSLT, JavaScript and CSS. The
                    website is a technical collaboration with Ethan Fremen.</p><p>Our approach is standards- and client-based. All features except bookmarking can
                    be used with static files accessed locally. This permits <emph>RolandHT</emph>
                    to be archived on a CD, DVD or other storage device; access to a networked
                    server is not necessary to view the work. This is an advantage for the purposes
                    of submitting a doctoral thesis, but being entirely client-side, our method
                    would not scale well: a substantially larger corpus will require an XML database
                    in order to remain efficient. As it stands, the roughly 800KB XML file
                    containing all text data (but not the separately-stored images or multimedia
                    files) must be loaded entirely before the project is viewed, rendering it
                    unwieldy for slow connections if <emph>RolandHT</emph> is accessed over the web.
                    However, once it is loaded, subsequent operations are performed client-side and
                    connection speed no longer matters, except when fetching the aforementioned
                    images and multimedia files. </p></div0><div0><head>The notion of corpus</head><p>The notion of <emph>corpus</emph> is used in the study of languages (corpus
                    linguistics), literature, and objects (architecture, archaeology). Definitions
                    of <emph>_corpus_</emph> provided by several different dictionaries of English
                    and of literary terms are variations of "a related 'body' of writings, usually
                    sharing the same author or subject-matter." (Baldick 52) It is almost never
                    further defined in the context of specific studies. Instead, <emph>corpus</emph>
                    is taken for granted, and is found far more often in headings than in
                    discussion. When it is used in the text itself, the set of objects under
                    consideration invariably has an author, time period and/or geographical area in
                    common. None of these things can usefully delimit the Roland corpus. However,
                    some past uses of <emph>corpus</emph> would justify the use of the word to
                    describe works about Roland. </p><p>Most often the contested word is used in corpus linguistics. One book in
                    particular defines <emph>corpus</emph> as "a subset of an ETL [electronic text
                    library], built according to explicit design criteria for a specific purpose."
                    (Ghadessy et al. 179) This is the only non-dictionary definition I have found,
                    and if we substitute "Western artistic production" for "ETL," it becomes
                    relevant to the construction of <emph>RolandHT</emph>. The purpose of defining
                    it is to shed light on how its protagonist has survived so unusually long while
                    at the same time undergoing fundamental changes. However, the subjective nature
                    of the definition process demands a willingness to alter design criteria as
                    texts are encoded, and a leap of faith that scholars may be reluctant to make.
                    Working with a semantically encoded body of work requires acceptance of XML as a
                    valid format for making a scholarly argument. This in turn calls for critical
                    responses that are also at least partly expressed in XML. ("I disagree with this
                    encoding. How about this alternative instead?") </p><p>Roland is a flexible corpus that emerges and evolves in the course of its
                    analysis. Its unifying subject may be a default connecting thread by virtue of
                    Roland's name, but since the actual connecting threads are recurrent themes and
                    imagery, the way to ascertain a work's status as a corpus object (or not) is a
                    close reading of it. In this case, micro-results of the close reading are
                    recorded by XML encoding.</p><p>The above describes a practical application of Gregory Ulmer's theory of
                    heuretics. In his 1994 <title level="m">Heuretics: The Logic of
                    Invention</title>, Ulmer states that theory is assimilated into the humanities
                    in two principal ways: by critical interpretation and by artistic experiment.
                    Heuretics is the latter – it is a heuristic approach to theory, a reading
                    process that, instead of attempting to theorize "what might be the meaning of an
                    existing work," guides "a generative experiment: Based on a given theory, how
                    might another text be composed?" (5) </p><p>Why not use words that have been used more frequently to describe Roland, such as
                        <emph>myth</emph> or <emph>legend</emph>? Both of these terms imply
                    homogeneity that the corpus does not possess, and deny Roland's historicity,
                    however tenuous. Similarly, the terms closest to <emph>corpus</emph> –
                        <emph>oeuvre</emph> and <emph>canon</emph> – are limiting to the point of
                    inaccuracy: the Roland corpus has too many authors to be called oeuvre and too
                    little institutionalized authority to be a canon. </p><p>Finally, <emph>RolandHT</emph> is not an archive. It does not strive for
                    completeness, either within single works (only excerpts are presented) or within
                    the corpus (which is, to date, representative but incomplete). More importantly,
                        <emph>RolandHT</emph> is intended to be the opposite of a static collection
                    of unchanging documents; its primary-source contents, encoding and annotations
                    are all meant to change as research progresses. </p></div0><div0><head>Summary</head><p>If semantic encoding is to be taken seriously as a research tool by philologists,
                    art historians and other humanists used to working in more traditional ways, a
                    common language must first be built and justified. At Digital Humanities 2007 I
                    hope to contribute to the effort of expanding the inflluence of digital research
                    methods into mainstream humanities. I will do this by expanding the notion of
                        <emph>corpus</emph> to include bodies of works that, because of their
                    disparate formats, do not lend themselves to formal study using traditional
                    methods.</p></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Ariosto, Ludovico">Ludovico Ariosto</name></author><title level="m">Orlando Furioso; Selections from the Translation of Sir
                                John Harrington</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Gottfried, Rudolf">Rudolf Gottfried</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace><publisher>Indiana University Press</publisher><date value="1963">1963</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Baldick, Chris">Chris Baldick</name></author><title level="m">The Concise Oxford Dictionary of Literary Terms</title><imprint><pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace><publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher><date value="2004">2004</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><title level="m">Beowulf</title><respStmt><resp>Dir.</resp><name reg="Baker, Graham">Graham Baker</name></respStmt><respStmt><resp>Perfs.</resp><name reg="Lambert, Christopher">Perfs. Christopher Lambert</name><name reg="Mitra, Rhona">Rhona Mitra</name><name reg="Cotton, Oliver">Oliver Cotton</name><name reg="Otto, Götz">Götz Otto</name></respStmt><edition>DVD</edition><imprint><publisher>Panorama Entertainment</publisher><date value="1999">1999</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Boiardo, Matteo Maria">Matteo Maria Boiardo</name></author><title level="m">Orlando Innamorato</title><respStmt><resp>Trans.</resp><name reg="Ross, Charles Stanley">Charles Stanley Ross</name></respStmt><imprint><pubPlace>Berkley, CA</pubPlace><publisher>University of California Press</publisher><date value="1989">1989</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Browning, Robert">Robert Browning</name></author><title level="a">Childe Roland to the Dark Tower Came</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">English Poetry Full-Text Database</title><imprint><pubPlace>Cambridge, UK</pubPlace><publisher>Chadwick-Healey Ltd</publisher></imprint></monogr><note>Accessed 2004-03-26.</note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="King, Stephen">Stephen King</name></author><title level="m">Dark Tower I-VII</title><imprint><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>Signet</publisher><publisher>Scribner</publisher><date value="1989-2003">1989-2003</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Konrad, Der Pfaffe">Der Pfaffe Konrad</name></author><title level="m">Priest Konrad's Song of Roland</title><respStmt><resp>Trans.</resp><name reg="Thomas, J. W.">J. W. Thomas</name></respStmt><imprint><pubPlace>Columbia, SC</pubPlace><publisher>Camden House</publisher><date value="1994">1994</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Roach, Greg">Greg Roach</name></author><title level="m">Madness of Roland</title><edition>CD-ROM</edition><imprint><pubPlace>Los Angeles, CA</pubPlace><publisher>HyperBole Studios</publisher><date value="1995">1995</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Silverstein, Shel">Shel Silverstein</name></author><title level="a">Roland the Roadie And Gertrude the Groupie</title></analytic><monogr><respStmt><resp>Perf.</resp><name>Dr. Hook and the Medicine Show</name></respStmt><title level="m">Belly Up!</title><imprint><publisher>CBS</publisher><date value="1973">1973</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><title level="m">Small Corpus Studies and ELT: Theory and Practice</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Ghadessy, Mohsen">Mohsen Ghadessy</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Henry, Alex">Alex Henry</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Roseberry, Robert L."> Robert L. Roseberry</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace><publisher>J. Benjamins Pub. Co.</publisher><date value="2001">2001</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><title level="m">The Song of Roland</title><respStmt><resp>Trans.</resp><name reg="Sayers, Dorothy L.">Dorothy L. Sayers</name></respStmt><imprint><pubPlace>Harmondsworth, UK</pubPlace><publisher>Penguin Books</publisher><date value="1957">1957</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Ulmer, Gregory L.">Gregory L. Ulmer</name></author><title level="m">Heuretics: The Logic of Invention</title><imprint><pubPlace>Baltimore, MD</pubPlace><publisher>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher><date value="1994">1994</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>