<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="poster_150_lavrentiev"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>BFM Old French Text Corpus: Current State and Prospective Developments</title><author><name reg="Lavrentiev, Alexei">Alexei Lavrentiev</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>poster</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>diachronical corpus</item><item>French linguistics</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Alexei Lavrentiev's text <date value="2007-04">April
                    2007</date></item><item>SAS: Revised incorporating Lavrentiev's revisions<date value="2007-05">May 2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="BFM Old French Text Corpus: Current State and Prospective Developments"><titlePart type="main">BFM Old French Text Corpus: Current State and Prospective
                    Developments</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Lavrentiev, Alexei">Alexei Lavrentiev</name><address><addrLine>Alexei.Lavrentev@ens-lsh.fr</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Ecole Normale Supérieure Lettres et Sciences
            humaines</titlePart></front><body><div0><p>The BFM (<emph>Base de Français Médiéval</emph>) Old French Corpus was founded
                    in 1989 by Prof. Ch. Marchello-Nizia, and its compilation continues.
                    Céline Guillot has been the project leader since 2006. At present, the main
                    corpus, BFM1, includes 74 complete Old and Middle French texts (approx. 3 000
                    000 words).</p><p>The texts included in the BFM cover a considerable geographic area and an
                    extensive time span, with texts from the 9th century (including the
                    first known French text, the <title level="m">Serments de Strasbourg</title>) to the end of
                    the 15th century. Both verse and prose texts are represented, as well as
                    different domains and genres.</p><p>The initial aim of the project was to provide scholars with reliable text data on
                    the oldest period of the history of the French language. It was meant to
                    complement the Middle French Text database (14th and 15th centuries) and
                    FRANTEXT database (16th – 21st centuries), both developed in Nancy by the ATILF
                    laboratory. However a number of Middle French texts have been added to the
                    database for different projects.</p><p>By now, about 50 theses and a significant number of research books and articles
                    have been prepared with the use of the BFM.</p><p>All texts in the main corpus are digitized critical editions. The choice to use
                    editions, and not manuscript transcriptions, was made in order to create an
                    extensive corpus in a relatively short period of time: transcribing a manuscript
                    requires much more time and funds than digitizing a modern edition. However, a
                    subcorpus of manuscript transcriptions is being developed. One of its aims is to
                    provide a precise evaluation of the reliability of critical editions as a source
                    of data for different kinds of linguistic research. In general we argue that
                    using editions or manuscripts are complementary and not mutually exclusive
                    approaches to creating old text corpora (cf. Heiden &amp; Lavrentiev 2004).</p><p>All BFM texts are XML encoded with the tags recommended by the TEI. However some
                    of them contain only a very limited markup (headers with some metadata and page
                    breaks or lines in verse for reference purposes). A richer TEI encoding is
                    applied to a little more than a half of the BFM texts. Its principles are
                    described in (Heiden &amp; Guillot 2002) and a complete description is
                    available at the BFM website.</p><p>The BFM texts are not directly accessible to users. They can be searched by means
                    of precise queries (e.g., discrete lexical items, word and phrase concordances,
                    co-occurrences, statistical analyses, etc.) via Weblex search and analysis
                    engine (using CQP query language).</p><p>At present, several directions have been chosen for the development of the BFM.</p><p>The first direction is concerned with the elaboration of precise text typology,
                    which is necessary to evaluate the representativeness of a text database, a
                    crucial question for all corpus studies. The texts in the BFM are characterized
                    by a number of variables, such as the date, the region, the author, the domain,
                    the genre, etc. The definition of almost each variable is in fact connected with
                    a number of methodological and technical issues. The date can be for instance
                    that of the original text composition or that of the manuscript. Author’s age
                    can also be a factor to take into consideration. Only approximate dating is
                    available for many texts and manuscripts.</p><p>Domain and genre are the main variables that contribute to characterizing the
                    reprensentativeness of a corpus (cf. Lee 2001). It is however extremely
                    difficult to set a unified genre taxonomy valid over a number of centuries. Many
                    texts belong simultaneously to several domains (e.g. religious and literary,
                    historical and literary).</p><p>To deal with this complexity, most of the variables have been encoded by means of
                    multiple fields in the metadata database. Depending on the nature of a query,
                    these can be used in different ways. If the aim of the query is to get a list of
                    texts corresponding to certain criteria, “informal” fields with keyword value
                    type can be used. If the aim is to “cut” the corpus for some kind of contrastive
                    analysis, a unique value is selected for each text on the basis of a formal
                    procedure. If the aim is to place a text in a multidimensional typological
                    environment, it is necessary to model the relations between the different values
                    of a variable and to quantify these values.</p><p>The work on text typology in the BFM is in progress, and we will present its
                    current state by the time of the conference.</p><p>Another direction in the BFM development is its linguistic annotation. A few
                    texts have been morphologically tagged in a semi-manual mode (with SATO software
                    developed by François Daoust at the University of Québec in Montréal). A
                    complete automatic morphological annotation optimized on the basis of text
                    typology is currently envisaged. Annotation of particular linguistic features
                    (e.g. semantic features of demonstrative adjectives) is conducted in the
                    framework of related linguistic research projects.</p><p>The development of the BFM is closely related to that of Weblex. A completely new
                    platform making possible personalized corpus creation and online annotation is
                    under construction.</p><p>An important effort is being made to work out consensual text encoding and
                    description procedures with the other projects of diachronic French corpora. The
                    TEI Recommendations are in fact too general to ensure real corpora
                    interoperability. A Consortium for Medieval French Corpora (CCFM) was created in
                    2004 with the purpose of consolidating efforts of different projects. The BFM
                    team participates in this consortium along with <emph>Laboratoire de français
                        ancien</emph> (University of Ottawa), DMF team (ATILF laboratory, Nancy,
                    France), University of Stuttgart (Germany), University of Zürich (Switzerland),
                    Anglo-Norman Dictionary project (UK) and others.</p></div0><div0><head>Web</head><note>BFM: <xptr to="http://bfm.ens-lsh.fr" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note><lb/><note>Weblex: <xptr to="http://weblex.ens-lsh.fr/wlx/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Heiden, S.">S. Heiden</name></author><author><name reg="Guillot, C.">C. Guillot</name></author><title level="a">Capitalisation des savoirs par le web: une application
                                de la TEI pour l’encodage et l’exploitation des textes de la Base de
                                Français Médiéval</title></analytic><monogr><editor><name reg="Kunstmann, Pierre">Pierre Kunstmann</name></editor><editor><name reg="Martineau, France">France Martineau</name></editor><editor><name reg="Forget, Danielle">Danielle Forget</name></editor><title level="m">Ancien et moyen français sur le Web, enjeux
                                méthodologiques et analyse du discours</title><imprint><pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace><publisher>Les éditions David</publisher><date value="2002">2002</date><biblScope type="pages">77-92</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Heiden, S.">S. Heiden</name></author><author><name reg="Lavrentiev, A.">A. Lavrentiev</name></author><title level="a">Ressources électroniques pour l’étude des textes
                                médiévaux: approches et outils</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Revue française de linguistique appliquée</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">IX.1</biblScope><date value="2004">2004</date><biblScope type="pages">99-118</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Lee, David Y. W.">David Y. W. Lee</name></author><title level="a">Genres, Registers, Text Types, Domains and Styles:
                                Clarifying the Concepts and Navigating a Path Through the BNC
                            Jungle</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Language Learning &amp; Technology</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">5.3</biblScope><date value="2001">2001</date><biblScope type="pages">37-72</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>