<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="poster_209_krowne"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Semantic Clustering in the Wild</title><author><name reg="Krowne, Aaron">Aaron Krowne</name></author><author><name reg="Hickcox, Alice">Alice Hickcox</name></author><author><name reg="Ingram, Stephan">Stephan Ingram</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Field, Hana S.">Hana S. Field</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>poster</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>semantic clustering</item><item>NMF</item><item>text clustering</item><item>digital libraries</item><item>collection development</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list><item>HSF: Created from Aaron P. Krowne's text<date value="2007-04">April
                    2007</date></item><item>SAS: Revised <date value="2007-05">May 2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Semantic Clustering in the Wild"><titlePart type="main">Semantic Clustering in the Wild</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Krowne, Aaron">Aaron Krowne</name><address><addrLine>akrowne@emory.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Emory Univeristy</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Hickcox, Alice">Alice Hickcox</name><address><addrLine>alice.hickcox@emory.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Emory University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Ingram, Stephan">Stephan Ingram</name><address><addrLine>frowey@gmail.com</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Emory University</titlePart></front><body><div0><head>Problem Space and Context</head><p>The Southern Changes Digital Archive is a digital collection of 25 years of
                    Southern Changes, a publication of the Southern Regional Council.<note n="1">
                        Southern Regional Council <xptr to="http://southerncouncil.org" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note> The Beck Center of Woodruff Library has digitized the issues of Southern
                    Changes and made them available as a fully searchable text archive. <note n="2">Southern Changes Digital Archive <xptr to="http://beck.library.emory.edu/southernchanges/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note> The collection consists of 25 volumes, over 100 issues, containing
                    nearly 1000 articles.</p><p>Emory University is participating in the Digital Library Federation's Aquifer
                    Project and the Southern Changes Digital Archive is one of the bodies of work
                    that we proposed to include. As we inspected the elements of the MODS Aquifer
                        schema,<note n="3">Aquifer MODS Guidelines <xptr to="http://www.diglib.org/aquifer/dlfmodsimplementationguidelines_finalnov2006.pdf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note> it became clear to us that every item in the metadata collection would
                    end up with identical labeling, since the collection lacked subject assignments
                    for the individual articles.</p><p>Thus, the challenge that we faced, in order to make this material useful to users
                    of the MODS-Aquifer metadata, was to assign subject classifications to each of
                    the articles in the collection with some level of automation and a minimum level
                    of human intervention (given the ~1000 individual articles). We also realized
                    that this undertaking would help to make the collection more browseable by
                    providing a subject-based access point into the digital library. To achieve
                    these ends, we turned to the tools and techniques developed on the MetaCombine
                    project here at Emory.</p></div0><div0><head>Semantic Clustering in the DL Production Environment</head><p>Semantic clustering is the notion of using computing techniques to group formerly
                    unorganized artifacts based on latent aspects of meaning. For library
                    information, this translates into grouping texts and metadata records by their
                    inherent “topics.” Semantic clustering techniques have come far in recent years,
                    and hold great promise for enriching many information applications. However,
                    there is a wide gulf between the state-of-the-art research in this area, and its
                    uptake in real-world applications.</p><p>A major reason for this disjunct is that research systems for semantic clustering
                    (and related techniques such as classification) are not fit for the production
                    environment: they are too ad hoc, too brittle, too encumbered by intellectual
                    property constraints, too specialized, poorly organized, and they typically
                    require programming to deploy in the local computing environment and adapt into
                    situational use.</p><p>But there is another factor that is more interesting for this study: that the
                    automated aspect of semantic clustering covers only part of the production
                    process; as we found on the MetaCombine <note n="4">MetaCombine project site
                    <xptr to="http://www.metacombine.org/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note>
                    project (and which many others confirm), some human refinement is always
                    needed. However, tools and facilities which mesh the automatic with the manual
                    to perform this refinement seem to be unavailable.</p><p>In sum, there exist few (if any) turnkey systems that are accessible to digital
                    librarians which allow the integration of semantic clustering into the DL
                    environment.</p><p>We began taking steps to address these problems on the MetaCombine project, by
                    adding to core semantic clustering systems a some HTML-based report, a visual
                    browsing application and a “scheme editing” system. All of these systems
                    operated on the "raw" outputs of semantic clustering, and served to help
                    comprehend, navigate, and (in the case of the latter) manually refine the
                    output.</p><p>The central specific problems we found with semantic clustering results in
                    MetaCombine <note n="5">MetaCombine Final Report
                     <xptr to="http://www.metacombine.org/reports/project/MetaCombine-Final-Report.pdf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note> were:<list type="unordered"><item>redundant clusters</item><item>confusing and otherwise "rough" cluster descriptors (labels)</item><item>spurious clusters</item><item>questionable classifications</item></list></p><p>The scheme editor was created to allow the revision of a cluster hierarchy to
                    ameliorate the above issues, helping to make it a more true category (or
                    subject) hierarchy, fit for end-use applications (such as subject tagging and
                    subject-based browsing).</p><p>We have now begun the process of using these tools to work semantic clustering
                    techniques into production digital library services. The focus of the present
                    paper is one of these real-world test cases: the Southern Changes collection and
                    digital library. However, key for our investigation is that the library
                    production environment itself is a major point of interest; thus this work
                    represents more of an exploration of the application of the MetaCombine tools to
                    this environment, rather than another quantitative test of clustering or
                    classification accuracy for the particular algorithmic kernel.</p></div0><div0><head>Our Study</head><p>We have approached the Southern Changes clustering investigation as an informal
                    study. This is both because the needs of the Southern Changes project are
                    practical and because this investigation does not have the scale to have the
                    form of a controlled experiment or series of experiments.</p><p>The structure of the study is:<list type="ordered"><item>interface the collection with the clustering system</item><item>perform clustering with a variety of parameter settings</item><item>explore and refine output in MetaCombine tools (HTML reports, scheme
                            editor, visual viewer).</item><item>implement refinements to clustering (tweak parameters, fix bugs)</item><item>implement refinements to MetaCombine tools programs</item><item>go to step 2.</item></list></p><p>The study thus has an iterative nature and is open-ended, and as we go through
                    these iterations, we are learning much about the nature of clustering and the
                    contextualization of the task in the digital library environment. As indicated
                    above, our clustering tools are also evolve throughout, moving beyond research
                    to practice.</p><p>The insights gleaned from this process form the core of our reporting for this
                    forum. The types of items we intend to report on, along with initial impressions
                    include (but are not limited to): <list type="unordered"><item>The utility of the scheme editor, HTML reports, and other tools</item></list></p><p>Thus far, these tools have proven quite useful for determining the latent topics
                    discovered by the clustering engine, and give a basic level of understanding of
                    what kind of documents are assigned to each. However, it remains difficult to
                    get a more complete or holistic sense of how well a large number of documents
                    has been assigned.</p><p><list type="unordered"><item>The difficulty of deploying the tools</item></list></p><p>Thus far, the difficulty is moderate, for a librarian with some programming
                    experience. Some problems in deployment of the scheme editor tool were isolated
                    and future distributions will have fixed them; so the difficulty level is
                    improving.</p><p>We have not broached the topic of re-deploying the clustering kernel itself for
                    this project. However, this may not ultimately be necessary, as we are pursuing
                    a federated model for this and other metadata enhancement services.</p><p><list type="unordered"><item>The utility of clustering itself</item></list></p><p>Flat (one-level) clustering seems to do quite well with the right parameters and
                    with the documents for which there is the most confidence. Fidelity seems to
                    deteriorate rapidly for hierarchical clustering past the first level (with the
                    first of two hierarchical clustering methods), though it is still unclear if
                    this is more a result of the collection or the clustering system. Our second
                    method of hierarchical clustering needs further development to be fully
                    evaluated in end-use.</p><p>We believe we have established that the multiclassification functionality of the
                    system is extremely useful; as topical ambiguity is compensated for by the
                    multiple labels. This makes intuitive sense, as there typically is no single
                    categorization for an interdisciplinary humanities article.</p><p>It appears significant work needs to be done in thresholding classification
                    assignments, as well as making the determination of if and when confidence is
                    high enough to consider a record “classified”.</p><p><list type="unordered"><item>The feasibility of integrating outputs of clustering into production
                            systems</item></list></p><p>As described in more detail below, we believe there will be little difficulty in
                    utilizing the outputs of this system, once we have determined that output is
                    satisfactory.</p><p>Given the proliferation of XML handling tools, at minimum, our current, simple
                    XML format for representing a clustered collection organization should be easily
                    translatable into our existing digital library system. The most challenging part
                    may in fact prove to be combining the generated subject tags with the existing
                    TEI metadata structure.</p></div0><div0><head>Implementation Plans</head><p>The results of the clustering are XML files that contain the renamed category,
                    associated with the article by means of the id attribute assigned to the
                    article. We will apply an XSLT transform to add an attribute that indicates the
                    subject(s) assigned to each article, using the TEI "ana" attribute. We can then
                    harvest the records with the subject information, and as a further step, add a
                    subject browsing capability to the web site, using the "interpGrp/interp"
                    elements. This will enable dynamically generated categories for searching and
                    browsing.</p></div0><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_209_krowne_1.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 1:</figDesc></figure></body></text></TEI.2>