<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="paper_179_furuta"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Viewing Texts: An Art-Centered Representation of Picasso’s Writings</title><author><name reg="Audenaert, Neal">Neal Audenaert</name></author><author><name reg="Karadkar, Unmil">Unmil Karadkar</name></author><author><name reg="Mallen, Enrique">Enrique Mallen</name></author><author><name reg="Furuta, Richard">Richard Furuta</name></author><author><name reg="Tonner, Sarah">Sarah Tonner</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Field, Hana S.">Hana S. Field</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>paper</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>Picasso</item><item>texts and images</item><item>information presentation</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list><item>HSF: Created from Richard Furuta's doc<date value="2007-04">April
                    2007</date></item><item>SAS: Revised <date value="2007-05">May 2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Viewing Texts: An Art-Centered Representation of Picasso’s Writings"><titlePart type="main">Viewing Texts: An Art-Centered Representation of Picasso’s
                    Writings</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Audenaert, Neal">Neal Audenaert</name><address><addrLine>neal@csdl.tamu.edul</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Texas A&amp;M University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Karadkar, Unmil">Unmil Karadkar</name><address><addrLine>unmil@csdi.tamu.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Texas A&amp;M University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Mallen, Enrique">Enrique Mallen</name><address><addrLine>e-mallen@tamu.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Texas A&amp;M University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Furuta, Richard">Richard Furuta</name><address><addrLine>furuta@cs.tamu.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Texas A&amp;M University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Tonner, Sarah">Sarah Tonner</name><address><addrLine>sarahtonner1@yahoo.com</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Texas A&amp;M University</titlePart></front><body><div0><head>Introduction</head><p>The <emph>Picasso Project</emph> is a web-based, dynamic <emph>catalogue raisonné</emph>currently containing digital images and descriptive metadata for more
                    than 11,000 of Picasso’s works (Mallen, 2006). The catalogue includes commentary
                    for many artworks, along with notes detailing sales of the item, exhibitions in
                    which it has been displayed, and scholarly literature in which it has been
                    cited. In addition to these works, the catalogue also provides extensive
                    biographical information including nearly 7,500 entries. The biography is linked
                    to artworks, photographs of key people, maps of the various places Picasso lived
                    and worked, and related documents (for example, Picasso’s birth certificate).
                    Tools are provided to support side-by-side comparisons of two artworks and to
                    build custom subcollections from which an illustrated, color catalogue can be
                    automatically generated for printing. Within this context, we have become
                    increasingly interested in exploring Picasso’s writings which have, until
                    recently, been largely neglected in favor of his more well known work in
                    painting, sculpture, and collage.</p><p>Picasso, first and foremost an artist, wrote texts that are strikingly visual,
                    both in terms of the design of the texts themselves, as well as the decorative
                    elements that adorn the pages on which these texts are found. These intensely
                    visual writings present his editor with significant challenges—challenges that
                    exemplify the TEI consortium's guidelines for when TEI should not be used
                    (Lavagnino, 2006). As Lavagnino points out, "to make the [TEI] edition work as
                    intended it is generally necessary to interpret features and not merely
                    reproduce their appearance." Picasso's writings do not readily yield to a single
                    fixed interpretation that can be understood by an editor and transcribed in some
                    definitive form. Indeed, their interest stems, in part, from their complex and
                    indeterminate nature. Furthermore, transcription involves the selection of
                    relevant features of a work and production of a digital (text plus encoding)
                    description of them. In cases where this digital description has little value
                    for analysis, alternative forms of presentation must be pursued. The two
                    examples of this cited by Lavagnino, "works intended as mixtures of words and
                    images, and very complex draft manuscripts in which the sequence of text or
                    inscription is difficult to make out," are both characteristic of Picasso's
                    writings.</p><p>Despite these difficulties, there have been a number of efforts to produce
                    transcriptions of Picasso’s writings as published books (Bernadac, 1998;
                    Michaël, 2005). This approach gives primacy to the textual content of these
                    works, at the expense of losing almost all of the visual elements. To remedy
                    this, most editions include facsimile reproductions of illustrative samples of
                    his writings alongside the transcriptions. While this is helpful in conveying a
                    sense of the original context of these works, it remains inadequate for many
                    purposes. Beyond limitations of scale (it is only feasible to include a limited
                    number of facsimiles), this approach treats the literal textual elements of
                    Picasso’s writings as 
                    <figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">paper_179_furuta_1.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 1: Two of Picasso's intensely visual texts.</figDesc></figure> primary, bringing in the images of the original, visually constructed
                    pages in order to illustrate and elaborate. This approach to remediate the
                    writings of Picasso divorces Picasso the writer from Picasso the artist,
                    limiting the productive interchange of ideas that might result from a blending
                    of literary and art history-based approaches.</p><p>While Picasso’s writings provide a compelling example of the limitations of a
                    purely textual approach to representing manuscripts and other documents, this
                    problem is not unique. Within the digital textual studies community there is an
                    increasing recognition of the need to pair robust text encoding with access to
                    images of the original source material (Dicks, 1997; McGann, 2001). Over the
                    past decade, a number of projects have focused on presenting documents as images
                    while providing additional support via transcriptions (McGann, 1996; Viscomi,
                    2002). Others have supplemented textually-oriented systems by providing access
                    to digitized images of the original documents in a variety of formats (Furuta,
                    2001; Robinson, 1996). Image based representations of documents have placed
                    particular strain on hierarchical methods for representing and encoding the
                    features of a text and alternative formal models have been proposed (Dekhtyar,
                    2006; Renear, Durand, and Mylonas, 1993).</p></div0><div0><head>Approach</head><p>Within the <emph>Picasso Project</emph>, we have encountered the
                    problem of developing digital representations of texts from a different
                    perspective than that found in either print based transcriptions or in digital
                    textual projects—namely, we have treated Picasso’s writings, first as works of
                    art, and secondarily as art that contains text. By conceiving of and
                    contextualizing the writings of Picasso in a form common to traditional
                    approaches to art (that is, the <emph>catalogue raisonné</emph>)
                    we are able to reap immediate benefits for understanding these texts in ways not
                    readily supported by the tools grounded in a textual approach to these works.
                    This approach to visualizing Picasso's texts places them squarely within the
                    context of the other works that he was painting and thinking about at the same
                    time. This helps inform our understanding of both the artworks that Picasso
                    produced as well as his writings. For example, Figure 2 shows a typical
                    thumbnail view of the last fifteen items in the catalogue for the year 1935. In
                    the poem in the center of the last line (OPP.35:004), Picasso refers to a small
                    girl. In the context of drawings made by Picasso around the same time we see
                    connections with Picasso’s daughter, Maya, at three and three and a half months
                    old (OPP.35:031 and OPP.35:032), followed by Marie-Thérèse, Maya’s mother
                    (OPP.35:034). Similarly, using the comparison tool to compare a text dated 28
                    November 1935 with a painting made earlier that year highlights possible
                    connections between verbal imagery of the text and the visual imagery of the
                    painting. References in the text to "tongue of fire," "stabbing," and "the eye
                    of the bull" take on new meanings when seen in this context.</p><p>In addition to visually contextualizing writings in relationship to Picasso’s
                    other works, the digital <emph>catalogue raisonné</emph> (unlike
                    a corresponding print version) allows us to make accessible images of Picasso’s
                    writings suitable for reading and analysis. Closer examinations of the text
                    enables scholars to consider multiple states of a text, to see annotations,
                    deletions, and additions to a text, to explore Picasso’s use of color to provide
                    structural divisions or graphical bars rather than traditional punctuation to
                    divide conceptual segments of the text. These tasks, which are difficult or
                    impossible to perform</p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">paper_179_furuta_2.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 2: la petite fille" with drawings of Maya and
                    Marie-Thérèse</figDesc></figure><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">paper_179_furuta_3.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 3: Courses de taureaux and "lengua de fuego"</figDesc></figure><p>using transcriptions alone, are encouraged by the online presentation. To further
                    enable access to the textual component of these works, we are initially adding
                    transcriptions of these texts to the biographical section of the catalogue.
                    Since the online catalogue presents the biographical text in parallel with the
                    artworks, this technique permits easy cross-referencing between the
                    transcriptions and images while we investigate more sophisticated means for
                    encoding and presenting the content of these writings.</p></div0><div0><head>Implications and Future Work</head><p>Framing our approach to Picasso’s writings in terms of artworks that contain
                    text, encourages us to look for text in artworks in general. Like many other
                    artists of his day, Picasso began incorporating words into his artworks in a
                    variety of ways and forms, notably in the newspaper clippings pasted into his
                        <emph>papiers-collés</emph>. These works reinforce our
                    conviction that we need develop tools for working with text in art grounded to
                    the needs of the artistic disciplines rather than those of the traditional
                    textual studies community.</p><p>Picasso's unique works offer fertile ground for exploring the techniques and
                    tools that can be applied to visually constructed texts but much work is
                    needed—both in terms of understanding the needs of the scholars and other
                    readers interested in Picasso’s writings as well as formulating new models for
                    representing and working with these texts in a digital environment. We are
                    currently investigating the potential for techniques based in spatial hypertext
                    research for interpreting and presenting these texts. In spatial hypertext,
                    Figure 3: Courses de taureaux and "lengua de fuego" nodes of information that
                    are connected by visual elements (for example, text style, 2-D position, color)
                    rather than by explicit links (Shipman, 1999). Our current efforts are focused
                    in understanding how the texts might be sub-divided into their constituent parts
                    and manipulated in a 2-D space in ways that enhance understanding. We are also
                    looking at how formal relationships between these parts can be incrementally
                    added as an expression of an editor/reader's evolving understanding. In addition
                    to purely image based approaches, we are interested in studying methods of
                    encoding the textual content of Picasso's works to support content based
                    retrieval, enable automatic processing, and facilitate reading.</p><div1><head>Summary</head><p>By translating a traditional print-based approach for working with a large
                        corpus of artworks, the <emph>catalogue raisonné</emph>, into
                        a digital format, we increase the level of support provided for three
                        scholarly primitives (Unsworth, 2000): comparing (either two works side by
                        side, or many works in a thumbnail view), sampling select artworks from the
                        collection as a whole, and representing the artworks not merely as
                        thumbnails, but also with higher resolution images. With these enhancements,
                        the digital <emph>catalogue raisonné</emph>, though not its
                        printed counter-part, provides a natural medium for presenting the writings
                        of Picasso. In this context, his writings are presented against the backdrop
                        of other artworks while enabling the textual elements of these artworks to
                        be read and carefully studied as texts. In addition to the immediate
                        benefits that this approach brings in terms of accessing Picasso’s writings,
                        it also offers a new paradigm for working with these texts that suggests
                        several promising directions for further work.</p></div1></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><monogr><title level="m">Picasso: Collected Writings</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Bernadac, M. L.">M. L. Bernadac</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>Aurum Press Ltd</publisher><date value="1989">1989</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Dekhtyar, Alex, et al.">Alex Dekhtyar et al</name></author><title level="a">Support for XML Markup of Image-based Electronic
                                Editions</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">International Journal on Digital Libraries</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">6.1</biblScope><date value="2006">2006</date><biblScope type="pages">55-69</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Dicks, R. S.">R. S. Dicks</name></author><title level="a">Third Commentary on “What is Text Really?”</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">SIGDOC Asterisk J. Computer Documentation </title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">21.3</biblScope><date value="1997">1997</date><biblScope type="pages">36-39</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Furuta, Richard, et al.">Richard Furuta, et al.</name></author><title level="a">The Cervantes Project: Steps to a Customizable and
                                Interlinked On-Line Electronic Variorum Edition Supporting
                                Scholarship</title></analytic><monogr><title level="s">ECDL 2001, Lecture Notes In Computer Science</title><editor role="role"><name reg="Constantopoulos, P.">P. Constantopoulos</name></editor><editor role="role"><name reg="Sølvberg I.">I. Sølvberg </name></editor><imprint><biblScope type="vol">2163</biblScope><pubPlace>Heidelberg</pubPlace><publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Lavagnino, John">John Lavagnino</name></author><title level="a">When Not to Use TEI</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Electronic Textual Editing</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Burnard, Lou">Lou Burnard</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="O'Brien O'Keeffe, Katherine">Katherine O'Brien O'Keeffe</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Unsworth, Johhn">John Unsworth</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>Modern Language Association of America</publisher><date value="2006">2006</date><biblScope type="pages">334-338</biblScope></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-11-10" to="http://www.tei-c.org/Activities/ETE/Preview/lavagnino.xml" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><title level="m" type="WWW document"><name reg="The Picasso Project">The Picasso Project</name></title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Mallen, Enrique">Enrique Mallen</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Texas A&amp;M University</pubPlace></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-11-06" to="http://picasso.tamu.edu/ " from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="McGann, Jerome">Jerome McGann</name></author><title level="a">The Rosetti Archive and Image-Based Electronic
                            Editing</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Literary Text in the Digital Age</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Finneran, Richard J.">Richard J. Finneran</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Ann Arbor</pubPlace><publisher>University of Michigan Press</publisher><date value="1996">1996</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="McGann, Jerome">Jerome McGann</name></author><title level="a">Rethinking Textuality</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Radiant Textuality</title><imprint><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>Palgrave-Macmillian</publisher><date value="2001">2001</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="11-6-2006" to="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/~jjm2f/old/jj2000aweb.html " from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><title level="m">Picasso: Poèmes</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Michaël, A.">A. Michaël</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace><publisher>Le Cherche Midi</publisher><date value="2005">2005</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Renear, Allen">Allen Renear</name></author><author><name reg="Durand, David">David Durand</name></author><author><name reg="Mylonas, Elli">Elli Mylonas</name></author><title level="m" type="WWW document">
                                Refining Our Notion of What Text Really Is: The Problem of
                                    Overlapping Hierarchies
                            </title><imprint/></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-11-01" to="http://www.stg.brown.edu/resources/stg/monographs/ohco.html " from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Robinson, P. M. W.">P. M. W. Robinson</name></author><title level="a">Is There a Text in These Variants'</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">The Literary Text in the Digital Age</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Finneran, Richard J.">Richard J. Finneran.</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Ann Arbor</pubPlace><publisher>University of Michigan Press</publisher><date value="1996">1996</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Shipman, F. M.">F. M. Shipman</name></author><author><name reg="Marshall, C. C.">C. C. Marshall</name></author><title level="a">Spatial Hypertext: An Alternative to Navigational and
                                Semantic Links</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">ACM Computing Surveys </title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">31.4</biblScope><date value="1999">1999</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="" to="http://doi.acm.org/10.1145/345966.346001" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Unsworth, John">John Unsworth</name></author><title level="a">Scholarly Primitives: What Methods Do Humanities
                                Researchers Have in Common, and How Might Our Tools Reflect
                            This?</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Paper presented at Humanities Computing: Formal
                                Methods, Experimental Practice, London, May 13, 2000</title><imprint><date value="2003">2003</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="11-6-2006" to="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/~jmu2m/Kings.5-00/primitives.html " from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Viscomi, J.">J. Viscomi</name></author><title level="a">Digital Facsimiles: Reading the William Blake
                            Archive</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Image-based Humanities Computing</title><edition>Special Issue of<title level="j"> Computers and the
                                Humanities</title></edition><editor role="editor"><name reg="Finneran, Richard J.">Richard J. Finneran.</name></editor><imprint><biblScope type="vol">36.1</biblScope><date value="2002">2002</date><biblScope type="pages">27-48</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>