<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="poster_221_vanhoutte"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title><emph>TEI By Example</emph></title><author><name reg="Van den Branden, Ron">Ron Van den Branden</name></author><author><name reg="Vanhoutte, Edward">Edward Vanhoutte</name></author><author><name reg="Terras, Melissa">Melissa Terras</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                book</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>poster</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>TEI</item><item>tutorial</item><item>multilingualism</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Edward Vanhoutte's doc<date value="2007-03">March
                    2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="TEI By Example"><titlePart type="main"><emph>TEI By Example</emph></titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Van den Branden, Ron">Ron Van den Branden</name><address><addrLine>ron.vandenbranden@kantl.be</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Centre for Scholarly Editing and Document Studies<lb/>Royal
                Academy of Dutch Language and Literature</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Vanhoutte, Edward">Edward Vanhoutte</name><address><addrLine>edward.vanhoutte@kantl.be</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Centre for Scholarly Editing and Document Studies<lb/>Royal
                Academy of Dutch Language and Literature</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Terras, Melissa">Melissa Terras</name><address><addrLine>m.terras@ucl.ac.uk</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University College London</titlePart></front><body><p>The TEI (Text Encoding Initiative)<note n="1"><xptr to="http://www.tei-c.org/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note> has provided a complex and comprehensive system of provisions for scholarly
                text encoding. Although a major focus of the “digital humanities” domain, there is
                little evidence that it has been embraced by and taught to humanities students at
                university level, which is important to encourage the adoption of the TEI’s
                recommendations and the widespread use of its text encoding guidelines. Very little
                training material exists for either individuals who wish to teach themselves TEI, or
                university level teachers who wish to have access to adequate training materials to
                use with their classes. </p><p>If the digital humanities community wants to promote the TEI markup framework as a
                serious candidate for dedicated courses in the booming curricula on digital
                humanities, humanities computing, digital culture, or humanities informatics, to
                name just a few of the labels this archipelago of disciplines gets, as well as
                integrating the TEI further with digital librarianship, then there is an urgent need
                for an on-line TEI course by example which is less generic than the two tutorials
                published on the TEI website (Sperberg-McQueen and Burnard (2002a) Sperberg-McQueen
                and Burnard (2002b)) and more user friendly, comprehensive, and up to date than the
                “latest” Teach Yourself TEI materials currently online (all of which date from
                    2002).<note n="2"><xptr to="ttp://www.tei-c.org/Tutorials/index-latest.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></p><p>The <emph>TEI By Example</emph><note n="3"><xptr to="http://www.teibyexample.org" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note> project is currently developing a range of freely available online tutorials
                walking individuals through the different stages in marking up a document in TEI.
                    <emph>TEI By Example</emph> aims to provide online tutorials which give examples
                for users of all levels. Examples will be provided of different document types, with
                varying degrees in the granularity of markup, to provide a useful teaching and
                reference aid for those involved in the marking up of texts. Likewise, the
                availability of a software toolkit for teaching text encoding will support the
                potential trainers to take up the challenge to teach TEI on several occasions. In
                order to support multilingualism in the text encoding community, the on-line
                tutorials are being considered for translation into a number of languages. The
                translations proper, however, are outside the scope of this project. </p><p>The deliverables of the project are: on-line tutorials <emph>TEI By Example</emph>, a
                printable PDF version of the tutorials <emph>TEI By Example</emph>, an on-line
                software toolkit for text encoding, a downloadable CD-ROM image for burning off-line
                toolkits for use by course participants, and adequate documentation to enable the
                tutorials to be used elsewhere if needed. </p><p>Project partners are The Centre for Scholarly Editing and Document Studies (CTB)<note n="4"><xptr to="http://www.kantl.be/ctb/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note> of the Royal Academy of Dutch Language and Literature, the Centre for
                Computing in the Humanities (CCH)<note n="5"><xptr to="http://www.kcl.ac.uk/schools/humanities/cch/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note> of King's College London, and the School for Library, Archive, and
                Information Studies (SLAIS)<note n="6"><xptr to="http://www.slais.ucl.ac.uk/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note> of University College London, with an international advisory board
                consisting of experts in textual encoding and markup. The deliverables will be
                published and hosted by CCH (King's College London) under endorsement by the
                Association of Literary and Linguistic Computing. Development of the tutorials began
                in October 2006 and will start to appear online in Spring 2007. It is hoped that the
                project results will be relevant to the trainers of TEI, the students of TEI, the
                text encoding, and the humanities computing community in general. </p><p>A major point of attention at the start of the project was the status of the TEI
                model. Since early 2002, the TEI Consortium has been engaged in a major
                (backward-incompatible) revision of the TEI specification, migrating it from version
                P4 (released in 2002, see TEI (2004) to P5 (2005 onwards, see TEI (2005)). Featuring
                more than just changes in the markup model and the content of the guidelines, P5
                entails an overhaul of the complete production process of the standard. It seems
                that the timing of this <emph>TEI By Example</emph> project coincides with a turning
                point in the transition of TEI P4 to P5: the advantages of P5 adoption for this
                project seemed to outweigh the disadvantages of P4. The most recent snapshot indeed
                suggests that stability is at hand (Van den Branden 2006). As a result, the project
                is developing materials in P5. </p><p>Eight tutorials are under construction. The first, an introduction to text encoding
                and the TEI, encourages the user to explore textual encoding and markup to foster an
                understanding of why this is useful, or even necessary, to allow texts to be
                processed automatically and used and understood by others. The TEI header tutorial
                covers the type of information and metadata captured in the header element. Three
                tutorials focus on examples of individual types of text: Prose, Poetry, and Drama,
                and a further two tutorials deal with examples of Manuscript Transcription and
                Scholarly Editing. The final tutorial investigates how the TEI can be customized,
                and the use of ODD and Roma.</p><p>Although under development at time of writing of this poster proposal, the tutorials
                will be available for demonstration by Digital Humanities 2007, and this poster aims
                to highlight the format, structure, testing, and development of the tutorials. As
                well as informing the academic audience at DH2007, and publicising the project, this
                poster will aim for feedback to allow further development of the online material.</p></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.">C. M. Sperberg-McQueen</name></author><author><name reg="Burnard, Lou">Lou Burnard</name></author><title level="a">A Gentle Introduction to XML</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">TEI P4: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                                Interchange, XML Compatible Edition</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.">C. M. Sperberg-McQueen</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Burnard, Lou">Lou Burnard</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace><pubPlace>Providence, RI</pubPlace><pubPlace>Charlottesville, VA</pubPlace><pubPlace>Bergen, NO</pubPlace><publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher><date value="2002">2002a</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/SG.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.">C. M. Sperberg-McQueen</name></author><author><name reg="Burnard, Lou">Lou Burnard</name></author><title level="m">TEI Lite: An introduction to Text Encoding for
                                Interchange</title><imprint><date value="2002">2002b</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.tei-c.org/Lite/teiu5_en.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><title level="m">TEI P4: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                                Interchange, XML Compatible Edition</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.">C. M. Sperberg-McQueen</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Burnard, Lou">Lou Burnard</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace><pubPlace>Providence, RI</pubPlace><pubPlace>Charlottesville, VA</pubPlace><pubPlace>Bergen, NO</pubPlace><publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.tei-c.org/P4X/index.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><title level="m">TEI P5: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Burnard, Lou">Lou Burnard</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Bauman, Syd">Syd Bauman</name></editor><imprint><publisher>TEI Consortium</publisher><date value="2005">2005</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.tei-c.org.uk/P5/Guidelines/index.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Van den Branden, Ron">Ron Van den Branden</name></author><title level="m">[TBE-R001] - TEI by Example, Initial Report, 2006/06/09</title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.kantl.be/ctb/project/2006/TBE-R001.htm" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>