<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="paper_167_sukovic"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Scholarly (R)evolution: Roles of E-texts in the Research Process in the
                    Humanities</title><author><name reg="Sukovic, Suzana">Suzana Sukovic</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the DH 2007 Conference Abstracts book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>paper</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>electronic texts</item><item>information behavior in the humanities</item><item>literary studies</item><item>historical studies</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Suzana Sukovic's doc<date value="2007-03"/>March
                    2007</item><item>SAS: Revised <date value="2007-05">May 2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Scholarly (R)evolution: Roles of E-texts in the Research Process in the         Humanities"><titlePart type="main">Scholarly (R)evolution: Roles of E-texts in the Research
                    Process in the Humanities</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Sukovic, Suzana">Suzana Sukovic</name><address><addrLine>suzana.sukovic@uts.edu.au</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of Technology, Sydney </titlePart></front><body><div0><head>Introduction</head><p>The study on the roles of electronic texts (e-texts) in the research process in
                    the humanities investigates how academics in literary and historical studies
                    work with electronic textual resources and how interaction with electronic texts
                    affects their research processes. It is situated in the context of discussions
                    about the cultural revolution triggered by the development of digital media. The
                    common comparison with the print revolution suggests that textual sources are at
                    the centre of the change, which is particularly significant for scholars in the
                    humanities. Since text is the basic working material for research in the
                    humanities, the provision of text in an adequate electronic form is crucial for
                    qualitatively new applications of computer technology in humanistic disciplines.
                    At the same time, an understanding of scholars’ interactions with e-texts is
                    critical for decisions on how to present existing sources and for any work on
                    further developments.</p><p>In his seminal book, <title type="m">Radiant textuality</title>, Jerome McGann
                    talks about the ‘material revolution’ in which we reconceive the entity of our
                    cultural archive of materials. Since these repositories provide the basis for
                    all traditional scholarly work, institutional changes have been having a radical
                    effect on the traditional scholarship (McGann 2001). The acceptance of digital
                    resources in the humanities has not been as clear and as decisive as in
                    sciences, but reports from different countries over the last few years point to
                    a positive shift in the quantity and quality of scholars’ engagement with
                    information and communication technologies (Houghton, Steele, and Henty 2003;
                    The British Academy 2005; American Council of Learned Societies 2006)</p><p>A range of studies explored the information behaviour of the humanities scholar;
                    some were focused on the use of digital resources in the humanities but none
                    dealt primarily with the use of electronic texts. Several studies have been
                    conducted, dealing briefly with the use of electronic texts as part of a broader
                    investigation (Massey-Burzio 1999; Brockman et al. 2001) or surveying the use of
                    a particular electronic resource (Flanders 1998; Porter 1998; Duff and Cherry
                    2000; Cherry and Duff 2002). The literature suggests that electronic texts,
                    while much appreciated by those who use them, have not become widely accepted,
                    even in disciplines that are heavily based on textual studies (Warwick 1999;
                    Brockman et al. 2001). Studies of citation patterns, such as Graham’s
                    investigation of citations in historians’ professional publications, show that
                    electronic resources do not rate highly in published works (Graham 2000, 2001).
                    However, citation patterns may indicate intellectual exchanges to some extent,
                    but they are not an accurate reflection of the use of electronic resources.
                    Palmer (2005) points out that there are scholars who have begun to create
                    digital resources for themselves, which is one of the indications of how
                    scholars wish to engage new technologies in their research.</p><p>There is a gap in our knowledge about the roles of electronic texts in the
                    research process so we need to explore various aspects of scholars’ interactions
                    with e-texts and explain how these interactions contribute to the research
                    process.</p></div0><div0><head>Methodology</head><p>The exploratory study on the roles of electronic text in the research enquiry
                    used qualitative methodology to investigate research projects in which e-texts
                    have been used and the nature of academics’ interactions with these texts. The
                    following research questions guided the development of the study: <list type="ordered"><item>How do academic researchers in literary and
                            historical studies work with electronic texts?<list type="unordered"><item>How and for what purposes do researchers interact with
                                    electronic texts?</item><item>How do researchers think and feel about the research context
                                    in which they work with e-texts</item></list></item><item>How are the interactions with e-texts integrated in
                            the research process?</item><item>What is the contribution of e-texts to the research
                            process?</item><item>What are the obstacles and aids in engagement with
                            electronic texts?</item></list></p><p>The study has dealt with the use of electronic texts as a resource and tool, as
                    opposed to projects that aim to produce electronic textual editions or enhance
                    electronic texts in any way. The participants saw their work as traditional
                    humanities research or discussed their projects aiming to have traditional
                    outputs. Investigated research projects were in the areas of literary and
                    historical studies, because both fields are known for extensive and
                    sophisticated use of textual resources. Participants from six universities in
                    two Australian cities and one participant from a university in the USA
                    (altogether 16 participants) participated in the study and discussed thirty
                    research projects.</p><p>The term ‘electronic text’ in this study means any textual material in electronic
                    form, used as a primary source in literary and historical studies. Primary
                    materials are usually poetry, stories, novels, plays, and a variety of
                    historical documents — government, public or private. Digitised archival copies
                    of magazines and newspapers, as well as web-sites and blogs, could be electronic
                    texts as defined here when they are used as primary sources. Electronic texts
                    could be written or spoken (e.g., oral histories), digitised or created
                    electronically, stand-alone documents or part of electronic databases and
                    editions.</p><p>The study has had two phases. The first phase included in-depth semi-structured
                    interviews, examination of participants’ manuscripts and published works as well
                    as examination of some e-texts they mentioned during interviews. The second
                    phase involved detailed data-gathering from a small group of academics drawn
                    from the participants in the first phase. The grounded theory techniques
                    described by Strauss (1987), Strauss and Corbin (1998a; 1998b) and Glaser (1998)
                    were used for data analysis.</p></div0><div0><head>Roles of e-texts</head><p>This paper presents findings directly related to roles of e-texts in the research
                    process but the understanding of the roles is based on other findings that
                    emerged from the study. Firstly, scholars in the study perceived e-texts as
                    fluid entities, which combine different media and formats in a way that does not
                    match the traditional divisions of library materials. The perceived fluidity of
                    electronic textuality leads to converging and transformed practices of
                    networking and information searching. These practices combine aspects of
                    networking, chaining, browsing and web-surfing in traditional and new ways so
                    that the pattern of a new information behaviour emerges. I called this new
                    practice <emph>netchaining</emph> (Sukovic 2006).</p><p>The roles of e-texts are based to a large extent on working with e-texts as fluid
                    entities. Four main roles of e-texts in the research process emerged from the
                    study.</p><p><emph rend="bold">1. Support in finding documents and information.</emph> Search
                    capabilities combined with the provision of full text documents provide a
                    powerful aid in information discovery. E-texts provide support in information
                    retrieval and discovery of primary materials; they lead to other sources and aid
                    in working with analogue sources; supplement hard copies and contribute to the
                    current awareness. </p><p>This is the most fundamental role. Not only do information discovery and
                    retrieval provide a basis for all other roles, but the nature of scholars’
                    interaction with e-texts during the retrieval determines other roles to a large
                    extent (Role 3, for example).</p><p><emph rend="bold">2. Aid in managing the research process.</emph> Access to
                    e-texts allows scholars to plan visits to remote collections; aids the
                    publication process and provides sources for some research activities (e.g.,
                    ordering digital images, confirming publication rights, and exchanging files
                    with collaborators and publishers).</p><p><emph rend="bold">3. Aid in investigation of the topic.</emph> The multiplicity
                    of sources, formats and textual information that could be quickly brought
                    together is a basis of exploration that allows scholars to see different
                    meanings and aspects of the topic. Exploration of research questions through
                    interactions with e-texts took four main forms: <list type="unordered"><item>exploration of patterns and connections by searching and comparing
                            diverse bodies of electronic texts;</item><item>production and/or interrogation of textual databases to explore
                            research questions;</item><item>exploration of electronically born literature and</item><item>exploration as part of the academic research to be used in
                        creative.</item></list></p><p><emph rend="bold">4. Contribution to writing and presenting research
                    results.</emph> The use of e-texts improves the speed and accuracy in writing by
                    allowing copying and pasting of passages. Interactions with e-texts and digital
                    media in general promote new, less structured and linear ways of thinking about
                    the topic, which influences the academic writing style. From subtle changes in
                    presenting the argument to more radical combinations of academic and creative
                    writing styles, the participants reflected on different ways in which electronic
                    textuality was influencing their traditional academic writing. Interactions with
                    e-texts also encourage thinking about alternative modes for presenting research
                    findings that do not fit traditional academic genres. E-texts contribute to the
                    final research stages in a complex process of negotiation with the research
                    tradition.</p><p>These roles serve two main functions: <list type="unordered"><item>aid in providing basis for research (support roles) or</item><item>aid in exploring the topic and presenting research findings
                            (substantive roles).</item></list></p><p>E-texts provide basis for research, or play support roles, when they make some
                    aspects of the research process quicker and easier. The speed and convenience,
                    or frustration sometimes associated with working with electronic sources, may
                    influence the process, but they normally do not affect the scholar’s
                    intellectual engagement with the topic in a significant way. The first two
                    roles, Support in finding information and Aid in managing research process, are
                    support roles. The fourth, Contribution to writing and presenting research
                    results, plays a support role when e-texts help in improving the speed and
                    accuracy.</p><p>E-texts aid in exploring the topic and presenting research findings, or play
                    substantive roles, when they take part in shaping the scholar’s thinking
                    process. Interactivity is an essential element in following hunches, testing
                    hypotheses and making connections in a way that was impossible or impractical
                    without e-texts. The scholar’s thinking about the topic develops in the
                    interplay with the e-text and this experience can influence the presentation of
                    research results. The third role, Aid in investigation of the topic, is a
                    substantive content-oriented role. In Contribution to writing and presenting
                    research results, e-texts have a substantive role when they influence the
                    writing style and presentation of research results.</p></div0><div0><head>Conclusion</head><p>Understanding of the roles of e-texts in the research process contributes to our
                    understanding of the envisaged scholarly change as well as information needs and
                    behaviour in the humanities. It confirms the recent reports on the change of
                    research practices resulting from the use of ICTs and explores the impacts of
                    interactions with e-texts on the research process. The study can have practical
                    implications for the development of digital collections and software
                    applications, approaches to text encoding and development of training programs
                    and institutional policies.</p></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="American Council of Learned Societies’ Commission on                                     Cyberinfrastructure for Humanities and Social Sciences">American Council of Learned Societies’ Commission on
                                    Cyberinfrastructure for Humanities and Social Sciences</name></author><title level="m">Our Cultural Commonwealth: the report of the American
                                Council of Learned Societies’ Commission on Cyberinfrastructure for
                                Humanities and Social Sciences</title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-08-12" to="http://www.acls.org/cyberinfrastructure/acls.ci.report.pdf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="British Academy">British Academy</name></author><title level="m">E-resources for Research in the Humanities and Social
                                Sciences: A British Academy Policy Review</title><imprint><pubPlace>London</pubPlace><publisher>The British Academy</publisher><date value="2005">2005</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Brockman, William S.">William S. Brockman</name></author><author><name reg="Neumann, Laura">Laura Neumann</name></author><author><name reg="Palmer, Carole L.">Carole L. Palmer</name></author><author><name reg="Tidline, Tonyia J.">Tonyia J. Tidline</name></author><title level="m">Scholarly Work in the Humanities and the Evolving
                                Information Environment</title><imprint><pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Digital Library Federation and Council on Library and Information Resources</publisher><date value="2001">2001</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-06-30" to="http://www.clir.org" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Cherry, Joan M.">Joan M. Cherry</name></author><author><name reg="Duff, Wendy M.">Wendy M. Duff</name></author><title level="a">Studying Digital Library Users Over Time: A Follow-up
                                Survey of Early Canadiana Online</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Information Research</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">7.2</biblScope><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2002-06-06" to="http://informationr.net/ir/7-2/paper123.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Duff, Wendy M.">Wendy M. Duff</name></author><author><name reg="Cherry, Joan M.">Joan M. Cherry</name></author><title level="a">Use of Historical Documents in a Digital World:
                                Comparisons with Original Materials and Microfiche</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Information Research</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">6.1</biblScope><date value="2000">2000</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2004-05-20" to="http://informationr.net/ir/6-1/paper86.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Flanders, Julia">Julia Flanders</name></author><title level="a"> Scholarly Research and Electronic Resources</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">WWP Newsletter</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">4.2</biblScope><date value="1998">1998</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2004-05-28" to="http://www.wwp.brown.edu/project/newsletter/vol04num02/scholarly042.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Glaser, Barney G">Barney G. Glaser</name></author><title level="m">Doing Grounded Theory: Issues and Discussions</title><imprint><pubPlace>Mill Valley, CA</pubPlace><publisher>Sociology Press</publisher><date value="1998">1998</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Graham, Suzanne R.">Suzanne R. Graham</name></author><title level="a">Historians and Electronic Resources: A Citation
                                Analysis</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Journal of the Association for History and Computing</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">3.3</biblScope><date value="2000">2000</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Graham, Suzanne R.">Suzanne R. Graham</name></author><title level="a">Historians and Electronic Resources: A Second Citation
                                Analysis</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Journal of the Association for History and Computing</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">4.2</biblScope><date value="2001">2001</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Houghton, John W.">John W. Houghton</name></author><author><name reg="Steele, Colin">Colin Steele</name></author><author><name reg="Henty, Margaret">Margaret Henty</name></author><title level="m">Changing Research Practices in the Digital Information
                                and Communication Environment</title><imprint><pubPlace>[Canberra?]</pubPlace><publisher>Department of Education, Science and Training</publisher><date value="2003">2003</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2005-05-11" to="http://www.dest.gov.au/sectors/research_sector/publications_resources/profiles/changing_research_practices.htm" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Massey-Burzio, Virginia">Virginia Massey-Burzio</name></author><title level="a">The Rush to Technology: A View from the
                            Humanities</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Library Trends</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">47.4</biblScope><date value="1999">1999</date><biblScope type="pages">620–639</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="McGann, Jerome">Jerome McGann</name></author><title level="m">Radiant Textuality: Literature After the World Wide Web</title><imprint><pubPlace>New York</pubPlace><publisher>Palgrave</publisher><date value="2001">2001</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Palmer, Carole L.">Carole L. Palmer</name></author><title level="a">Scholarly Work and the Shaping of Digital
                            Access</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Journal of the American Society for Information Science
                                and Technology</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">56.11</biblScope><date value="2005">2005</date><biblScope type="pages">1140-1153</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Porter, Sarah">Sarah Porter</name></author><title level="a">Reports from the Front: Six Perspectives on Scholar's
                                Information Requirements in the Digital Age</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">The New Review of Academic Librarianship</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">4</biblScope><date value="1998">1998</date><biblScope type="pages">167–189</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Strauss, Anselm">Anselm Strauss</name></author><author><name reg="Corbin, Juliet">Juliet Corbin</name></author><title level="m">Basics of Qualitative Research: Techniques and
                                Procedures for Developing Grounded Theory</title><edition>1987. Second Edition</edition><imprint><pubPlace>Thousand Oaks, CA</pubPlace><publisher>SAGE Publications</publisher><date value="1998">1998</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Strauss, Anselm">Anselm Strauss</name></author><author><name reg="Corbin, Juliet">Juliet Corbin</name></author><title level="a">Grounded Theory Methodology: An Overview</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Strategies of Qualitative Inquiry</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Denzin, N. K.">N. K. Denzin</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Lincoln, Y. S.">Y. S. Lincoln</name></editor><imprint><pubPlace>Thousand Oaks, CA</pubPlace><publisher>SAGE Publications</publisher><date value="1998">1998</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Strauss, Anselm">Anselm Strauss</name></author><title level="m">Qualitative Analysis for Social Scientists</title><imprint><pubPlace>Cambridge, UK</pubPlace><pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace><publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher><date value="1987">1987</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Sukovic, Suzana">Suzana Sukovic</name></author><title level="a"> Electronic Texts in the Humanities: Converging Media,
                                Formats, Practices and Ideas.</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Paper read at IR 7.0: Internet Convergences, presented
                                by the Association of Internet Researchers (AoIR), at Brisbane,
                                27–30 September</title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-10-24" to="http://conferences.aoir.org/index.php?cf=5" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Warwick, Claire">Claire Warwick</name></author><title level="a">English Literature, Electronic Text and Computer
                                Analysis: An Impossible Combination? </title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Paper read at ACH-ALLC '99 International Humanities
                                Computing Conference, June 9-13, at Charlottesville, Virginia</title><imprint><date value="1999">1999</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2002-04-05" to="http://InformationR.net/ir/5-2/paper71.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>