<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="poster_143_bradley"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Making a Contribution: Modularity, Integration and Collaboration Between
                    Tools in <emph>Pliny</emph></title><author><name reg="Bradley, John">John Bradley</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>poster</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>tool modularity</item><item>tool building</item><item>collaboration</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from John Bradley's doc <date value="2007-04">April
                2007</date></item><item>SAS: Revised incorporating Bradley's revisions <date value="2007-05"> May 2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Making a Contribution: Modularity, Integration and Collaboration Between                 Tools in Pliny"><titlePart type="main">Making a Contribution: Modularity, Integration and
                    Collaboration Between Tools in <emph>Pliny</emph></titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Bradley, John">John Bradley</name><address><addrLine>john.bradley@kcl.ac.uk</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Centre for Computing in the Humanities<lb/>King's College London</titlePart></front><body><div0><p>Computing tools have been an issue since the foundation of Humanities Computing,
                    and building modular tools that work together has been recognised as important
                    since at least the CETH meetings in 1995. Geoffrey Rockwell and I first raised
                    issues of modularity in our paper given at the Canadian Learned Societies
                    Conference in June 1992 entitled “Towards new Research Tools in
                    Computer-Assisted Text Analysis”. Our proposed tool framework combined data-flow
                    tool modularity with the ability to create pages that mixed scholarly writing
                    with interactive elements like in a <emph>Mathematica</emph> “Notebook”. Of
                    course the WWW was sweeping all this away by 1995 and when we took a paper
                    (Bradley, Rockwell 1995) to the CETH “tools” meeting we were merging our modular
                    view with the WWW as it was then emerging. </p><p>In our community “modularity” often comes down to the sharing of file formats.
                    Separate tools that can all read the same file format can all operate on common
                    data, and therefore can contribute their particular facilities to the task at
                    hand. File- or Unix-style modularity is a part of what I called the
                    “transformation model” of computing (Bradley 2005), and provides a powerful
                    approach to manipulating data. TuStep (described in Ott 2000) is a splendid
                    example. The model holds a strong attraction within the Digital Humanities
                    community – even extraordinarily creative projects as TAPoR’s text analysis
                    portal (TAPoR 2006) or the Nora project (Nora 2006) are, in fact, primarily
                    based on this. However, thinking of modularity primarily in those terms limits
                    our views to those of computing about 25 years ago – before the advent of the
                    graphical user interface (GUI).</p><p>The GUI radically changed the way we think about computing, and even today, more
                    than 25 years later, its significance continues to reverberate. It is surely
                    true to say that most humanists have the GUI as a model driving how they think
                    of their computer. The impact has been twofold: <list type="unordered"><item>First, users now expect that the computer screen will allow them to
                            directly manipulate materials that interest them. Think of the words in
                            a word processor.</item><item>Second, interaction between tools needs to be possible not only
                            between files, but also on the screen as well. Users expect to be able
                            to incorporate parts of spreadsheets inside word documents, for
                        example.</item></list></p><p>To reflect this broader sense of collaboration between tools, we need some
                    different language. In this paper I will use the word <emph>integration</emph>
                    for that aspect of tool collaboration that focuses on GUI issues. The use of
                        <emph>integration</emph> might make us also think of the integrative nature
                    of humanities scholarship – an intentional parallel. </p><p>Integration in the GUI presents challenges. First, the development of tools
                    allowing for direct manipulation of objects on the screen is more complex and
                    costly than resolving file-sharing issues. Furthermore, if independent tools are
                    to interact on the screen – elements maintained by potentially different tools
                    sharing screen space – then they must operate in a computing framework that
                    makes this kind of thing practical.</p><p><emph>Pliny</emph> (Pliny 2006) has been developed precisely to draw attention to
                    these two issues and to encourage some thinking about cooperating tools beyond
                    file-oriented “modularity”. It both significantly broadens how computers can
                    support humanities research and suggests a much richer and more acceptable
                    interface to those tools that might well attract a larger number of scholars.
                        <emph>Pliny</emph> tackles this in two ways. First, it is supports
                    annotation and note taking – functions central to several aspects of humanities
                    scholarship and which I believe have been largely neglected by the DH community
                    – and, second, it is built using a framework called Eclipse (Eclipse 2006) which
                    is deliberatively created to support GUI-level interaction between tools of the
                    kind I mentioned above. Eclipse also supports rich collaboration between tools
                    developed by independent developers.</p><p>Personal annotation and note-taking compels us to think about tool integration
                    because it is widespread in humanities scholarship and runs across all kinds of
                    scholarly work. Scholars write notes to record their reactions to not only books
                    they read, but also web pages they view. Furthermore, if they have tools that do
                    (say) text analysis, they would probably want to record notes about that as
                    well. The provision of note-taking within a <emph>particular</emph> website is
                    insufficient for personal note-taking (although it might well fulfil a useful
                    need supporting public comment about the material the website offers) because
                    most scholars work across a broad range of materials, and their note taking
                    capability must reflect this. Notes from a book will at some point need to be
                    brought in contact with notes about, say, an online archive or a journal, or
                    about findings from the text analysis tool. Personal scholarly note taking
                    integrates by its very nature.</p><p>Personal annotation also draws our attention back to the <emph>software
                        application</emph> as the context in which tools can and should be built,
                    rather than thinking of the browser as the context for tool delivery. It is
                    surprising how difficult it is to make this point to those in the Digital
                    Humanities. Of course part of the reason is that XML, one of the key
                    technologies that fuels some portion of the DH community, has been developed
                    specifically to work in the context of the WWW. However, if we wish to develop a
                    more broadly based humanities community who use technology in more sophisticated
                    ways to support their research we need to broaden our focus beyond the WWW.
                    Providing scholarly resources on the WWW supports scholars, of course, and
                    there remains some excitement that they can get materials readily right to their
                    desktop. However, as I argued in Bradley 2005, once on that desktop all they can
                    do with them is read them on the screen or print them out – a webpage, even one
                    designed with all the clever parts of CSS and AJAX, allows only manipulation
                    within its own page context. It contributes little to the integrative aspect of
                    personal scholarship which must, by its very nature, often bring materials
                    together from disparate sources. </p><p>Software Applications work with personal materials. Surely this is a central
                    element of humanities scholarship. A word processor creates materials that
                        <emph>belong</emph> to the researcher. Until web browsers can be used to
                    create materials that are stored as personal data – on the user’s own machine –
                    they cannot replace applications (see a similar assertion from a technical
                    perspective in Charland 2005). Even the XML folk – part of the community driving
                    a WWW view of humanities computing because of XML’s compatibility with website
                    creation – use an application such as Oxygen to create XML materials in the
                    first place. For the same reason that the creation of an XML file involves an
                    editor rather than a web browser, the creation of personal notes – especially
                    those gathered from reactions across a great range of sources – requires a
                    personal application. Furthermore, more than one study into computing and
                    humanities scholarship (see both Brockman <emph>et al</emph> and Siemens
                        <emph>et al</emph> 2004) has found that scholars have tried to apply
                    inappropriate applications such as word processors to support this need, and
                    have not been very satisfied with the result.</p><p>Applications can be built in several different frameworks. <emph>Pliny</emph> is
                    written in Java using the Eclipse framework rather than the one provided by Sun
                    to create desktop tools. I didn’t choose Eclipse because it was easy for me to
                    use it – indeed I had to learn it from the beginning during the past year or so.
                    I choose Eclipse because it is designed specifically to support the integration
                    of tools developed by separate developers. Eclipse provides a way to share out
                    screen space between windows managed by different tools. Furthermore, it also
                    provides mechanisms for elements from separate tools to share the same window
                    (called “making a contribution” in Eclipse). Tools built with the Eclipse
                    plug-in model need not operate in isolation from other related tools. A text
                    analysis tool built in Eclipse could use <emph>Pliny</emph> elements to allow
                    users to record notes while using the TA tool, and the notes that were recorded
                    in this way would also be visible in the context of notes created with other
                    materials – say from reading a book, or annotating a web page.</p><p>So, in this presentation I have an impossible task. First, I am promoting the
                    idea that we focus more on application development than web development, a
                    technically more demanding activity, and one that goes against the grain of much
                    work in DH over the last decade. Second, for those who might subscribe to this
                    idea, I am promoting that we build our tools according to the Eclipse model
                    rather than the more widely understood Sun/Java framework. Perhaps I won’t
                    convince anyone here. However, I believe that unless we start to think of tools
                    in the context of applications, as our scholarly community does, and unless we
                    start to think more seriously of tool building in the context of GUI integration
                    in addition to data sharing, we will never get the attention of most scholars in
                    the humanities.</p></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Bradley, John">John Bradley</name></author><author><name reg="Rockwell, Geoffrey">Geoffrey Rockwell</name></author><title level="a">Towards New Research Tools in Computer-Assisted Text
                                Analysis</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Paper presented at The Canadian Learned Societies
                                Conference, June 1992</title><imprint><date value="1992">1992</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/legacy/staff/jdb/papers/learneds.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Bradley, John">John Bradley</name></author><author><name reg="Rockwell, Geoffrey">Geoffrey Rockwell</name></author><title level="a">The Components of a System for Computer Assisted Text
                                Analysis</title></analytic><monogr><title level="u">Paper presented at the CETH Workshop on Future Text
                                Analysis Tools, October 1995</title><imprint><date value="1995">1995</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/legacy/staff/jdb/papers/ceth95.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Bradley, John">John Bradley</name></author><title level="a">What You (Fore)see is What You Get: Thinking about
                                Usage Paradigms for Computer Assisted Text Analysis</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Text Techology</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">14.2</biblScope><date value="2005">2005</date><biblScope type="pages">1-19</biblScope></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-09-01" to="http://texttechnology.mcmaster.ca/pdf/vol14_2/bradley14-2.pdf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Brockman, William S.">William S. Brockman</name></author><author><name reg="Neumann, Laura">Laura Neumann</name></author><author><name reg="Palmer, Carole L.">Carole L. Palmer</name></author><author><name reg="Tidline, Tonyia J.">Tonyia J. Tidline</name></author><title level="m">Scholarly Work in the Humanities and the Evolving
                                Information Environment</title><imprint><pubPlace>Washington, D.C.</pubPlace><publisher>Digital Libary Federation and Council on Library and Information Resources</publisher><date value="2001">2001</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Charland, Andre">Andre Charland</name></author><title level="a">Will Ajax Replace the Desktop?</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">developer.com</title><imprint><date value="2005">2005</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-10-01" to="http://www.developer.com/design/article.php/10925_3574116_1" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><title level="m"><name reg="Pliny">Pliny</name></title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-10-01" to="http://pliny.cch.kcl.ac.uk/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><title level="m"><name reg="Eclipse">Eclipse</name></title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-10-01" to="http://www.eclipse.org/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><title level="m"><name reg="m">Nora</name></title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr crdate="2006-10-01" to="http://www.noraproject.org/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Ott, Wilhelm">Wilhelm Ott</name></author><title level="a">Strategies and Tools for Textual Scholarship: the
                                Tübingen System of Text Processing Programs (TUSTEP)</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">15.1</biblScope><date value="2000">2000</date><biblScope type="pages">93-108</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Siemens, Ray">Ray Siemens</name></author><author><name reg="Toms, Elaine">Elaine Toms</name></author><author><name reg="Sinclair, Stéfan">Stéfan Sinclair</name></author><author><name reg="Rockwell, Geoffrey">Geoffrey Rockwell</name></author><author><name reg="Siemens, Lynne"/>Lynne Siemens</author><title level="a">The Humanities Scholar in the Twenty-first Century: How
                                Research is Done and What Support is Needed</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2004 Conference Abstracts</title><imprint><pubPlace>Göteborg</pubPlace><publisher>Göteborg University</publisher><date value="2004">2004</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><title level="m"><name reg="TAPoR: Text Analysis Portal for Research">TAPoR: Text Analysis Portal for Research</name></title><imprint><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://test-tapor.mcmaster.ca/portal/portal" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>