<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="poster_244_smith"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Lost in the Archives, Found in Digital Collections</title><author><name reg="Smith, Natalia (Natasha)">Natalia (Natasha) Smith</name></author><author><name reg="Xie, Dongqing">Dongqing Xie</name></author><author><name reg="McAulay, Elizabeth">Elizabeth McAulay</name></author><author><name reg="Cooper, Todd">Todd Cooper</name></author><author><name reg="MacKay, Adrienne W.">Adrienne W. MacKay</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Field, Hana S.">Hana S. Field</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>poster</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>digital library</item><item>scholarly digital publishing</item><item>metadata</item><item>TEI</item><item>Java</item><item>open-source technology</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list><item>HSF: Created from Natalia (Natasha) Smith's doc <date value="2007-04"> April
                        2007</date></item><item>SAS: Revised <date value="2007-05"> May 2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Lost in the Archives, Found in Digital Collections"><titlePart type="main">Lost in the Archives, Found in Digital
                Collections</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Smith, Natalia (Natasha)">Natalia (Natasha) Smith</name><address><addrLine>nsmith@email.unc.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill Library</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Xie, Dongqing">Xie Dongqing</name><address><addrLine>dongqing.xie@gmail.com</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill Library</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="McAulay, Elizabeth">Elizabeth McAulay</name><address><addrLine>elizabethmcaulay1@yahoo.com</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill Library</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Cooper, Todd">Todd Cooper</name><address><addrLine>cojere@email.unc.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill Library</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="MacKay, Adrienne M.">Adrienne M. MacKay</name><address><addrLine>awmackay@gmail.com</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill Library</titlePart></front><body><div0><head>Abstract</head><p>The proliferation of digital collections on the web has dramatically expanded
                    access to content that would remain otherwise underutilized or undiscovered.
                    Organizations that have been actively involved in large scale
                    digitization—through Google, the Open Content Alliance (OCA), or other
                    means—most often limit the scope of these projects to digital replication of
                    materials. Not surprisingly, given the size and extent of many collections
                    selected for digitization, the costs of applying extensive research and
                    scholarship to primary documents are often prohibitive, if such actions are even
                    considered by project staff. Digital scholarly editions offer many research
                    advantages that exceed the limitations of traditional and linear print
                    publications. Their potential has been already instantiated by a few prominent
                    projects, among them Rotunda by the University of Virginia Press and the Perseus
                    Digital Library. <note n="1"><xptr to="http://rotunda.upress.virginia.edu/index.php?page_id=About " from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/> and <lb/><xptr to="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note> Encouraged by these exemplars, <emph>Documenting the American
                        South</emph> (DocSouth), UNC-Chapel Hill Library’s digital publishing
                    program, sought to create two online scholarly documentary histories: a
                    collection of documents related to antebellum student life at the University of
                    North Carolina and a collection of documents about the institutional development
                    of the university during the same period. Through careful planning and analysis,
                    collaboration with research scholars and subject librarians, and the application
                    of open-source technology and international standards, DocSouth's "True and
                    Candid Compositions: The Lives and Writings of Antebellum Students at the
                    University of North Carolina" and "The First Century of the First State
                    University" <note n="2">"True and Candid Compositions: The Lives and Writings of
                        Antebellum Students of the University of North Carolina."<title level="m">
                            Documenting the American South</title> Ed. Erika Lindeman. (University
                        of North Carolina at Chapel Hill Libraries). <xptr to="http://docsouth.unc.edu/true/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>"The
                        Carolina at Chapel Hill Libraries</note> represent rare examples of
                    scholarly publications with annotations and interpretive essays that include
                    both color facsimile and transcription access to unique primary documents.</p><p>Documenting the American South has ten years of experience encoding printed
                    materials using TEI guidelines; however, creating online documentary histories
                    required a more complex approach than had previously been employed with our
                    collections. "True and Candid Compositions", for example, was originally
                    conceived as a monograph including diplomatic transcription of manuscript
                    documents; textual, biographical, and interpretive annotations; several
                    scholarly essays; and an extensive index—all prepared by Dr. Erika Lindemann,
                    professor of composition at the UNC-Chapel Hill. In presenting Lindemann's
                    project on the web, we strove to include all of the features of her project,
                    plus features only possible through and valuable for an online publication. [See
                    Figure 1 and Figure 2 for screenshots.]</p></div0><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_244_smith_1.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 1: Screenshot of True and Candid index page</figDesc></figure><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_244_smith_2.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 2: Screenshot of document with image of manuscript</figDesc></figure><div0><head>Application of Technologies</head><p>In both online publications, we wanted to provide users with several options to
                    fully explore and discover content in these unique collections. We offer several
                    "browse by" indices that were compiled by extracting information from the
                    TEI-XML files. For "True and Candid Compositions" and for "The First Century," a
                    total of 500 transcribed manuscript documents and over 20 scholarly essays were
                    encoded by graduate students from the English Department and School of
                    Information and Library Science using "TEI in the Libraries" recommendations for
                    level 5 of encoding.<note n="3">The TEI Consortium, "TEI Text Encoding in
                        Libraries. Guidelines for Best Encoding Practices" <xptr to="http://www.diglib.org/standards/tei.htm" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>.</note> All personal, place, and organization names were disambiguated by
                    scholars and assigned a unique id number, a regularized name, and one of three
                    type descriptors (i.e., person, place, organization). This information was then
                    encoded within <hi rend="code">&lt;name&gt;</hi> elements with relevant
                    attributes as part of each document XML file. Images of all manuscript pages
                    were scanned and saved in TIFF and JPEG formats. </p><p>The XML and image files became input for a publishing mechanism comprised of two
                    distinct parts: (1) conversion of XML to XHTML and (2) generation of search and
                    browse functionality in XHTML pages on the web. [See Figure 3: Document
                    Processing Workflow.]</p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_244_smith_3.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 3: Document Processing Workflow</figDesc></figure><p>First, we extracted metadata from each XML file (one XML file per document) and
                    then converted the XML files to XHTML. The resulting XHTML files have the
                    distinctive DocSouth format and include links to images and biographical
                    annotations, both of which open in separate windows (pop-ups). This step is
                    accomplished with the use of the XSLT technology, available from the
                    &lt;teiPublisher&gt; software<note n="4"><xptr to="http://sourceforge.net/projects/teipublisher/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note>, which we modified to meet our project needs. We used
                    &lt;teiPublisher&gt; with locally customized XSLT files to transform
                    manuscript and essay XML files into XHTML files. Our customizations included:
                    displaying the TEIHeader under tabbed buttons; highlighting names for which
                    regularized names are viewable as a mouseover; adding icons to personal names to
                    indicate that biographical essays are available in pop-up window, and adding URL
                    links to scanned page images in separate XHTML files.</p><p>Second, we generated indices with a custom Java program and our primary MySQL
                    database, using JAXP/JDBC/XPath technologies. "XML is a good match for Java. It
                    pairs Java’s code portability feature with its data portability…"<note n="5">Akmal B. Chaudhri, <title level="m"> XML Data Management: Native XML and XML-Enabled
                        Database Systems</title> (Boston: Addison-Wesley, 2003) p. 342.</note> The Java
                    programming language has a number of proven APIs for working with XML, including
                    the Java API for XML Processing (JAXP). In concert with XPath and JDBC (Java API
                    for database interactions), the language is a powerful tool for performing a
                    variety of operations with XML documents. Additionally, Java is platform
                    agnostic and secure. We designed this program to perform a wide range of
                    operations, including: reporting errors in XML files for quality control;
                    retrieving a variety of data from XML files; exporting data into the MySQL
                    database; generating an XHTML file for every page image of each document; and
                    extracting data from the database to create indices of personal names,
                    geographic names, organization names, authors, genres, and topics.</p><p>This Java program extracted rich metadata from the XML files, specifically from
                    the <hi rend="code">&lt;teiHeader&gt;</hi> and from the key, reg, and
                    type attributes of the <hi rend="code">&lt;name&gt;</hi> element. These
                    varied data were stored in the primary DocSouth MySQL database, which contains
                    all the metadata for all DocSouth online collections. In processing, the Java
                    program extracted all encoded names and recorded their regularized names, types,
                    and occurrence locations in the XML files to the database. In a similar process,
                    biographical information contained in an additional XML file was processed and
                    stored in the same database. A number of scholars and subject librarians wrote
                    this expansive biographical information for hundreds of identified and
                    researched proper names, which has served to add valuable contextual richness to
                    the collection. </p><p>We also designed our Java program to generate two types of "browse by"
                    indices—proper name indices and document indices. The program generated proper
                    name indices by type; these indices are hyperlinked to a PHP program that
                    searches the database and provides a list of documents in which the name
                    appears. Each linked document displays a document page highlighting the selected
                    name. Finally, the program uses available metadata to generate document indices
                    that offer other chapter-level "browse by" options, including: documents listed
                    by chapter, topic, genre, and author. As a result of this Java processing, these
                    two online documentary histories have 2,340 personal names, 170 organization
                    names, and 420 place names in indices generated from the XML files.</p><p>DocSouth's "True and Candid Compositions" and "First Century" collections
                    represent exciting additions to our digital library. More than just collections
                    of digitized manuscripts, these online histories benefit from collaboration with
                    scholars and DocSouth's considerable experience and technical expertise. The
                    confluence of unique primary documents, scholarship, and judicious application
                    of open-source technology solutions allowed us to develop two online scholarly
                    documentary histories that far exceed the limitations of traditional print
                    publications. No longer lost in the archives, these enhanced digitized primary
                    source materials are readily available to enthusiasts, scholars, and learners
                    everywhere.</p></div0></body></text></TEI.2>