<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="paper_257_remnek"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Digital Text Projects in Eastern Europe: Promoting International
                    Interoperability</title><author><name reg="Remnek, Miranda">Miranda Remnek</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>paper</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>collaboration</item><item>interoperability</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Miranda Remnek's doc <date value="2007-04">April
                2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Digital Text Projects in Eastern Europe: Promoting International Interoperability"><titlePart type="main">Digital Text Projects in Eastern Europe: Promoting
                    International Interoperability</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Remnek, Miranda">Miranda Remnek</name><address><addrLine>mremnek@uiuc.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Slavic &amp; Eastern European Library<lb/>University of
                Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</titlePart></front><body><div0><p>The widely divergent languages and cultures of Russia, Eastern Europe &amp;
                    Eurasia (hereafter Eastern Europe), present a rich terrain for digital
                    scholarship, but owing to a number of factors—including poorly-endowed or
                    mutually-incompatible infrastructures, language barriers, and different
                    approaches to the construction of metadata—the corpora already in existence and
                    those in development are often poorly known elsewhere, and in many cases are
                    hidden from international resource discovery and data sharing.</p><p>In view of this situation, it was clear to the Digital Projects Subcommittee of
                    the <emph>American Association for the Advancement of Slavic Studies</emph>
                        (<xptr to="http://www.aaass.org" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>) that improved
                    documentation would constitute an important step toward the promotion of
                    knowledge sharing and interoperability.<note n="1">Other points in the group’s
                        charge include: (2) fostering informed participation in future initiatives;
                        (3-4) increasing digital information and training opportunities for Slavic
                        librarians; (5) complementing national efforts to establish digital
                        repositories. See <xptr to="http://www.library.uiuc.edu/spx/BnD/DigPro.htm#charge" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note> The Slavic &amp; East European Library at
                    UIUC is therefore building an international <emph>Inventory of Slavic, East
                        European and Eurasian Digital Projects</emph> (<xptr to="http://www.library.uiuc.edu/spx/inventory" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>).
                    The <emph>Inventory</emph> already describes at least 360 collections in 110
                    projects, and we also foresee web submissions from international partners to
                    promote collaborative registration. But even now the <emph>Inventory</emph> is
                    heavily used; recent statistics indicate that in the period July 2005-June 2006
                    it received around 25,000 hits. It has also become an OAI Data Provider, and
                    although inventory contents (unlike the digital collections they record) are
                    sometimes not reflected in aggregated search services like OAIster (<xptr to="http://oaister.umdl.umich.edu/o/oaister/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>),
                    the <emph>Inventory’s</emph> records have indeed been harvested and now display
                    in OAIster searches—likely to improve dramatically the visibility of substantive
                    digital projects in the Slavic field. </p><p>But the project goals go far beyond the compilation of a mere inventory. Besides
                    the implementation of intensive content development, promotion of metadata
                    standardization, expanded reference assistance and interactive user options, the
                    Inventory will focus on an expansion of the OAI data provider system and
                    item-level harvesting. (It also hopes to explore customized delivery services
                    and an archival framework for at-risk collections in the Slavic field, currently
                    being explored through an inter-institutional grant proposal).</p><p>Nevertheless, the project team acknowledges that metadata practices in Eastern
                    Europe are still very diverse, and far from standardized. At one end of the
                    scale, where relatively simple encoding is involved, even schemes like Dublin
                    Core are poorly recognized. This makes the implementation of relatively
                    well-established data-sharing protocols like OAI-PMH (<emph>Open Archives
                        Initiative: Protocol for Metadata Harvesting</emph>) little known in Eastern
                    Europe. A registry of OAI data providers at UIUC demonstrates that while OAI
                    data providers are well established in the US and Western Europe, they are much
                    less widely encountered further East.<note n="2">See <xptr to="http://gita.grainger.uiuc.edu/registry/ListTLDs.asp" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>. U.S. providers are proliferating: in the past year the
                        number of “edu” domains increased from 265 to 332, and “org” domains from
                        149 to 182. Likewise in Western Europe: U.K. DPs went from 89 to 114,
                        Germany from 73 to 99. But in Eastern Europe it is different; the totals for
                        Hungary (4), Czech Republic (2) and Slovenia (2) stayed the same this year,
                        and Russia increased only slightly, from 3 to 4. Only Poland increased
                        significantly, from 4 to 18.</note> True, the implementation of OAI data
                    interchange is not necessarily well standardized in countries with far more
                        providers.<note n="3">As reported at the Oct. 2005 OAI workshop in Geneva,
                        the German Initiative for Networked Information (DINI) has installed a
                        certificate system in order to bring OAI providers into greater
                        standardization.</note> Furthermore, the whole question of the efficacy of
                    OAI-PMH as a metadata transfer protocol is still somewhat open to question.<note n="4">The Open Archives Initiative OAI-Implementers group announced on Nov.
                        3 2005 that it is “studying the effectiveness of OAI and some other related
                        methods of creating interoperable online libraries” and has “posted a
                        questionnaire 'Survey on Common Interface Frameworks for Online Libraries'
                        on the web.”</note> Nevertheless, its power is generally well-recognized,
                    and its further penetration into Eastern Europe is certainly a desirable goal.</p><p>At the other end of the scale, the level of deep encoding is even less widely
                    standardized in Eastern Europe. The decade-long Institute of World Literature
                    project in Moscow known as FEB (<emph>Fundamental'naia elektronaia
                    biblioteka</emph>) (<xptr to="http://www.feb-web.ru/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>) has an enviable collection of over 50,000 Russian literature texts, all
                    heavily encoded in SGML—but not according to the <emph>Text Encoding
                    Initiative</emph> (TEI) Guidelines. True, the TEI is not a standard, but
                    interoperability with such an impressive collection would be highly desirable.
                    Other such examples are available. To be sure, there are exceptions: the recent
                    TEI meeting in Sofia, Bulgaria revealed the extent to which TEI projects are
                    beginning to gain root in South Eastern Europe.<note n="5">See Milena Dobreva,
                        “TEI in South-Eastern Europe: Experience and Prospects,” TEI Members
                        Meeting, Sofia, Bulgaria, October 28, 2005.</note> There are also similar
                    developments in a more abstract sense. The TEI Guidelines have been translated
                    into Russian,<note n="6">See <xptr to="http://www.tei-c.org.uk/Lite/teiu5_ru.rtf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>.</note> and efforts are also being made to promote the further
                    internationalization of the Guidelines, and to ensure their availability in a
                    greater number of languages, including Bulgarian. </p><p>Yet even when East European scholarly projects adopt the TEI, standardized
                    approaches to the conversion of metadata to OAI-compliant formats are also at
                    issue, and there is evidently much ground still to be covered. Hence, the object
                    of this paper will be to:<list type="ordered"><item>Design and conduct a survey of metadata practices in
                            a number of East European digital centers (including existing UIUC
                            partners) that are sponsored both by institutions and by individual
                            faculty teams;</item><item>Produce an up-to-date analysis of their awareness,
                            evaluation and observance of international metadata standards;</item><item>Identify problems and practices preventing their
                            implementation;</item><item>Suggest ways in which steps can be taken to
                            ameliorate this situation, including crosswalks and other technical
                            procedures.</item></list></p><p>The results of this exercise will not only assist in a practical sense the
                    development of the <emph>Inventory of Slavic, East European and Eurasian Digital
                        Projects</emph> (the only registry of substantive, scholarly East European
                    digital initiatives), but will also result in better awareness and
                    information-sharing among Slavic digital practitioners. This is especially vital
                    as the institutional repository movement gains ground.<note n="7">Here again the
                        number of East European repositories lags far behind. In July 2006 there
                        were 144 DSpace instances worldwide, and less than half were in the U.S. and
                        U.K. (62), indicating that many non-English-speaking countries (like Japan)
                        are aware of and attracted to this increasingly popular open source
                        software. But in Eastern Europe only 2 DSpace sites were listed (in Russia).
                        This lack of awareness was substantiated at an e-text conference in Eastern
                        Russia in July 2006 entitled <emph rend="bold">Modern Informational
                            Technologies and Written Heritage: From Ancient Manuscripts to
                            Electronic Texts</emph> at which I gave a presentation entitled
                        “Promoting the TEI in scholarly communities: OAI harvesting, digital
                        repositories.” Conference attendees described many sophisticated projects,
                        but there was little familiarity with OAI or digital repository software
                        used in the West. One scholar was familiar with these technologies, but in a
                        presentation entitled: “A Computer System for the Creation and Maintenance
                        of Electronic Collections of Ancient Texts,” V. S. Iuzhikov (Kazan State
                        University) wrote: “For the creation and development of electronic libraries
                        there are several systems. Among the best known are Greenstone and DSpace.
                        But they are oriented mostly toward text libraries with small number of
                        illustrations, which are poorly suited for the collection of old printed
                        works. Therefore it is less time-consuming and gives better result to build
                        a local system.” Given the specialized nature of his material, this
                        conclusion was understandable. Yet the general lack of East European
                        involvement with these international standards and methodologies remains
                        true.</note> Experience shows, particularly in West Europe, that the issue
                    of standardized metadata is paramount, and that subject repositories are
                    becoming of even greater interest since they tend to be populated by scholars
                    working on their own projects and producing more substantive metadata. In this
                    environment, East European scholars should not excluded from the pool of
                    informed experience. </p></div0></body></text></TEI.2>