<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="poster_186_poster"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Extracting Stylistic Distances from Texts for Forensic Linguistics Purposes</title><author><name reg="Frantzi, Katerina T.">Katerina T. Frantzi</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Field, Hana S.">Hana S. Field</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>poster</classCode><keywords><list><item>forensic linguistics</item><item>corpus linguistics</item><item>author identification</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list><item>HSF: Created from Katerina T. Frantzi's doc<date value="2007-03"> March
                    2007</date></item><item>SAS: Revised <date value="2007-05"> May 2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Extracting Stylistic Distances from Texts for Forensic Linguistics                 Purposes"><titlePart type="main">Extracting Stylistic Distances from Texts for Forensic
                    Linguistics Purposes</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Frantzi, Katerina T.">Katerina T. Frantzi</name><address><addrLine>frantzi@rhodes.aegean.gr</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart>Department of Mediterranean Studies<lb/>University of the Aegean </titlePart></front><body><div0><p>The paper proposes a method for the automatic processing of forensic texts for
                    the extraction of similarities and dissimilarities to be used for authorship
                    identification purposes. Forensic Linguistics expresses the application of
                    linguistics to the analysis of forensic language in written or oral form, the
                    study of the language of the law, the study of legal interpretation and
                    translation, the alleviation of disadvantage produced by language in legal
                    processes, the provision of forensic linguistic evidence and of linguistic
                    expertise in issues of legal drafting and interpretation (Conley &amp;
                    O’Barr, 1998; Shy 1998; Cotterill, 2002; McMenamin &amp; Dongdoo 2002;
                    Semino &amp; Culpeper, 2002; Gibbons, 2003). Our forensic texts belong to a
                    Greek terrorist organization, “17 November” (Kassimeris, 1997; Παπαχελάς
                    &amp; Τέλλογλου, 2002; Frantzi, 2004). 17N started its action in 1975, while
                    the summer/autumn of 2002, all (or most) of the members were arrested. The case
                    is currently in court for the second time. 84 of the proclamations, that used to
                    follow a 17N attack, have been characterized as genuine (Κάκτος, 2002). Their
                    authorship is an open issue. The final aim of this project is to map each of the
                    17N proclamations to its possible author (Frantzi &amp; Ananiadou, 2006). In
                    this work we propose a way to characterise an organization’s text, i.e.
                    proclamation, pleading, replication, by values on its stylistic characteristics.
                    The values are used for extracting similarities and dissimilarities among texts.</p><p>We consider the following stylistics features: the average sentence and word
                    length, the number of different nouns, proper nouns, adjectives, active voice
                    verbs, passive voice verbs, adverbs, the number of future tense references, the
                    use of conjunctions, preposition, pronouns, particles, determiners, articles,
                    question words, punctuation, content words. For each pair of possibly owned by
                    the same author writings, we create a matrix which we call
                    <emph>distance-matrix</emph> (Table 1). Each cell of the matrix contains a
                    number that corresponds to a stylistic feature distance between the two
                    writings.</p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_186_frantzi_1.jpg</xref></p><figDesc/></figure><p>In order to compute the <emph>distance-matrix</emph> for a pair of writings, we
                    need to assign a value to each cell that corresponds to a particular stylistic
                    feature. This value gives the difference (distance) between the two writings
                    regarding the specific feature. Then the distance between the two writings is
                    evaluated by the average value of all the <emph>feature-distances</emph> in the
                        <emph>distance-matrix</emph>. A <emph>feature-distance</emph> is assigned to
                    a cell and is calculated by the average of all phenomena distances for that
                    feature. The phenomena distances for a feature are calculated by their
                    normalized frequencies of occurrence in the two writings. The algorithm for the
                    processing of the <emph>feature-distances</emph> is the following:</p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_186_frantzi_2.jpg</xref></p><figDesc/></figure><p>Each author is characterized by his/her pleadings and replications. If we could
                    match a proclamation to a pleading (and replication) then we could possibly
                    match a proclamation to the corresponding author. We need to compare all
                    pleadings (and replications) to the proclamations, to find the smallest
                    “distance” in terms of their feature values. The smallest distance assigns a
                    proclamation to a pleading, i.e. an author.</p><p>In this work we apply the <emph>distance-table</emph> method for comparisons
                    between the pleadings and replications: we already know the authors of the
                    pleadings and proclamations, so we can present how the
                    <emph>distance-table</emph> works. We apply the method to three writings: one
                    pleading and two replications. Let us consider Yotopoulos’s (the person accused
                    to be the main leader and one of the main authors of the proclamations) pleading
                    of 18321 words, and replication of 2036 words, and Koufontinas’s (also accused
                    to be a leading member) replication of 326 words. We will evaluate the
                        <emph>distance-matrix</emph> for the pairs of writings (Yotopoulos’s
                    pleading, Yotopoulos’s replication) and (Yotopoulos’s pleading, Koufontinas’s
                    replication). We will show the evaluation for one of the cells of the two
                        <emph>distance-matrixes</emph>, the <emph>distance-matrix</emph>[1,1], i.e.
                    the cell that keeps the distance regarding the stylistic feature of the
                    particles’ use, while the evaluation is analogous for the rest of the
                        cells.<note n="1">We cannot present the evaluation of all cells here due to
                        space restrictions.</note> There are five particles in Greek: “να”, “για”,
                    “θα”, “ας” and “μα”. Table 2 gives the frequencies of occurrence and normalized
                    frequencies (to 10,000 words) for the five particles found in Yotopoulos’s
                    pleading (Yp) and replication (Yr) and those in Koufodinas’s replication (Kr).</p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_186_frantzi_3.jpg</xref></p><figDesc/></figure><p>The <emph>distance-matrix</emph>[1,1] cell for the (Yotopoulos’s pleading,
                    Yotopoulos’s replication) <emph>distance-matrix</emph> holds the distance
                    regarding the use of particles. We evaluate the distance on the use of each of
                    the five particle between the two writings and we assign to the
                        <emph>distance-matrix</emph>1,1] cell the average of all the particles’
                    distances. Then we do the same for the <emph>distance-matrix</emph>1,1] cell of
                    the (Yotopoulos’s pleading, Koufodinas’s replication)
                    <emph>distance-matrix</emph>. The particles’ distances for the particle “να” for
                    the two pair of writings are calculated according the above-given algorithm
                    as:The <emph>distance-matrix</emph>[1,1] cell for the (Yotopoulos’s pleading,
                    Yotopoulos’s replication) <emph>distance-matrix</emph> holds the distance
                    regarding the use of particles. We evaluate the distance on the use of each of
                    the five particle between the two writings and we assign to the
                        <emph>distance-matrix</emph>[1,1] cell the average of all the particles’
                    distances. Then we do the same for the <emph>distance-matrix</emph>[1,1] cell of
                    the (Yotopoulos’s pleading, Koufodinas’s replication)
                    <emph>distance-matrix</emph>. The particles’ distances for the particle “να” for
                    the two pair of writings are calculated according the above-given algorithm as:</p><l>Particles_distance(Yp,Yr)[να]=|245.619 - 294.695| / (245.619 + 294.695)=0.091</l><l>Particles_distance(Yp,Κr)[να]=|245.619 - 122.699| / (245.619 + 122.699)=0.334</l><p>Table 3 gives the results of the calculations for all the particles’ distances
                    for those pair of writings. We get the average for each of the columns of Table
                    3, i.e. 0.289 and 0.409. These averages will be assigned to
                        <emph>distance-matrixes.</emph>[1,1] cells for the two pairs of writings
                        <emph>distance-matrixes.</emph></p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_186_frantzi_4.jpg</xref></p><figDesc/></figure><p>Table 4 gives all the <emph>feature-distances</emph> for the (Yotopoulos’s
                    pleading, Yotopoulos’s replication) <emph>distance-matrix</emph>while Table 5
                    for the (Yotopoulos’s pleading, Koufodinas’s replication) one. </p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_186_frantzi_5.jpg</xref></p><figDesc/></figure><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_186_frantzi_6.jpg</xref></p><figDesc/></figure><p>When matrixes are filled up, we can evaluate the total distances for the pairs of
                    writings as the average of all the cell values:</p><l><emph>matrix-distance</emph>(Yp, Kr)= 0.5593</l><l><emph>matrix-distance</emph> (Yp,Yr)= 0.3382</l><p>As a result Yotopoulos’s pleading is linked to Yotopoulos’s replication (smaller
                    distance), which actually means that these two writings have been found to be
                    closer as for their language style than the writings of Yotopoulos’s pleading
                    and Koufodinas’s replication.</p><p>Future work involves: <list type="unordered"><item>Augmentation of the <emph>distance-matrix</emph> with more stylistics
                            features, e.g. the use of collocations (Frantzi &amp; Ananiadou,
                            2007),</item><item>use of weights for the stylistics features,</item><item>application of the method for characterizing the proclamations for the
                            provision of authorship evidence,</item><item>comparisons among the proclamations for their grouping according to
                            their linguistic profile.</item></list></p></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Conley, John M.">John M. Conley</name></author><author><name reg="O'Barr, William M..">William M. O'Barry</name></author><title level="m">Just Words – Law, Language, and Power</title><imprint><pubPlace>Chicago and London</pubPlace><publisher>The University of Chicago Press</publisher><date value="1998">1998</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><title level="m">Language in the Legal Process</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="Cotterill, Janet">Janet Cotterill</name></editor><imprint><publisher>MacMillan</publisher><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Gibbons, John">John Gibbons</name></author><title level="m">Forensic Linguistics: An Introduction to Language in
                                the Justice System</title><title level="s">Language in Society 32</title><imprint><publisher>Blackwell Publishing Ltd</publisher><date value="2003">2003</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Frantzi, Katerina T.">Katerina T. Frantzi</name></author><author><name reg="Ananiadou, Sophia">Sophia Ananiadou</name></author><title level="a">Automatic Authorship Identification</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Proceedings of the International Association of
                                Forensic Linguistics 2nd European Conference on Forensic Linguistics
                                / Language &amp; the Law</title><imprint><pubPlace>Barcelona, Spain</pubPlace><biblScope type="pages">14-16</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Frantzi, Katerina T.">Katerina T. Frantzi</name></author><author><name reg="Ananiadou, Sophia">Sophia Ananiadou</name></author><title level="a">C-value for Authorship Identification</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">Proceedings of the International Association of
                                Forensic Linguistics 8th Biennial International Conference on
                                Forensic Linguistics / Language &amp; the Law – IAFL 8, Seattle,
                                Washington, July 12-15 2007</title><imprint><date value="forthcoming">forthcoming</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Frantzi, Katerina T.">Katerina T. Frantzi</name></author><title level="a">Corpus Linguistics: What can it do with
                            Terrorism?</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">International Journal of Humanities</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">2.2</biblScope><date value="2004">2004</date><biblScope type="pages">1603-1608</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Κάκτος">Κάκτος</name></author><title level="m">17N – Οι προκηρύξεις</title><imprint><pubPlace>Αθήνα</pubPlace><publisher>Κάκτος</publisher><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Kassimeris, George">George Kassimeris</name></author><title level="m">Europe’s Last Red Terrorists: The Revolutionary
                                Organization 17 November</title><imprint><publisher>C. Hurst &amp; Co. Ltd</publisher><date value="1997">1997</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><title level="m">Forensic Linguistics : Advances in Forensic Stylistics</title><editor role="editor"><name reg="McMenamin, Gerald R.">Gerald R. McMenamin</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Dongdoo, Choi">Choi Dongdoo</name></editor><imprint><publisher>CRC Press</publisher><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Παπαχελάς, Α.">A. Παπαχελάς</name></author><author><name reg="Τέλλογλου, Τ.">T. Τέλλογλου</name></author><title level="a">Φάκελος 17 Νοέμβρη</title><imprint><pubPlace>Αθήνα, Ελλάδα</pubPlace><publisher>Εστία</publisher><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><editor role="editor"><name reg="Semino, Elena">Elena Semino</name></editor><editor role="editor"><name reg="Culpeper, Jonathan">Jonathan Culpeper</name></editor><title level="m">Cognitive Stylistics: Language and Cognition in Text
                                Analysis</title><title level="s">Linguistic Approaches to Literature 1</title><imprint><publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Company</publisher><date value="2002">2002</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Shuy, Roger W.&gt;">Roger W. Shuy</name></author><title level="m">The Language of Confession, Interrogation and Deception </title><title level="s">Empirical Linguistics Series</title><imprint><publisher>Sage Publications</publisher><date value="1998">1998</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>