<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="panel_207_porter"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>Digital Humanities and the Solitary Scholar</title><author><name reg="Birnbaum, David J.">David J. Birnbaum</name></author><author><name reg="Norton, Michael L.">Michael L. Norton</name></author><author><name reg="Patrik, Linda E.">Linda E. Patrik</name></author><author><name reg="Porter, Dorothy Carr">Dorothy Carr Porter</name></author><author><name reg="Rockwell, Geoffrey">Geoffrey Rockwell</name></author><author><name reg="Aguera, Helen">Helen Aguera</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>panel</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>independent scholarship</item><item>collaboration</item><item>digital humanities community</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from Dorothy Carr Porter's doc <date value="2007-05">May
                    2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="Digital Humanities and the Solitary Scholar"><titlePart type="main">Digital Humanities and the Solitary Scholar</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Birnbaum, David J.">David J. Birnbaum</name><address><addrLine>djbpitt@pitt.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of Pittsburgh</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Norton, Michael L.">Michael L. Norton</name><address><addrLine>nortonml@jmu.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil"> James Madison University </titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Patrik, Linda E."> Linda E. Patrik</name><address><addrLine>patrikl@union.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Union College</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Porter, Dorothy Carr"> Dorothy Carr Porter</name><address><addrLine>dporter@uky.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of Kentucky </titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Rockwell, Geoffrey">Geoffrey Rockwell</name><address><addrLine>georock@mcmaster.ca</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">McMaster University</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Aguera, Helen">Helen Aguera</name><address><addrLine>haguera@neh.gov</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">National Endowment for the Humanities</titlePart></front><body><div0><ab><cit rend="block"><q>"The process of creating new knowledge -- of research and scholarship --
                            is also evolving rapidly away from the solitary scholar to teams of
                            scholars, perhaps spread over a number of disciplines."</q><bibl>James J. Duderstadt, "Transforming the University to Serve the Digital
                            Age," CAUSE/EFFECT 20.4 (Winter 1997-98): 21-32.</bibl></cit></ab><p>In the epigraph for our session, Duderstadt succinctly describes a major
                    challenge facing the humanities – specifically the scholars who make the
                    practice of humanities research their own – as they head into a digital future.
                    The typical scholar in the humanities is generally perceived as a loner, an
                    individual working more or less in isolation towards publications that will be
                    his or her sole responsibility. Scholars are not completely isolated, of course.
                    The sharing of pre-publication knowledge is common, and workshops and
                    conferences abound in all fields to give scholars the opportunity to find out
                    what others are doing, to present their own work to the community, and to talk
                    with others whose interests and research overlap their own. However, as a glance
                    at the contents pages of the most recent issue of any historical or literary
                    journal will suggest, it is not common for more than one humanist to claim
                    authorship for a single piece of scholarship. There is contrast here with
                    scholarship in the hard sciences and engineering, where much work is done by
                    groups, collaboration is the norm, and where several people usually claim
                    authorship to any one publication. Digital humanities inherits from both of
                    these traditions, encouraging cross-disciplinary collaboration within a
                    community that has traditionally valued independence.</p><p>This short paper session will present the experiences of three scholars working
                    more or less in isolation within the context of this collaborative environment.
                    These individuals are alike in that they are all actively involved in the
                    development of digital projects, but their experiences vary widely with regard
                    to time available for working on these projects, their own technical/programming
                    skills and like support available from their institutions, and the availability
                    of funding to support their projects. In addition to these three scholars, we
                    also welcome two others whose work exists to support the efforts of solitary
                    scholars. However, it may be seen that even "solitary" scholars are not so alone
                    in the digital humanities.</p></div0><div0><head>"I'm ready to start a project! What do I need to know?"</head><p>Our first two speakers represent the technically skilled scholar.</p><p>Birnbaum has developed two XML-related projects on his own and he will report on
                    the logistics of these projects. Funding and support for both projects is light
                    and he is responsible for all the technology, although his colleagues provide
                    philological knowledge.</p><p>Norton will discuss his experience as a computer scientist with a PhD in Music
                    History developing a project on digital representations of medieval liturgical
                    manuscripts. He is working on the project independently, and while he has the
                    programming and design skills necessary for success, he is facing limitations of
                    time (as he is also trying to write a book, a familiar problem for many).</p></div0><div0><head>"Well, how do I learn?"</head><p>Our third speaker will discuss alternatives for solitary scholars to learn how to
                    take steps towards developing digital projects.</p><p>Rockwell will talk first about how to take advantage of university resources.
                    Many universities have Teaching and Learning Centers and Digital Library
                    Services that you can draw on for help. Some universities have special
                    Humanities Computing units that specialize in supporting digital projects in the
                    humanities. Rockwell will summarize some of the services you can look for at
                    your university.</p><p>In addition, Rockwell will speak as a the project leader of the Text Analysis
                    Portal for Research (TAPoR) project (<xptr to="http://www.tapor.ca/" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>), which makes text analysis tools available to scholars for
                    integration into their electronic text projects. Rockwell will discuss the TAPoR
                    tools, and will discuss how scholars working in isolation can take advantage of
                    them without the need for programming experience or access to programming
                    support.</p></div0><div0><head>"I have the skills, I have a great idea... what about funding?"</head><p>Our final two speakers will present two different aspects of acquiring funding
                    for digital humanities projects.</p><p>Patrik will discuss issues that she has encountered while attempting to organize
                    a TEI encoding project at a liberal arts college. Although Patrik's institution
                    is supportive of her digital endeavors, she has not had success applying for
                    funds from the major funding agencies. Unfortunately, without access to graduate
                    student labor and a dedicated support staff and with the lack of time that comes
                    from being a full-time professor in an institution where the focus is on
                    undergraduate teaching, Patrik is at a disadvantage. She is interested in
                    exploring the possibilities of collaborating with larger institutions, moving
                    from isolation to collaboration.</p><p>Winter will discuss the NEH Digital Humanities Initiative, and how the initiative
                    can support the work of solitary or independent project directors. He will focus
                    on two of the new DH-specific grant initiatives: Digital Humanities Start-Up
                    Grants<lb/> (<xptr to="http://www.neh.gov/grants/guidelines/digitalhumanitiesstartup.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>) and Digital Humanities Fellowships<lb/> (<xptr to="http://www.neh.gov/grants/guidelines/dhfellowships.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>). </p><p>Each of our speakers will have seven to ten minutes to discuss his or her work,
                    making reference to limitations of time, technical support, and funding, and how
                    those limits impact their projects. The remainder of the session will be a
                    roundtable discussion, and the audience will be encouraged to ask questions of
                    the panel and to discuss their own experiences working in isolation</p></div0></body></text></TEI.2>