<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="poster_181_miyake"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>A Network Structure of the Synoptic Gospels Employing Clustering Coefficients</title><author><name reg="Miyake, Maki">Maki Miyake</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Field, Hana S.">Hana S. Field</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>poster</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>semantic network</item><item>graph clustering</item><item>Marov Clustering</item><item>biblical studies</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list><item>HSF: Created from Maki Miyake's text<date value="2007-04">April
                    2007</date></item><item>SAS: Revised <date value="2007-05">May 2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="A Network Structure of the Synoptic Gospels Employing Clustering Coefficients"><titlePart type="main">A Network Structure of the Synoptic Gospels Employing
                    Clustering Coefficients</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Miyake, Maki">Maki Miyake</name><address><addrLine>mmiyake@lang.osaka-u.ac.jp</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">Osaka University</titlePart></front><body><div0><p>In this presentation, we propose a graph-theory approach to the systematization
                    of the texts of the Synoptic Gospels. Specifically, we apply a new
                    graph-clustering technique for data processing that utilizes a
                    clustering-coefficient threshold in creating semantic networks for the Gospels.
                    Taking Greek texts (Nestle-Aland, 1979) as the textual source, an adjacency
                    matrix for graphs is created from word co-occurrence data for a given range of
                    the texts. We also develop a web-based application for the dynamic
                    representation of the network structures based on the relationships between
                    words and concepts.</p><p>Network representations are useful in modeling natural language semantics
                    (Stevers, &amp; Tenenbaum, 2005). Recently, Dorow (2006) has proposed the
                    notion of curvature (clustering coefficient) as a clustering tool to detect
                    ambiguity and to acquire semantic classes rather than using word frequencies.
                    The clustering coefficient represents the interconnective strength between
                    neighboring nodes in a graph. Following Watts and Strogatz (1998), the
                    clustering coefficient of the node (n) can be defined as: (number of links among
                    n's neighbors)/(N(n)*(N)-1)/2), where N(n) denotes the set of n's neighbors. The
                    coefficient assumes values between 0 and 1.</p><p>In processing a text, word pairs are computed by a windowing method (Takayama,
                    Flournoy, Kaufmann, &amp;. Peters). The windowing method provides a
                    relatively simple representation of similarity levels that is suitable for
                    clustering. The technique involves moving a certain sized window over a text to
                    extract all fixed-sized word grams (Vechthomova, Roberston, &amp; Jones,
                    2003). Word pairings are subsequently made by combining all extracted words.
                    Co-occurrence data is computed with two window sizes that reflect syntactic and
                    semantic considerations. The first size is set at 2 for the nearest
                    co-occurrence, while the second size is set to 20 to collect words both before
                    and after a sentence. Morphological data for the BibleWorks Greek New Testament
                    Morphology (BNM) was used in a stemming process to obtain base word forms from
                    morphological variants. Consequently, 2,688 word occurrences were identified.</p><p>In Figure 1, the degree distribution for the word occurrences nodes are plotted
                    in log-log coordinates with showing the best fitting power law distribution
                    (r=1.4). Following Barabasi and Albert (1999), the feature of power-law degree
                    distribution indicates the small-world structure of the semantic network. Figure
                    2 is a plot for the clustering coefficient as a function of degree. There are 16
                    words that have a clustering coefficient value of less than 0.1. These are
                    articles, prepositions, pronouns, and conjunctions, which are usually regarded
                    as "noise" words. We use the clustering coefficient value as a threshold in
                    order to eliminate such noise words and to control the datasets for graph
                    clustering. In applying the clustering technique, nine datasets were created
                    with 0.1 increments in the value of the clustering coefficient (from 0.1 to
                    0.9). The datasets for each window size were converted into adjacency matrices
                    for Recurrent Markov Clustering (RMCL) (Jung, Miyake, &amp; Akama, 2006).</p><p>RMCL is an improved form of Markov Clustering (MCL) (van Dongen, 2000). The MCL
                    algorithm is based on random walks for a graph, and its model simulates flow by
                    using the two simple algebraic operations of expansion and inflation on the
                    stochastic transition matrix. The method has been applied to a number of
                    corpora, such as a French synonym dictionary (Gfeller, 2005) and the British
                    National Corpus (Dorow, Widdows, Ling, Eckmann, Danilo, and Moses, 2005). In
                    contrast, RMCL allows for greater control over the sizes of concept domains by
                    modifying graph granularity and the generality of concepts. The recurrent
                    process gets feedback from the state of overlapping clustering before the output
                    of MCL. This reversal procedure is a key feature of RMCL in generating a virtual
                    adjacency matrix for the non overlapping clusters as a resultant state of
                    convergence actually yielded by the MCL process. The resultant downsized matrix
                    provides a simpler graph of the conceptual structures underlying similar words.</p><p>Figure 3 shows the transitions in cluster sizes for the MCL and RMCL processes as
                    a function of the clustering coefficient with a window size of 2, while Figure 4
                    shows similar data with a window size of 20. The term input data refers to the
                    initial adjacency matrices. Figure 4 indicates that while cluster sizes are
                    almost identical for RMCL and MCL at clustering coefficient values of 0.6 or
                    more, RMCL clearly yields smaller clusters at values of 0.5 or less. The MCL
                    clustering results in Figure 4 for the window size of 20 indicate the strong
                    connectedness between nodes, as all nodes are grouped into a single cluster for
                    coefficient values of 0.2 or less.</p><p>The results for both the MCL and RMCL processes are implemented as graph network
                    structures in a web application, which has been developed to dynamically
                    represent the relationships between words and how MCL components might
                    correspond to concepts. Figure 5 is a screen shot of the web application, which
                    uses Apache2 as an http server and Tomcat5 as a JSP and servlet engine.
                    WebMathematica is used to call a Mathematica kernal to calculate the graphs.</p><p>In conclusion, the clustering coefficient represents a useful tool for
                    manipulating datasets to eliminate noise words. The RMCL methods allows for the
                    creation of compact semantic networks, which clearly present the relationships
                    between words.</p><p>In future works, we will apply different clustering-coefficient thresholds to
                    detect ambiguous words, particularly words with low coefficient-low degree
                    values. We will also evaluate systematizations of the Synoptic Gospels by
                    biblical scholars and explore the effectiveness of our approach in furthering
                    biblical studies.</p><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_181_miyake_1.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 1: The Degree Distributions</figDesc></figure><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_181_miyake_2.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 2: Clustering coefficient plotted as a function of
                    degree</figDesc></figure><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_181_miyake_3.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 3: Clustering Coefficient (window size =2)</figDesc></figure><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_181_miyake_4.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 4: Clustering Coefficient (window size =20)</figDesc></figure><figure rend="ImageLink"><head/><p><xref to="DITTO" from="ROOT" targOrder="U">poster_181_miyake_5.jpg</xref></p><figDesc>Figure 5: Screen shot of a web application</figDesc></figure></div0></body><back><div type="Bibliography"><head>Bibliography</head><listBibl><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Baranbasi, A.L.">A.L. Baranbasi</name></author><author><name reg="Albert R.&gt;">R. Albert</name></author><title level="a">Emergence of Scaling in Random Networks</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Science</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">286</biblScope><date value="1999">1999</date><biblScope type="pages">509-512</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Dorow, B.">B. Dorow</name></author><author><name reg="Widdows, D.">D. Widdows</name></author><author><name reg="Ling, K.">K. Ling</name></author><author><name reg="Eckmann, J.">J. Eckmann</name></author><author><name reg="Sergi, D.">D. Sergi</name></author><author><name reg="Moses, E..">E. Moses</name></author><title level="a">Using Curvature and Markov Clustering in Graphs for
                                Lexical Acquisition and Word Sense Discrimination</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">MEANING-2005, 2nd Workshop organized by the MEANING
                                Project, February 3rd-4th 2005, Trento, Italy</title><imprint><pubPlace>Trento,Italy</pubPlace><date value="2005">2005</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Dorow, K.">K. Dorow</name></author><title level="u">"A Graph Model for Words and Their Meaning"</title><edition>Doctoral Thesis</edition><imprint><publisher>University of Stuttgart</publisher><date value="2006">2006</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://elib.uni-stuttgart.de/opus/volltexte/2007/2985/pdf/diss_27022007.pdf" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Gfeller, D.">D. Gfeller</name></author><author><name reg="Chappelier, J. C.">J. C. Chappelier</name></author><author><name reg="De Los Rios, P.">P. De Los Rios</name></author><title level="a">Synonym Dictionary Improvement through Markov
                                Clustering and Clustering Stability</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">International Symposium on Applied Stochastic Models
                                and Data Analysis</title><imprint><biblScope type="pages">106-113</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Jung, J.">J. Jung</name></author><author><name reg="Miyake, Maki">Maki Miyake</name></author><author><name reg="Akama, H.">H. Akama</name></author><title level="a">Recurrent Markov Cluster (RMCL) &amp;
                                #12288; Algorithm for the Refinement of the Semantic Network,
                                LREC2006lity</title></analytic><monogr><title level="m">International Conference on Language Resources and
                                Evaluation</title><imprint><biblScope type="pages">1428-1432</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Nestle-Aland">Nestle-Aland</name></author><title level="m">Novum Testmentum Graece </title><edition>26th edition</edition><imprint><pubPlace>Stuttgart</pubPlace><publisher>German Bible Society</publisher><date value="1987">1987</date></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="Takayama, Y.">Y. Takayama</name></author><author><name reg="Flournoy, R.">R. Flournoy</name></author><author><name reg="Kaufmann, S.">S. Kaufmann</name></author><author><name reg="Peters, S.">S. Peters</name></author><title level="m" type="WWW document"><name reg="Information Mapping: Concept-based Information Retrieval Based on Word Associations">Information Mapping: Concept-based Information Retrieval Based
                                    on Word Associations.</name></title><imprint/></monogr><note><xptr to="http://www-csli.stanford.edu/semlab-hold/infomap/theory.html" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><monogr><author><name reg="van Dongen, Stijn Marinus">Stijn Marinus van Dongen</name></author><title level="u">"Graph Clustering by Flow Simulation"</title><edition>PhD Thesis</edition><imprint><publisher>University of Utrecht</publisher><date value="2000">2000</date></imprint></monogr><note><xptr to="http://igitur-archive.library.uu.nl/dissertations/1895620/inhoud.htm" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/></note></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Steyvers, M.">M. Steyvers</name></author><author><name reg="Tenenbaum, J. B.">J. B. Tenenbaum</name></author><title level="a">The Large-Scale Structure of Semantic Networks:
                                Statistical Analyses and a Model of Semantic Growth</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Cognitive Science</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">29.1</biblScope><date value="2005">2005</date><biblScope type="pages">41-78</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Vechthomova, O.">O. Vechthomova</name></author><author><name reg="Robertson, S.">S. Robertson</name></author><author><name reg="Jones, S.">S. Jones</name></author><title level="a">Query Expansion With Long-Span Collocate</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Information Retrieval</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">6</biblScope><date value="2003">2003</date><biblScope type="pages">251-273</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct><biblStruct><analytic><author><name reg="Watts, D.">D. Watts</name></author><author><name reg="Strogatz, S.">S. Strogatz</name></author><title level="a">Collective Dynamics of ‘Small-World’ Networks</title></analytic><monogr><title level="j">Nature</title><imprint><biblScope type="vol">393</biblScope><date value="1998">1998</date><biblScope type="pages">440-442</biblScope></imprint></monogr></biblStruct></listBibl></div></back></text></TEI.2>