<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2 id="panel_233_adho"><teiHeader><fileDesc><titleStmt><title>ADHO Panel: Beyond Text</title><author><name reg="Unsworth, John">John Unsworth</name></author><author><name reg="Franklin, Kevin">Kevin Franklin</name></author><author><name reg="Manovich, Lev">Lev Manovich</name></author><author><name reg="McPherson, Tara">Tara McPherson</name></author><author><name reg="Plaisant, Catherine">Catherine Plaisant</name></author><author><name reg="Wardrip-Fruin, Noah">Noah Wardrip-Fruin</name></author><respStmt><resp>Marked up by</resp><name reg="Schmidt, Sara A.">Sara A. Schmidt</name></respStmt></titleStmt><publicationStmt><p>Marked up to be included in the Digital Humanities 2007 Conference Abstracts
                    book.</p></publicationStmt><sourceDesc><p>None</p></sourceDesc></fileDesc><profileDesc><textClass><classCode>panel</classCode><keywords><list type="simple"><item>society panel</item><item>humanities computing</item><item>new media</item><item>digital humanities centers</item><item>beyond text</item></list></keywords></textClass></profileDesc><revisionDesc><list type="simple"><item>SAS: Created from John Unsworth's email text<date value="2007-05"> May
                2007</date></item></list></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text><front><docTitle n="ADHO Panel: Beyond text"><titlePart type="main">ADHO Panel: Beyond text</titlePart></docTitle><docAuthor><name reg="Unsworth, John">John Unsworth</name><address><addrLine>unsworth@uiuc.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Franklin, Kevin">Kevin Franklin</name><address><addrLine>kfranklin@hri.uci.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of California
                Humanities Research Institute (UCHRI)</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Manovich, Lev">Lev Manovich</name><address><addrLine>manovich.lev@gmail.com</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of California, San Diego</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="McPherson, Tara">Tara McPherson</name><address><addrLine>tmcphers@usc.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of Southern California</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Plaisant, Catherine">Catherine Plaisant</name><address><addrLine>plaisant@cs.umd.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of Maryland</titlePart><docAuthor><name reg="Wardrip-Fruin, Noah">Noah Wardrip-Fruin</name><address><addrLine>nwf@ucsd.edu</addrLine></address></docAuthor><titlePart type="affil">University of California, San Diego</titlePart></front><body><div0><p>This panel will engage in a discussion of work being done in the humanities
                        that is computational but not literary/linguistic, or at least not primarily
                        focused on text. The panel will also discuss the possibilities for
                        collaboration across the different paradigms of humanities computing/new
                        media/visual culture/grid computing/critical studies.</p><p><hi rend="bold">Moderator:</hi> John Unsworth</p></div0><div0><head>Participants:</head><div1><p rend="Presenter">Kevin Franklin</p><p>Kevin Franklin is executive director of the University of California
                            Humanities Research Institute (UCHRI) and a former deputy director of
                            the San Diego Supercomputer Center. He serves as co-chair for the
                            Humanities, Arts and Social Science Research Group for the Global Grid
                            Forum and is a member of the UC Humanities, Arts and Social Science
                            Technology Council and the Worldwide University Network Grid Advisory
                            Committee. Franklin coordinates UCHRI research and development
                            activities at the interface of the humanities, arts, science and
                            technology.</p></div1><div1><p rend="Presenter">Lev Manovich</p><p>Lev Manovich (<xptr to="http://www.manovich.net" from="ROOT" targOrder="U"/>) is an Associate Professor in the Visual Arts
                            Department, University of California, San Diego where he teaches courses
                            in new media art and theory. He is the author of The Language of New
                            Media (The MIT Press, 2001), Tekstura: Russian Essays on Visual Culture
                            (Chicago University Press, 1993) as well as many articles which have
                            been published in 28 countries. Manovich is in demand to lecture on new
                            media; since 1999 he delivered over 180 lectures in North and South
                            America, Europe, and Asia. His awards include Mellon Fellowship and
                            Guggenheim Fellowship (2002-2003). </p></div1><div1><p rend="Presenter">Tara McPherson</p><p>Tara McPherson Chair, Division of Critical Studies Associate Professor,
                            Gender Studies and Critical Studies Editor, Vectors: Journal of Culture
                            and Technology in a Dynamic Vernacular Professor McPherson teaches
                            courses in television, new media, and popular culture in USC's School of
                            Cinema-TV. Her Reconstructing Dixie: Race, Gender and Nostalgia in the
                            Imagined South (Duke UP: 2003) received the 2004 John G. Cawelti Award
                            for the outstanding book published on American Culture and was a
                            finalist for the Katherine Singer Kovacs Book Award from the Society for
                            Cinema and Media Studies. She is co-editor of the anthology Hop on Pop:
                            The Politics and Pleasures of Popular Culture (Duke UP: 2003). Her
                            writing has appeared in numerous journals, including Camera Obscura, The
                            Velvet Light Trap, Discourse, and Screen, and in edited anthologies such
                            as Race and Cyberspace, The New Media Handbook, The Visual Culture
                            Reader 2.0, Virtual Publics and Basketball Jones.</p></div1><div1><p rend="Presenter">Catherine Plaisant</p><p>Dr. Catherine Plaisant is Associate Research Scientist at the
                            Human-Computer Interaction Laboratory of the University of Maryland
                            Institute for Advanced Computer Studies. She earned a Doctorat
                            d'Ingenieur degree in France in 1982. In 1987 she joined Professor Ben
                            Shneiderman at the Human-Computer Interaction Laboratory. She enjoys
                            most working with multidisciplinary teams on designing and evaluating
                            new interface technologies that are useable and useful. Her research
                            contributions range from focused user interaction techniques (e.g.
                            Excentric Labeling) to innovative visualizations (such as LifeLines for
                            personal records or SpaceTree for hierarchical data exploration) and
                            interactive search interface techniques such as Query Previews. Those
                            interaction techniques have been carefully validated with user studies
                            and are finding applications in industry and government information
                            systems and digital libraries. She has written over 90 refereed
                            technical publications on the subjects of information visualization,
                            digital libraries, universal access, image browsing, input devices,
                            online help, home automation, network management, telemedicine etc. She
                            recently co-authored with Ben Shneiderman the 4th Edition of Designing
                            the User Interface, one of the major books on the topic of
                            Human-Computer Interaction.</p></div1><div1><p rend="Presenter">Noah Wardrip-Fruin</p><p>Noah Wardrip-Fruin is a digital media creator and scholar whose current
                            work is focused on fiction and play. His digital writing/art creates new
                            experiences of reading through bodily interaction, algorithmic
                            recombination, game mechanics, and exploration of the potential of the
                            network as more than a delivery mechanism. These projects have been
                            presented by galleries, arts festivals, scientific conferences, DVD
                            magazines, VR Caves, and the Whitney and Guggenheim museums -- as well
                            as discussed in books such as Digital Art (2003) and Art of the Digital
                            Age (2006). He has recently edited three books and a monograph is
                            forthcoming. He has previously been a research scientist at New York
                            University, a creative writing fellow at Brown University, and an
                            assistant professor at the University of Baltimore. He is a
                            Vice-President of the Electronic Literature Organization.</p></div1></div0></body></text></TEI.2>