
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Automatic Extraction of Hidden Keywords by Producing “Homophily” within
                    Semantic Networks</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-106.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-106.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: Automatic Extraction of Hidden Keywords by Producing “Homophily” within
                    Semantic Networks</h2><h4>
                    Akama, Hiroyuki, 
                    <a href="mailto:akama@dp.hum.titech.ac.jp">akama@dp.hum.titech.ac.jp</a>
                    Tokyo Institute of Technology, 
                    <a href="mailto:"></a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Miyake, Maki, 
                    <a href="mailto:mmiyake@lang.osaka-u.ac.jp">mmiyake@lang.osaka-u.ac.jp</a>
                    University of Osaka, 
                    <a href="mailto:"></a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Jung, Jaeyoung, 
                    <a href="mailto:catherina.rosset@gmail.com">catherina.rosset@gmail.com</a>
                    Tokyo Institute of Technology, 
                    <a href="mailto:"></a>
                </h4><hr />
            

                <p class="noindent">A complex network is usually conceived of in the form of a graph consisting of
                    nodes representing individual, or atomic, entities and edges linking them
                    according to information about semantic attributes or some weighting value. This
                    intellectual intuition can be applied to the world of language where a sign
                    makes sense through the concurrent presence of other signs (Saussure, 1916). In
                    particular, the semantic aspect of a document, as a group of more or less
                    coherent sentences, depends on co-occurrence information about the words being
                    bound together to form topics. When a content-bearing word is found within a
                    neighborhood of other words, one may assume that they produce a constellation of
                    meaning (Schütze, 1997; Takayama, 1999). Conceptual interrelatedness can be
                    represented in a graph form called a semantic network. Similarly, in the field
                    of digital humanities, the graph-based approach to document analysis is becoming
                    a major research trend (Miyake, 2009).</p>
                <p class="noindent">In semantic networks, graph coefficients are useful for examining the features of
                    language data, such as a document or corpus, from the perspective of meaning.
                    Hubs with the highest degree values can be regarded as being as key words
                    (excluding functional words), that are highly involved in producing the document
                    context. In normal cases, the bias of degree distributions to follow a power law
                    (or, more concretely, Zipf’s law) has been handled by the concept of scale-free
                    (Barabási et al., 1999) for complex networks. However, one graph index that
                    researchers are increasingly paying close attention to is the concept of
                    ‘intrinsic weights’ that are not distributed to edges but to vertices
                    (Caldarelli et al., 2002; Boguñá et al., 2003; Masuda et al, 2004). The
                    emergence of this weighting within some network settings certainly leads a
                    situation where vertex degree generates a phenomena known as the ‘Rich Club’
                    (Zhou et al, 2004; Colizza et al., 2006), consisting of hubs with high intrinsic
                    weights. However Masuda et al. (2006) have revealed a contrastive kind of
                    subgraph area, which they figuratively refer to as a ‘VIP Club’, where vertices
                    with similar weighting values are exclusively connected to form a confined
                    circle of privileged elites. This “homophily” tendency (Axelrod, 1997; Barrat et
                    al., 2004; Centola et al.2007) makes the average shortest path length
                    significantly longer, so that the innermost graph area becomes harder to access,
                    forming a preserve for the so-called ‘masterminds’ (Masuda et al., 2006).</p>
                <p class="noindent">These elite entities may be, in some sense, regarded as ‘hidden keywords’ within
                    complex networks, where all the words are interconnected—at dense intervals—from
                    a paradigmatic perspective (Jacobson, 1963). These mastermind words are
                    unquestionably of moderately high frequency or degree, but they are tightly
                    related to one another by ‘homophilous’ ties to form very important but discreet
                    lexical patterns. The term homophilous here means a significantly high value of
                    ‘degree correlation’ (Boguñá et al, 2003; Boccaletti et al., 2006), which serves
                    as a marker for the VIP-Club phenomenon (See Figure I). These mastermind words,
                    which are relatively difficult to retrieve during comprehension within the
                    reading process, sometimes play a crucial role in producing well-calculated
                    subliminal effects or hinting at authors’ obsessions with their long-cherished
                    themes.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Be that as it may, the Incremental Advancing Window (IAW), a windowing method
                    (Burges, 1998; Lemaire et al., 2005) that Akama et al (2008) have proposed in
                    order to extract word association patterns from a whole document, clearly
                    satisfies the requirements for creating a homophilous semantic network from
                    lexical co-occurrence information. From such a graph, it is possible to extract
                    hidden keywords with moderate frequencies as members of the clusters regarded as
                    being VIP-Clubs. In this method, the window proceeds step by step through an
                    entire document (after the removal of noise words) to collect all word pairs
                    appearing at least once inside the frame. The list of all pair instances thus
                    obtained with their frequencies makes it possible to generate a semantic
                    network. However, two parameters are set to some specific values to adjust for
                    recall and precision in the data gathering: namely, the window size (diameter)
                    is changed from 1 to m and the threshold for word pair frequency (theta; θ) is
                    changed from 1 to n (m and n are both natural numbers larger than 1). For
                    example, if the theta value is 3, word pairs appearing less than 3 times in the
                    window are ignored. Precisely, this means that, no matter how frequently a word
                    appears in a text, keywords are rejected from the list of vertices for the
                    semantic network representing the text, if the instances of paired words are
                    extremely rare with recorded frequencies lower than θ. This is why a graph
                    derived by IAW exhibits the homophily tendency, if we consider degree itself to
                    be an intrinsic weighting for a vertex.</p>
                <p class="noindent">For instance, let us cite a study conducted by Akama et al (2008) which applied
                    IAW to Saint-Exupéry’s novel "Le petit prince" (original French version). The
                    sample consisted of 1,312 content-bearing words remaining after a stop list was
                    applied. If window size (diameter) is at the smallest level and threshold is
                    similarly maximally strict, then the words extracted by IAW are numerically low,
                    but they form tightly cohesive aggregates, suggesting that the precision rate,
                    P, and the recall rate, R, are always in a trade-off relationship. A severe
                    windowing condition with a threshold value set to 6 allowed us to recall the 38
                    most important words from the standpoint of co-occurrence patterns, but some of
                    them were not included in the list of the 38 most frequent words. These hidden
                    keywords, or mastermind words, were «apprivoiser», «boa», «cent un», «consigne»,
                    «fermé», «manger», «monde», «posséder», «ramoner», «région», «unique», and
                    «volcan», which could all be characterized as homophilous in terms of degree
                    similarity.</p>
                <p class="noindent">In contrast, words that were among the top words but excluded from the most
                    severe IAW computational conditions were «aimer», «ami», «baobab», «connaître»,
                    «croire», «dessin», «jour», «nuit», «grande personne», «rose», «sérieux», and
                    «venir», which are all ordinary keywords sharing the feature of heterophily in
                    terms of degree-frequency—a tendency to be linked, or even collocated, with many
                    different words (Figure II). In the smallest semantic network containing both
                    groups of words (window size = 7, threshold for pair frequency = 6), the average
                    shortest path lengths from all dangling nodes representing peripheral words to
                    the vertices of these 12 masterminds (the first group) and to those of the
                    purely general keywords (the second group) were 4.172 and 3.747, respectively,
                    representing a highly significant difference according to a conducted t test
                    (Figure III).</p>
                <p class="noindent">This result reveals much about the characteristic traits of mastermind words,
                    which when coupled with graph clustering, permits us to understand how they
                    shape communities that deserve the label of VIP-Clubs. To prove this, Markov
                    Clustering (MCL) was applied to the smallest semantic network with IAW
                    parameters of window size = 1 and threshold for pair frequency = 6 (thus
                    screening out many weak co-occurrence patterns and focusing on the most frequent
                    instances of bi-gram). MCL proposed by Van Dongen (2001) is well known as a
                    scalable unsupervised cluster algorithm for graphs that decomposes a whole graph
                    into small coherent groups by simulating the probability movements of a random
                    walker across the graph. It is assumed that when MCL is applied to semantic
                    networks, it yields clusters of words that share certain similarities in meaning
                    or that appear to be related to common concepts (Dorow et al., 2005; Jung et al,
                    2007). As a matter of fact, the present clustering results produced some
                    clusters which consist almost exclusively of homophilous masterminds, such as
                    {monde, unique}, {boa, fermé, serpent}, and {éteindre, volcan, ramoner}. These
                    clusters suggest a series of subtopics that are not so dominating within the
                    novel, but that convey a persistent and deep resonance to the readers.</p>
                <p class="noindent">As described, a text, when treated in the form of a graph, exhibits some hidden
                    keywords that can be enumerated as mastermind entities through the analysis of a
                    homophilous semantic network. Furthermore, if a graph clustering method, such as
                    MCL, is applied to the network, the vertices with such features are categorized
                    into sub-topic clusters, known as VIP-Clubs. Despite the moderate degrees
                    (frequencies) of these vertices (words), they are inconspicuously combined to
                    create lexical patterns which, although they are minor, or subsidiary, in
                    nature, are yet effective.</p>
                <p class="noindent">
                    <p>
                        <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//106/Figure1.jpg" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-106.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//106/Figure1.jpg','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                    </p>
                </p>
                <p class="noindent">Figure I : A homophilous graph (left) and a heterophilous graph (right) : an
                    agglomeration of ‘VIP-Club’ is recognizable in the homophilous graph, while
                    homogeneity underlies the heterophilous graph. Both networks with the same
                    number of nodes (50) and the same connectivity (38.5%) are produced by
                    respectively applying different <i>pruning functions</i>--which
                    consist of trimming edges with probabilities varying according to the weight
                    correlation--to an identical random graph whose distribution of ‘intrinsic
                    weights’ follows the degree distribution of the equal-sized BA model (scale-free
                    graph). The two pruning functions are <p>
                        <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//106/Formula1.jpg" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-106.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//106/Formula1.jpg','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                    </p> where <i>abs</i>log<i>diff</i> stands
                    for the absolute value of the logarithmically-transformed difference of
                    ‘intrinsic weights’ between any two vertices.</p>
                <p class="noindent">
                    <p>
                        <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//106/Figure2.jpg" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-106.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//106/Figure2.jpg','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                    </p>
                </p>
                <p class="noindent">Figure II: Subgraph (extracted from the semantic network made under the condition
                    of window size = 7, threshold for pair frequency = 6) around the homophilous
                    words (masterminds: blue) and the heterophilous words (purely general keywords:
                    red). The size of a vertex corresponds to the degree.</p>
                <p class="noindent">
                    <p>
                        <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//106/Figure3.jpg" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-106.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//106/Figure3.jpg','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                    </p>
                </p>
                <p class="noindent">Figure III : The average shortest path lengths from the words with degrees 1, 2
                    and 3 respectively to the homophilous words (masterminds) and to the
                    heterophilous words (purely general keywords)</p>
            
        <h2>References:</h2>
            
                
                    <p>
                        Akama, H., MiyakeM., Jung, H.
                        2008
                         “A New Evaluation Method for Graph Clustering of Semantic
                            Networks Built from Lexical Co-occurrence Information, ” 
                        <i>Post-Conference Journal Paper of the
                            18th International Congress of Linguistics (CDROM)</i>, 
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Axelrod, R.
                        1997
                         “The Dissemination of Culture: A Model with Local
                            Convergence and Global Polarization, ” 
                        <i>Journal of Conflict Resolution</i>, 
                        2
                        41
                        203-226
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Barabási, A.-L.Albert, R.
                        1999
                         “Emergence of scaling in random net-works., ” 
                        <i>Science</i>, 
                        286
                        509-512
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Barrat, A.Barthelemy
                            M.Pastor-Satorras, R.Vespignani,
                            A.
                        2004
                         “The architecture of complex weigthed networks., ” 
                        <i>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</i>, 
                        101
                        11
                        3747-3752
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Boccaletti, S.Latora, V.
                        Moreno, Y.Chavez, M.Hwang
                            D.-U.
                        2006
                         “Complex networks: Structure and dynamics, ” 
                        <i>Physics Reports</i>, 
                        424
                        4-5
                        175-308
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Boguñá, M.Pastor-Satorras,
                            R.Vespignani A.
                        Jan 20, 2003
                         “Epidemic spreading in complex networks with degree
                            correlations, ” 
                        <i>cond-mat.stat-mech</i>, 
                        10
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Burgess, C.Livesay, K.Lund,
                            K.
                        1998
                         “Explorations in context space: words sentences and
                            discourse., ” 
                        <i>Discourse Process</i>, 
                        25
                        211-257
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Caldarelli, G.Capocci, A.De Los
                            Rios, P.Munoz, M.-A.
                        2002
                         “Scale-free networks from varying vertex intrinsic
                            fitness, ” 
                        <i>Physical Review Letters</i>, 
                        89
                        258702
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Centola D, González-Avella J.-C.Eguíluz
                            V.-M.San Miguel, M.
                        2007
                         “Homophily, Cultural Drift, and the Co-Evolution of Cultural
                            Groups., ” 
                        <i>Journal of Conflict Resolution</i>, 
                        51
                        6
                        905-929
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Colizza, V., Flammini, A.Serrano, M.-A., and
                            Vespignani, A.
                        2006
                         “Detecting rich-club ordering in complex networks, ” 
                        <i>Nature Physics</i>, 
                        2
                        110-115
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Dorow, B.Widdows, D.Ling,
                            K.Eckmann, J.-P.Sergi, D.Moses, E.
                        2005
                         “Using Curvature and Markov Clustering in Graphs for
                            Lexi-cal Acquisition and Word Sense Discrimination., ” 
                        <i>MEANING-2005, 2nd Workshop or-ganized by
                            the MEANING Project</i>, 
                        February 3rd-4th, 2005.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Jakobson, R.
                        1963
                        <i>Linguistique et théorie de la communication: Essais de
                            linguistique Générale.</i>, 
                        Les Éditions de Minuit
                        Paris
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Jung, J.Akama, H.
                        2008
                         “Employing Latent Adjacency for Appropriate Clustering of
                            Semantic Networks, ” 
                        <i>New Trends in Psychometrics</i>, 
                        Universal Academy Press
                        Tokyo
                        131-140
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Lemaire, B.Denhière,G.
                        2004
                         “Incremental Construction of an associated Network from a
                            Corpus., ” 
                        <i>Proceedings of the 26th Annual Meeting
                            of the Cognitive Science Society</i>, 
                        825-830
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Masuda, N.Miwa, H.Konno, N.
                        2004
                         “Analysis of scale-free networks based on a threshold graph
                            with intrinsic vertex weights, ” 
                        <i>Phys. Rev. E</i>, 
                        70
                        036124
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Masuda, N.Konno, N.
                        2006
                         “VIP-club phenomenon: Emergence of elites and masterminds in
                            social networks, ” 
                        <i>Social Networks</i>, 
                        Volume 28, Issue 4
                        297-309
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Miyake, M.
                        2008
                         “Investigating word co-occurrence selection with extracted
                            sub-networks of the Gospels Employing Clustering Coefficients, ” 
                        <i>Digital Humanities</i>, 
                        VENUE, 
                        2008
                        258-260
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Saint-Exupéry, A. de.
                        1971
                        <i>Le Petit Prince</i>, 
                        Harcourt, Brace &amp; World, Inc.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Saussure, F. de.
                        1916
                        <i>Cours de linguistique générale</i>, 
                        Payot
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Schütze H.Pederson, J.-O.
                        1997
                         “A coocurrence-based thesaurus and two applications to
                            information retrieval, ” 
                        <i>Information Processing &amp; management</i>, 
                        33(3)
                        307-318
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Takayama Y. et al.
                        1999
                         “Information Retrieval Based on Domain-Specific Word
                            Associations, ” 
                        <i>Proceedings of PACLING '99</i>, 
                        Waterloo, Ontario, Canada, 
                        June 1999
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Van Dongen, S.
                        2000
                        <i>Graph Clustering by Flow Simulation</i>, 
                        University of Utrecht PhD thesis
                        Amsterdam
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Zhou, S.Mondragon, R.J.
                        2004
                         “The rich-club phenomenon in the Internet topology, ” 
                        <i>IEEE Communications Letters</i>, 
                        8
                        180-182
                    </p>
                
            
        </div></div></body></html>