
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Lurking in Museums: In Support of Passive Participation</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-129.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-129.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: Lurking in Museums: In Support of Passive Participation</h2><h4>
                    Smith Bautista, Susana , 
                    University of Southern California, 
                    <a href="mailto:susanesm@usc.edu">susanesm@usc.edu</a>
                </h4><hr />
            
                <p class="noindent">Lurking is a term that has gained popularity with the advent of online
                    communities. Museums are no exception to this renewed interest in community
                    building, both online and onsite. The Internet has helped museums to better
                    serve their communities, connecting physical events and exhibitions with online
                    services, information, and activities. The greater museum community is
                    compartmentalized into different groups, including educators, scholars,
                    teenagers, families and more, but their dues-paying members are perhaps the
                    closest to what is more commonly known as <i>affinity spaces</i>
                    (James Gee) or knowledge-sharing communities of practice (CoP). Many of the
                    membership groups organize events at the museum, raise funds for the museum,
                    socialize regularly, and even have online profiles, blogs, or pages on social
                    media sites. The term <i>lurking</i> has arisen because online
                    communities have high expectations for their members to participate and
                    contribute, in particular with online games and chat forums. The web usability
                    expert Jakob Nielsen (2006) proposed the well-known 90-9-1 rule of user
                    participation in online communities, which states that 90% of users are lurkers,
                    9% of users contribute from time to time, and 1% of users account for most
                    contributions. The more passive acts of being present (virtually or physically),
                    listening, watching, and reading – that is, lurking – are considered negative
                    when contrasted to the more dynamic acts of writing, contributing information,
                    performing tasks, or discourse that are all viewed as essential to the formation
                    and maintenance of community. Even the spectatorial can be considered
                    negatively, as in <i>voyeurism</i> that is often perceived as
                    leading to perverse and criminal acts. </p>
                <p class="noindent">Analogous to the conventional concept of community is the idea of a social
                    network as a system of individual nodes that are all related, first proposed by
                    J. A. Barnes in the early 1950s. The concept of <i>the network
                        society</i> has been best developed by Manuel Castells (2000, p. 12) who
                    states that, “The ability of an actor in the network – be it a company,
                    individual, government, or other organization – to participate in the network is
                    determined by the degree to which the node can contribute to the goals of the
                    network… This leads to a binary process of inclusion and exclusion from the
                    network. The people at the bottom are those who, with nothing to offer the
                    network, are excluded.” Similar to lurking but more related to economics is the
                        <i>free rider</i> problem, as it can be argued that every
                    community – regardless of its size or nature – offers a public good and is based
                    upon some type of exchange system. </p>
                <p class="noindent">Art museums are spaces that have traditionally encouraged lurking, as visitors
                    are invited to leisurely appreciate works of art in a reverent environment that
                    prioritizes observation, contemplation, learning, and personal interpretation.
                    There are some exceptions, however, such as with participatory art practices
                    that gained prominence in the early 1960s and continue to be exhibited in
                    museums today, dependent on visitors’ active participation for their
                    realization. Museums have entered the digital age just as have other traditional
                    socio-cultural institutions, and consequently they are incorporating new
                    technologies for the purposes of facilitating exhibition, interpretation,
                    education, and participation. The modern museum presumes that visitors –
                    especially younger ones (<i>digital natives</i>) – expect a more
                    interactive museum experience that allows them to actively participate and even
                    share their opinions within a community that is becoming perceptibly less
                    hierarchical and authoritarian. New technologies offer tremendous possibilities
                    for all visitors to engage more deeply with art, but they can also distract from
                    the passive acts of contemplation and observation if they demand too much
                    physical interaction. Nevertheless, art museums remain a trusted and respected
                    place in which to observe, think, feel, and learn. This paper will assert that
                    lurking is a necessary and useful part of community engagement and learning in
                    the digital age, and that art museums are a valuable and unique space for such
                    activity. Some specific technologies used by art museums today will be discussed
                    in the context of whether they promote a more active or passive experience. A
                    critical distinction must also be made, however, between the terms interaction
                    and participation, the latter of which is more open-ended than the former. </p>
                <p class="noindent">In writing about participatory culture and the digital age, many scholars such as
                    Henry Jenkins and Mikuzo Ito discuss the importance of participation amongst
                    youth while also stressing the importance of other skills, characteristics, and
                    stages of learning that could easily be construed as lurking. We understand from
                    Richard Bartle’s (1996) taxonomy, D.T. Schaller et al.’s (2007) four learning
                    preferences, and Ito et al.’s (2008) three genres, that there are many ways to
                    engage in activities, including both play and learning. The more active forms
                    include creating, producing, sharing, contributing, playing, and commenting.
                    These forms of participation are the most visible to the community and as such,
                    are most prized in that they serve as an example for other members to emulate.
                    More passive forms include listening, reading, watching, and browsing, as well
                    as the introspective acts of thinking, reflecting, evaluating, and forming
                    opinions. When these passive acts are shared with other individuals, discourse
                    arises (physical or virtual), which can then be considered a more active and
                    public form of participation. Different personalities also emerge within groups,
                    and more active contributors will try to lead others less inclined to
                    participate. Jenkins et al. (2008, p. 7) assert that, “In such a world
                    [participatory culture], many will only dabble, some will dig deeper, and still
                    others will master the skills that are most valued within the community.” This
                    paper will show that all types of participation are essential to the development
                    and maintenance of communities. The formation of knowledge and learning is a
                    linear process that begins with more introspective and often individual acts,
                    which in many instances then become public when thoughts, creations, and
                    knowledge are shared with others. If thoughts are not shared and knowledge
                    remains private, then the learning process merely continues with the individual. </p>
                <p class="noindent">The negative implications of lurking arise mostly from within the communities
                    themselves. What cultural communities tend to forget, however, is that lurkers
                    play an important role; they provide an audience, they carefully observe
                    community norms and practices, and they contemplate and interpret that which
                    they observe to perhaps share later with others. Performers do not want to
                    perform without an audience, writers do not want to write books that nobody
                    reads, and museums cannot open without visitors. Certainly, artists have a
                    personal drive to create that does not require an audience or even a client, but
                    even the most dedicated artist desires feedback, validation, or public
                    acknowledgment. Physical spaces and organizations have long measured success in
                    quantitative terms of the number of seats filled, visitors through the front
                    door, or books or tickets sold. Online spaces are no different; the success of
                    websites are most commonly measured by the number of clicks, page views, or
                    downloads, rather than the more interactive number of comments, links, or
                    uploads. As Web 2.0 features become more common on websites, these interactive
                    metrics will surely begin to matter more. Still the number of people “passively”
                    watching, reading, and listening are a strong measure of success, as well as a
                    strong incentive for creators, organizations, and funders alike. </p>
                <p class="noindent">Museums need to protect the act of lurking. Any expectation of active
                    participation, interaction, and sharing may inhibit lurkers from eventually
                    participating, for lurkers need not be defined as having rigid characteristics
                    but rather as representing merely one stage in the long process of learning and
                    civic engagement. In its recent report <i>Museums &amp; Society
                        2034: Trends and Potential Futures</i>, the American Association of Museums
                    (2008, p. 19) states that, “While technological progress has brought much value
                    to society, one byproduct of these emergent structural shifts in communication
                    technologies is almost certainly going to be a world with fewer and fewer places
                    where the public can find respite and retreat.” Through their expertly
                    researched and curated exhibitions and related public programming, museums are
                    best able to teach their visitors and members how to observe, how to critically
                    think, and how to develop opinions in order to more effectively act on them if
                    so desired. They can also teach the value of being an audience within a socially
                    networked environment, which is the first step to recognizing the importance of
                    community and public goods. This paper will discuss how museums might continue
                    to encourage lurking in synergy with new digital technologies, and likewise how
                    youth can become empowered to not only act, but also to observe and contemplate.
                    As Jenkins et al. surmise (2008, p. 39), “…knowing how to act within the
                    distributed knowledge system is more important than learning content. Because
                    content is something that can be ‘held’ by technologies such as databases,
                    websites, wikis, and so forth, the curricular focus is on learning how to
                    generate, evaluate, interpret, and deploy data.” Those who lurk in museums
                    (online or physically) are not evading their role; they do have a very important
                    role within their community and within the process of acquiring, forming and
                    sharing knowledge, and even more so in the participatory culture of the digital
                    age.</p>
            
        <h2>References:</h2> </div></div></body></html>