
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Integrating Digital Papyrology</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-193.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-193.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2> Panel: Integrating Digital Papyrology</h2><br /><h4>
          Baumann, Ryan, 
          University of Kentucky, Lexington, 
          <a href="mailto:rfbaumann@gmail.com">rfbaumann@gmail.com</a>
        </h4><h4>
          Bodard, Gabriel, 
          King's College, London, 
          <a href="mailto:gabriel.bodard@KCL.AC.UK">gabriel.bodard@KCL.AC.UK</a>
        </h4><h4>
          Cayless, Hugh, 
          New York University, 
          <a href="mailto:hugh.cayless@nyu.edu">hugh.cayless@nyu.edu</a>
        </h4><h4>
          Sosin, Joshua, 
          Duke University, 
          <a href="mailto:joshua.sosin@DUKE.EDU">joshua.sosin@DUKE.EDU</a>
        </h4><h4>
          Viglianti, Raffaele, 
          King's College, London, 
          <a href="mailto:raffaele.viglianti@KCL.AC.UK">raffaele.viglianti@KCL.AC.UK</a>
        </h4><br /><h2></h2>
      
        
          <p class="noindent">
            <blockquote>Integrating Digital Papyrology</blockquote>(IDP) is a series of projects funded by the Andrew
            W. Mellon Foundation. It represents the integration of three longstanding digital
            papyrology efforts: the Duke Databank of Documentary Papyri (DDbDP), the Heidelberger
            Gesamtverzeichnis der griechischen Papyrusurkunden Ägyptens (HGV), and the Advanced
            Papyrological Information System (APIS), and the migration to a single format, the
            EpiDoc recommendations for the application of TEI XML to ancient documentary texts.
              
              
         (<a href="http://epidoc.sourceforge.net/" target="blank">link</a>)
   ; see also <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-193.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#cayl2009#X" target="_top">Cayless (2009)</a></p>
          <p class="noindent">This panel aims first to present an historical overview of the transformation of the
            DDbDP from a digital index of print scholarship to a community-managed resource for
            peer-reviewed scholarly control of core disciplinary assets, and then to suggest some
            ways in which we hope that the new suite of tools that we have been building around the
            data may help to transform scholarship in this important domain.</p>
          <p class="noindent">The DDbDP began in 1983 as a collaboration between Duke University and David R.
            Packard. Greek and Latin were encoded in Beta Code and searchable on CD using custom
            software. In 1996/7 the DDbDP migrated its authoritative version to the web-based
            Perseus Project, encoded in Beta Code and TEI SGML. In 2004/5 the DDbDP and HGV began
            mapping their theretofore discrete but complementary sets of text and descriptive
            metadata, while Duke obtained a planning grant from the Mellon Foundation.
            Papyrologists, IT specialists, librarians and university administrators came together to
            map out a sustainable future for the DDbDP. The way forward was clear: open source,
            standards-based development, greater collaboration, increased vesting of data-control in
            the user community, and greater interoperability with other projects.</p>
          <p class="noindent">With clear objectives and generous support from the Mellon Foundation, Duke launched
            IDP1 (2007/8). Its goals were to migrate the DDbDP from SGML to EpiDoc XML, and from
            Betacode Greek to Unicode Greek; to merge DDbDP texts and HGV metadata and translations
            into a single stream; to map these texts to corresponding APIS records, including
            images; to enhance the Papyrological Navigator (PN—see http://papyri.info) to
            enable search of the newly merged data. The fruits of these efforts were released under
            open access provisions in October 2008 (all content under CC BY and software under GNU
            GPL). In October 2008 the team began work on IDP2, again with support from Mellon. At
            the same time, APIS, under a grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities, began
            work on enhancing the PN, and the two projects joined forces. The results of IDP2 are
            (1) improved usability of the PN search interface on the merged and mapped data from the
            DDbDP, HGV and APIS, (2) facilitated third-party use of the data and tools, and (3) a
            version controlled, transparent and fully audited, multi-author, web-based, real-time,
            tagless editing environment (SoSOL), which—in tandem with a new editorial
            infrastructure—will allow the entire community of papyrologists to take control of
            the process of populating these communal assets. The discipline is now on the cusp of
            having the the entire life-cycle of the papyrological discipline represented online in a
            transparent, open, peer-reviewed and community-driven environment.</p>
        
      
      <h2>References:</h2>
        
          
            <p>
              Cayless, Hugh
              2009
               “Epigraphy in 2017, ” 
              <i>Digital Humanities Quarterly</i>, 
              3.1
              
         (<a href="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/1/000030/000030.html" target="blank">link</a>)
   
            </p>
          
        
      
    <hr /><h2>Lessons from the conversion of the Duke Databank of Documentary Papyri from legacy
            formats into EpiDoc TEI XML</h2><br /><h4>
            Bodard, Gabriel, 
            King's College London, 
            <a href="mailto:gabriel.bodard@kcl.ac.uk">gabriel.bodard@kcl.ac.uk</a>
          </h4><br /><br /><h4>
            Sosin, Joshua, 
            Duke University, 
            <a href="mailto:joshua.sosin@duke.edu">joshua.sosin@duke.edu</a>
          </h4><br /><br /><h4>
            Viglianti, Raffaele, 
            King's College London, 
            <a href="mailto:raffaele.viglianti@kcl.ac.uk">raffaele.viglianti@kcl.ac.uk</a>
          </h4><br />
      
        
          <p class="noindent">When the DDbDP began in 1983 at Duke University, Oates (1993)Greek and
            Latin were encoded in Beta Code (an ASCII representation of text in different scripts
            and of various sigla and structural features, also used by the TLG,Nicholas
              (1999)that combines language encoding and some semantic markup features) and
            searchable on CD-ROM via a dedicated platform provided by the Packard Humanities
            Institute. These texts were entered manually by students at Duke, following a data entry
            manual, and using published editions of papyrological texts as the basis. When the DDbDP
            migrated from the CD-ROMs to the Web-based Perseus Project, the texts were
            machine-translated to a format mixing Beta Code and TEI P3 SGML (and the resultant
            hybrid encoding formed the basis of an updated data entry manual). Sosin
              (2010).</p>
          <p class="noindent">The first stage of the Mellon-funded Integrating Digital Papyrology project (2007-2008)
            involved the conversion of the DDbDP from largely regular and sometimes consistent
            format, but highly varied contents, into Unicode and EpiDoc XML. At this point the
            hybrid encoding scheme was a mixture of Beta Code (varying slightly over thirteen years
            of evolution and multiple generations of graduate students), machine-tagged TEI SGML
            (and hand-entered since the Perseus conversion). This basic consistency, compromised but
            not destroyed by this technical history of the project, is further complicated by the
            wide variety of papyrological material, including editions published over a century by
            editors with differing standards of editorial detail, and even occasionally inconsistent
            uses of conventions. These variations were somewhat, but not entirely, flattened by data
            entry practice.</p>
          <p class="noindent">Due to the size of the dataset, some 55,000 records, the conversion of these texts into
            both Unicode character encoding and EpiDoc-conformant TEI XML structural and semantic
            features had to be almost entirely automated, with only a small amount of human
            intervention for difficult or unique cases. This first round of conversion work was
            carried out by a team at the Centre for Computing in the Humanities at King’s
            College London. The tools to convert from the complex, legacy formats to the more
            sustainable, open standard TEI XML were open source and based on ongoing work in the
            EpiDoc community.</p>
          <p class="noindent">The CCH team built the data conversion as a four-step pipeline: (1) the SGML was turned
            into validating XML, and entities resolved, using a tool based on OSX; OSX, OpenJade Distribution, available: 
         (<a href="http://openjade.sourceforge.net/doc/sx.htm" target="blank">link</a>)
   .(2) the Beta Code
            representation of Greek and Coptic characters and certain symbols was converted to
            Unicode using Transcoder; Hugh Cayless, Transcoder, available: 
         (<a href="http://epidoc.sourceforge.net/resources.shtml#transcoder" target="blank">link</a>)
   .(3) a new
            set of regular expressions was added to CHETC, Hugh Cayless,
                Chapel Hill Electronic Text Converter, available: 
         (<a href="http://epidoc.sourceforge.net/resources.shtml" target="blank">link</a>)
   .a regular
            expression-based conversion tool to convert much of the structural Beta Code to XML; (4)
            XSLT was applied to transform the XML produced by steps 1 and 3 into validating EpiDoc.
            In order to write these steps simultaneously, and iteratively to improve the tools, the
            process was pipelined so that the master copy of the texts remained the Beta Code/SGML
            hybrid, which continued to be manually improved. Only at the end of the process, when
            the output validated to the EpiDoc DTD, would the transformation be complete, and
            hand-fixes begin to be performed on this new version of the DDbDP.</p>
          <p class="noindent">In the second phase of the project, work on the DDbDP focussed on ongoing hand-fixes to
            the now canonical XML to improve the consistency of the text. This became ever more
            essential as the SoSOL tool (see Baumann, below) requires very consistent, valid EpiDoc.
            The EpiDoc recommendations were also updated to TEI P5 in this phase, and both Duke
            texts and HGV metadata encoded in this new format. The third phase (awaiting funding
            decision) will work to make the metadata translation into EpiDoc stable, rather than a
            pipelined crosswalk as it is currently.</p>
          <p class="noindent">Among the important lessons we learned from the DDbDP translation from the hybrid
            format to standarized TEI XML are the following technical points (all of value not only
            to our ongoing work with HGV metadata, but potentially to others contemplating
            large-scale up-coding from legacy formats): </p>
          <p class="noindent">
            
              <li>Beta Code was a well-designed encoding scheme for Ancient Greek script, but even
                so there were issues that needed to be resolved. Where Unicode has two characters
                for medial and terminal Greek sigma (σ and ς), Beta considers these to be
                unambiguous by position and so uses ‘S’ to encode both. For a converter
                that had to parse mixed-content XML, relying on position proved unreliable.
                Similarly, Unicode now has separate ranges for Greek and Coptic alphabets, but Beta
                only distinguishes between the scripts in the case of the six characters that are
                unique to Coptic. In the Classics world there are also tools in wide use that expect
                Beta Code input (for example the Morpheus morphological parser), which is no doubt
                part of the reason why this legacy format is in use so long after the general
                adoption of Unicode.</li>
              <li>Because of the complexity of even what seemed to be the simplest task, above,
                the integrity of the processing pipeline was especially important, since changes at
                every stage could otherwise turn out to be irreversible. At one stage, before the
                end of the project, we decided to abandon the first step of the conversion process
                and consider the validating XML version to be the master copy. It was only after
                several rounds of hand-fixes and global corrections had been made to this new master
                copy, that we noticed an error in the first step of the conversion process, which
                lost an important distinction in some thousands of cases. It was possible, but
                difficult, to go back and diff the new version against the SGML in this case, but
                the issue remains that moving from a legacy master text to an automated improvement
                of same requires careful checking.</li>
              <li>Possibly the most interesting challenge in this conversion process was the
                hybrid data format that combined Beta Code sigla, SGML tags and entities to encode
                structural and semantic information about the papyrological editions. Translating
                these multiple encoding schemes to valid EpiDoc XML was not as simple as writing
                transformations for each of the levels, since a span of lost or restored text
                (represented by Beta Code brackets) and an abbreviation (represented by SGML tags)
                might overlap, leading to ill-formed XML. (In fact, it is probably because of this
                thorny problem of overlapping spans that the Beta Code was never fully translated to
                SGML in the initial conversion). The problem was ultimately solved by a combination
                of fine-tuned Regex, XSLT and some hand-correction.</li>
              <li>The interaction of regular expressions and XSLT in the translation of the markup
                was also an important lesson. It was obvious from the start that Regexes were suited
                to replacing textual sigla with XML, and XSLT to transforming SGML/XML tags into
                other XML, but the relationship between these two processes was both complex and
                interesting. In some cases it was simpler to replace sigla with well-formed but
                invalid XML tags, and then fix those to good EpiDoc with XSLT; in other cases a
                combination of hand-fixing and one-off regular expressions were used to regularize
                inconsistencies to a single, consistent error, which the two stages of the markup
                translation process could then fix in one pass. The choice of which stage of the
                process to fix any given issue proved to be worth careful planning. (By the same
                token, it was important to decide when the scale of a problem meant hand-fixing was
                more efficient than a dynamic solution in the pipeline.)</li>
              <li>Another important lesson was that sometimes the markup in the papyrological
                editions was ambiguous in a way that spanned two different semantic distinctions in
                the EpiDoc guidelines (for example, corrections and regularizations used the same
                encoding in the DDbDP, but are represented by choice/sic/corr and choice/orig/reg
                respectively in TEI). Given the scale of the project it was impossible to
                disambiguate the many thousands of instances of these, and markup was devised to
                preserve this lack of granularity.</li>
              <li>Although 55,000 texts is not huge by database standards, for a corpus of ancient
                texts in XML, processed using XSLT it was larger than we had dealt with before. The
                tools that had been adequate for dealing with smaller numbers of text (individual
                Java calls to the Saxon processor; Subversion for version control) led to processes
                and commits that took up to 24 hours at a time on the scale of this project. The
                solutions were relatively straightforward: pipelining multiple texts to Saxon
                through one Java call saved 95% of the processing time; migrating to Git from
                Subversion improved commit speed manyfold. Such optimizations are clearly essential
                at large scales.</li>
              <li>The management of a distributed project (including members from five
                institutions based in Alabama, Heidelberg, Kentucky, London, New York, and North
                Carolina) offered additional lessons. Project communication is handled via several
                channels: there is a project mailing list for asynchronous conversations, we hold
                weekly conversations in Skype between representatives from each location, there is
                an always-on chatroom on IRC that project members use for daily conversations, and
                we have impromptu Skype calls when voice communication is needed. In addition, we
                have held several week-long, all-hands meetings during which planning and intensive
                collaborative work is done. Project communication and coordination does not follow
                the management hierarchies of the member institutions, and this flat organization
                greatly improves efficiency and implementation speed.</li>
            
          </p>
        
      
      <h2>References:</h2>
        
          
            <p>
              Nicholasm, Nick et al.
              1999-2000
              <i>The TLG Beta Code Manual,</i>, 
              
         (<a href="http://www.tlg.uci.edu/encoding/%E2%80%85BCM2010.pdf" target="blank">link</a>)
   
            </p>
            <p>
              Oates, John
              1993
               “The Duke Databank of Documentary Papyri, ” 
              <i>Accessing Antiquity: The Computerization of Classical Studies</i>, 
              Jon Solomon
              Arizona
              62-72
            </p>
            <p>
              Sosin, Joshua
              2010
               “Digital Papyrology, ” 
              <i>Congress of the International Association of
                Papyrologists</i>, 
              Geneva, 
              19 August 2010
              
         (<a href="http://www.stoa.org/archives/1263" target="blank">link</a>)
   
            </p>
          
        
      
    <hr /><h2>The Papyrological Navigator: Project Integration with RDF</h2><br /><h4>
            Cayless, Hugh, 
            <a href="mailto:hugh.cayless@nyu.edu">hugh.cayless@nyu.edu</a>
            New York University, 
          </h4><br />
      
        

          <p class="noindent">One of the major difficulties encountered during IDP1 was the problem of aggregating
            related content. The main purpose of the Papyrological Navigator (PN) is to present a
            merged, searchable view of the DDbDP, HGV, and APIS datasets. IDP1 attempted to produce
            an aggregated dataset, where related DDbDP and HGV records were merged into a single
            EpiDoc XML document. The mapping processes whereby this was accomplished were flawed,
            however, and resulted in both spurious and missing relationships. In addition, combining
            documents from projects with different update schedules and sometimes different
            interpretations of what constitutes a document was problematic. For IDP2, it was clear
            that the mapping process would have to be re-imagined. The new process, described in
            this paper, uses a combination of semantic web technology and standard tools to produce
            a merged collection.</p>
          <p class="noindent">IDP draws on datasets from the DDbDP, HGV, APIS, and Trismegistos See 
         (<a href="http://www.trismegistos.org/" target="blank">link</a>)
   . The varied origins of these
            projects meant that different decisions were made in each about how to record
            information about source documents. For example, if several pieces of papyrus contain
            text that are part of the same <blockquote>document,</blockquote>then DDbDP will tend to transcribe the
            whole, marking the separate sheets of papyrus with &lt;div&gt; elements. HGV on the
            other hand, tends to treat each piece as an entity, each with its own record. APIS,
            since it is essentially a unified export of the catalogs of museums and libraries with
            papyrus holdings, treats the document the way the host collection does. While APIS is
            organized according to the source collection, DDbDP and HGV use the publication history
            of the papyrus as an organizing principle. HGV has the idea of a <blockquote>principal
              edition,</blockquote>i.e. the best published version of the papyrus. DDbDP is similarly based
            on a single published edition, though HGV and DDbDP may not agree on what is the
            principal edition. When a better publication comes out for an existing document, DDbDP
            replaces the existing document with the new version, leaves a <blockquote>stub</blockquote>record with a
            pointer to the new version in place of the old, and the new edition points back at the
            old one. HGV, similarly, sometimes retires identifiers. But these updates are not always
            efficiently propagated across projects, so references may become stale over time.</p>
          <p class="noindent">DDbDP identifiers are constructed from short-form citations of the document edition on
            which the transcription was based, so, for example bgu;1;2 is the identifier for the 2nd
            item in the first volume in the BGU ( <p>
              Aegyptische Urkunden aus den Königlichen (later Staatlichen) Museen zu Berlin,
                Griechische Urkunden
            </p>) series. Trismegistos assigns numeric identifiers to individual documents (e.g.
            1234), and HGV bases its identifiers on these. When HGV data is finer-grained than TM,
            it will append alphabetic characters to the TM id (e.g. 1234a, 1234b, etc.). APIS bases
            its identifiers on the collection name plus a number, e.g. berkeley.apis.15.</p>
          <p class="noindent">DDbDP and HGV began the process of reconciling their collections in 2004, so where
            there are correspondences, the documents include the id numbers of related records in
            their document headers. For example, http://papyri.info/ddbdp/p.oxy;4;744/source encodes
            identifiers both for itself and for the related HGV record in its publicationStmt: 
            <p>
              <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//193/fig1.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-193.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//193/fig1.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
            </p></p>
          <p class="noindent">Likewise, 
         (<a href="http://papyri.info/hgv/20442/source" target="blank">link</a>)
   , the related HGV record, contains the
            DDbDP identifier in its header: <p>
              <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//193/fig2.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-193.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//193/fig2.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
            </p>In this (simple) case, the relationships are easy to establish, and can be
            represented in RDF (using N3 syntax) thus: 
              &lt;http://papyri.info/ddbdp/p.oxy;4;744/source&gt;
              &lt;http://purl.org/dc/terms/relation&gt;
              &lt;http://papyri.info/hgv/20442/source&gt;
              &lt;http://papyri.info/hgv/20442/source&gt;
              &lt;http://purl.org/dc/terms/relation&gt;
              &lt;http://papyri.info/ddbdp/p.oxy;4;744/source&gt;
            That is, the resource http://papyri.info/ddbdp/p.oxy;4;744/source has a
              <blockquote>relation</blockquote>(which is a term drawn from the Dublin Core Metadata Initiative Terms
              DCMI Metadata Terms, available: 
         (<a href="http://dublincore.org/documents/dcmi-terms/" target="blank">link</a>)
   .list)
            http://papyri.info/hgv/20442/source, and the latter has a reciprocal relationship to the
            former.</p>
          <p class="noindent">The question of aggregation becomes much more complicated when APIS enters the
            equation. Because of its origin as a union catalog (the data for which was contributed
            by a variety of insitutions), the quality of APIS’s information is more uneven.
            The method used by the first version of the PN to establish relationships with DDbDP,
            namely looking for matching citations, produced results that were sometimes inaccurate.
            For IDP2, we looked for pieces of information that could be extracted (like the
            &lt;idno&gt;s in DDbDP and HGV) and represented as RDF triples. HGV contains URLs for
            images of papyri and ostraka when they are available, and when these are hosted at
            Columbia (the original home of APIS), they contain the same APIS id as the APIS
            documents do. In addition, APIS records sometimes include references to the relevant
            DDbDP document in their bibliography: 
              &lt;bibl type="ddbdp"&gt;P.Oxy.:4:744&lt;/bibl&gt;
            This does not use the DDbDP identifier scheme, but it can be converted to the DDbDP
            identifier, p.oxy;4;744 easily enough. APIS contains some spurious references of this
            type (to collections that don’t exist, for example), but all that is needed to
            check their validity is to check for the existence of a corresponding DDbDP file.</p>
          <p class="noindent">In addition to the collections mentioned above, there are also HGV translations, which
            use the same numbering scheme as the HGV metadata, and APIS images, which are
            represented by a static RDF file mapping image names to APIS ids. A representation of
            the incomplete graph that can be constructed by extracting these relations from the
            source documents looks something like: <p>
              <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//193/fig3.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-193.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//193/fig3.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
            </p></p>
          <p class="noindent">So there are locations in an IDP EpiDoc document (and in associated artifacts) where we
            can check for reference information, and from these we can build a (partial) graph of
            relationships between documents in the three collections. The database import method is
            simple. A program crawls each directory in our repository containing EpiDoc documents,
            runs each through an XSLT transformation which converts it to RDF XML, and inserts that
            RDF into a Mulgara# triple store. Once the relations have been converted to RDF, we can
            do some simple inferencing to <blockquote>fill out</blockquote>the rest of the incomplete relation graph.
            In practice, this means running SPARQL queries that produce results like <blockquote>A is related
              to B, because B is related to A</blockquote>and <blockquote>A is related to C, because A is related to B
              and B is related to C,</blockquote>and then inserting the results of those queries back into
            the triple store. The resulting graph looks more like: <p>
              <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//193/fig4.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-193.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//193/fig4.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
            </p></p>
          <p class="noindent">Besides relation data, we can also extract hierarchical and bibliographical information
            from the collection. Because DDbDP’s identifiers are hierarchical and carry
            meaning, they can be decomposed and used to identify not just the items, but their
            containers, the volumes and series in which they were published. APIS ids can be
            decomposed to collection and item. HGV and TM ids are opaque, but HGV’s principal
            edition bibliographic record can be used to construct a hierarchy for that collection.
            HGV’s bibliography also points to the primary source for its record.</p>
          <p class="noindent">The APIS, DDbDP, and HGV collections are hosted in the Papyrological Navigator, while
            TM has its own website. This means that we are able to mint URLs using the APIS, DDbDB,
            and HGV identifiers, so http://papyri.info/ddbdp/bgu;1;2/source represents the EpiDoc
            XML document that transcribes BGU 1 2, http://papyri.info/ddbdp/bgu;1;2 retrieves an
            HTML document that aggregates the DDbDP transcription with metadata from HGV #8961 and
            links out to TM #8961, http://papyri.info/ddbdp/bgu;1;2/rdf is shorthand for an RDF
            query that pulls together a subgraph of triples with
            http://papyri.info/ddbdp/bgu;1;2/source as the subject, and so on.</p>
          <p class="noindent">The primary internal uses of the RDF triple store in papyri.info are as the driver for
            generating and indexing the site, and as a means for SoSOL (see Ryan Baumann’s
            paper) to reference valid identifiers. The method for generating the site uses the
            triple store to load, first, all of the identifiers associated with DDbDP using the
            hierarchical relations, then all of the HGV ids not linked to a DDbDP identifier, then
            all of the unrelated APIS identifiers. The collections are then transformed to HTML, and
            the files corresponding to file identifiers (along with any related EpiDoc documents)
            are transformed both to HTML and to Solr add documents, which are then ingested into the
            search engine. In this fashion, we create the entire papyri.info site, with correctly
            aggregated data, using a few basic tools.</p>
          <p class="noindent">Developments slated for the near future include using the triple store as a container
            for relations to external projects. An effort was made during the summer of 2010 to link
            HGV place names to Pleiades and Trismegistos Places URLs, and once the data has been
            processed, it will be loaded into our triple store and used as the basis for linking to
            data at these sites. We hope, for example, to be able to display maps drawn from
            Pleiades, as well as linking to the site. Another planned use for the triple store is to
            have it handle the normalization and display of bibliography for papyri.info.</p>
          <p class="noindent">The method outlined above for extracting data from source documents, storing it as RDF
            triples, and then using inferencing to fill out gaps in the graph has potential
            applications well beyond papyri.info. For example, it could be used to manage
            relationships between EAD finding aids and digitized archives, or to merge data from
            other overlapping collections. Any data management situation where joins between
            discrete but related objects as desired, and where it is possible to extract a partial
            relationship graph from the sources could profit from using semantic web tools in this
            fashion.</p>
        
      
    <hr /><h2>The Son of Suda Online: Collaborative editing and workflow tool</h2><br /><h4>
            Baumann, Ryan, 
            <a href="mailto:rfbaumann@gmail.com">rfbaumann@gmail.com</a>
            University of Kentucky, 
          </h4><br />
      
        
          <p class="noindent">The Son of Suda On Line We regard SoSOL as the intellectual heir
              of the Suda Online project, available: 
         (<a href="http://www.stoa.org/sol/" target="blank">link</a>)
   .(SoSOL) is one of the main components of the Integrating Digital Papyrology
            project (IDP), aiming to provide a repurposable web-based editor for the digital
            resources in the DDbDP and HGV. SoSOL integrates a number of technologies to provide a
            truly next-generation online editing environment. Using JRuby JRuby, available: 
         (<a href="http://www.jruby.org/" target="blank">link</a>)
   .with the Rails Ruby on Rails, available: 
         (<a href="http://rubyonrails.org/" target="blank">link</a>)
   .web framework, it is able to take advantage of Rails’s wide support in
            the web development community, as well as Java’s excellent XML libraries and
            support. This includes the use of XSugar XSugar provides a means of
              converting between equivalent XML and non-XML vocabularies. See XSugar, available:
                
         (<a href="http://www.brics.dk/xsugar/" target="blank">link</a>)
   .to define an alternate,
            lightweight syntax for EpiDoc XML markup, called Leiden+. Because XSugar uses a single
            grammar to define both syntaxes in a reversible and bidirectional manner, this is ideal
            for reducing side effects of transforming text in our version-controlled system. SoSOL
            uses the Git Git, available: 
         (<a href="http://git-scm.com/" target="blank">link</a>)
   .distributed version control system as its versioning backend, allowing it to
            use the powerful branching and merging strategies it provides, and enabling
            fully-auditable version control. SoSOL also provides for editorial control of changes to
            the main data repository, enabling the democracy of allowing anyone to change anything
            they choose while preserving the academic integrity of canonical published data. This
            talk will provide a demonstration of these features of SoSOL as implemented for IDP2, as
            well as a discussion of its repurposable design for applicability to other projects and
            the ongoing documentation work being done to increase usability and adoption in the
            wider community.</p>
          
            <h2>Next-Generation Version Control</h2>
            <p class="noindent">Many online editing environments, such as MediaWiki, use an SQL database as the sole
              mechanism for storing revisions. This can lead to a number of problems, such as
              scaling (most SQL servers are not performance optimized for large text fields) and
              distribution of data (see for example the database downloads of the English Wikipedia,
              which have been notoriously problematic for obtaining the full revision history). Most
              importantly, they typically impose a centralized, linear, single-branch version
              history. Because Git is a distributed version control system, it does not impose any
              centralized workflow. As a result, branching and merging have been given high priority
              in its development, allowing for much more concurrent editing activity while
              minimizing the difficulty of merging changes. SoSOL’s use of Git is to have one
                <blockquote>canonical</blockquote>Git repository for public, approved data and to which commits are
              restricted. Users and boards each get their own Git repositories which act as forks of
              the canonical repository. This allows them to freely make changes to their repository
              while preserving the version history as needed when these changes are merged back into
              the canonical repository. These repositories can also be easily mirrored, downloaded,
              and worked with offline and outside of SoSOL due to the distributed nature of Git.
                See <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-193.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#baum2011#X" target="_top">Baumann (2011)</a>.This
              enables a true democracy of data, wherein institutions still retain control and
              approval of the data which they put their names on, but any individual may easily
              obtain the full dataset and revision history to edit, contribute to, and republish
              under the terms of license.</p>
          
          
            <h2>Alternative Syntax for XML Editing</h2>
            <p class="noindent">While XML encoding has many advantages, users inexperienced with its use may find its
              syntax difficult or verbose. It is still desirable to harness the expertise of these
              users in other areas and ease their ability to add content to the system, while
              retaining the semantically explicit nature of XML markup. To do this, we have used
              XSugar to allow the definition of a <blockquote>tagless</blockquote>syntax for EpiDoc XML, which
              resembles that of the traditional printed Leiden conventions for epigraphic and
              papyrological texts where possible. Structures which are semantically ambiguous or
              undefined in Leiden but available in EpiDoc (e.g. markup of numbers and their
              corresponding value) have been given additional text markup, referred to
              comprehensively as Leiden+. XSugar enables the definition of this syntax in a single,
              bidirectional grammar file which defines all components of both Leiden+ and EpiDoc XML
              as correspondences, which can be statically checked for reversibility and validity.
              This provides much more rigorous guarantees of these properties than alternatives such
              as using separate XSLT stylesheets for each direction of the transform, as well as
              encoding the relation between the components of each syntax in a single location.</p>
            <p class="noindent">As an example, we might have the following XML fragment: <p>
                <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//193/fig5.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-193.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//193/fig5.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
              </p>Corresponding to the typical Leiden print transcription: <p>
                <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//193/fig6.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-193.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//193/fig6.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
              </p>While transforming the XML to Leiden+ through our XSugar grammar yields: <p>
                <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//193/fig7.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-193.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//193/fig7.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
              </p></p>
            <p class="noindent">As you can see, things such as the Greek letter <blockquote>κ</blockquote>on line four being the
              number <blockquote>20</blockquote>are implicit in print, but explicit in both EpiDoc and Leiden+. The
              user can work on either the Leiden+ or XML representation of the text, and we store
              only the XML representation in our data repository (that is, the Leiden+
              representation is only an intermediate form used for editing and is transformed back
              to XML when saved). A traditional Leiden <blockquote>print preview</blockquote>is possible by applying
              the standard EpiDoc XSLT stylesheets to this XML. In theory, this particular XSugar
              grammar could be re-used by other EpiDoc projects wishing to enable the same kind of
              alternative markup.</p>
          
          
            <h2>Repurposable Design</h2>
            <p class="noindent">Due to institutional requirements, the DDbDP and HGV datasets needed separate
              editorial control and publishing mechanisms. In addition, their control over different
              types of content necessitated different editing mechanisms for each component. These
              requirements informed the design of how SoSOL interacts with data under its control
              and how this design is repurposable for use in other projects. The two high-level
              abstractions of data made by SoSOL are <blockquote>publications</blockquote>and <blockquote>identifiers</blockquote>.
              Identifiers are unique strings which can be mapped to a specific file path in the
              repository, while publications are arbitrary aggregations of identifiers. By defining
              an identifier superclass which defines common functionality for interacting with the
              data repository, we can then subclass this to provide functionality specific to a
              given category of data. The SoSOL implementation for IDP2, for example, provides
              identifier subclasses for DDbDP transcriptions, HGV metadata, and HGV translations.
              Editorial boards consequently have editorial control for only certain subclasses of
              identifiers. Publications in turn allow representation and aggregation of the complex
              many-to-many relationships these components can have (for example, a document with two
              sides that may have one transcription and two metadata components). Packaging these
              related elements together both allows the user to switch between them and editorial
              boards to check related data which they may not have editorial control over but still
              require to make informed decisions about validity and approval. SoSOL can thus be
              integrated into other systems by implementing the identifier subclasses necessary for
              the given dataset as well as coherent means for aggregating these components into
              publications. One can imagine the simplest implementation as being an identifier whose
              name is the file path, which just presents the plaintext contents of the file for
              editing, and which has no relationships with other identifiers so that each
              publication is a single identifier.</p>
          
          
            <h2>Conclusions</h2>
            <p class="noindent">Though SoSOL is still under development, early reception and feedback at training
              workshops conducted to introduce users to the system has been good. Thousands of texts
              have been created, edited, or corrected, and submitted through the editorial boards
              for voting, peer review, and publication. In addition to being publicly viewable
              through the Papyrological Navigator, these changes are regularly mirrored to a public
              copy of the Git data repository available on GitHub, where anyone may view and
              download the complete revision history (see previous footnote). Under IDP3, the
              currently-active final phase of the IDP project, user experience studies are being
              conducted and feedback from this process will be incorporated into the system.</p>
            <p class="noindent">In addition to the possible reuse of the system itself, we hope the more general goal
              of making data available with the full revision history will become a more widely
              adopted practice in digital humanities. Particularly for collaborative editing
              projects, this can allow anyone to see how changes have actually been effected, even
              outside of the specific editing environment employed. We feel that using a distributed
              version control system such as Git as the core data backend is conducive to this goal,
              as it enables easy distribution and updating of the data set alongside its complete
              version history. Thus, even if our particular editing environment is eventually
              outdated and replaced, or the data needs to be interacted with and edited using other
              mechanisms, the data backend can still be used for the next generation of tools and
              scholars.</p>
          
        
      
      <h2>References:</h2>
        
          
            <p>
              Ryan Baumann
              <i>IDP Data available on GitHub</i>, 
              3 March, 2011
              
         (<a href="http://digitalpapyrology.blogspot.com/2011/01/idp-data-available-on-github.html" target="blank">link</a>)
   
            </p>
          
        
      
    <hr /></div></div></body></html>