
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Between Close and Distant: Historical Editing Methods at Intermediate Scale</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-182.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-182.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Poster: Between Close and Distant: Historical Editing Methods at Intermediate Scale</h2><h4>
          Knox, Douglas W., 
          Newberry Library, 
          <a href="mailto:knoxdw@gmail.com">knoxdw@gmail.com</a>
        </h4><hr />
      
        <p class="noindent">Between mass digitization of millions of images and texts and intensive scholarly work on
          close digital representation, in the humanities there are many collections of texts at
          intermediate scales that require their own strategies for management, editing, and
          analysis. The Text Encoding Initiative grew out of scholarly needs in working with digital
          texts that were encoded manually with considerable editorial care. In recent years it has
          become possible to begin to address the challenge of working with digital resources at
          scales that had been difficult to imagine previously—a challenge captured in Gregory
          Crane's memorable question, "What Do You Do with a Million Books?" (Crane,
            2006).</p>
        <p class="noindent">More recently Crane seemed to reply to his own question with the demand, "Give us
          editors!," recognizing the need for new kinds of editing and scholarship that will combine
          the strengths of digital methods and domain-appropriate human judgment (Crane
            2010). Between markup of single texts and mass digitization of millions of books,
          increasing attention is called for at intermediate scale. The present project is a case
          study of one modest example of this sort of work.</p>
        <p class="noindent">At the scale of tens of thousands of texts, manual editing methods are impractical or not
          cost-effective, yet there is often still considerable value in structured markup to
          support management, discovery, and scholarly use beyond what uncorrected OCR or plain text
          can support. While this is not in itself a novel observation, thinking about interpretive
          issues and scale in relation to digital editing has in general been much more developed
          with respect to literary texts than it has been for nonliterary historical sources.</p>
        <p class="noindent">The poster will outline some of editing questions and processes that can arise in
          applying digital methods to a large aggregation of related historical documents, drawing
          on examples from the Chicago Foreign Language Press Survey, an NEH-funded project of the
          Newberry Library that is creating an electronic publication and database using relatively
          simple TEI structures to represent a collection of thousands of newspaper articles
          prepared in the 1930s. The original Press Survey was a project of the U.S. Works Progress
          Administration in the 1930s that selected, translated into English, edited, and organized
          articles published in Chicago from 1861 to 1938 in newspapers in twenty-two linguistic and
          ethnic groups. The project produced 120,000 half-sheets of typescript, recording what we
          now know are more than 48,000 articles. </p>
        <p class="noindent">The present-day Press Survey project worked with a vendor to produce a set of simple TEI
          transcription files from images digitized from microfilm by the library at the University
          of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign. The body of each article has been transcribed into
          paragraphs and occasionally tables, without further markup below that level. Considerable
          effort, however, went into making sure the files accurately capture the structure of
          information that constitute metadata for each article: ethnic group, primary and secondary
          subject code classifications, source, date, and title. At the publication end of the
          process, web developers populate a database with metadata drawn from edited TEI files and
          create a searchable, browseable interface for the collection.</p>
        <p class="noindent">Between the vendor's XML and the web presentation is an essential set of editing tasks.
          Many editing steps, beginning with XML validation, apply to single documents, and scale up
          through simple repetition, preferably automated repetition with manual exception handling
          as required. Often this is a matter of imagining what might have gone wrong, and then
          devising tests for it. Are any items, pages, or essential data structures missing? Are
          there paragraphs that are suspiciously short? Are there any duplicate values one would not
          expect, whether identifiers, file name references, or page numbers? Is there data
          integrity in expected relations between file names and internal identifiers? Is there the
          sequential continuity we would expect in any numbering or other patterns where the
          sequence of the original material implies some kind of consistency or order in metadata
          fields?</p>
        <p class="noindent">Some of the most interesting editing tasks, however, are those that relate to the
          collection as a whole, and require an iterative exploratory process. The 1930s editors of
          the Press Survey thought carefully about their choices and methods in organizing a large
          body of material. They invented their own hierarchical subject code scheme, and the linear
          arrangement of the typescript indicates how they prioritized ethnic groups and primary
          subject codes over date of publication and secondary subject terms. They faced inevitable
          limitations in trying to managing a textual database of tens of thousands of records with
          nothing more than paper, procedural guidelines, and human attention. For seventy years, in
          the absence of a digital representation of the editorial model of the WPA editors, it was
          impossible to get a full picture of the choices they made. Now, with digital methods, we
          can better enjoy the benefit of their work and yet also see the limitations of their
          methods, even according to their own intentions, better than they themselves were able
          to.</p>
        <p class="noindent">While scholars have made good use of typescript, microfilm, and digital images, until the
          Press Survey was modeled as a database of articles its aggregate characteristics were
          obscure. No index recorded the range and distribution of values in important metadata
          fields, including dates and the names of newspapers and other sources. Creating a digital
          representation now requires simultaneous analysis and editorial decision-making. How often
          did the original editors depart from their own advertised controlled vocabularies? What
          simple errors should now be corrected, what normalization of data would best serve the
          current digital project? Do the data structures chosen in anticipation of full-scale
          digitization fit what we can now know about the documents in the aggregate? With an eye to
          both central tendencies and odd but perhaps telling exceptions, how can editing choices
          mediate a digital collection for efficient use while also preserving some necessary kinds
          of transparent resistance to user expectations, features that may be essential to its
          character as a complex historical primary source? </p>
        <p class="noindent">The poster will be organized around these kinds of questions and tasks, with a series of
          illustrative case studies drawn from Foreign Language Press Survey documents and data.</p>
        <p class="noindent">Generalizing from this case, the primary point is that intermediate scale matters in its
          own right. If a collection is interesting as such, it will likely require more than the
          repeated application of the kind of editing applied to individual texts, and it may also
          require decision-making beyond the methods and standards designed to provide access to
          aggregations at much larger scale. We must be able to see both the forest and the
          trees.</p>
      
    <h2>References:</h2>
      
        
          <p>
            Crane, G.
            2010
             “Give us editors! Re-inventing the edition and re-thinking the
              humanities, ” 
            <i>Connexions</i>, 
            May 14, 2010
            March 9, 2011
            
         (<a href="http://cnx.org/content/m34316/" target="blank">link</a>)
   
          </p>

          <p>
            Crane, G.
            2006
             “What Do You Do with a Million Books?, ” 
            <i>D-Lib Magazine,</i>, 
            12
            3
            March 9, 2011
            
         (<a href="http://www.dlib.org/dlib/march06/crane/03crane.html" target="blank">link</a>)
   
          </p>

          <p>
            TEI Consortium
            2007
            <i>TEI P5</i>, 
            <i>Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
              Interchange</i>, 
            TEI Consortium
            March 9, 2011
            
         (<a href="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5" target="blank">link</a>)
   
          </p>
        
      
    </div></div></body></html>