
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>The Wheaton College Digital History Project: Digital Humanities and
                    Undergraduate Research </title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-175.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-175.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Poster: The Wheaton College Digital History Project: Digital Humanities and
                    Undergraduate Research </h2><h4>
                    Tomasek, Kathryn, 
                    Wheaton College, 
                    <a href="mailto:ktomasek@wheatonma.edu">ktomasek@wheatonma.edu</a>
                </h4><hr />
            
                <h2>Digital History</h2>
                <p class="noindent">Can undergraduates contribute meaningfully to a long-term digital history
                    project? What role can transcription and markup play in the undergraduate
                    history curriculum? How can collaborations among instructor, archivist, and
                    technologist contribute to undergraduate research? What is the role of
                    collaborations with other small liberal arts colleges and with large research
                    universities?</p>
                <p class="noindent">All too often, students majoring in non-science disciplines have little exposure
                    to computational thinking and working with computer code.  At the same time,
                    digital methods of analysis exert growing influence on the practice of many
                    disciplines in the humanities and social sciences.  The Wheaton College Digital
                    History Project seeks to bridge this gap using tools from Digital
                    Humanities.</p>
            
            
                <h2>The Wheaton College Digital History Project</h2>
                <p class="noindent">Since fall 2004, undergraduates in History courses at Wheaton College have been
                    transcribing and marking up nineteenth-century documents from the Wheaton
                    College Archives and Special Collections for digital publication. The
                    opportunity to begin this work arose when a confluence of events combined new
                    interest in and experience with the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI) at Wheaton
                    College and the acquisition of the pocket diaries of Eliza Baylies Wheaton.
                    Beginning in January 2004, Wheaton College collaborated with Mount Holyoke
                    College to host a two-part conference that explored uses of TEI in teaching and
                    research at liberal arts colleges. The conference included instruction in TEI
                    from Julia Flanders and Syd Bauman of the Women Writers Project at Brown
                    University.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Our first effort at incorporating TEI into a course occurred in fall 2004.
                    Students in an introductory course on women's history, U.S. Women to 1869,
                    learned about the economic uncertainties in the lives of unmarried white women
                    when they transcribed and marked up the journal of Maria E. Wood, the daughter
                    of a Maine Baptist minister. Each student was assigned to transcribe a set of
                    pages from the journal, and then groups of students marked up the entire journal
                    using themes from the course: family, work, religion, death and mourning. At the
                    end of the course, the students expressed a sense of having gotten to know Wood
                    and having understood the past better than they ever had before.</p>
                <p class="noindent">In subsequent semesters and summers, students have collaborated with members of
                    the faculty and staff to create digital editions of the diaries of Eliza B.
                    Wheaton. The three students who worked together in summer 2005 became a
                    community of enthusiastic historians. As they transcribed the travel journal and
                    pocket diaries of Eliza Baylies Wheaton, they used their spare time to explore
                    the town of Norton, especially its cemeteries, where they looked for the birth
                    and death dates of people mentioned in the documents. During subsequent summers,
                    student workers continued to transcribe and mark related documents.</p>
                <p class="noindent">In spring 2009, the project took a new turn, as students in the research methods
                    course for History majors began to transcribe and mark up pages from the daybook
                    that Laban Morey Wheaton kept between 1828 and 1859. This book records financial
                    transactions that reflect some of the range of Wheaton’s business interests
                    during these forty years, including agricultural pursuits and rentals for land
                    and houses as well as tax collections, fees for legal services, and the
                    operation of a general store in Norton, Massachusetts.</p>
            
            
                <h2>Undergraduate Research</h2>
                
                    <h2>Teaching Module</h2>
                    <p class="noindent">Students examine Laban Morey Wheaton’s daybook alongside his account ledger
                        and cashbooks that date from the same period to get a fuller idea of the
                        financial context for the daybook transactions. Each student transcribes a
                        two-page spread using a Google spreadsheet to facilitate keeping track of
                        the tabular data. The academic technology liaison converts these documents
                        into XML files that students open in oXygen and mark up using the guidelines
                        of the TEI. Students code the transactions for personal names, commodities,
                        amounts purchased, amounts charged, and mode of payment—cash or credit. </p>
                    <p class="noindent">In another class meeting, the academic technology liaison demonstrates
                        visualization tools to show students examples of ways to display results of
                        querying the files. Students write short History Engine episodes based on
                        the transaction of their choice, in preparation for writing papers based on
                        the data they have transcribed, coded, and queried.</p>
                
            
            
                <h2>Collaborations: Archiving, Pedagogy and Research</h2>
                    <p class="noindent">Since Wheaton College is a liberal arts college that prioritizes teaching and
                        learning, including students in the process of scholarly research makes
                        sense, as does promoting a collaborative pedagogy in which members of the
                        faculty and staff come together to deploy their complementary expertise in
                        leading students through the process of research and writing. The College
                        Archivist and Curator of Special Collections identifies the documents to be
                        transcribed in collaboration with the instructor, who uses her scholarly
                        expertise to identify secondary sources that will help the students
                        contextualize and interpret their findings. The archivist guides students to
                        sources that help establish the local context for the documents. The
                        Technology Liaison for Humanities instructs students in markup and querying
                        data. He also performs backstage transformations that make the data
                        available in appropriate forms for students to mark up, query, and
                        manipulate.</p>
                    <p class="noindent">Students contribute more than their labor since they bring to the documents a
                        perspective distinct from those of the archivist, instructor, and
                        technologist. Their very unfamiliarity with the historical context allows
                        them to bring to the project questions that enable new insights into the
                        implications of the data that they help create. Whilst we do not expect them
                        to contribute to the digital humanities at the same level as graduate
                        students, we do value their participation, and we hope to prepare them for
                        advanced study in the field.</p>
            
            
                <h2>Next Steps: Transcribe Wheaton</h2>
                    <p class="noindent">Since we have developed a workflow and are comfortable with using this
                        assignment as a teaching module, we are piloting targeted crowd-sourcing to
                        speed transcription. Students continue to transcribe, mark up, query, and
                        write about transactions from the daybook in courses.</p>
                    <p class="noindent">Transcribe Wheaton, modeled on the Transcribe Bentham project at University
                        College London, will provide a portal and tools to allow students and
                        friends of Wheaton College to participate in digitization of financial
                        documents from the Wheaton Family Papers either as part of their coursework
                        or as a volunteer contribution to the ongoing work of the Wheaton College
                        Digital History Project. We hope that faculty members in courses in
                        Anthropology, Computer Science, Economics, and other fields will use the
                        teaching module to employ transcription and markup in their courses. We also
                        hope that graduates of the college will assist in the project, and we expect
                        to be able to open transcription beyond the college by 2012.</p>
            
            
                <h2>The Long Term</h2>
                <p class="noindent">When we began transcribing the pocket diaries of Eliza Baylies Wheaton, we chose
                    TEI because we appreciated the flexibility of XML and we liked the idea of
                    performing transcription once and being able to manipulate the data thereafter.
                    That initial decision has affected the choices we made as we began transcribing
                    the financial records, which are much more abundant in the Wheaton Family Papers
                    collection than are diaries and letters. Such records are in fact abundant in
                    many archives, yet they are underutilized by historians, in part because of
                    their inaccessibility. We hope that our project will contribute to the
                    development of standards for TEI markup of tabular records, thus encouraging
                    similar projects that will increase the accessibility of historical financial
                    records and other tabular data.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Since our project combines archival, pedagogical, and scholarly purposes, we find
                    ourselves negotiating constantly among them. The collaborative nature of our
                    project and the multiple varieties of expertise and interest brought to it by
                    each member of the team necessitate ongoing consultations among the archivist,
                    instructor, and technologists. Like many projects in digital humanities, ours
                    requires a certain amount of comfort with technology from the archivist and
                    instructor, combined with an equivalent amount of comfort with the humanities
                    from the technologists.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Because ours is a small liberal arts college, we rely on collaborations with
                    other institutions to support our project. Our technologists, for example, have
                    spent 2010 collaborating with colleagues from other liberal arts colleges as
                    well as from Brown University and the University of Virginia as they plan a
                    presentation tool for TEI documents produced at small colleges. And members of
                    our project team have taken additional courses with Julia Flanders and Syd
                    Bauman as we continue to hone our TEI skills.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Our poster/demo features our project website: http://wheatoncollege.edu/dhp/.
                    Whilst the website currently serves as a brochure for the project, we hope to
                    include additional features by the time of the conference, including links to
                    student writing about individual transactions from the daybook, as well as a
                    portal for transcribers.</p>
                <p class="noindent">We share our project as an example of a long-term project in digital history that
                    includes undergraduates as significant partners in the digitization and
                    interpretation of a hidden collection that offers insight into the relationship
                    between capitalist accumulation and women's education in the nineteenth-century
                    United States.</p>
            
        </div></div></body></html>