
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>The Object of Platform Studies: Relational Materialities and the Social
                    Platform (the case of the Nintendo Wii)</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-150.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-150.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: The Object of Platform Studies: Relational Materialities and the Social
                    Platform (the case of the Nintendo Wii)</h2><h4>
                    Jones, Steven E., 
                    Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola
                        University Chicago, 
                    <a href="mailto:s3jones1@gmail.com">s3jones1@gmail.com</a>
                    
         (<a href="http://stevenejones.org" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                </h4><h4>
                    Thiruvathukal, George K., 
                    Center for Textual Studies and Digital Humanities, Loyola
                    University Chicago, 
                    <a href="mailto:thiruvathukal@gmail.com">thiruvathukal@gmail.com</a>
                </h4><hr />
            

                <p class="noindent"><i>Racing the Beam: The Atari Video Computer System</i>, by Ian
                    Bogost and Nick Montfort, inaugurated the Platform Studies series at MIT Press
                    in 2009. We’ve coauthored a new book in the series (currently under contract and
                    final review, MIT Press), <i>Codename: Revolution: the Nintendo
                        Wii Video Game Console</i>. Platform studies is a quintessentially
                    Digital-Humanities approach, since it’s explicitly focused on the
                    interrelationship of computing and cultural expression. According to the series
                    preface, the goal of platform studies is “to consider the lowest level of
                    computing systems and to understand how these systems relate to culture and
                    creativity.” In practice, this involves paying close attention to specific
                    hardware and software interactions--to the vertical relationships between a
                    platform’s multilayered materialities (Hayles; Kirschenbaum), from transistors
                    to code to cultural reception. Any given act of platform-studies analysis may
                    focus for example on the relationship between the chipset and the OS, or between
                    the graphics processor and display parameters or game developers’ designs. In
                    computing terms, platform is an abstraction (Bogost and Montfort), a pragmatic
                    frame placed around whatever hardware-and-software configuration is required in
                    order to build or run certain specific applications (including creative works).
                    The object of platform studies is thus a shifting series of possibility spaces,
                    any number of dynamic thresholds between discrete levels of a system. As with
                    the “text” in recent textual studies (McKenzie; McGann), the “platform” in
                    platform studies is actually observed in action, as one or more transactional
                    events, defined in the act of observation or performance. In this sense,
                    platform studies examines the ways in which material conditions of computing
                    systems determine (by constraining and affording) the experience of creative or
                    expressive works.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Although there are now competing systems coming on to the market from Microsoft
                    (Kinect) and Sony (Move), Nintendo’s Wii (2006) was the first major video game
                    console to be based on motion control, to make use of what Jesper Juul has
                    called a mimetic interface to capture player movements in physical space and
                    represent those movements in the game world. This paper will explain and
                    demonstrate in precise terms how that’s made possible through the use of a
                    relatively off-the-shelf multichannel system of infrared (IR) and Bluetooth
                    communications, along with data collected dynamically by the Analog Devices
                    ADXL330 triple-axis accelerometer, a MEMS (Micro Electronic Mechanical Systems)
                    device, a chip inside the wand-like Wii Remote--a tiny machine, with moving
                    parts that measures motion along X, Y, and Z axes in relation to gravity. In
                    this paper we’ll show how this piece of hardware with accompanying code is used
                    to design new software for the Wii, and we’ll illustrate some of the specific
                    constraints and affordances of the accelerometer by tracing the particular case
                    study of third-party software developer Ubisoft’s Samurai-Western FPS games, Red
                    Steel I and II. The two games in this franchise mark points on a brief timeline,
                    starting with the release of the first realistic action adventure game in 2006,
                    as an exclusive title for the original Wii platform, followed by its relative
                    critical failure, and then, four years later, the subsequent introduction of a
                    “reboot” sequel, with completely revamped, cel-shaded, manga-style aesthetics,
                    and all-new swordplay mechanics. This second game was timed to coincide with
                    Nintendo’s release of the controller add-on, Wii MotionPlus, a second MEMS
                    device that plugs into the base of the Wii Remote and contains a “tuning-fork”
                    gyroscope (the Invensense IDG-600), and thus adds more measurable dimensions to
                    the system, giving the controller pseudo-global sensitivity and something closer
                    to 1:1 mapping of player motions with in-game events. (This retrofit solution
                    has now been superseded with the release of a new Wii Remote that ships with
                    integrated versions of the two MEMS devices combined in one controller.)</p>
                <p class="noindent">That timeline, from 2006-2010, clearly marked a learning curve for Ubisoft’s
                    developers (including moving to the LyN 3D game engine, designed for the Wii, to
                    make the second game), and the radical changes they made over the intervening
                    four years serve as a vivid example of creative works being shaped in response
                    to (and anticipation of) the constraints and affordances of a specific platform.
                    The story of the two <i>Red Steels</i> highlights an important
                    fact--that a video game console is in effect a platform for production,
                    transmission, publishing, and player reception, all in one system. In this way,
                    a game platform--even at the lowest level--is an inherently social phenomenon,
                    determined by developer as well as consumer and player expectations. Drawing
                    from textual studies’ idea of the social text, we’ll argue that the “social
                    platform” that is the object of platform studies is “social” in a particular
                    sense: it’s based on the relational materialities that both constrain and afford
                    the production, transmission, and reception of creative works, the whole process
                    that links hardware and software design to the player and the wider culture.
                    This paper will illustrate this larger theoretical point by explaining one chain
                    of concrete materialities on multiple levels in the case of Red Steel for the
                    Wii--from tiny MEMS devices to in-game graphics, programming to marketing,
                    transistors to cultural contexts.</p>
            

        <h2>References:</h2>
            
                
                    <p>Bogost, Ian and Nick Montfort
                        2009
                        <i>Racing the Beam: The Atari Video Computer System.</i>, 
                        MIT Press
                        Cambridge, MA</p>
                    <p>Hayles, N. Katherine
                        2008
                        <i>Electronic Literature: New Horizons for the
                            Literary</i>, 
                        University of Notre Dame
                        Notre Dame, IN</p>
                    <p>Jones, Steven E. and George K. Thiruvathukal
                        Forthcoming, 2012
                        <i>Codename: Revolution: The Nintendo Wii Video Game
                            Console</i>, 
                        MIT Press
                        Cambridge, MA</p>
                    <p>Kirschenbaum, Matthew G.
                        2008
                        <i>Mechanisms: New Media and the Forensic Imagination</i>, 
                        MIT Press
                        Cambridge, MA</p>
                    <p>McGann, Jerome J.
                        1985
                        <i>Textual Criticism and Literary Interpretation</i>, 
                        University of Chicago Press
                        Chicago</p>
                    <p>McKenzie, D. F.
                        1986
                        <i>Bibliography and the Sociology of Texts. The Panizzi
                            Lectures, 1985.</i>, 
                        The British Library
                        London</p>

                
            
        </div></div></body></html>