
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Comparing the Similarities and Differences between Two Translations</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-221.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-221.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: Comparing the Similarities and Differences between Two Translations</h2><h4>
                    Lucic, Ana, 
                    Graduate School of Library and Information Science, University of
                        Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, 
                    <a href="mailto:alucic2@illinois.edu">alucic2@illinois.edu</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Blake, Catherine, 
                    Graduate School of Library and Information Science, University of
                        Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, 
                    <a href="mailto:clblake@illinois.edu">clblake@illinois.edu</a>
                </h4><hr />
            
                <h2>Abstract</h2>
                <p class="noindent">Burton Pike described Rainer Marie Rilke’s style in Rilke’s only prose novel, <i>The Notebooks of Malte Laurids Brigge</i>, as “… arresting,
                    haunting, and beautiful, but it is not smooth. His style is explicit, direct,
                    almost laconic, and it has an edge.” (2008, p. xvii) Pike argues that this
                    “edge” was not sufficiently emphasized in previous English language translations
                    and he thus wrote a new translation. The goal of this research is to explore the
                    degree to which automated text analysis tools can capture the different styles
                    used by Burton Pike and Stephen Mitchell in their respective translations. We
                    are particularly interested in what kinds of similarities and differences can be
                    captured between two renderings of Rilke’s novel and in the implications of
                    these findings on the reviews, reader reception, and critical analysis of the
                    original work in two translations.</p>
            
            
                <h2>Method</h2>
                <p class="noindent">Two candidate analysis tools were used to identify similarities and differences
                    between the Pike and Mitchell translations of Rilke’s novel <i>The Notebooks of Malte Laurids Brigge</i>. The first approach used a
                    syntactic representation of the texts which was generated using the Stanford
                    Lexical parser (
         (<a href="http://nlp.stanford.edu/index.shtml" target="blank">link</a>)
   ). Before
                    running the parser, each translation was tokenized into sentences using the
                    Natural Language Toolkit tokenizer (
         (<a href="http://www.nltk.org/" target="blank">link</a>)
   ). The
                    generated lexical dependencies, which capture grammatical relations between
                    words in a sentence, were then uploaded to the oracle database for subsequent
                    analysis.</p>
                <p class="noindent">The second approach used a statistical approach–principal component analysis–to
                    compare the manifestations of the novel. Our experiment reflects McKenna et
                    al.’s study (1999) of similarities and differences between Samuel Beckett’s
                    French and English translation of Molloy. Three matrixes were produced
                    comprising the 99 most common words in each of Pike and Mitchell’s translation
                    and the original text. The rows of the matrix reflect 8 text blocks of 7,500
                    words. Principal component analysis, which measures the variance of 99 most
                    frequent words in the 8 blocks, was then applied to each matrix and the top
                    eigenvectors produced were mapped into a two dimensional space for visual
                    analysis.</p>

            
            
                <h2>Results</h2>
                <p class="noindent"><i>Dependency grammar analysis</i></p>
                <p class="noindent">Table 1 provides the summary statistics of grammatical relations which showed the
                    largest difference captured in the parser for each translation. Although the two
                    translations show a remarkable degree of similarity in the frequency and type of
                    grammatical relations they employ, the dependencies revealed several differences
                    between the two renderings. The main areas of difference were found in the use
                    of negation modifiers, prepositional modifiers, object of preposition,
                    parataxis, and in the word choices for adjectival and adverbial modifiers.</p>
                <p class="noindent">The dependency grammar results show that Pike used many more negation modifiers
                    than Mitchell, which is confirmed by word frequency analysis. Pike uses the
                    non-contracted verb, which places more emphasis on negation and thus also stays
                    closer to the original text whereas Mitchell rarely uses a non-contracted verb
                    form. The word “not” is not the only word in Pike’s translation which indicates
                    a negation that is used with higher frequency. Pike uses “no” with higher
                    frequency than Mitchell, and also “nothing,” “never,” and “none.”</p>
                <p class="noindent">The frequencies of prepositional modifier and object of preposition relations in
                    two texts indicate a difference in how the prepositions are used in the text.
                    This result shows a higher overall frequency of prepositions in Mitchell’s
                    translation (Table 1). The sentence level analysis of two texts, however,
                    revealed that Pike is more likely to repeat and thus emphasize the same
                    preposition throughout the sentence whereas Mitchell is more likely to leave out
                    the preposition rather than repeat it. This finding suggests that in addition to
                    the overall difference in the frequency of prepositions captured through the
                    parser, there are indicators that the use of prepositions, their placement and
                    distribution throughout the sentence, show differences in two texts.</p>
                <p class="noindent">The comparison of two translations revealed a higher frequency of sentences that
                    use a semicolon to separate sub-clauses in Mitchell’s translation (parataxis).
                    Mitchell frequently arranges independent sentences using semicolons and colons,
                    and in this way follows closely the original text, while Pike occasionally
                    intersperses “but” and “and” in place of semicolons and colons. This finding is
                    supported by the frequency of conjunction “but” in two translations which is
                    found at higher frequency in Pike’s translation, 559, than in Mitchell’s, 506.
                    This difference in sentence structure may provide the “edge” which Pike claims
                    was missing in previous translations.</p>
                <p class="noindent">An examination of the unique adverbs and adjectives used in each translation
                    revealed that although Mitchell and Pike may use similar grammatical relations
                    in their respective renderings, their word choices are frequently different.
                    This suggests that a semantic rather than the syntactic analysis may reveal
                    additional differences.</p>
                <p class="noindent"><i>PCA analysis</i></p>
                <p class="noindent">Figure 1 shows the score plots of the translations and suggests that the
                    distribution of frequent terms is very similar between the two translations.
                    However, the grouping of the 7th block with 4th, 5th, and 6th rather than with
                    8th block, in Mitchell’s translation, calls for a closer analysis of the 7th
                    block of the novel and its comparison with the 7th block in Rilke’s original
                    text and Pike’s translation. The last part of the novel, which corresponds to
                    the 8th block of text, is visibly different in style and tone from the rest of
                    the novel and this difference is indicated by the location of the 8th block in
                    the far right corner of the plot in each version.</p>

            
            
                <h2>Conclusion</h2>
                <p class="noindent">Our results thus far suggest that syntactic grammatical relations reveal
                    differences between the two translations that are not captured when using a
                    bag-of-word approach (word frequencies of function words and 1,000 most frequent
                    words). In contrast, the PCA analysis using matrices of frequent terms in the 8
                    blocks of text suggests that only small differences exist between the
                    translations, with the exception of the 7th block of text, which warrants
                    further investigation.</p>
                <p class="noindent">The similarity captured between translations using the PCA analysis brings to
                    mind Jan Rybicki’s article “Burrowing into Translation: Character Idiolects in
                    Henryk Sienkiewicz’s Trilogy and its Two English Translations” in which Rybicki
                    analyzes the distinctiveness of character idiolects in Henryk Sienkiewicz’s
                    trilogy and concludes that: “… the patterns of difference and similarity are
                    almost mysteriously preserved in the translations—so well that the
                    above-mentioned linguistic differences might be the sole reason for the small
                    differences between the original and the translation. In the greater picture,
                    characters differ one from another in the translations just as they do in the
                    original.” (Rybicki, 2006, p.102)</p>
                <p class="noindent">The differences between two translations that were established will help create
                    the linkages between these findings and the reader reception, reviews, and
                    critical analysis of two translations. We also hope that they will help trace
                    the contours along which the creation of the new variant and new literary
                    rendering begins to emerge and the differences that speak directly to the
                    explicit, direct, and laconic style of Pike’s translation.</p>
                <p class="noindent">We plan to extend this work to include M. D. Herter Norton’s translation (1949)
                    of <i>The Notebooks of Malte Laurids Brigge</i> and to
                    investigate how well this method generalizes to different translations of
                    different genres.</p>
            
            
                <p class="noindent"><p>
                        <h2>Table 1 - Dependency distributions with the largest difference between
                            the Pike and Mitchell translations of The Notebooks of
                                Malte Laurids Brigge by Rainer Maria Rilke</h2>
                    <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//221/221-1.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-221.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//221/221-1.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                        <br /><span class="down1"></span>
                    </p></p>
                <p class="noindent"><p>
                        <h2>Figure 1 - Score plots</h2>
                    <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//221/221-2.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-221.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//221/221-2.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                        <br /><span class="down1"></span>
                    </p></p>
            
        <h2>References:</h2>
            
                
                    <p>
                        de Marneffe, M. &amp; Manning, D. C.
                        2008
                        <i>Stanford typed dependencies manual.</i>, 
                        30 October 2010
                        
         (<a href="http://nlp.stanford.edu/software/dependencies_manual.pdf" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Lucic, A.
                        2010
                         “Measuring Similarities and Differences between Two
                            Translations., ” 
                        <i>Research Showcase 2010 at the Graduate
                            School of Library and Information Science, University of Illinois at
                            Urbana-Champaign</i>, 
                        Champaign, IL, 
                        2010
                        
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        McKenna, W., Burrows, J., Antonia, A.
                        1999
                         “Beckett’s Trilogy: Computational Stylistics and the Nature
                            of Translation., ” 
                        <i>RISSH</i>, 
                        35
                        151-71
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Rilke, R.M.
                        2000
                        <i>Die Aufzeichnungen des Malte Laurids Brigge. [Plain Text
                            UTF-8]</i>, 
                        30 October 2010
                        
         (<a href="http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/2188" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Rilke, R.M.
                        1949
                        <i>The Notebooks of Malte Laurids Brigge (Translated by M. D.
                            H. Norton).</i>, 
                        W.W. Norton &amp; Company
                        New York
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Rilke, R.M.
                        1982
                        <i>The Notebooks of Malte Laurids Brigge (Translated by S.
                            Mitchell).</i>, 
                        Random House
                        New York
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Rilke, R.M.
                        2008
                        <i>The Notebooks of Malte Laurids Brigge (Translated by B.
                            Pike).</i>, 
                        Dalkey Archive Press
                        Champaign
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Rybicki, J.
                        2006
                         “Burrowing into translation: Character Idiolects in Henryk
                            Sienkiewicz’s Trilogy and its Two English Translations., ” 
                        <i>Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</i>, 
                        21(1)
                        477-495
                    </p>

                
            
        </div></div></body></html>