
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Tasks vs. Roles: A Center Perspective on Data Curation Needs in the
                    Humanities</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-223.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-223.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: Tasks vs. Roles: A Center Perspective on Data Curation Needs in the
                    Humanities</h2><h4>
                    Muñoz, Trevor, 
                    Center for Informatics Research in Science and Scholarship,
                            University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign,
                            USA, 
                    <a href="mailto:munoz14@illinois.edu">munoz14@illinois.edu</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Varvel, Virgil, 
                    Center for Informatics Research in Science and Scholarship,
                            University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign,
                            USA, 
                    <a href="mailto:vvarvel@illinois.edu">vvarvel@illinois.edu</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Renear, Allen H., 
                    Center for Informatics Research in Science and Scholarship,
                            University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign,
                            USA, 
                    <a href="mailto:renear@illinois.edu">renear@illinois.edu</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Trainor, Kevin, 
                    Center for Informatics Research in Science and Scholarship,
                            University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign,
                            USA, 
                    <a href="mailto:trainor1@illinois.edu">trainor1@illinois.edu</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Dolan, Molly, 
                    West Virginia University,
                        USA, 
                    <a href="mailto:molly.dolan@mail.wvu.edu">molly.dolan@mail.wvu.edu</a>
                </h4><hr />
            
                <h2>Abstract</h2>
                <p class="noindent">To support the development of curricular content for the Data Curation Education
                    Program (DCEP) at the Graduate School of Library and Information Science
                    (GSLIS), University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign, a needs analysis case study
                    focusing on digital humanities centers was carried out in late 2010.
                    Collectively the results paint an interesting picture of the perception of
                    humanities data curation needs by directors and key staff. Several results were
                    contrary to what we anticipated; for instance, there was only modest agreement
                    on critical areas of expertise needed to sustain meaningful access to digital
                    humanities scholarship over time. Most importantly, there was one result that,
                    if confirmed, could have a substantial impact on the design of data curation
                    education programs. In the humanities, center directors and managers appear to
                    resist the notion that a particular staff role, that of data curator, is
                    specifically needed, preferring instead to develop distributed expertise and
                    responsibilities as part of existing staff roles, calling on institutional
                    resources as needed. This suggests, among other things, that the standing
                    recommendation to place data curation professionals “upstream” in
                    projects may need to be re-envisioned in this context.</p>
            
            
                <h2>Introduction</h2>
                <p class="noindent"><i>Data curation</i> has been described as “the active and
                    ongoing management of data throughout its entire lifecycle of interest and
                    usefulness to scholarship” (<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-223.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Cragin et
                        al., 2007</a>). Curation activities enable data discovery and retrieval,
                    maintain quality, add value, and provide for re-use over time. Originally
                    conceptualized as an e-Science problem precipitated by large amounts of data in
                    digital formats, data curation is an emerging problem for the humanities as
                    well, as both data and analytical practices become increasingly digital (<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-223.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Renear et al., 2009</a>; <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-223.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Crane, Babeu, &amp; Bamman, 2007</a>).</p>

                <p class="noindent">GSLIS received a grant from the Institute of Museum and Library Services (IMLS)
                    to extend the existing data curation specialization within the school's
                    ALA-accredited master's program to include humanities data as well as science
                    data (<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-223.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Renear et al., 2009</a>). Among the
                    activities carried out under the grant was a study of data management and
                    curation practices in the digital humanities. The study was designed and
                    directed by social science researchers from the Center for Informatics Research
                    in Science and Scholarship (CIRSS). The main goals were to assess the levels and
                    types of data curation expertise needed by researchers actively engaged in
                    digital humanities projects and to better understand the potential roles that
                    information professionals trained to meet the unique challenges of working with
                    humanities data in digital formats might fulfill.</p>
            
            
                <h2>Methods</h2>
                <p class="noindent">To develop a rich picture of data curation practices in the humanities, we
                    employed a case study method, taking digital humanities centers as our case. We
                    chose to focus on established digital humanities centers in preference to
                    libraries, repositories, or individual research teams or scholars for a number
                    of reasons. First, many significant early projects were likely to be located at
                    or affiliated with centers—meaning these centers have experience handling
                    data over longer time scales (<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-223.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Daigle,
                        2005</a>). Second, centers bring together faculty and staff, and we
                    believe this makes them sites where the most sophisticated curation practices
                    are likely to be found (<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-223.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Zorich,
                    2008</a>).</p>

                <p class="noindent">We interviewed directors and upper-level staff members at 14 digital humanities
                    centers located in the United States, the United Kingdom, Europe, and Australia
                    with one interview per site. High profile, established centers were chosen that
                    were available and willing to participate in the research. Most centers chosen
                    were located at large research universities but the size of the centers ranged
                    from several staff members to large units. Our intuition was that researchers
                    working at the level of a single project might see data curation as something
                    inextricably tied to their specific job and thus not be able to envision it as a
                    stand-alone function; therefore, upper-level staff with responsibilities for
                    hiring and coordination between projects were chosen in order to elicit views of
                    the curator position from that overarching perspective. Participants were asked
                    about a range of topics related to data management including formats and
                    standards, data storage, security and redundancy, staff roles and background,
                    and significant unsolved problems.</p>

                <p class="noindent">Study participants completed a pre-interview worksheet and their responses were
                    used to guide and focus semi-structured interviews. The pre-interview worksheet
                    also included a series of questions asking participants to rank various
                    categories of skills on a Likert scale ranging from “very important”
                    to “not important at all” for curating humanities data. From the
                    ranked list of skills we were able to develop an overview of researchers' views
                    of data curation in the context of multi-project digital humanities centers.
                    From the interviews, we were able to capture more in-depth information such as
                    complex discussions of tradeoffs and rationales that could not be adequately
                    represented in a simple survey. We are therefore able to report both
                    quantitative and qualitative results from our case study.</p>
            
            
                <h2>Results</h2>
                
                    <h2>Variability and Convergence of Skills</h2>
                    <p class="noindent">When asked to rank the importance of various areas of expertise needed for a
                        data management professional to be effective working with humanities data,
                        participants revealed an unexpectedly high degree of variability in their
                        answers.</p>

                    <p class="noindent">From among a list of 30 kinds of expertise provided in the pre-interview
                        worksheet, at least one study participant gave each category of knowledge
                        the highest score, indicating it was “very important.” While we
                        can rank order the areas of expertise according to an average score, the
                        differences between rankings are not statistically significant by
                        Chi-squared analysis. However, we observe that a handful of skills were both
                        highly ranked on average and showed higher positive skew: every respondent
                        ranked expertise in areas such as interoperability, markup, database design,
                        and metadata as being of moderate importance or higher. Project management
                        also had a high rank order. One surprising result among our findings was the
                        strong emphasis on skills related to teaching and training. This may be due
                        to staff at digital humanities centers being tasked as consultants to
                        scholarly projects or it may simply be due to the expectation within the
                        community that skills will be developed through peer-to-peer training in the
                        course of carrying out job duties. Overall, our results coupled with
                        interview data could not identify a consensus as to the most relevant areas
                        of expertise needed by staff engaged in humanities data curation.</p>
                
                
                    <h2>Organizational and Management Trends</h2>
                    <p class="noindent">Our interviews reveal a picture of current practice in which the work of data
                        management and curation at digital humanities centers is parceled out among
                        multiple staff members at multiple levels in the organizational hierarchy.
                        Important data curation tasks may be left for scholars or managers of
                        projects to decide individually, or they may be handled by staff, who work
                        on multiple projects for a center, or they may be outsourced to other campus
                        units above the level of the center.</p>

                    <p class="noindent">The staff who did have responsibility for data management and curation at the
                        centers we studied were often either those with programming, systems
                        administration, or other IT training, or were people who had received
                        advanced training in a humanities discipline and had taught themselves
                        technical skills.</p>

                    <p class="noindent">In keeping with the emphasis on interoperability noted in our quantitative
                        results and also perhaps in response to a changing funding environment and
                        newly available services, we observed a trend in which efforts were being
                        made to move data management expertise from the staff member who had
                        developed it in the course of his or her duties to a center-wide or perhaps
                        institution-wide level where it would be a part of documentation and
                        institutional memory rather than personal memory.</p>

                    <p class="noindent">However, our interviews with managers also suggest that even though data
                        management and curation is beginning to be elevated to a higher position in
                        organizations, there is skepticism about the potential role for a data
                        curator at digital humanities centers. Participants in our study were
                        interested in adding skills relevant to data curation to their organizations
                        but rather than doing so in the form of a dedicated position for an
                        information professional, they appeared to be looking for staff with
                        computing or disciplinary skills who also had some training in data
                        curation.</p>

                    <p class="noindent">This finding is consistent with another trend we observed. Just as digital
                        humanities centers are already using outside groups such as campus IT or
                        vendors for certain aspects of data management, we noted an increasing
                        orientation to and interest in working with campus-wide services such as
                        institutional repositories to curate humanities data.</p>
                
            
            
                <h2>Discussion</h2>
                <p class="noindent">Since effective curation, management, and preservation of data in digital formats
                    involves intervention at every stage of the data lifecycle from creation
                    onwards, it has been a common belief in the data curation community that
                    information professionals trained in curation will need to work
                    “upstream” in scientific labs and digital humanities centers (<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-223.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Swan &amp; Brown, 2008</a>). The current
                    resistance of directors of humanities data centers to such dedicated data
                    curation staff must be taken seriously as it undoubtedly reflects relevant
                    experience and judgment, and their sense of the sorts of arrangements that are
                    likely to succeed. However, our case study in combination with prior work on the
                    role of information work in scientific research suggests that models of
                    provisioning data curation expertise may need to be more nuanced.</p>

                <p class="noindent">As the humanities become increasingly “data-rich,” information
                    science research on data management in the natural sciences becomes increasingly
                    relevant (<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-223.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Choudhury &amp; Stinson, 2007</a>;
                        <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-223.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Renear, Muñoz, &amp; Trainor,
                    2010</a>). For example, intensive case studies in neuroscience suggest that
                    information services for researchers are likely to be most effective at project
                    stages when information work is most routine or when it is highly speculative,
                    as is often the case with new interdisciplinary research questions or in
                    emerging collaborations (<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-223.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Palmer, 2006</a>;
                        <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-223.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Palmer, Cragin, &amp; Hogan 2007</a>).
                    In the humanities we have also seen that conceptions of what constitutes
                    information or support work and what constitutes professional work within
                    disciplines change in response to the introduction of digital methodologies
                        (<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-223.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Flanders, 2005</a>; <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-223.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">Bradley, 2008</a>; <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-223.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">McCarty, 2009</a>). While the distribution of curation
                    activities may not follow the same types of (re)arrangements we are seeing in
                    the sciences, we still believe that some data curation work will be most
                    effective upstream and integrated into scholars' research endeavors, such as at
                    decision points about project planning and re-use value.</p>

                <p class="noindent">As digital curation practices evolve, libraries and institutional repositories
                    will likely take on a larger role in curating humanities data in the future. The
                    results of our study can serve as a useful point of comparison for future work
                    in this area. In addition to having someone who owns data curation problems and
                    manages solutions on a research-center-level, institutions may explore both how
                    to provide services from a central organization (such as the university library)
                    and also, ways to increase the formal, in-service training available to
                    researchers in the digital humanities.</p>
            
            
                <h2>Acknowledgments</h2>
                <p class="noindent">This work was funded by a grant from the Institute of Museum and Library Services
                    (RE-05-08-0062-08). We have benefited from the expertise of Melissa Cragin,
                    Carole Palmer, and other staff from the Center for Informatics Research in
                    Science and Scholarship in designing and carrying out this research.</p>
            
        <h2>References:</h2>
            
                
                    <p>
                        Bradley, J.
                        2008
                         “What the Developer Saw: An Outsider’s View of Annotation,
                            Interpretation and Scholarship, ” 
                        <i>Digital Studies / Le champ numérique</i>, 
                        1(1)
                        
         (<a href="http://www.digitalstudies.org/ojs/index.php/digital_studies/article/viewArticle/143" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Choudhury, G.S., &amp; Stinson, T.
                        2007
                         “The virtual observatory and the Roman de la rose:
                            Unexpected relationships and the collaborative imperative, ” 
                        <i>Academic Commons</i>, 
                        
         (<a href="http://www.academiccommons.org/commons/essay/VO-and-roman-de-la-rose-collaborative-imperative" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Cragin, M. H., Heidorn, P. B., Palmer, C. L., &amp; Smith, L.
                            C.
                        2007
                         “An Educational Program on Data Curation, ” 
                        <i>American Library Association Conference,
                            Science and Technology Section</i>, 
                        Washington, D.C., 
                        June 25, 2007
                        
         (<a href="http://hdl.handle.net/2142/3493" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Cragin, M. H., Palmer, C. L., Varvel, V., Collie, A., &amp; Dolan,
                            M.
                        2009
                         “Analyzing Data Curation Job Descriptions, ” 
                        <i>5th International Digital Curation
                            Conference</i>, 
                        London, U.K., 
                        December 2-4, 2009
                        
         (<a href="http://hdl.handle.net/2142/14544" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Crane, G., Babeu, A. &amp; Bamman, D.
                        2007
                         “eScience and the Humanities, ” 
                        <i>International Journal on Digital Libraries</i>, 
                        7
                        117-122
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Daigle, B. J.
                        2005
                         “How Do We Sustain Digital Scholarship?, ” 
                        <i>Free Culture and the Digital Library
                            Symposium Proceedings</i>, 
                        Martin Halbert
                        Metascholar Initiative, Atlanta, GA, 
                        October 14, 2005
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Flanders, J.
                        2005
                         “Detailism, Digital Texts, and the Problem of
                            Pedantry, ” 
                        <i>Text Technology</i>, 
                        14(2)
                        41-70
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        McCarty, W.
                        2009
                         “Literary enquiry and experimental method: What has
                            happened? What might?, ” 
                        <i>Storia della Scienza e Linguistica Computazionale:
                            Sconfinamenti Possibili</i>, 
                        Liborio Dibattista
                        Francoangeli
                        Milan
                        32-54
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Nowviskie, B., &amp; Porter, D.
                        2010
                         “The Graceful Degradation Survey: Managing Digital
                            Humanities Projects Through Times of Transition and Decline, ” 
                        <i>Digital Humanities</i>, 
                        London, U.K., 
                        July 7-10, 2010
                        
         (<a href="http://dh2010.cch.kcl.ac.uk/academic-programme/abstracts/papers/html/ab-722.html" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Palmer, C. L.
                        2006
                         “Weak Information Work and ‘Doable’ Problems in
                            Interdisciplinary Science, ” 
                        <i>Proceedings of the American Society for Information Science
                            and Technology</i>, 
                        43(1)
                        1-16
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Palmer, C. L., Cragin, M. H., &amp; Hogan, T. P.
                        2007
                         “Weak information work in scientific discovery, ” 
                        <i>Information Processing and Management</i>, 
                        43
                        808-820
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Palmer, C. L., Renear, A. H., &amp; Cragin, M. H.
                        2008
                         “Purposeful Curation: Research and Education for a Future
                            with Working Data, ” 
                        <i>4th International Digital Curation
                            Conference</i>, 
                        Edinburgh, Scotland, 
                        December 1-3, 2008
                        
         (<a href="http://hdl.handle.net/2142/9764" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Renear, A. H., Dolan, M., Trainor, K., &amp; Muñoz, T.
                        2010
                         “Extending an LIS Data Curation Curriculum to the
                            Humanities: Selected Activities and Observations, ” 
                        <i>iSchools Conference</i>, 
                        Champaign-Urbana, IL, 
                        February 3-6, 2010
                        
         (<a href="http://hdl.handle.net/2142/15061" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Renear, A. H., Muñoz, T., &amp; Trainor, K.
                        2010
                         “Data Curation Education for the Humanities: Principles
                            &amp; Challenges, ” 
                        <i>5th Annual Chicago Colloquium on Digital
                            Humanities and Computer Science</i>, 
                        Northwestern University, Evanston, IL, 
                        November 21-22, 2010
                        
         (<a href="http://hdl.handle.net/2142/17421" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Renear, A. H., Teffeau, L. C., Hswe, P., Dolan, M., Palmer, C. L.,
                            Cragin, M. H., &amp; Unsworth, J.
                        2009
                         “Extending an LIS Data Curation Curriculum to Include
                            Humanities Data, ” 
                        <i>DigCCurr Conference</i>, 
                        Chapel Hill, N.C., 
                        April 1-3, 2009
                        
         (<a href="http://hdl.handle.net/2142/14548" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Smith, A.
                        2003
                        <i>New-Model Scholarship: How Will It Survive?</i>, 
                        Council on Library and Information Resources
                        Washington, D.C.
                        
         (<a href="http://www.clir.org/pubs/reports/pub114/contents.html" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Swan, A. &amp; Brown, S.
                        2008
                        <i>The Skills, Role and Career Structure of Data Scientists
                            and Curators: An Assessment of Current Practice and Future Needs</i>, 
                        JISC
                        
         (<a href="http://www.jisc.ac.uk/publications/reports/2008/dataskillscareersfinalreport.aspx" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Zorich, D.
                        2008
                        <i>A Survey of Digital Humanities Centers in the United
                            States</i>, 
                        Council on Library and Information Resources
                        Washington, D.C.
                        
         (<a href="http://www.clir.org/pubs/abstract/pub143abst.html" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                
            
        </div></div></body></html>