
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Possible Worlds: Authorial Markup and Digital Scholarship</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-232.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-232.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: Possible Worlds: Authorial Markup and Digital Scholarship</h2><h4>
                    Wernimont, Jacqueline, 
                    Scripps College, 
                    <a href="mailto:jwernimo@ScrippsCollege.edu">jwernimo@ScrippsCollege.edu</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Flanders, Julia, 
                    Women Writers Project, Brown University, United States of
                    America, 
                    <a href="mailto:Julia_Flanders@brown.edu">Julia_Flanders@brown.edu</a>
                </h4><hr />
            
                <p class="noindent">Alan Liu’s “Imagining the New Media Encounter” (2008) calls for “a poiesis of
                    digital literary studies” through which we can renegotiate the relationships
                    between new and old media as productive encounters rather than as something
                    other than “conversion” encounters. Liu helps us open up a critical space in
                    which to rethink how the problematic notion of “conversion,” with its
                    implications of oppositional media, complete transformation, and religious
                    fervor, shape our understandings of related pairs: writing and encoding, mimesis
                    and creation, imagination and simulation. We suggest that our understanding of
                    text markup is closely implicated in our reimagination of writing, and that the
                    modes of modeling suggested by possible worlds scholars may destabilize our
                    understanding of mimesis and its role in both literary composition and text
                    markup. In short, we propose considering markup as a “world-constructing”
                    (Doložel 1997) form of discourse.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Our starting point of reference is the long-standing conceptual tension within
                    the markup (and especially the TEI) community between two models of markup. The
                    first is rooted in mimesis and surrogacy: the domain of transcriptional and
                    editorial markup. The second is more concerned with meaning creation and the
                    domain of annotation, interpretation, authoring. These two models have different
                    textual commitments and establish different relationships between text, markup,
                    reader, and encoder. In the first, the encoder uses markup to transact a
                    connection between a text and a reader; it is understood that the markup is
                    non-transparent, but its role is to communicate about the text and about its own
                    role as transmission medium, so that the reader can (to the greatest extent
                    possible) apprehend some truth of the text. The primary commitment, the goal of
                    the exercise, is for the reader to have access to the text (that is, to some
                    textual artifact that pre-existed the markup relationship). Some form of this
                    approach is extremely common in current applications of the TEI Guidelines: for
                    thematic research collections, scholarly editions, linguistic corpora, oral
                    histories, digital archives, and the like.</p>
                <p class="noindent">The second model, though much less common in practice, is of great importance
                    theoretically as a counterpoise to the first, and its importance has been
                    shadowed forth by a number of key interventions during recent years. Theorists
                    like Renear (2000) and McGann (2004) in very different ways have suggested that
                    the performative and illocutionary qualities of markup bear close scrutiny.
                    Sperberg-McQueen and Huitfeldt (2000) explored how markup represents meaning
                    (and by extension, suggest a shift of emphasis onto markup itself as a
                    meaning-bearing system, apart from the text it marks). Flanders (2006) and
                    Flanders and Fiormonte (2007) have turned attention to the rhetoric of authorial
                    markup and to its significance for scholarly communication, thinking of markup
                    as a discourse that is situated at the boundary of production and reproduction.
                    In this more “authorial” model, the encoder uses markup to transact a connection
                    between <i>herself</i> and a reader <i>that
                        concerns</i> a text. The role of markup is to instantiate, to bring into
                    communicative reality, the encoder’s ideas and beliefs about a textual ecology
                    that is oriented towards a particular textual artifact but is not limited to
                    representing that artifact. Rather, the markup may represent a much broader
                    context of interpretation, related information, and argumentation for which the
                    text itself is only the catalyst or point of inspiration. The most common
                    examples in the present day include annotation, “interpretive” markup such as
                    the association of themes and keywords with spans of text (e.g. using the TEI
                    @ana and <i>interp</i> mechanism), and the creation of new
                    documents such as articles using an XML markup language as an authoring system.
                    But these examples do not really give us a field within which to consider what
                    —in a radical sense—we might mean by “authorial markup”, or to pursue the full
                    critical pressure of McGann’s challenge to the markup world: “No autopoietic
                    process or form can be simulated under the horizon of a structural model like
                    SGML” (McGann 2004, 201-2). </p>
                <p class="noindent">The way these questions are framed within the digital humanities—as an opposition
                    between mimetic representation and presentation on the one hand, and generative
                    or creative authorship and interpretation on the other—has a correlate in
                    literary history. As Doležel argues (1997), possible world texts, with their
                    “world-constructing” features, contrast with the strongly mimetic and material
                    world truth claims of “world-imaging” texts. We suggest that an exploration of a
                    “possible worlds” ontology of non-mimetic discursive modes may offer a critical
                    vocabulary for thinking about the relationship of authorial markup to other
                    encoding models. It can also help us describe how authorial markup might
                    leverage the formal tools of a structural model in order to enact a generative
                    or poetic mode of markup.</p>
                <p class="noindent">We focus in particular on the authoring, interpretation, and markup of texts from
                    the early modern period that concern themselves with precisely this domain.
                    While Gottfried Leibniz nominally inaugurated discussion of possible worlds (in
                        <i>Essays on the Goodness of God, the Freedom of Man and the
                        Origin of Evil</i>, 1710), early modern writers from Thomas More and Sir
                    Philip Sidney to René Descartes and Margaret Cavendish were concerned with the
                    ability of the written word or number to, as Descartes put it, write about that
                    “which does not actually exist…but is capable of so doing” (Descartes, Writing,
                    332). Such propositional discourse refers less to a verifiable “real” than to a
                    set of possibilities without a fixed ontological status. Instead, as Ruth Ronen
                    suggests, “their state of being is confined to what meaning-units of the text
                    reveal” (Ronen 1994, 98-9). The early modern romance in particular (of which
                    Cavendish is a major exemplar) is the single prose genre most invested in
                    explicit exploration of the mimetic/poetic distinction and in which narrative
                    structures themselves enact the generative logic of world-construction.
                    Cavendish herself argues in her 1667 <i>A New World Called the
                        Blazing World</i>, that her “romancicall” tale offers readers a model by
                    which “they may create worlds of their own, and govern themselves as they
                    please" (Cavendish 225). Her model of romantic poiesis draws on a poetic
                    tradition exemplified by Sidney’s <i>Defense of Poesie</i>
                    (1579), which refutes directly the critique that poiesis is a form of feigning,
                    by suggesting an epistemological and ethical role for generative authoring.</p>
                <p class="noindent">When we turn from Cavendish’s own authoring process to our own use of markup as a
                    means of representing and interpreting her text—and of creating a new work of
                    scholarship of which we are the authors—these arguments have a double impact.
                    Within the world of an encoded text, the “meaning-units” include (for our
                    purposes, most significantly) the markup itself. The markup itself becomes a
                    world-generating mode of knowing that must carry several registers of meaning
                    arising from different kinds of scholarly agency. There are also important
                    questions which we will address in the full paper about how we can anchor and
                    access the domain of meaning such a world establishes. </p>
                <p class="noindent">Following Saul Kripke’s assertion that “possible worlds are stipulated, not
                    discovered by telescopes,” we see in both Cavendish’s authoring and our reading
                    and encoding of her text a series of generative or poetic “stipulations” that
                    carry both epistemological and ethical implications (cited in Doložel 1998,
                    787). We stipulate that a given structure can be characterized as a poem, or
                    that a new paragraph begins in this place. Because there is such agreement (e.g.
                    on disciplinary grounds) about how we read and name literary structures, this
                    stipulation reads like a statement of fact, but if we consider more unfamiliar
                    genres (or genre-resistant texts, like the confounding recursive narratives of
                    Mary Wroth’s <i>Urania</i> or entries in commonplace books), the
                    contentiousness of the assertion becomes more apparent. Possible worlds theory
                    elaborates on what such stipulations accomplish, and on the terms in which we
                    can understand the truth-value of what is created thereby. In the full version
                    of this paper, we will consider how schemas may operate as another way of
                    modeling the possible worlds of texts and genres, and also how possible worlds
                    theory may help us envision more radically authorial forms of markup that may
                    push our ideas of text encoding as scholarly communication into new terrain.</p>
            
        <h2>References:</h2>
            
                
                    <p>
                        Cavendish, Margaret, Duchess of Newcastle
                        <i>Observations on Experimental Philosophy. To Which is Added,
                            The Description of a New World, Called the Blazing-World</i>, 
                        1666
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Descartes, René
                        <i>Method, Optics, Geometry, and Meteorology</i>, 
                        1637
                        Paul J. Olscamp
                        2001
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <i>The philosophical writings of Descartes, Volume 3</i>, 
                        John Cottingham
                        Robert Stoothoff
                        Dugald Murdoch
                        Anthony Kenny
                        1991
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Doležel, Lubomir
                        <i>Heterocosmica: Fiction and Possible Worlds</i>, 
                        1997
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Doležel, Lubomir
                         “Possible Worlds of Fiction and History, ” 
                        <i>New Literary History</i>, 
                        29.4
                        1998
                        785-809
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Flanders, Julia
                         “The Rhetoric of Performative Markup, ” 
                        <i>DH2006</i>, 
                        July 2006
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Flanders, Julia
                        Domenico Fiormonte
                         “Markup and the Digital Paratext, ” 
                        <i>DH2007</i>, 
                        June 2007
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        McGann, Jerome
                         “Marking Texts of Many Dimensions, ” 
                        <i>A Companion to Digital Humanities</i>, 
                        Susan Schreibman
                        Ray Siemens
                        John Unsworth
                        2004
                        198-217
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Poovey, Mary
                        <i>Genres of the Credit Economy</i>, 
                        2008
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Renear, Allen
                         “The Descriptive/Procedural Distinction is Flawed, ” 
                        <i>Markup Languages: Theory and Practice</i>, 
                        2.4
                        2001
                        411-420
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Ronan, Ruth
                        <i>Possible Worlds in Literary Theory</i>, 
                        1994
                    </p>
                
            
        </div></div></body></html>