
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>New Models of Digital Materialities</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-263.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-263.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2> Panel: New Models of Digital Materialities</h2><br /><h4>
               Blanchette, Jean-François , 
                Information Studies, UCLA, 
               <a href="mailto:blanchette@gseis.ucla.edu">blanchette@gseis.ucla.edu</a>
            </h4><h4>
               Drucker, Johanna, 
                Information Studies, UCLA, 
               <a href="mailto:drucker@gseis.ucla.edu">drucker@gseis.ucla.edu</a>
            </h4><h4>
               Kirschenbaum, Matthew, 
               Department of English; Maryland Institute for Technology in the
                  Humanities, University of Maryland, 
               <a href="mailto:mgk@umd.edu">mgk@umd.edu</a>
            </h4><br /><h2></h2>
         
            
               <p class="noindent">One persistent myth of the digital age is that it differs fundamentally from all
                  previous information epochs because in digital form information has finally
                  achieved the long-standing historical aspiration to unburden itself from the
                  shackles of matter. As a mere collection of 0s and 1s, digital information is
                  imagined to be independent of the particular media on which it is stored—hard
                  drive, optical disk, etc.—and the particular signal carrier which encode bits,
                  whether magnetic polarities, voltage intensities, or pulses of light. Digital
                  information also achieves a separation of content and form that could only be
                  partially realized with analog carriers. This fantasy has implications for the
                  ways we think about design, preservation, storage, use, and every other aspect of
                  digital media. What can the digital humanities learn from and contribute to an
                  engagement with the many aspects of the materialities of information? </p>

               <p class="noindent">The authors of these three papers undertake a common questioning of this purported
                  independence from matter, a concept that has two distinct and important
                  consequences: (a) the idea that digital information can be reproduced and
                  distributed at negligible cost and high speed, and thus, is immune to the
                  economics and logistics of analog media; (b) and that it can be accessed, used, or
                  reproduced without the noise, corruption, and degradation that necessarily results
                  from the handling of material carriers of information. Thus the concept of digital
                  information as immaterial is fundamental to the ability of the digital to upend
                  the analog world, and the foundation of a belief that any media that can be
                  digitized or produced digitally will eventually succumb to the logics of digital
                  information and its circulation through electronic networks—an argument powerfully
                  encapsulated by Negroponte’s slogan, “from atom to bits.” </p>

               <p class="noindent">Such widespread assumptions have obscured the specific material constraints that
                  obtain in digital environments. Only recently that the issue has emerged as a
                  legitimate concern for scholarly enquiry—engaging concepts of materiality from
                  literary, visual, media, and cultural studies and bringing them to bear on the
                  analysis of digital environments. The papers in this session take up some of these
                  issues by reading the machines, the specific properties of digital media from
                  surface screen to deeper structures, as a demonstration of the ways the
                  materiality of digital media can be engaged. The purpose of this work is to inform
                  some of the basic tasks of digital humanists – the interpretation of digital media
                  artifacts, the skills sets necessary to interrogate these artifacts, but also, our
                  responsibility for the preservation and use of these objects as part of our
                  cultural legacy. </p>

            
         
      <hr /><h2>“Infrastructural Thinking” as Core Computing Skill</h2><br /><h4>
                  Blanchette, Jean-François , 
                   Information Studies, UCLA, 
                  <a href="mailto:blanchette@gseis.ucla.edu">blanchette@gseis.ucla.edu</a>
               </h4><br />
         
            

               <p class="noindent">It is often suggested that all digital humanists would benefit from learning
                  programming. Through the acquisition of this core skill, they would engage with
                  the practice that defines computing and directly experience its possibilities and
                  constraints. Beyond mere mastery of a language, programming would expose them to
                  formal methods for abstracting and modeling concepts and real-world phenomena. The
                  current wave of interest in a “computational thinking” pedagogical paradigm
                  mirrors this argument: computer science is primarily about modeling and
                  abstraction of phenomena in ways amenable to algorithmic processing. </p>

               <p class="noindent">In this paper, I argue that programming, or its more complex formulation,
                  “computational thinking,” provides only a partial picture of computing, and
                  correspondingly, only a partial skill set. A fuller picture requires engagement
                  with the material foundations of computing. I use “material” here in a very
                  literal sense, to point to the physicality of bits (their encoding as magnetic
                  polarities, voltages, etc) and the material constraints of the devices that
                  process, store, and transport them. While the material dimension of computing
                  constantly informs the practices of the computing professions, this dimension is
                  also repressed, in the context of a general discourse that has emphasized the
                  abstract dimension of the digital over its material substrate. Yet, this
                  materiality, perhaps unexpectedly, holds the key to analyzing the shape and
                  evolution of the computing infrastructure. And while digital humanists may well
                  benefit from engaging in “computational thinking,” I will argue the computing
                  infrastructure implicitly performs much of that thinking, before a single line of
                  application code is written. </p>

               <p class="noindent">While programming deals with creating applications that provide service to users,
                  infrastructure software provides services to applications, by mediating their
                  access to computing resources, the physical devices that provide processing power,
                  storage, and networking. Infrastructure software is most commonly encountered in
                  the form of operating systems, but is also embedded in hardware (the firmware in a
                  hard drive) or in specialized computers (e.g., web servers, or routers). Whatever
                  its specific form, the role of infrastructure software is to provide a series of
                  transformations whereby the signals that encode bits on some physical media (fiber
                  optic, magnetic drive, electrical wires) become accessible for symbolic
                  manipulation by applications. Infrastructure software must be able to accommodate
                  growth in size and traffic, technical evolution and decay, diversity of
                  implementations, integration of new services to answer unanticipated needs, and
                  emergent behaviors, among other things. It must provide programmers with stable
                  interfaces to system resources in the face of continuously evolving computing
                  hardware—processors, storage devices, networking technologies, etc. </p>

               <p class="noindent">The computing industry manages to accomplish this feat through the design strategy
                  of <i>modularity</i>, whereby a module’s implementation can be
                  designed and revised without knowledge of other modules’ implementation.
                  Modularity performs this magic by decoupling functional specification from
                  implementation: operating systems, for example, enable applications to open, write
                  to, and delete files, without any knowledge of the specific storage devices on
                  which these files reside. This decoupling provides the required freedom and
                  flexibility for the management, coordination, and evolution of complex technical
                  systems. However, in abstracting from specific implementations of physical
                  resources, such decoupling necessarily involves efficiency trade-offs. The TCP/IP
                  protocols for example provide abstractions of networks that favor resilience (the
                  network can survive nuclear attacks) over quality of service (the network provides
                  no minimum delays for delivery of packets). Applications sensitive to such delays
                  (e.g., IP telephony or streaming media) must thus overcome the infrastructural
                  bias of the protocols to secure the quality of service they require. </p>

               <p class="noindent">An important point is that efficiency trade-offs (or biases) embedded in a given
                  modular organization become entrenched through their institutionalization in a
                  variety of domains: standards, material infrastructure (e.g., routers), and social
                  practices (e.g. technical training) may all provide for the endurance of
                  particular sets of abstraction. This entrenchment is further enabled by the
                  economies of scale such institutionalization affords. An immediate consequence is
                  that the computing infrastructure, like all other infrastructures, is
                  fundamentally conservative in character. Yet, it is also constantly under pressure
                  from the need to integrate changes in the material basis of computing: multi-core,
                  cloud-based, and mobile computing are three emerging material changes that will
                  register at almost every level of the infrastructure. </p>

               <p class="noindent">Computing, it turns out, is material through and through. But this materiality is
                  diffuse, parceled out and distributed throughout the entire computing ecosystem.
                  It is always in subtle flux, structured by the persistence of modular
                  decomposition, yet pressured to evolve as new materials, requiring new tradeoffs
                  emerge. This paper thus argues that, in a very literal and fundamental sense,
                  materiality is a key entry point for reading infrastructural change, for
                  identifying opportunities for innovation that leverage such change, and for
                  acquiring a deep understanding of the possibilities and constraints of computing.
                  This understanding is not particularly provided by exposure to programming
                  languages. Rather, it requires familiarity with the conflicts and compromises of
                  standardization, with the principles of modularity and layering, and with a
                  material history of computing that largely remains to be written. </p>
            
         
      <hr /><h2>Performative Materiality and Interpretative Interface</h2><br /><h4>
                  Drucker, Johanna, 
                   Information Studies, UCLA, 
                  <a href="mailto:drucker@gseis.ucla.edu">drucker@gseis.ucla.edu</a></h4><br />
         
            
               <p class="noindent">Approaches to interface design have come mainly from the HCI community, with an
                  emphasis on maximum efficiency in the user-centered experience. Since the days of
                  Douglas Engelbart and Ivan Sutherland’s experiments with head sets, pedals, mice,
                  and screens, in work that led to the development of the Graphical User Interface,
                  the dominant paradigm in the human-machine relationship has come from an
                  engineering sensibility. Leading practitioners in that field, from Stuart Card,
                  Ben Shneiderman, and others, have defined basic principles for design methodology
                  and display that are premised on a mechanistic analysis of user’s abilities to
                  process information effectively. This approach, taken from flight simulators and
                  applied to the vast numbers of tasks for searching navigating, buying, and
                  communicating online, is grounded in a user-as-consumer model. Criticisms from
                  inside that community, such as the work of Jesse James Garrett (showing the
                  confusion between information and task based approaches) or Aaron Marcus’s group
                  (analyzing cultural differences and their connection to interface functionality)
                  have provided useful insights and shifted design principles to be more nuanced.
                  But the basic model of the user-centered approach to interface design remains in
                  place. And it has been adopted by humanists, particularly when the resources to do
                  so are available. </p>

               <p class="noindent">If we bring the legacy of critical theory to bear on this model, however, we see
                  that the same critique leveled by post-structuralists against New Criticism is
                  pertinent here. The “text” of an interface is not a thing, stable and
                  self-evident, whose meaning can be fixed through a detailed reading of its
                  elements. An interface is a site of provocation for reading, and, in the same
                  manner as a film, literary work, or any other “text” (fashion magazine,
                  instruction manual), it is a space for interpretation involved an individual <i>subject</i>, not a generic user. In critical parlance, both an
                  enunciating and enunciated subject – the speaking and the spoken subject – are
                  aspects of textual production. (Text here is meant broadly.) This concept of
                  performativity, articulated by John Austin in <i>How to do things
                     with Words</i>, has echoes within the field of anthropology, gender studies,
                  and cultural studies. By situating texts and speakers within pragmatic
                  circumstances of use, ritual, exchange, and communities of practice,
                  performativity stripped away any foundation for thinking meaning was inherent in a
                  text or work. Performativity offered a sharp rebuke to notions of agency
                  (individuals) and autonomy (of texts). </p>

               <p class="noindent">How can we, that is, the community of digital humanists, take these critical
                  insights from literary, cultural, and gender studies into our current practice? If
                  the object is merely to demonstrate that one may read an interface with the same
                  techniques we used to read <i>Young Mr. Lincoln</i> or to follow
                  Laura Mulvey’s arguments into a new realm of semiotic analysis, a rather tedious
                  and predictable path would like ahead. This might have some value in the
                  undergraduate classroom, as the unpacking of ideological subtexts fascinates the
                  young. But for those of us concerned with the design of environments for digital
                  humanities and its research agendas, the questions that arise from this critical
                  encounter are quite different. Can we conceive of models of interface that are
                  genuine instruments for research? That are not merely queries within pre-set data
                  that search and sort according to an immutable agenda? How can we imagine an
                  interface that allows content modeling, intellectual argument, rhetorical
                  engagement? In such an approach, the formal, graphical materiality of the
                  interface might register the performative dimensions as well as support them. Such
                  approaches would be distinct from those in the HCI community in terms of their
                  fundamental values. In place of transparency and clarity, they would foreground
                  ambiguity and uncertainty, unresolvable multiplicities in place of singularities
                  and certainties. Sustained interpretative engagement, not efficient completion of
                  tasks, would be the desired outcome. </p>

               <p class="noindent">This is not an argument in favor of bad design. Nor is it a perverse justification
                  for the ways in which under-resourced projects create confusion, as if that were a
                  value for humanists. Quite the contrary. The challenge of creating an interface in
                  which the performative character of interpretation can be supported and registered
                  builds on demonstrable principles: multiple points of view, correlatable displays,
                  aggregated data, social mediation and networking as a feature of scholarly work,
                  and some of the old, but still charming, qualities of games like Nomic, with their
                  emerging rule sets. </p>

               <p class="noindent">My argument is that the humanities embody a set of values and approaches to
                  knowledge as interpretation that cannot be supported by a mechanistic approach to
                  design. This is not just a semantic exercise, but a point of departure for
                  implementation. The concept of performative materiality has a double meaning here.
                  In the first sense, materiality is understood to produce meaning as a performance,
                  just as any other “text” is constituted through a reading. That notion is
                  fundamental to humanistic approaches to interpretation as situated, partial,
                  non-repeatable. In the second sense, performative materiality suggests an approach
                  to design in which use registers in the substrate and structure so that the
                  content model and its expressions evolve. The “structure of knowledge” becomes a
                  “scheme of knowing” that inscribes use as well as provoking it. The idea of a
                  user-consumer is replaced by a maker-producer, a performer, whose performance
                  changes the game. This takes us back to some of the earlier theory of games, to
                  the work of Brenda Laurel and others, whose theoretical training brought notions
                  of subjectivity and performance into the study of online environments. </p>

               <p class="noindent">This paper does not claim to have a toolset of design solutions, since by
                  definition, that would put us right back into the HCI model. Instead, it is an
                  attempt to lay out some basic ideas on which to imagine a performative approach to
                  materiality and the design of an interpretative interface. Such an interface
                  supports acts of interpretation (does not merely return selected results from a
                  pre-existing data set) and also is changed by acts of interpretation, it evolves.
                  Performative materality and interpretative interface are co-dependent and
                  emergent. </p>
            
         
      <hr /><h2>Checksums: Digital Materiality in the Archive</h2><br /><h4>
                  Kirschenbaum, Matthew, 
                  Department of English; Maryland Institute for Technology in the
                     Humanities, University of Maryland, 
                  <a href="mailto:mgk@umd.edu">mgk@umd.edu</a>
               </h4><br />
         
            
               <p class="noindent">The general conversation about “materiality” in digital media has been ongoing for
                  quite some time (notably Markley 1997; Hayles 2002). A number of new foci, models,
                  and constructions have also recently been introduced into the conversation around
                  the term. These include Kirschenbaum’s “formal materiality” and accompanying work
                  on digital forensics (2008), the “media archeology” paradigm emerging out of
                  several key European writers following in the wake of Friedrich Kittler (Parikka
                  2007, Ernst 2005), and the platform studies approach developed and encouraged by
                  Montfort and Bogost (2009). At the same time, in the archival community,
                  practitioners are finding themselves confronted with the materiality of
                  born-digital objects in palpable and often increasingly time-sensitive real-world
                  ways: as more and more collections begin to process and receive digital storage
                  media as elements in the acquisition of personal “papers” from writers,
                  politicians, and other public figures, those charged with their long-term care are
                  implementing their own working models of materiality as they make decisions about
                  what to save, what to index, and what to provide access to. (Given the venue for
                  this year’s conference, it’s worth noting that Stanford University Libraries has
                  been a pioneer in this area, with such efforts as the Self-Archiving Legacy
                  Toolkit (SALT), the AIMS project on Born-Digital Collections and New Models for
                  Inter-Institutional Model for Stewardship, and their participation in the
                  Preserving Virtual Worlds project.) This paper will therefore seek to evaluate
                  recent developments in the theoretical conversation about digital materiality in
                  the specific context of applied practice in the archival community. However, it
                  will not assume that born-digital archival content can function only as a test-bed
                  for the various theoretical models; instead, it will also look at how the
                  decisions being made in archival settings have the potential to inform critical
                  and theoretical discourse. </p>

               <p class="noindent">The paper follows a case-study approach. Thus, it will consider media archeology,
                  which one definition glosses as “histories of suppressed, neglected, and forgotten
                  media [. . .] ones that do not point selectively and teleologically to the present
                  cultural situation and currently dominant media as their 'perfection’” (Huhtamo
                  2010) in light of the Deena Larsen Collection at the University of Maryland.
                  Larsen, who is traditionally associated with the Eastgate stable of hypertext
                  authors through work such as <i>Marble Springs</i> (1993) and <i>Samplers</i> (1997) has deposited a large and heterogeneous
                  array of hardware, software, storage media (some eight hundred 3½-inch diskettes),
                  notebooks, manuscripts, correspondence, and ephemera at the Maryland Institute for
                  Technology in the Humanities. This material includes a number of items related to
                  her best-known work, <i>Marble Springs</i> (1993), written in
                  Hypercard and published the same year, it turns out, as a much more famous work of
                  digital storycraft, Cyan’s <i>Myst</i>, also authored in
                  Hypercard. The Maryland collection includes the original text, with annotations,
                  as a manuscript in a notebook, various electronic drafts and early
                  implementations, installed copies of the work (which allows the user to add
                  marginal notes, thus creating the capacity to render every copy unique), and most
                  unusually, a shower curtain which contains laminated screenshots of different
                  nodes (lexia) pasted up and linked together with colored string to diagram the
                  affective relations between the different elements of the text. How can media
                  archeology, which, following Foucault’s venerable formulations, seeks to tease out
                  “hitherto unnoticed continuities and ruptures” (Huhtamo 2010) inform curatorial
                  practice around this work? Among other things, this paper will argue for a
                  network-oriented model of access, whereby a user of the collection, through
                  metadata packaging, is encouraged to access and evaluate items in relation to one
                  another rather than in isolation, as atomized treasures sprung from a Hollinger
                  box (or its digital equivalent, a FEDORA record). </p>

               <p class="noindent">Similarly, the platform studies approach advocated by Montfort and Bogost will be
                  evaluated in relation to a second recent project from MITH, a site devoted to
                  vintage computing which uses a considered metadata and modeling approach to
                  computing hardware, whereby individual components of the vintage machines are
                  documented, contextualized within their relation to the system as a whole, and
                  expressed using Dublin Core. While not “platform studies” in its own right, the
                  extent to which formalized representations of vintage computing systems can serve
                  as the basis for further work in that vein is important, since there are currently
                  few precedents for cataloging actual artifacts of computer history, and in
                  particular considering specific components as individualized entities rather than
                  as generic classes of mass-produced material. The paper will therefore ask what
                  kind of documentation and metadata a scholar interested in the affordances and
                  individuality of a particular computing system would need in order to use a
                  cataloged instance as the basis for critical work in the platform studies model. </p>

               <p class="noindent">Finally, the paper will consider Kirschenbaum’s interwoven strands of formal and
                  forensic materiality in relation to an event which post-dated his 2008 book, the
                  recovery, reconstitution, and successful emulation of the original software
                  program for William Gibson’s famously self-effacing poem “Agrippa” (Kirschenbaum,
                  et al. 2009). Emulation in particular allows us to usefully consider the armature
                  of “formal materiality,” since emulation functions precisely to naturalize or
                  operationalize one baseline computing system as the virtual host for a working
                  instantiation of another. Yet emulation is also an uncanny event, a kind of
                  literalization of the age-old conceit of the “ghost in the machine” as a
                  contemporary operating system becomes the proxy for one long (un)dead. “Agrippa”
                  itself, with its themes of memory, media, and loss is an apt vehicle for a
                  meditation on formal materiality and the limits of absolute emulation, especially
                  since there is one overridingly obvious fact about any virtual implementation or
                  emulation of “Agrippa”: unlike the original, which, famously, was a one-off “run”
                  encrypted with a military-grade one-way key, here one can spawn “images” of the
                  original disk at will and pass them through the emulator time and again.
                  Emulation, the paper concludes, is finally chimerical as is, perhaps, the notion
                  of formal materiality itself: virtualization will always be interrupted by the
                  individuality of original events. </p>

               <p class="noindent">One last word: the paper has a broader agenda beyond putting theory through its
                  paces, using archival content as a “checksum” for critical debate. Digital
                  humanities itself, as a community, has much to offer to ongoing efforts in the
                  archives world, yet thus far there has been a curious gulf between the two, with
                  only a handful of individuals serving as ambassadors between the two communities.
                  If digital humanities can offer a forum in which the artifacts and objects of
                  contemporary cultural heritage, many of which will be <i>born-digital</i> rather than digitized, can serve as the basis for critical
                  and technical inquiry then it will be well positioned to take part in the
                  increasingly urgent societal conversation around the future of our digital and
                  material present. </p>
            
         
      <hr /></div></div></body></html>