
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Modeling Event-Based Historical Narratives: A Conversation Between Digital Humanists,
          Information Scientists and Computer Scientists</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-233.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-233.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2> Panel: Modeling Event-Based Historical Narratives: A Conversation Between Digital Humanists,
          Information Scientists and Computer Scientists</h2><br /><h4>
          Meeks, Elijah, 
          Stanford University, 
          <a href="mailto:emeeks@stanford.edu">emeeks@stanford.edu</a>
        </h4><h4>
          Mostern, Ruth , 
          University of California, Merced, 
          <a href="mailto:rmostern@ucmerced.edu">rmostern@ucmerced.edu</a>
        </h4><h4>
          Grossner, Karl, 
          University of California, Santa Barbara, 
          <a href="mailto:karlg@geog.ucsb.edu">karlg@geog.ucsb.edu</a>
        </h4><h4>
          Shaw, Ryan, 
          University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, 
          <a href="mailto:ryanshaw@unc.edu">ryanshaw@unc.edu</a>
        </h4><h4>
          Jain, Ramesh, 
          University of California, Irvine, 
          <a href="mailto:jain@ics.uci.edu">jain@ics.uci.edu</a>
        </h4><h4>
          Kantabutra, Vitit, 
          Idaho State University, 
          <a href="mailto:vkantabu@coe.isu.edu">vkantabu@coe.isu.edu</a>
        </h4><br /><h2></h2>
      
        <p class="noindent">As digital humanities scholars increase the technological sophistication of their
          methodologies and tool use to represent historical change, their work becomes more
          theoretically complex from an information and computer science perspective. While much DH
          scholarship can be performed using off-the-shelf tools and simple data models, attempts to
          model highly nuanced historical knowledge, especially in event-based representation,
          requires a greater theoretical investment. This panel will present humanities scholars
          whose work focuses on using graph and semi-graph data models that track historical change
          as events in different parts of the digital scholarly media ecosystem—from the theoretical
          layout of the data and the representation of historical fact to the creation and
          population of a data structure to the analysis, representation and interaction with the
          product—in a dialectic with computer scientists and information scientists who have
          grappled with the problems of designing robust models and implementing performant
          technology in this domain. Through analysis of the digital scholarly media process from
          theory to creation to review, we hope to reveal sophisticated practical and theoretical
          solutions for representing, creating and reviewing historical knowledge.</p>
        <p class="noindent">The panel will be chaired by Elijah Meeks and allow for a short presentation by each of
          the discussants on the topics described below. This will be followed by a roundtable-style
          discussion with media examples from each discussant's work cued up so that, if the
          conversation focuses on one of these works, it can then be demonstrated and examined in
          detail. The guiding themes of the panel are theoretical challenges of event-based
          historical models, practical issues in creating sophisticated digital scholarly media
          using such models, and methods to review the models and the media created from them.</p>
        <p class="noindent">The panel presents a continuum of scholars from the humanities through information
          science to computer science, with Elijah Meeks (Digital Humanities Specialist, Stanford
          University) and Ruth Mostern (Associate Professor of History, University of California,
          Merced) representing the traditional humanities scholars. Elijah Meeks will speak about
          his work transitioning the <i>Mapping the Republic of Letters</i> database
          into a pure graph model and the challenges and benefits that this representation of
          historical knowledge presents in contrast to traditional relational databases as well as
          the suitability of graph data for event modeling. Ruth Mostern will focus on the role of
          event modeling in her current Yellow River research, tracking the linkages between
          historical environmental change and socio-political change, with an emphasis on the
          temporal and spatial reconciliation of differing scales and emphases of data, specifically
          comparing historical data collected for environmental science and traditional textual
          sources for tracking political and social change over time and space.</p>
        <p class="noindent">Karl Grossner (Geography, University of California, Santa Barbara) and Ryan Shaw
          (Assistant Professor of Information and Library Science, University of North Carolina at
          Chapel Hill) are both information scientists whose work has focused on issues critical to
          historical narrative modeling: ontologies and periodization. Ryan Shaw will speak to the
          complexities of event representation, focusing on periods and events as not only existing
          in the past, but also produced by discourse about the past, and the need for an approach
          to representation in which we can move back and forth between treating periods and events
          as, on the one hand, shared intersubjective points of reference and, on the other, unique
          perspectives on the past articulated through narrative techniques. Karl Grossner will
          discuss his work developing a spatial history ontology in which historical processes are
          modeled as theories of event relations, as well as its implementation in a PostgreSQL
          spatial database able to support mapping, analytical applications and representations of
          narrative.</p>
        <p class="noindent">Finally, Ramesh Jain (University of California, Irvine) and Vitit Kantabutra (Idaho State
          University) will discuss the practical issues of implementing such theoretical constructs
          in software. Vitit Kantabutra will spend some time explaining his work with Jack Owens
          fleshing out the Intentionally Linked Entity model, which is a generalized graph data
          model with a wide range of applications, and is especially suitable for the representation
          of historical and spatiotemporal events. Ramesh Jain will engage with the processing of
          event-based data semantically, both through typical searches and by exploring the emergent
          attributes of the database as an object itself.</p>
        <p class="noindent">By presenting a continuum of academic specialties that are unified in their focus on
          sophisticated digital representation of historical knowledge, we feel this panel will
          provide useful practical and theoretical value to the Digital Humanities community. We
          also hope to add to the growing discussion of how to judge the quality of the media
          produced in these endeavors, not only from the perspective of humanist scholars but from
          scholars in the field of information science and computer science.</p>
      
    <hr /></div></div></body></html>