
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Computational Discovery and Visualization of the Underlying Semantic
                    Structure of Complicated Historical and Literary Corpora</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-372.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-372.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Poster: Computational Discovery and Visualization of the Underlying Semantic
                    Structure of Complicated Historical and Literary Corpora</h2><h4>
                    Walsh, John A., 
                    Indiana University, 
                    <a href="mailto:jawalsh@indiana.edu">jawalsh@indiana.edu</a>
                </h4><h4>
                    Hooper, Wally, 
                    Indiana University, 
                    <a href="mailto:whooper@indiana.edu">whooper@indiana.edu</a>
                </h4><hr />
            
                <p class="noindent">This admirable invention [computation by logarithms] added to the ingenious
                    algorithm of the Indians, by reducing to a few days the labour of several
                    months, doubles—if we may so speak—the life of astronomers, and spares them the
                    errors and disgust inseparable from long calculations . . . </p>
                <p class="noindent">–Pierre Simon de LaPlace (1749-1827) Système du Monde, liv. iv, chap. iv</p>
            
        
            
                <p class="noindent">In addition to offering the possibility of new forms of scholarship beyond the
                    traditional article or monograph, digital humanities and the computational tools
                    developed as part of many digital humanities projects allow scholars to practice
                    an accelerated hermeneutics and analysis on ever larger collections of texts and
                    other cultural artifacts. Most projects that create scholarly digital editions
                    of important corpora are consciously addressing a range of research issues in
                    their respective fields and disciplines. Many of these projects are now also
                    developing components and applying computational tools to exploit their new
                    resources with the goal of solving those problems in an efficient and effective
                    way.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Napier’s logarithms (1614) eased the efforts of early modern astronomers. Today,
                    computational tools promise to accomplish lengthy mechanical tasks of review and
                    notation that generations of scholars have done by hand. Effective methods now
                    exist that will aid trained professionals to see into the heart and structure of
                    digital corpora.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Our project is associated with two major digital editions based at Indiana
                    University: the Chymistry of Isaac Newton Project (http://www.chymistry.org),
                    led by William R. Newman, general editor and co-investigator, which is
                    publishing a digital edition of one hundred nineteen alchemical manuscripts
                    written by Isaac Newton, thirty-two of which are now online; and the Swinburne
                    Project (http://www.swinburneproject.org/), edited by Walsh, which is publishing
                    the works of Victorian poet and critic Algernon Charles Swinburne.</p>
                <p class="noindent">The National Science Foundation has funded a three-year project (2009–12,
                    #0620868) to develop computational tools for the analysis of the alchemical
                    language in Newton alchemical corpus. We are investigating the usefulness of
                    methods from computational linguistics, information retrieval, and network
                    sciences for the analysis of the contents of the Newton corpus and the
                    visualization of its structures. We have been running experiments on IU’s
                    Teragrid supercomputer system and at the Computational Linguistics Lab for the
                    last two years.</p>
                <p class="noindent">We have developed a working suite of analytical tools that support effective
                    real-time investigation of the semantics and structure of the corpus. Data from
                    our analytical tools is fed into another suite of tools, the Network Workbench
                    (http://nwb.slis.indiana.edu/), to produce meaningful visualizations that help
                    the user to comprehend the breadth of the materials and their
                    interconnections.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Newman has already used the tools to demonstrate the order of composition of
                    significant parts of Portsmouth MSS. 3973 and 3975, two of Newton’s most
                    important notebooks recording his alchemical experiments performed at
                    Cambridge.</p>
                <p class="noindent">While the tools are being designed primarily for the analysis of alchemical
                    language in Newton's alchemical corpus, we of course hope the tools will be
                    useful in analyzing documents from other disciplines, and so we are also
                    applying these tools to a significant corpus of literary documents by
                    Swinburne.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Among Swinburne's works are six volumes of collected poems, five volumes of
                    collected tragedies, and a number of volumes of prose literary criticism. The
                    style, vocabulary and structures of Swinburne's 19th-century literary works are
                    obviously quite different from Newton's 17th-century scientific texts.
                    Furthermore, Swinburne's prose criticism is very distinct—in style, vocabulary,
                    and structure—from his poetry. An earlier effort from The Swinburne Project,
                    reported on at last year's conference, focused on thematic networks in
                    Swinburne's 1880 volume Songs of the Springtides. Many instances of networked
                    themes were found by simple keyword searching. More elusive instances were
                    identified by traditional methods of close reading, study, and analysis. We are
                    exploring whether our computational tools are successful at locating some of
                    these more elusive instances of previously identified themes and whether the
                    tools can identify clusters that suggest additional themes and streams of
                    meaning.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Our poster and real-time demonstration of the tools will present our results thus
                    far with the Newton and Swinburne projects.</p>
            
            
                <h2>Methods and Results</h2>
                <p class="noindent">We have found that Latent Semantic Analysis (LSA) is very effective for
                    discovering the semantic structure and organization of Newton’s alchemical
                    corpus. LSA methods use singular-value decomposition (SVD) to uncover hidden
                    layers of structure in a body of information and make it possible to capture and
                    expose similarities and dissimilarities across an entire corpus with a single
                    set of operations.</p>
                <p class="noindent">LSA technologies were discussed in the literature in the early 1990s primarily in
                    the context of information retrieval. That was a problem because LSA methods for
                    formulating and executing freeform user queries over growing datasets are less
                    effective than other methods based on Bayesian modeling like Latent Dirichlet
                    Allocation (LDA), Topic Analysis, and Latent Profile Analysis, which superseded
                    LSA after 2003. Many who follow the current literature regard LSA as an old and
                    limited technology. But the goals of close study and analysis are often distinct
                    from the goals of information retrieval, and there is little useful literature
                    on the use of SVD and LSA for actual text analysis beyond a report produced by a
                    team at Sandia National Laboratories in September 2010.</p>
                <p class="noindent">For our purposes, methods like LDA and LPA, which are based on identifying k-dimensional patterns from one set of document to the next and strategically
                    neglecting what is not pertinent to those dimensions, are less useful for text
                    analysis than methods that explicitly capture and model all relations between
                    all words and document chunks in corpora. SVD and LSA do that very well.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Our research plan includes collocational analysis of the Newton manuscripts
                    (almost a millions word of English, Latin, and French), and we are collaborating
                    with IU computational linguist Sandra Kübler to do part-of-speech markup,
                    lemmatization, and sentence parsing. As part of that effort, we have been
                    varying the size of our LSA document chunks downward from 1000 words to 250 and
                    100, approaching the sentence level where the distinction between “bag-of-
                    words” approaches and syntax-based methods tends to vanish for practical
                    purposes and the two can be welded in combined operations.</p>
                <p class="noindent">We have created web-based components that generate comprehensive lists of
                    correlated results based upon user-selected documents, document fragments, or
                    word. In the case of document-fragment queries, the user can select any pair of
                    correlated fragments and view them side by side. (<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-372.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">See Figure 1</a>) <p>
                        <h2>Figure 1: Screen capture of user component showing a side-by-side view
                            of two brief fragments from Portsmouth Add. MS. 3973, f. 19r, and Add.
                            MS. 3975, f.77r: The yellow color and red dots indicate shared
                            vocabulary and passages.</h2>
                        <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//372/372.1.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-372.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//372/372.1.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                    </p></p>
                <p class="noindent">Strongly correlated fragments (those correlating at 0.7 and above on a scale
                    ranging between -1.0 and 1.0) almost always share long phrases and sentences.
                    The method is robust enough to detect paraphrases too. One SVD calculation
                    detects and maps all the passages in that large, arcane corpus which share
                    vocabulary, phrases, and ideas, saving investigators considerable time in
                    working through those texts and revealing correlations that might otherwise
                    escape notice.</p>
                <p class="noindent">A useful way to present SVD results for interpretation is to graph them as
                    networks—the document chunks or the terms are graphed as nodes and the cosine
                    similarities or correlations between them as edges. Our tools make network graph
                    files for use in the Network Workbench (NWB) tool developed by our colleague
                    Katy Börner’s team at Indiana University. (<a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-372.xml&amp;chunk.id=&amp;toc.id=&amp;toc.depth=1&amp;brand=default&amp;anchor.id=#X" target="_top">See
                        Figure 2</a>) <p>
                        <h2>Figure 2: Sample network graph of relations between a small number of
                            correlated fragments in Keynes MS. 41, Dibner MS. 1070A, Yahuda MS. 259,
                            Babson MS. 417, and Royal Society M/M/6/5.</h2>
                        <img class="inline" src="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//372/372.2.png" /><p><a href="javascript://" onclick="javascript:window.open('http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-372.xml&amp;doc.view=popup&amp;fig.ent=http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/data/tei//372/372.2.png','popup','width=800,height=600,resizable=yes,scrollbars=yes')">Full Size Image </a></p>
                    </p> NWB is designed to be a “large-scale network analysis, modeling and
                    visualization toolkit for biomedical, social science and physics research.”
                    Another of our contributions is testing this tool in humanities research
                    contexts for which it was not initially designed.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Figure 2 shows that two passages on Keynes 41, ff. 12r and 13r, are better
                    correlated with four fragments in other manuscripts than they are with each
                    other (their correlation is 0.46). Newton worked back and forth between sets of
                    reading notes as he attempted to make sense of the alchemical literature. The
                    algorithms and graphs make all the connections visible at a glance.</p>
                <p class="noindent">We expect that the combination of LSA-based tools and network graphs derived from
                    them will provide invaluable means of problem solving and discovery for the
                    experienced researcher who is working with large, complicated corpora.</p>
            

        <h2>References:</h2>
            
                
                    <p>Börner, K.
                        2007
                         “Making Sense of Mankind's Scholarly Knowledge and
                            Expertise: Collecting, Interlinking, and Organizing What We Know and
                            Different Approaches to Mapping (Network) Science, ” 
                        <i>Environment and Planning B: Planning and Design</i>, 
                        34
                        5
                        808-825
                        Pion
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Deerwester, S. C.
                        Dumais, S. T.
                        Landauer, T.K.
                        Furnas, G. W.
                        Harshman, R. A
                        1990
                         ““Indexing by latent semantic analysis.”, ” 
                        <i> Journal of the American Society for Information
                            Science</i>, 41
                        6
                        391–407
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Dunlavy, D.
                        Shead, T.M.
                        Crossno, P.J.
                        Stanton, E.T.
                        September 2010
                         ““ParaText - Scalable Solutions for Processing and Searching
                            Very Large Document Collections: Final LDRD Report.”, ” 
                         “Technical Report SAND2010-6269, ” 
                        Sandia National Laboratories
                        Albuquerque, NM and Livermore, CA
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Skillicorn, D.
                        2007
                        <i>Understanding Complex Datasets. Data Mining with Matrix
                            Decompositions</i>, 
                        Boca Raton, FL
                        Chapman and Hall</p>
                    <p>
                        Walsh, J.
                        2010
                         “"Quivering web of living thought:" Conceptual networks in
                            Swinburne's Songs of the Springtides., ” 
                        Y. Levin
                        <i>A. C. Swinburne and the singing word: New perspectives on
                            the mature work</i>, 
                        Farnham, England
                        Ashgate
                        29-53
                    </p>
                
            
        </div></div></body></html>