
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Victorian Women Writers Project Revived: A Case Study in Sustainability</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-308.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-308.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: Victorian Women Writers Project Revived: A Case Study in Sustainability</h2><h4>
               Dalmau, Michelle, 
               Indiana University Digital Library Program, 
               <a href="mailto:mdalmau@indiana.edu">mdalmau@indiana.edu</a>
            </h4><h4>
               Courtney, Angela, 
               Indiana University Libraries, 
               <a href="mailto:ancourtn@indiana.edu">ancourtn@indiana.edu</a>
            </h4><hr />
         

            <p class="noindent">The <i>Victorian Women Writers Project</i> (<i>VWWP</i>, 
         (<a href="http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/collections/vwwp/" target="blank">link</a>)
   ) began in 1995 at
               Indiana University under the editorial leadership of Perry Willett and was celebrated
               early on for exposing lesser-known British women writers of the 19th century. The <i>VWWP</i>’s original focus on poetry was meant to complement <i>The English Poetry Full-Text Database</i>, but soon Willett
               acknowledged the variety of genres in which women of that period were writing –
               novels, children’s books, political pamphlets, religious tracts. The collection
               expanded to include genres beyond poetry, and continued active development from 1995
               until roughly 2000 at which point the corpus reached approximately two hundred texts. </p>

            <p class="noindent">These nearly two hundred texts comprise only a small fraction of Victorian women’s
               writing. Encouraged by renewed interest among Indiana University’s English faculty
               and graduate students, the Indiana University Libraries and the English Department
               are exploring ways to reinvigorate the project. The real challenge lies in the
               project’s past and present susceptibility to graceful degradation, which can be
               defined as stagnation or “deterioration of a system in such a manner that it
               continues to operate, but provides a reduced level of service rather than failing
               completely” (“Graceful degradation”). This has been a recurring topic in the digital
               humanities community as evidenced by a recently published article cluster, “Done,” in
               the <i>Digital Humanities Quarterly</i> (Spring 2009, v 3 n 2) and
               research by Bethany Nowviskie and Dot Poter on the very topic: </p>

            <p class="noindent">“Decline is a pressing issue for digital scholarship because of the
               tendency of our projects to be open ended. One could argue that digital projects are,
               by nature, in a continual state of transition or decline. What happens when the
               funding runs out, or the original project staff move on or are replaced? What happens
               when intellectual property rests with a collaborator or an institution that does not
               wish to continue the work? How, individually and as a community, do we weather
               changes in technology, the patterns of academic research, the vagaries of our
               sponsoring institutions?” (“Graceful Degradation: Managing Digital Projects in Times
               of Transition and Decline”). </p>

            <p class="noindent">The <i>Orlando Project</i> is a text-based resource containing
               primary texts, archival documents, biographies, chronologies and bibliographies.
               Despite the collection’s extensive size, Brown et al. reveal their sustainability
               challenges in an article published as part of the “Done” cluster: </p>

            <p class="noindent">Lack of people, time, or funding has consigned more than one project
               involuntarily to becoming a static tribute to its former activity. The reasons for
               this include people moving on, intellectually or institutionally, without taking
               their projects along with them, or people using electronic media to disseminate
               without particularly desiring to exploit their potential for continual updating, but
               even where the will to continue persists, inadequate funding mechanisms for
               sustainability may make it impossible. This is a shame, since, as we have argued here
               in the case of <i>Orlando</i> and many other digital publications not
               only does there remain the potential to enrich the contents, but the first iteration
               often merely begins to tap the potential of the project’s data architecture and
               potential for interface development (“Published Yet Never Done”). </p>

            <p class="noindent">Unfortunately and to no surprise, the <i>VWWP</i>, quite modest
               compared to its <i>Orlando Project</i> counterpart, has also suffered
               from nearly all the challenges highlighted by Nowviskie, Porter, and Brown. </p>

            <p class="noindent">In an effort to combat this “darker side of project management,” a framework for
               continual project support is being explored that reaches beyond any one individual or
               department (Nowviskie and Porter). At the crux of this framework is digital
               humanities-focused curriculum-building for the English department in partnership with
               the library, with a concentration on scholarly encoding and textual editing, working
               with English faculty, librarians, and technologists. The goals are to leverage domain
               expertise in the English Department; integrate the <i>VWWP</i> as a
               core research and teaching tool in the English curriculum; develop TEI and text
               encoding expertise in faculty and students; and through coursework, internships, and
               other opportunities, encourage English literature students— graduates and
               undergraduates—to continually contribute new content to the <i>VWWP</i>. Tools and workflows, such as robust encoding guidelines, quality
               control assessment, etc. will be provided to ensure proper markup, and the <i>VWWP</i> editorial board will additionally vet course output before
               submission to the project. </p>

            <p class="noindent">Through our newly offered graduate English course (L501, Digital Humanities
               Practicum), an eager and curious group of students learned not only encoding skills
               but also began to develop the collaborative practices pervasive in the digital
               humanities. As part of our talk, we plan to explore whether cultivating “markup
               skills” are sufficient enough in establishing a digital humanities curriculum
               (Rockwell) and whether “majoring in English” today means the curriculum should
               include awareness of the possibilities that arise for new scholarship when technology
               is applied to literary studies (Lanham). Certainly Indiana University is not breaking
               new ground or alone in this endeavor, but the literature is scarce is terms of
               understanding successes of graduate level digital humanities curricula situated in an
               English or any other humanities department. As Diane Zorich reports in her recent
               review of digital humanities centers, “A Survey of Digital Humanities Centers in the
               United States,” archives such as the Willa Cather and Walt Whitman Archives are
               precisely leveraged for teaching and learning, and this reporting is promising for
               the <i>Victorian Women Writers Project</i> as a project reconceived
               to meet both teaching and research needs in a classroom setting (19). </p>

            <p class="noindent">Currently, the <i>VWWP</i> is a standard e-text project, although
               current plans call for phased, modular development that will eventually include now
               commonplace “Web 2.0/3.0” functionalities. By garnering institutional commitment (at
               the risk of wavering priorities) across multiple departments (thereby minimizing
               risk), we hope to achieve the following: 
                  <li> Encourage English department buy-in and continual collaboration by updating
                     the current state of the <i>VWWP</i>’s functionality and
                     modernizing the look-and-feel (eliminate “first impressions” syndrome discussed
                     by Brown et al.) </li>

                  <li> Establish a sustainable scholarly encoding infrastructure based in the
                     English department curriculum </li>

                  <li> Provide a consistent mechanism (e.g., coursework output) for critical
                     content to accompany the encoded texts </li>

                  <li> Facilitate connections between other DLP-supported Victorian projects like
                     the <i>Swinburne Project</i> and the <i>Victorian Studies Bibliography</i>
                  </li>

                  <li> Evolve the project’s encoding guidelines, inclusion of critical contextual
                     materials, and advanced functionality (e.g., visualizations, textual analysis
                     tools, blog integration, etc.) so that the <i>VWWP</i> becomes
                     a dependable, growing and relevant online resource that can be adopted as a
                     pedagogic and research tool for Victorian scholars </li>
               
            </p>

            <p class="noindent">Our talk will introduce the <i>Victorian Women Writers Project</i>,
               explore curriculum-building strategies; and propose ways in which faculty and
               students can reliably and perpetually contribute to the <i>VWWP</i>.
            </p>
         
      <h2>References:</h2>
         
            


               <p>Brown, Susan
                   “Published Yet Never Done: The Tension Between Projection and
                     Completion in Digital Humanities Research., ” 
                  <i>Digital Humanities Quarterly</i>, 
                  3.2
                  2009
                  Web
                  12 April 2010
                  
         (<a href="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/2/000040/000040.html" target="blank">link</a>)
   
               </p>

               <p> “Graceful Degradation, ” 
                  <i>Federal Standard 103C: Glossary of Telecommunications
                     Terms</i>, 
                  Institute for Telecommunication Sciences
                  23 Aug. 1996
                  Web
                  12 April 2010
                  
         (<a href="http://www.its.bldrdoc.gov/fs-1037/dir-017/_2479.htm" target="blank">link</a>)
   </p>

               <p>
                  Lanham, Richard
                   “The Electronic Word: Literary Study and the Digital
                     Revolution, ” 
                  <i>New Literary History</i>, 
                  20.2
                  1989
                  265-290
                  Web
                  30 October 2010
                  
         (<a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/469101" target="blank">link</a>)
   
               </p>

               <p>
                  Nowviskie, Bethany
                   “Graceful Degradation, ” 
                  10 July 2009
                  Web
                  10 April 2010
                  
         (<a href="http://nowviskie.org/2009/graceful-degradation/" target="blank">link</a>)
   </p>

               <p>
                  Porter, Dot
                  Bethany Nowviskie
                   “Graceful Degradation: Managing Digital Projects in Times of
                     Transition and Decline, ” 
                  Digital Resources for the Humanities and Arts7-9
                     September 2009
                  Belfast, Ireland
               </p>

               <p>Rockwell, Geoffrey
                   “A Graduate Education in Humanities Computing, ” 
                  <i>Computers and the Humanities</i>, 
                  37.3
                  2003
                  243-244
                  Web30 October 2010
         (<a href="http://www.jstor.org/stable/30204899" target="blank">link</a>)
   </p>

               <p>Willett, Perry “The Victorian Women Writers
                     Project: The Library as a Creator and Publisher of Electronic Texts, ” 
                  <i>The Public-Access Computer Systems Review</i>, 
                  7.6
                  1996
                  Web
                  10 April 2010
                  
         (<a href="http://epress.lib.uh.edu/pr/v7/n6/will7n6.html" target="blank">link</a>)
   
               </p>

               <p>
                  Zorich, Diane
                  “A Survey of Digital Humanities Centers in the United
                     States.”
                  Council on Library and Information Services
                     (2008): 1-86
                  Web
                  30 October 2010
                  
         (<a href="http://www.clir.org/pubs/reports/pub143/pub143.pdf" target="blank">link</a>)
   
               </p>
            
         
      </div></div></body></html>