
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>The Digital Materiality of Early Christian Visual Culture: Building on John
                    20:24-29</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-315.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-315.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: The Digital Materiality of Early Christian Visual Culture: Building on John
                    20:24-29</h2><h4>
                    Heath, Sebastian , 
                    Institute for the Study of the Ancient World, New York
                        University, 
                    <a href="mailto:sebastian.heath@nyu.edu">sebastian.heath@nyu.edu</a>
                </h4><hr />
            
                <p class="noindent">This paper explores the nature of digital materiality as it resides in the visual
                    and written culture of Early Christianity. Within archaeology and related
                    disciplines, “materiality” is a theoretical approach that focuses on physical
                    things - such as objects, books, or buildings - as one starting point for
                    building an understanding of past thought and behavior (White 2009). As a term,
                    "digital materiality" does not yet have a fixed meaning and can refer to the
                    physical manifestations of the computer age (Manoff 2006), to the processes by
                    which digital representations become physical architecture (Gramazio and Kohler
                    2008) or to the effects of digital information in the modern world (Leonardi
                    2010). Here, I mean "digital materiality" as the transport of information about
                    the material culture of past societies, and particularly the material culture of
                    Early Christianity. Looking for fluid relationships between thought and object
                    in ancient evidence suggests that "digital materiality" is an appropriate
                    metaphor for both recovering past interactions with material culture and for
                    describing the role of networked information in modern archaeological and art
                    historical scholarship. It is this intersection of past and present that is of
                    particular interest. While stressing potential, this paper also looks to the
                    practical consequences of current efforts to digitize ancient activity that
                    survives in material form.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Existing virtual representations have already exposed clear overlaps between the
                    written word as object and the manifestation of those concepts in visual media.
                    The Codex Sinaiticus is a fourth century codex bible removed from Saint
                    Catharine’s monastery on the Sinai Peninsula in Egypt in the 19th century and
                    now largely in the British Museum. Its early date makes it plausibly the first
                    extant bible as that term is conceived in Christian terms. Most of the surviving
                    pages of the codex are available online at the site http://codexsinaiticus.org/
                    . Among the passages found there is John 20:24-29, where the disciple Thomas, of
                    “doubting Thomas” fame, demands to touch the wounds of the resurrected Jesus
                    when he appears to his followers. The passage ends with the exhortation, “20:29.
                    Because you have seen me, you have believed; blessed are those who have not seen
                    and yet have believed.”</p>
                <p class="noindent">The traction this concept had in Early Christian culture is clear from a hammered
                    gold disk produced in Egypt and now in the collection of the American Numismatic
                    Society that has a stable digital representation available at the URI
                    http://numismatics.org/collection/0000.999.51006 . This physical object quotes
                    the text of John 20:29 while illustrating Thomas in the act of touching Christ.
                    This paper stresses that the modern opportunity to engage in such a
                    self-referential illustration of the materiality of thought in the Later Roman
                    Mediterranean is a serendipitous result of independent efforts to digitize the
                    material record of that time and place. Just as the creation of the surviving
                    material record should be recognized as the cumulative action of many
                    individuals, it is likely that exploration of that record will be enabled by
                    many projects and institutions working within their own areas of expertise and
                    with content specific to their domain (Heath 2010, Terras 2010). It is the
                    interactions of a series of self-digitizing and independent communities – here
                    Early Christian textual studies and Numismatics – that can recover relationships
                    between physical object and human thought that is a primary goal of materiality
                    as a methodological approach.</p>
                <p class="noindent">It is, of course, important to recognize that while the Internet will make
                    evident the material implications of past human thought and action, it will not
                    of its own bring scholars into direct contact with the material culture they
                    study. Digital Humanities as applied to archaeology and visual culture will
                    usually mean working with surrogates: one cannot download an object, one can
                    only see its representation . The network does not take us to a site, it only
                    provides access to descriptions and pictures. Digital materiality is therefore
                    an act of transmission (Liu 2004) so that its deficiencies leave it open to
                    criticism.</p>
                <p class="noindent">Trends within the study of textual evidence as embodied in manuscripts suggest
                    that this observation is not a barrier to analytical progress. Projects such as
                    the Codex Sinaiticus digitization effort are showing that digital access to
                    manuscripts is returning the material to a central place in the study of primary
                    sources that had been abstracted in critical editions. The digitized page images
                    show in great detail the large number of variants and corrections that make
                    plain that written evidence for the ancient world does not exist independently
                    of its physical media. The Homer Multi-Text project
                    (http://chs.harvard.edu/chs/homer_multitext) is self-consciously engaged in
                    enabling virtual access to multiple manuscripts of the Iliad and Odyssey that
                    range from the Hellenistic to Medieval periods. Such initiatives indicate that
                    material and thought become meaningfully unified in a digital domain.
                    Accordingly, digital materiality is not a poor substitute for direct autopsy of
                    material culture. Rather than de-emphasizing the physical, Digital Humanities
                    will bring it to the fore. But it needs to be pointed out that at this moment,
                    the best critical editions of the <i>New Testament</i> (Aland and Nestle 2006, Aland et
                    al. 2006), with rich apparatus for the Gospel of John, is not available online
                    so that commercial interests are an impediment to to the study of the text,
                    whether considered as an idealized abstraction or a material object. This
                    suggests that the constituent components of both modern and ancient digital
                    materiality are at a transitional point where "primary sources" are more
                    accessible than "secondary works".</p>
                <p class="noindent">It is particularly important to stress this point when we recognize that it is no
                    longer possible within archaeological scholarship to have hands-on access to all
                    relevant material (Stewart 2008). To recall the ending sentiment of the doubting
                    Thomas story, “blessed are those who have not seen and yet have believed.” This
                    can be applied to the current state of archaeological and material studies and
                    lightly reformulated as an invitation to both make use of the full potential of
                    material and textual sources on the internet, and to aggressively pursue such
                    availability.</p>
            
        <h2>References:</h2>
            
                
                    <p>
                        Aland, B. et al.
                        2006
                        <i>Greek New Testament 4th Edition</i>, 
                        Hendrickson Publishers
                        Peabody, MA
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Aland, B.
                        Nestle, E.
                        2006
                        <i>Novum testamentum Graece 27th Edition</i>, 
                        Deutsche Bibelgesellschaft
                        Stuttgart
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Gramazio, F.
                        KOHLER, M.
                        2008
                        <i>Digital Materiality in Architecture</i>, 
                        Lars Müller Publishers
                        Baden
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Heath, S.
                        2010
                         “Diversity and reuse of digital resources for ancient
                            Mediterranean material culture, ” 
                        <i>Digital Research in the Study of Classical
                            Antiquity</i>, 
                        G. Bodard
                        S. Mahony
                        Ashgate
                        Farnham, UK
                        35-52
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Leonardi, P.
                        2006
                         “Digital materiality? How artifacts without matter,
                            matter., ” 
                        <i>First Monday</i>, 
                        15.6 (6-7 Jine 2010)
                        
         (<a href="http://www.uic.edu/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/3036/2567" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Liu, A.
                        2004
                         “Transcendental data: toward a cultural history and
                            aesthetics of the new encoded discourse, ” 
                        <i>Critical Inquiry</i>, 
                        31 (Autumn 2004)
                        49-84
                        
         (<a href="http://criticalinquiry.uchicago.edu/features/artsstatements/arts.liu.htm" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Manoff, M.
                        2006
                         “The materiality of digital collections: theoretical and
                            historical perspectives, ” 
                        <i>Portal: Libraries and the Academy</i>, 
                        6.3 (July 2006)
                        311-235
                        
         (<a href="http://dspace.mit.edu/handle/1721.1/35689" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Stewart, P.
                        2008
                        <i>The social history of Roman art</i>, 
                        Cambridge University Press
                        New York
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Terras, M.
                        2010
                         “Digital curiosities: resource creation via amateur
                            digitization, ” 
                        <i>Literary and Linguistic Computing</i>, 
                        25.4 (2010)
                        425-438
                        
         (<a href="http://llc.oxfordjournals.org/content/25/4/425.full" target="blank">link</a>)
   
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        White, C.
                        2009
                        <i>The materiality of individuality: archaeological studies of
                            individual lives</i>, 
                        Springer Science
                        New York
                    </p>
                
            
        </div></div></body></html>