
<!DOCTYPE html
  PUBLIC "-//W3C//DTD XHTML 1.0 Transitional//EN" "http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/DTD/xhtml1-transitional.dtd">
<html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xml:lang="en" lang="en"><head><meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8; charset=UTF-8" /><title>Civil War Washington: An Experiment in Freedom, Integration, and
               Constraint</title><link rel="stylesheet" href="css/default/results.css" type="text/css" /><script src="script/yui/yahoo-dom-event.js" type="text/javascript"></script><script src="script/yui/connection-min.js" type="text/javascript"></script></head><body class="home blog"><div id="wrapper" class="hfeed"><div id="header"><div id="masthead"><div id="branding" role="banner"><h1 id="site-title"><span><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Digital Humanities 2011: June 19 – 22" rel="home">Digital Humanities
                2011: June 19 – 22</a></span></h1><div id="site-description">Big Tent Digital Humanities</div><img src="https://www.stanford.edu/group/dh2011/cgi-bin/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2010/09/tieDyeLarge.jpg" width="940" height="198" alt="" /></div><div id="access" role="navigation"><div class="menu"><ul><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/" title="Home">Home</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=3" title="About">About</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=15" title="Accommodations &amp; Travel">Accommodations &amp; Travel</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=887" title="Accommodations">Accommodations</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=883" title="Travel">Travel</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=311" title="Registration">Registration</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=411" title="Schedule">Schedule</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=475" title="Workshops">Workshops</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=489" title="Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD">Tutorial 1: Introductory TEI ODD</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=499" title="Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the Undergraduate Curriculum">Tutorial 2 / Workshop: Integrating Digital Humanities Projects into the
                      Undergraduate Curriculum</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=507" title="Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can Help Your Project">Tutorial 3: An Introduction to XForms for Digital Humanists: How XForms Can
                      Help Your Project</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=517" title="Tutorial 4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools">Tutorial
                      4: Introduction to Text Analysis With Voyeur Tools</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=521" title="Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation">Tutorial 5: Gabmap: A Web Application for Analyzing Linguistic Variation</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=525" title="Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities">Tutorial 6: Natural Language Processing Tools for the Digital Humanities</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=529" title="Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and Sci2">Tutorial 7: Network and Topical Analysis for the Humanities using NWB and
                      Sci2</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=493" title="Workshop: Visualization for Literary History">Workshop: Visualization
                      for Literary History</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=471" title="Social Program">Social
                  Program</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=541" title="Literary San Francisco (Full Day)">Literary San Francisco (Full
                      Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=547" title="Silicon Valley History (Half-Day)">Silicon Valley History
                      (Half-Day)</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=537" title="Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)">Sonoma Wine Country (Full-Day)</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=181" title="CFPs">CFPs</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=97" title="General CFP">General
                      CFP</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=175" title="CFP en Español">CFP en
                      Español</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=287" title="CFP in German">CFP in
                      German</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=207" title="CFP in Greek">CFP in
                      Greek</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=229" title="CFP in Hungarian">CFP
                      in Hungarian</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=257" title="CFP in Italiano">CFP
                      in Italiano</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=157" title="Tutorial/Workshop CFP">Tutorial/Workshop CFP</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=19" title="Contacts">Contacts</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=801" title="Venue">Venue</a><ul class="children"><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=829" title="Local Lunch Spots">Local Lunch Spots</a></li><li><a href="https://dh2011.stanford.edu/?page_id=845" title="Palo Alto Restaurants">Palo Alto Restaurants</a></li></ul></li></ul></div></div><br class="clear" /></div></div><div class="resultsHeader"><table><tr><td><a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/search" target="_top">New Search</a> | <span class="notActive">Return to Search Results</span> | <a href="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view?docId=tei/ab-338.xml&amp;doc.view=print;chunk.id=0" target="_top">Print View</a></td><td align="right"><form action="http://dh2011abstracts.stanford.edu/xtf/view" target="_top" method="get"><input name="query" type="text" size="15" /><input type="hidden" name="docId" value="tei/ab-338.xml" /><input type="hidden" name="chunk.id" value="0" /><input type="submit" value="Search this Book" /></form></td></tr></table></div><hr /><div class="results"><h2>Paper: Civil War Washington: An Experiment in Freedom, Integration, and
               Constraint</h2><h4>
               Price, Ken, 
               University of Nebraska-Lincoln, 
               <a href="mailto:kprice2@unl.edu">kprice2@unl.edu</a>
            </h4><h4>
               Barney, Brett, 
               University of Nebraska-Lincoln, 
               <a href="mailto:bbarney2@unl.edu">bbarney2@unl.edu</a>
            </h4><h4>
               Lorang, Liz, 
               <a href="mailto:liz.lorang@gmail.com">liz.lorang@gmail.com</a>
            </h4><hr />
         
            <p class="noindent">Civil War Washington (CWW) is a thematic research collection that strives to enable
               users to visualize, analyze and interpret the physical, social, cultural, and
               political transformation of Washington, D.C. The development of Washington, D.C.,
               during the Civil War is pivotal in American history. When the Compensated
               Emancipation Act went into effect on April 16, 1862, Washington became the first
               emancipated city—and the country's largest and most important magnet for freed and
               runaway slaves. From that moment forward, the city would lead the nation in the
               sometimes tortuous route from slavery to freedom and from an entrenched system of
               legal inequality to a new commitment to equality for all. Our work on slavery, race,
               and emancipation in Washington, D.C., is crucial to our larger long-term study of the
               city in this time of crisis. We are already studying Civil War Washington from a
               medical perspective (the number of hospitals jumped from three to nearly one hundred
               making it a city of hospitals), from a military perspective (the city was the prized
               objective of Southern military strategy and in response the Union army made it the
               most fortified city in the world), and in fact from numerous other perspectives as
               well. With the assistance of a collaborative research grant from the National
               Endowment for the Humanities, our emphasis in 2010-2013 is to study the history of
               race, slavery, and emancipation in the city, a story of national importance. </p>
            <p class="noindent">The transformation of the U.S. capital has received surprisingly little sustained
               examination. One reason for this, no doubt, is that developing a rich and accurate
               understanding of the city's remaking requires not only access to but also synthesis
               and analysis of large and diverse sets of data, most of which exist only in analogue
               form. Our project, for example, draws on government reports, journalism, legal
               documents, diaries, census records, correspondence, city directories, poems, maps,
               and photographs. A further (and we believe necessary) complication is added by our
               desire to make a temporally-aware and user-manipulable GIS a significant constituent
               of our project, perhaps in some ways even its core. </p>
            <p class="noindent"> The number of projects, both emergent and established, that claim an interest in GIS
               and place-based scholarship seems to grow daily. This developing interest is
               reflected in an increasing number of seminars and training opportunities focused on
               GIS for the humanities, including at the University of Victoria's Digital Humanities
               Summer Institute, the Digital Humanities Observatory Summer School in Dublin, and the
               NEH-funded Geospatial Institute hosted by Scholars' Lab at the University of
               Virginia. In addition, there is a growing body of work on the value of spatial
               analysis in the humanities, and historians have taken a leading role in theorizing
               and conceptualizing the integration of GIS into humanities research, as well as in
               advancing arguments informed by GIS-enabled research. </p>
            <p class="noindent"> In recent years, at conferences such as this, a fair number of projects have been
               presented as models for addressing the still-daunting set of obstacles to the use of
               GIS for humanities projects.Martyn Jessop, in his talk At the first Digital
                  Humanities conference in 2006, “The Inhibition of Geographical Information in
                  Digital Humanities Scholarship," presented a list of barriers to the
                  application of GIS to humanities projects. This talk, later published in Literary
                  and Linguistic Computing (April 2008), is largely still relevant. In addition, see
                  also the report of the 7th Scholarly Communication Institute at the University of
                  Virginia, "Spatial Technologies and the Humanities":
                  http://www.uvasci.org/wp-content/uploads/2009/10/sci7-published-full1.pdf
               Our experience on Civil War Washington for the past five years, though, suggests that
               several important challenges have not yet been adequately investigated (let alone
               addressed). Our talk, then, is designed to be not a celebration of goals achieved but
               a case study for the consideration of several large issues that face our project and
               others like it.) Whereas most projects presented as models began with fairly well
               defined sets of data,For example, see the following DH2010 abstracts: Ian
                  Gregory, "GIS, Texts and Images: New Approaches to Landscape Appreciation in
                  the Lake District," Elton Barker, et al., "Mapping the World of an
                  Ancient Greek Historian: The HESTIA Project," and " Wayne Graham,
                  "A New Spatial Analysis of the Early Chesapeake Architecture," available
                  at http://dh2010.cch.kcl.ac.uk/academic-programme/abstracts/ ours began
               with a research question to which we want to apply as comprehensive a variety of data
               as possible. Our goal is not the digitization of materials for the sake of
               digitization but the exploration of a complex set of questions about the
               transformation of Washington, D.C. Further, our goal ultimately is to produce both a
               scholarly argument of our own and a resource that will enable our users to perform
               original, and truly meaningful, research based on our data and interfaces. Given
               these aims, on what basis should one decide the best technologies and methods for
               data capture, storage, and retrieval? We have responded to these questions based in
               part on the expertise of project members and the technologies that are familiar to us
               and local support staff. This strategy has the benefit of quicker development and an
               ever-more-refined knowledge in specific tools and technologies. Too heavy a reliance
               on the technologies and methods that one already knows, however, can lead to
               overlooking a more appropriate approach or set of approaches. 2) Given the fact that
               capture and storage of geo-referenced textual data can be accomplished in several
               different ways (e.g., through wholly TEI-XML, through assigning atomistic textual
               units to database fields, or through a combination strategy that uses both XML and
               database), what principles should guide the adoption of a particular encoding
               strategy? What tools exist or are most easily imaginable for making such data
               available for a wide variety of research approaches? TEI began providing for the
               georeferencing of textual data only with the release of P5 in late 2007, and we
               believe that the integration of textual and geospatial data remains an underdeveloped
               area to which the DH community should give greater thought. Surely it has potential
               beyond its rather modest application in existing projects. 3) How should a project
               deal with the catch-22 situation of wanting to develop and enable geospatial and
               historical analysis using open source tools even as the most adequate tools for the
               task, regrettably, are proprietary and the use of these proprietary tools is taught
               in leading DH institutions? In other environments, work on open source GIS has
               emerged as part of the larger open source and open access movement. The Open Source
               Geospatial Foundation, for example, is working to “promote the collaborative
               development of open geospatial technologies and data.”See
                  http://www.osgeo.org/content/foundation/about.html Humanities scholars,
               however, do not seem to be involved in the organization. What is and should be the
               role of humanities scholars in the developer community for GIS software? Does the
               existing open source GIS software originally conceived of by organizations such as
               the Army Corps of Engineers (Grass GIS) or NASA (MapServer) meet the needs of
               humanities scholars? We have considered these questions not merely in the realm of
               abstract ideals, but as immediate and pressing concerns; we wish to use our project's
               responses to them not as recommendations but as opportunities for critical reflection
               and discussion. </p>
         
      </div></div></body></html>