<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">A Workbook Application for Digital Text
                    Analysis</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Worthy</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">N.</forename>
                        <surname>Martin</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Virginia</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Olga</forename>
                        <surname>Gurevich</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Virginia</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Thomas</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">B.</forename>
                        <surname>Horton</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Florida Atlantic University</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Robert</forename>
                        <surname>Bingler</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Virginia</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Text Encoding</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>The workbook facility for scholars in the humanities aims to help them
                        organize the results of their research in a convenient and easily accessible
                        manner. The recent proliferation of marked-up electronic corpora has
                        produced a need for tools that would allow structured search and extraction
                        from texts. However, not all potentially interesting features of a text can
                        be described in terms of the mark-up hierarchy: some features involve
                        overlapping elements of markup, others are too fine-grained to be marked up.
                        Thus we need a mark-up independent method of searching, and tools that
                        combine both. The text region-based approach to processing digital text
                        resources is the proposed method of searching and extracting both marked-up
                        and non marked-up information from a collection of texts. The workbook
                        facility is a prototype application of this method that allows extraction
                        and linking of portions of XML-formatted texts. The selection of the regions
                        can be based either on their structural characteristics or on other
                        features.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Concepts</head>
                    <p>A text region (a.k.a. span) is a continuous portion of a document identified
                        by its start and end offsets. It can be a complete XML element or just a
                        string of characters. A text region can be created through a variety of
                        operations described below. In our use of the concept, most XML elements are
                        assigned a unique identifier within the document. The offsets for text
                        regions are therefore relative to the nearest preceding ID within the
                        document. A text occurrence object (TOO) consists of one or more text
                        regions as well as notes and a user-defined name. The text regions can come
                        from one or more documents and do not have to be contiguous. SGREP
                        (structured grep) is a command-line search tool. It allows structured
                        searches on XML and SGML formatted texts and collections of texts, as well
                        as simple searches. The search results are returned as a set of text regions
                        that can be organized into a text object occurrence. SGREP allows nested
                        searches (for example an XML element labeled "verse" containing the word
                        "Hamlet" within a DIV1 element) as well as unions and intersections of
                        search expressions.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Workbook Facility</head>
                    <p>The workbook facility aims to help humanities scholars to organize the
                        results of their research in a convenient and easily accessible manner. It
                        provides a way to bookmark and annotate documents without changing the
                        original texts, and to store and link annotated extractions from texts. The
                        workbook consists of a set of TOO's, each of which contains one or more text
                        regions that can originate from different documents. A TOO can thus link
                        portions of texts from different places in a document or from different
                        documents. The workbook facility has a built-in XML parser that creates a
                        DOM structure. We are using IBM's Java-based parser, and the rest of the
                        workbook is also written in Java. The following operations are available to
                        the user:<list type="bulleted">
                            <item>Select a collection of XML documents with which he wants to work
                                (the base collection).</item>
                            <item>For each document, view the raw text or the DOM (Document Object
                                Model) structure resulting from parsing the XML document. The DOM
                                structure is displayed in a tree control.</item>
                            <item>Create text occurrence objects in several different ways.</item>
                            <item>Select a complete XML element from the DOM, in which case the TOO
                                will consist of a single text region.</item>
                            <item>Select any continuous portion of raw text from any document in the
                                collection to create a TOO.</item>
                            <item>Run an SGREP search on one or more documents in the collection. If
                                the search is successful, SGREP will return one or more text regions
                                which will be put together into a TOO.</item>
                            <item>Name and annotate all TOO's in the same manner, regardless of how
                                a particular TOO was created. The list of TOO's constitutes the
                                workbook and is displayed separately.</item>
                            <item>By clicking on any text region within a TOO, view the spot within
                                the document from which the text region originated. Thus, it is
                                possible to view the larger context of a particular
                                extraction.</item>
                            <item>Produce a word distribution list for any particular TOO, and
                                compare word distributions between several TOO's. The word
                                distribution list can be sorted by relative frequency of words or by
                                alphabetical order, and two lists can be viewed side by side.</item>
                            <item>Order and re-order the TOO's within the workbook.</item>
                            <item>Organize the TOO's into folders with arbitrary depth of nesting,
                                similar to how files are organized on a disk.</item>
                            <item>Save the workbook (i.e. the individual TOO's along with folders or
                                TOO's) and re-open it later. The ability to return to the original
                                documents remains after the workbook has been re-opened.</item>
                            <item>Save particular TOO's and sets of TOO's as separate XML documents
                                and include them in the base collection.</item>
                            <item>Run SGREP searches on documents created from parts of the workbook
                                in the same way as on the original ones.</item>
                        </list></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Impact</head>
                    <p>The proposed workbook facility will be useful for several research goals.
                        Extracting, ordering and naming textual fragments is a convenient way for an
                        instructor to prepare for a lecture about a particular text. Scholars that
                        study different versions of the same text (i.e. versions in different
                        languages or different editions) can use the workbook to link parallel
                        passages and annotate the resulting TOO. Since the creation of text regions
                        can be markup-independent, this can be done even if the parallel passages in
                        two documents are not contained within a single XML element. Moreover,
                        extracting regions that share particular features can be automated with the
                        help of SGREP. The word distribution feature of the program is intended to
                        demonstrate that operations found in software like TACT and similar tools
                        can be easily integrated with our workbook approach. Once a workbook is
                        created, it still contains links to the original documents and the history
                        of how the extractions were made. That is, the process is completely
                        retraceable, and the user can view the context from which any text region
                        came.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">DOM (Document Object Model) standard</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.w3.org/DOM/"/>&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Thomas</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">B.</forename>
                                    <surname>Horton</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">A region-based approach for Processing Digital Text
                                Resources</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Digital Resources for the Humanities, King's College,
                                London, Sept. 12-15, 1999</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">47-49</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Jani</forename>
                                    <surname>Jaakkola</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="firstname">Pekka</forename>
                                    <surname>Kilpeläinen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">SGREP (structured grep)</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>at the University of Helsinki, Finland</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.cs.helsinki.fi/~jjaakkol/sgrep.html"
                            />&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">XML standard</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.w3.org/XML/"/>&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">XML4J, the XML parser for Java produced by IBM</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.alphaworks.ibm.com/tech/XML4"/>&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
