<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Perdita's Progress: Raising Standards in a TEI-based
                    Approach to Cataloguing Early Modern Manuscripts</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jill</forename>
                        <surname>Seal</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Nottingham Trent University</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Claire</forename>
                        <surname>Warwick</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Sheffield University</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Elizabeth</forename>
                        <surname>Clarke</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Nottingham Trent University</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Perdita Project was established in 1997 at the Nottingham Trent University,
                    by Elizabeth Clarke and Victoria Burke of the English &amp; Media Studies
                    department, with Martyn Bennett of the History department, funded initially by
                    the Nottingham Trent University. A substantial AHRB grant in 1999 meant that we
                    could appoint research fellow Jonathan Gibson and researchers Jill Seal and
                    Gillian Wright. Claire Warwick from the Department of Information Studies at
                    Sheffield is electronic publication consultant to the project, which runs until
                    2002.</p>
                <p>We regard this paper as a collaborative exercise. In it we aim to introduce some
                    of the dilemmas which we have faced during the project. We hope that our
                    progress may be of interest to those at the conference, and that our discussions
                    with the humanities computing community will also be of help to us in the
                    continuation of the project.</p>
                <p>The Perdita Project is producing a comprehensive guide to manuscript compilations
                    of early modern women. We are carrying out research on over 450 manuscripts
                    written or compiled by women, which include miscellanies, commonplace books,
                    account books, medical and cookery receipt books, religious writing, and
                    autobiographical material. Our descriptions of the manuscripts will be encoded
                    in SGML to allow extensive searching capacity, and will be published on the
                    Internet in 2002.</p>
                <p>The interdisciplinary nature of the project is vital to our work, and is
                    something that we will discuss throughout the paper. By describing previously
                    unpublished materials by women of the 16th &amp; 17th centuries, we aim to be a
                    resource for scholars both literary and historical, enabling access to
                    manuscript sources which are often very difficult to trace in comparison with
                    published texts. We see ourselves as part of the movement to rewrite literary
                    history, moving the emphasis from printed text and male and/or canonical works
                    to a fuller picture of the writing of the period (Ezell, 1993). Electronic
                    publication also allows us to address important issues to do with the
                    dissemination of text in an electronic medium. This seems uniquely appropriate,
                    since as Woodmansee (1994) argues, the transmission of scholarly electronic text
                    shares some features with the coterie traditions of manuscript dissemination
                    which we are studying in the early modern period.</p>
                <p>In the paper we shall explore some of the challenges we face in attempting to
                    combine the two traditions and when working with the different media of
                    manuscript, print and electronic text. We will discuss why we have chosen to
                    encode manuscript descriptions rather than the texts themselves, and how far we
                    should interpret the manuscripts in the descriptions that we provide. To what
                    level, and in what way should these descriptions be encoded, and how will this
                    affect their usefulness? How far should we try to consider the present user
                    community? Standards, whether in manuscript description or in electronic text
                    encoding, are also vital to our work.</p>
                <p>Projects which deal with the electronic publication of manuscripts tend either to
                    provide users with digitised images of manuscript pages, and/or to transcribe
                    and encode the text. However, we have chosen a different strategy, since we are
                    not presently intending to transcribe entire manuscripts. Rather, we will
                    present descriptions, which will take the form of an extended catalogue entry,
                    including a list of contents, a physical description, and a biographical article
                    on the compiler(s). We believe that there are valid scholarly reasons for doing
                    so.</p>
                <p>There is already a certain amount of literary text available in electronic form,
                    much of which is lacking any kind of commentary or contextual material. Given
                    the time and financial constraints of our project, we therefore preferred to
                    concentrate on a more novel research area. Our methodology has been designed as
                    a response to the shift in focus in manuscript studies from the search for
                    authoritative texts to the historical circumstances of manuscript production and
                    circulation (Beal, 1980-, Marotti, 1995, Woudhuysen, 1996, Hobbs, 1992, Love,
                    1993). Rather than simply producing large amounts of transcribed text with no
                    accompanying commentary or contextual research, we prefer to make an important
                    scholarly contribution to this research area.</p>
                <p>We also consider that it is important that our resource should lead scholars to
                    visit archives, and consult the manuscripts themselves, when possible. Since the
                    provision of digital surrogates tends to increase the amount of usage of the
                    original material (Lee 1998, Chapman, Kingsley &amp; Dempsey, 1999), we feel
                    that out efforts should be directed to descriptive scholarly research to aid
                    researchers in their use of original documents.</p>
                <p>We do, however, acknowledge the problematic nature of our task and of
                    classifications such as authorship, function and gender in looking at manuscript
                    compilations, and pledge ourselves to giving "as much information as possible to
                    facilitate useful readings of the manuscript compilations". But what are
                    "useful" readings, how much information should we give, and in what form? We
                    therefore intend to conduct a study of our potential user community in
                    collaboration with Sheffield University DIS to try to answer these, and other,
                    questions.</p>
                <p>However, we are aware of the potential problems of trying to ensure that the
                    resource remains usable and accessible by a community of future users whose
                    needs we cannot hope to predict. This means that we need to apply, and in some
                    cases set, standards in various areas. Most obviously, we must apply the highest
                    standards in manuscript cataloguing and description. There are also other areas
                    which we are particularly well-equipped to explore, for instance, a standard
                    vocabulary for describing handwriting. Most fascinating of all is the question
                    of what a woman's hand might look like. Electronic delivery will provide us with
                    an ideal opportunity to contribute to this discussion, by providing visual
                    samples of women's hands.</p>
                <p>We are also concerned with the standards necessary for electronic publication. We
                    must be aware of how far the standards necessary for text encoding and useful
                    searching impose interpretations on the manuscript, since already, in our
                    editing and cataloguing process, we are working at several removes from the
                    original text (see fig. 1).We are conscious that the decisions we make in
                    encoding the descriptive material must not be so prescriptive that they hinder
                    usage, but at the same time we aim to aid searching by appropriate markup. We
                    therefore approach this project in the spirit of the text-encoding initiative.
                    However, further complications are caused by the fact that what we are encoding
                    is essentially metadata, not simply transcribed text.</p>
                <p>We would like to explore the ideological, conceptual and practical differences
                    between the TEI, metadata systems, and the use of controlled vocabulary. In the
                    world of electronic resources there appears to be a culture clash between a
                    post-structuralist, qualitative 'search for anything you like - create your own
                    text' ideology and the controlled, quantitative approach to classifying objects
                    taken by museums. This may represent the difference between dealing with text
                    and dealing with objects, or the difference between English and History, where
                    computing projects tend to deal with statistics. However, we at Perdita are
                    faced with the problem of trying to balance the two approaches. We are aware
                    that the TEI header is ideal for a project which wants to shape the data in the
                    form of the original text, even if it does not encode it. Some historians are
                    now beginning to recognise that 'data' is deeply embedded in text, which is why
                    we believe that TEI is the best ideological option.</p>
                <p>Yet, database pioneers such as The Getty Institute in LA are encouraging us to
                    adopt database methodology and to use terminology and Thesauri, because of their
                    more systematic nature. This view is supported by research by DIS at Sheffield,
                    which suggests that when constructing and using metadata, many users find the
                    lack of a controlled vocabulary inhibits the ease with which they can search
                    electronic resources. (Whittaker 1999) At the British Women Writers' Conference
                    at Albuquerque in September, everyone recognised the need for a standard set of
                    keywords. Unfortunately no such resource yet exists.</p>
                <p>We have therefore decided to view our work in the light of future users. We will
                    describe our attempts to combine both standards and to provide some sense of the
                    original text, using TEI markup, with a standardised search vocabulary for ease
                    of searching.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Beal</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Index of English Literary Manuscripts</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">(2 vols, 2 pts)</biblScope>
                                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Mansell</publisher>
                                <date when="1980">1980-</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Chapman</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">N.</forename>
                                    <surname>Kingsley</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Dempsey</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Full Disclosure. Releasing the Value of Library and
                                Archive Collections</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Bath</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>UKOLN</publisher>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Ezell</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Writing Women's Literary History</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Johns Hopkins U. P.</publisher>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Hobbs</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Early Seventeenth-Century Verse Miscellany
                                Manuscripts</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Aldershot</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Scholar Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1992">1992</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Lee</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="u">Scoping the Future of Oxford's Digital
                                Collections</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.bodley.ox.ac.uk/scoping"/>&gt; , last
                            accessed 4/5/99. </note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Love</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Scribal Publication in Seventeenth-Century
                                England</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Marotti</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Manuscript, Print, and the English Renaissance
                                Lyric</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Ithaca</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Cornell U. P.</publisher>
                                <date when="1995">1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Whittaker</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">The construction of Dublin Core Metadata by
                                non-specialist users</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <edition>Unpublished MA dissertation</edition>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>University of Sheffield</publisher>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Woodmansee</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">On the Author Effect: Recovering Collectivity</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Martha</forename>
                                    <surname>Woodmansee</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Peter</forename>
                                    <surname>Jaszi</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">The Construction of Authorship: Textual Appropriation
                                in Law and Literature</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Durham, NC</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Duke U.P.</publisher>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">H.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Woudhuysen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Sir Philip Sidney and the Circulation of Manuscripts
                                1558-1640</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
