<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Metainformation Strategies for Electronic
                    Resources</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Susan</forename>
                        <surname>Schreibman</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University College Dublin</name>, Eire <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Text Encoding</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>This paper will address the theoretical and practical issues in devising and
                    implementing a project-specific metainformation scheme for electronic resources.
                    While one can argue that a scheme like the Text Encoding Initiative provides for
                    encoding which greatly enhances plain text retrieval, in practice without
                    extensive use of the keyword or indexing elements, retrieval of information is
                    limited to what is explicit in the text. Searching for what is explicit in the
                    text, even if that text has been encoded logically (as opposed to physically),
                    does not provide the kind of functionality most humanists expect from digital
                    archives.</p>
                <p>This paper then is an exploration of the advantages and disadvantages in creating
                    a meta-meta information or classification scheme for electronic resources. For
                    this talk I will draw heavily on theoretical models (both pre-and post-computer
                    indexing models) from library and information studies. I will also adopt the
                    position that creators of electronic resources are encoding their primary
                    material in a SGML or XML-based metainformation scheme, such as the Text
                    Encoding Initiative. I will also assume that the project directors have already
                    made certain specific decisions in encoding what is explicit in the text in
                    accordance with the project's goals. In other words, I am assuming that a
                    digital project is already taking advantage of the tagging structure afforded in
                    a scheme like the TEI in providing for the encoding of titles of text, place,
                    personal, geographic and organisation names, etc., as deemed important to a
                    particular project.</p>
                <p>There can be no doubt that this type of tagging greatly enhances retrieval, for
                    example by distinguishing the occurrence of WB Yeats as a title as opposed to a
                    personal name, or facilitating the searching of all strings within a
                    &lt;placename&gt; element. And although this type of encoding of electronic
                    resources gives users unprecedented access in locating very specific strings of
                    text, in practice users are frustrated by limited and relatively simplistic
                    search and retrieval strategies. In most electronic resources, users are limited
                    to retrieving only what is explicit in the text, i.e. strings of text, some of
                    which have been encoded logically. In the case of images, the situation is even
                    more problematic. Unless a project has developed a header consisting of detailed
                    metainformation, most images can only be retrieved by image title. Boolean and
                    proximity searches go a very small way in solving the problem of retrieving more
                    than single word searches, but do not provide the conceptually and theoretically
                    rigorous searches most scholars in the humanities want and expect from
                    electronic resources.</p>
                <p>Specifically, this paper will address the practical and theoretical issues raised
                    by devising a classification or indexing scheme which facilitates search and
                    retrieval by going beyond encoding what is explicit in the text. To this end,
                    several points will be raised:<list type="bulleted">
                        <item>although encoding what is implicit in the text facilitates retrieval
                            of concepts not possible by explicit encoding, this process is much more
                            subjective;</item>
                        <item>how this subjectivity influences retrieval;</item>
                        <item>the concept of granularity will be raised, and the problems of
                            encoding to various levels;</item>
                        <item>the problems of encoding implicit metainformation which is transparent
                            to users.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>While at past ALLC/ ACH conferences many papers have discussed the difficulties
                    in consistent encoding of explicit text in large projects in which many people
                    participate in the encoding process, the possibilities for inconsistent encoding
                    of implicit text multiplies exponentially. Yet, I would argue, that without the
                    development of classification or indexing schemes, digital archives remain
                    hidden behind front ends which may look resplendent, but which barely reveal
                    their complexity and richness.</p>
                <p>To this end, the rest of the paper will be divided into three parts. Part I will
                    provide an overview of some of the major metainformation schemes which were
                    developed in a pre-digital environment, such as AACR2, the Dewey Decimal
                    Classification, and the Library of Congress Subject Headings. Topics to be
                    covered will include:<list type="bulleted">
                        <item>the theoretical impetus behind these schemes;</item>
                        <item>how and why these schemes were conceived and made extensible;</item>
                        <item>why these schemes cannot be transferred to a digital environment
                            without adaptation.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>The second part of the paper will explore current applications of some of these
                    schemes to a digital environment, such as the Art and Architecture Thesaurus and
                    the Thesaurus for Graphic Materials. Specifically, I will address how these
                    schemes have been adapted from facilitating indexing codex-based texts to
                    digital ones. In addition, the special case of indexing images will also be
                    discussed.</p>
                <p>The third part of this paper will explore metainformation schemes devised for
                    several specific digital archives, including The Blake Archive and The Thomas
                    MacGreevy Archive, both published at the Institute for Advanced Technology in
                    the Humanities at the University of Virginia. In the case of the Thomas
                    MacGreevy Archive, I will demonstrate how we, working within the TEI, developed
                    a metainformation scheme which facilitated very specific genre searching for
                    both texts and images.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
