<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">An American National Corpus: a Large Balanced Text
                    Corpus for American English</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Catherine</forename>
                        <surname>Macleod</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">New York University</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Nancy</forename>
                        <surname>Ide</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Vassar College</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Computational / Corpus Linguistics</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction:</head>
                    <p>The importance of corpora as resources has become more and more accepted over
                        the years. Many types of corpora have been used for various different
                        purposes but if one is searching for examples of "general" application and
                        not restricting oneself to a particular sub-language, the development of a
                        balanced corpus is of primary importance. Of equal importance is the
                        adoption of a uniform standard annotation. The main areas of application of
                        a text corpus are lexicography (also computational lexicography) and natural
                        language processing, including specifically, adaptation to different domains
                        and genres. For these purposes the corpus must be large (at least 100
                        million words), contemporary, heterogeneous, uniformly annotated and, for
                        use in the United States, must contain American English. The size will
                        ensure the adequate representation of infrequent words. The selection of
                        contemporary texts is important for both lexicography and NLP, particularly
                        in view of the significant changes in common text genres over the last few
                        years brought about by electronic communication. Heterogeneity ensures that
                        the range of language usage needed for the creation of "general language
                        resources" is represented, and that one can explore a wide spectrum of
                        language genres for NLP. Uniform annotation is paramount in any corpus and
                        the collection of American texts ensures that the grammatical and lexical
                        differences found in British English will not interfere with the classifying
                        of American English.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Background:</head>
                    <p>The first American text corpus that strived for this balance was the Brown
                        Corpus developed by Kucera and Francis at Brown University in the 1960's. It
                        was the model for many corpora that followed and is still being used today.
                        However, it is a small corpus (one million words) and somewhat dated (the
                        texts are at least 30 years old). It is true that a written language changes
                        rather slowly over time with regard to grammar but there are changes in the
                        structure and there are quite frequent additions of new lexical items.</p>
                    <p>Recently, the British National Corpus (BNC) was released. It is a rather
                        carefully balanced corpus and a very large corpus (one hundred million
                        words). It also has the advantage of covering the time period from where the
                        Brown Corpus left off until 1993. There are, nonetheless, two distinct
                        disadvantages for Natural Language researchers and dictionary producers in
                        the United States: (1) the corpus is, as yet, unavailable for use outside of
                        Europe and (2) the corpus contains texts of British not American English.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Differences between American and British English:</head>
                    <p>The grammar of American English (A.E.) varies from British English (B.E.)
                        quite significantly. For example, British English often makes use of a
                        to-infinitive complement where American English does not. In the following
                        examples from the BNC, "assay", "engage", "omit" and "endure" appear with a
                        to-infinitive complement; there were no examples found in our corpus of this
                        construction although the verbs themselves did appear.</p>
                    <p>Examples: <lb/><lb/><eg>B.E. "Jerome crept to the foot of the steps, and
                            there halted, baulked, rather, like a startled horse, drew hard breath
                            and ASSAYED TO MOUNT, and then suddenly threw up his arms to cover his
                            face, fell on his knees with a lamentable, choking cry, and bowed
                            himself against the stone of the steps." </eg><lb/><lb/><eg>B.E. "A
                            magnate would ENGAGE TO SERVE with a specified number of men for a
                            particular time in return for wages which were agreed in advance and
                            paid by the Exchequer." B.E. " 'What did you OMIT TO TELL your priest?'
                            " A.E. "`What did you OMIT TELLING your priest?'"</eg><lb/><lb/><eg>B.E.
                            "But Carteret's wife, who frequented health spas, could not ENDURE TO
                            LIVE with him or he with her: there were no children."
                            </eg><lb/><lb/><eg>A.E. "But Carteret's wife, who frequented health
                            spas, could not ENDURE LIVING with him or he with her: there were no
                            children."</eg></p>
                    <p>For the first two verbs, one can argue that there is not an equivalent verbal
                        meaning in A.E. but, for the last two, the meaning can be paraphrased in
                        A.E. by the gerund.</p>
                    <p>Adverbial usage is also different. The B.E. use of "immediately" in sentence
                        initial position is not allowed in A.E. For example, B.E. "Immediately I get
                        home, I will attend to that." is incorrect in A.E. where we would say "As
                        soon as I get home, I will attend to that."</p>
                    <p>Other syntactic differences are formation of questions with the main verb
                        "have". In B.E., one can say, "Have you a pen?" where A.E. speakers must use
                        "do" ("Do you have a pen?"). Support verbs for nominalizations also differ.
                        Note the B.E. "take a decision" vs the A.E. "make a decision".</p>
                    <p>With these considerable differences and the fact that lexical items may be
                        over- or under-represented or not present at all, it is clear that a corpus
                        of American English is needed.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The proposed American National Corpus:</head>
                    <p>As seen above, the corpora we have been working with are inadequate and the
                        BNC although meeting our standards of size and balance does not deal with
                        our language. In 1998, at the first LREC conference a proposal was made to
                        create an American National Corpus (ANC) much on the lines of the BNC
                        (Fillmore et al, 1998 [1]).</p>
                    <p>The corpus should be as far as possible, contemporary (1990's). It should be
                        both static (like the BNC) and dynamic (COBUILD). We will add regular
                        increments but retain the capability to return to the initial corpus as well
                        as the static stages between increments.</p>
                    <p>The corpus will be both balanced and heterogeneous. The collection of more
                        than 100 million words will make this possible. 100 million words of the ANC
                        should be comparable in balance to the BNC to enable cross linguistic
                        studies between British and American English. There is no set definition for
                        what it means for a corpus to be balanced. The BNC made a principled effort
                        to balance their corpus (see the BNC User's Reference Guide [2] for a break
                        down of their corpus). The ANC will use this as a model. However, since it
                        is also desirable to provide significant components from a wide range of
                        styles, the remaining text will be varied rather than balanced (i.e. we will
                        not try for differing percentages of texts according to their representative
                        importance in the language but will try for smaller samples of a greater
                        variety of texts). The corpus will be annotated at two levels, which serve
                        two different user groups. Base Level will be annotated fully automatically
                        with document, paragraph, sentence, token with POS marking. Level 1 will be
                        heavily manual with the added text structure (titles, headers, footnotes,
                        tables, captions, lists, etc.) which follow the CES standard (Ide, et.al
                        [3]). </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Progress towards the creation of the ANC:</head>
                    <p>The ANC has progressed since its genesis at LREC 98. In May of 1999 the first
                        ANC meeting preceded the Dictionary Society of North America (DSNA) meeting
                        at the University of California at Berkeley. It was attended by a number of
                        representatives of publishing houses. The idea of an American National
                        Corpus was well received and plans for a second meeting were agreed upon. </p>
                    <p>The second meeting took place at New York University. Invitees to this
                        meeting included not only those present at the May meeting but publishers
                        from Japan and representatives from various software companies from the U.S.
                        and Europe. More substantial issues were discussed including the structure
                        of the consortium, questions of balance in the corpus, funding, time
                        schedules and licensing agreements. Some questions were decided, others such
                        as balance and licensing were referred to committees for further discussion.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The shape of the consortium and future plans:</head>
                    <p>The licensing and base level annotation is to be done through LDC (UPenn).
                        UPenn will obtain licenses from text providers and provide licenses to
                        users. With regard to data rights, there will be multiple classes. The
                        expectation is that there will be some subset of the data which can be made
                        available under a form of general public license, and hence can be freely
                        redistributed under this license.</p>
                    <p>The membership agreement provides for paid memberships from commercial
                        organizations. These members will receive the data as soon as it is
                        processed and have exclusive rights to this data for a period of three
                        years. They are expected to make monetary as well as data contributions. The
                        data will be freely available to non-profit educational and research
                        organizations (aside from a nominal fee for licensing and distribution). </p>
                    <p>Our plan is for the base level to be paid for with consortium fees. We have a
                        3-year time-frame starting Jan. 2000, with 10% of the corpus deliverable by
                        summer 2000. Level 1 annotation which will require external funding, will
                        proceed dependent on this funding. Therefore, this may lag as much as a year
                        behind the base level corpus. Our goal is a fully annotated level 1 corpus
                        compliant with the CES standard.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct n="1">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Fillmore</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">N.</forename>
                                    <surname>Ide</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <surname>Jurafsky</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Macleod</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">An American National Corpus: A Proposal</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">The Proceedings of LREC, Granada, Spain, May
                                28-30</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                                <biblScope>965-969</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book" n="2">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Burnard</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">British National Corpus: User's Reference Guide for the
                                British National Corpus</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>Oxford University Computing Service</publisher>
                                <date when="1995">May 1995</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">13-19</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="3">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">N.</forename>
                                    <surname>Ide</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Romary</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Bonhomme</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">CES/XML: An XML-based Standard for Linguistic
                                Corpora</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">Submitted to the Second International Language
                                Resources and Evaluation Conference.</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date>(submitted)</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book" n="4">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">W.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">N.</forename>
                                    <surname>Francis</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Kucera</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Manual of Information to Accompany 'A Standard Sample
                                of Present-Day Edited American English, for Use with Digital
                                Computers</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Providence, RI</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Department of Linguistics, Brown University</publisher>
                                <date when="1964">1964</date>
                                <date when="1979">(revised 1979)</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
