<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Back to the Cave of Shadows: Stylistic Fingerprints in
                    Authorship Attribution</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">Harald</forename>
                        <surname>Baayen</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Nijmegen</name>, The Netherlands <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Fiona</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Tweedie</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Glasgow</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Anneke</forename>
                        <surname>Neijt</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Nijmegen</name>, The Netherlands <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Hans</forename>
                        <surname>van Halteren</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Nijmegen</name>, The Netherlands <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Loes</forename>
                        <surname>Krebbers</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Max Planck Institute for Psycholinguistics</name>, The
                            Netherlands <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Stylistics</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>Attempts to assign authorship of texts have a long history. They have been
                        applied to influential texts such as the Bible, the works of Shakespeare and
                        the Federalist Papers. A wide variety of techniques from many disciplines
                        have been considered, from multivariate statistical analysis to neural
                        networks and machine learning. Many different facets of texts have been
                        analysed, from sentence and word length to the most common or the rarest
                        words, or linguistic features. Holmes (1998) provides a chronological review
                        of methods used in the pursuit of the authorial "fingerprint".</p>
                    <p>A key issue raised at the panel on non-traditional authorship attribution
                        studies at the ACH-ALLC conference in Virginia, 1999, by Joe Rudman is
                        whether authorial "fingerprints" do in fact exist. Is it truly the case that
                        any two authors can always be distinguished on the basis of their style, so
                        that stylometry can provide unique stylistic fingerprints for any author,
                        given sufficient data?</p>
                    <p>Despite the long history of authorship attribution, almost all stylometric
                        studies have been carried out on the assumption that stylometric
                        fingerprinting is possible. However, often control texts are inappropriately
                        chosen or not available. In addition, the imposition of editorial or
                        publisher's style can distort the original words of the author. To our
                        knowledge, no one has yet carried out a strictly controlled experiment of
                        authorship attribution, with texts of known authorship being analysed
                        between and within genres as well as between and within authors.</p>
                    <p>In this abstract we present such an experiment. The next section describes
                        the design of the experiment. This is followed by a description of the
                        analysis carried out, then by the results and our conclusions.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Experimental Design</head>
                    <p>The experiment was carried out in Dutch. Eight students of Dutch literature
                        at the University of Nijmegen participated in the study. All the students
                        were native speakers of Dutch, four were in their first year of study, and
                        four were in their fourth year. The students were asked to write texts of
                        around 1000 words.</p>
                    <p>Each student wrote in three genres: fiction, argument and description. Three
                        texts were written in each genre, on the following topics.<list
                            type="bulleted">
                            <item><emph rend="bold">Fiction:</emph> a retelling of the fairy tale of
                                Little Red Riding-Hood, a detective story about a murder in the
                                university, and a romance of chivalry.</item>
                            <item><emph rend="bold">Argument:</emph> defending a position about the
                                television program 'Big Brother', the unification of Europe, and
                                smoking.</item>
                            <item><emph rend="bold">Descriptive:</emph> football, the upcoming new
                                millennium, and a book-review of the book read most recently by the
                                participant.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>The order of writing the texts was randomised so that practice effects were
                        reduced as much as possible. We thus have nine texts from each participant,
                        making a total of seventy-two texts in the analysis. The main question is
                        whether it will be possible to group texts by their authors using the
                        state-of-the-art methods of stylometry. A positive answer would support the
                        hypothesis that stylistic fingerprints exist, even for authors with a very
                        similar background and training. A negative answer would argue against the
                        hypothesis that each author has her/his unique stylistic fingerprint.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Analysis</head>
                    <p>There are many methods proposed for the analysis of texts in the attempt to
                        identify authorship. In this abstract we describe three, and a fourth will
                        be described at the conference. The first is that proposed by Burrows in a
                        series of papers, see e.g. Burrows (1992), and used by many practitioners.
                        Here we consider the frequencies of the forty most common words in the text.
                        Principal components analysis is used to identify the most important aspects
                        of the data.</p>
                    <p>The second method considered is that of letter frequency. Work by Ledger and
                        Merriam indicates that the frequencies of letters used in texts may be
                        indicators of authorship. We use the standardised frequencies of the 26
                        letters of the alphabet, with capital and lower-case letters being treated
                        together. As above, the standardised frequencies are analysed using
                        principal components analysis.</p>
                    <p>Thirdly, we consider methods of vocabulary richness. Tweedie and Baayen
                        (1998) show that Orlov's Z and Yule's K represent two separate families of
                        measures, measuring richness and repeat rate respectively. Plots of Z and K
                        can be examined for structure.</p>
                    <p>Finally, we are planning to tag the text and to annotate the text for
                        constituent structure. Baayen et al. (1996) show that increased accuracy in
                        authorship attribution can be obtained by considering the syntactic, rather
                        than lexical vocabulary. The results from this part of the analysis will be
                        presented at the conference.</p>
                    <p>The texts written in this analysis are available from the authors upon
                        request and, once all annotation has been completed, will be made available
                        on the Web as well.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Results</head>
                    <p>Each student was asked to write around 1000 words in each text. In fact, the
                        average text length is 908 words. The shortest text has 628 words and the
                        longest 1342. The texts were processed using the UNIX utility awk and the R
                        statistics package.</p>
                    <p>We first consider all of the texts together. The Burrows analysis of the most
                        common function words shows no authorial structure. Genre appears to be the
                        most important factor, with fiction texts having negative scores on the
                        first principal component, while argumentative and descriptive texts have
                        positive scores on this axis. In addition, argumentative texts tend to have
                        higher values on the second principal component than descriptive texts. It
                        appears that fiction texts are more similar to other fiction texts than they
                        are to other texts by the same author. Analysis of letter frequencies gives
                        similar results, while the measures of vocabulary richness show some
                        indication of structure with respect to the education level of the writer.
                        Those in their first year of studies appear to have lower values of K, and
                        hence a lower repeat-rate. In addition, higher values of Z are the province
                        of first-year students also, indicating a greater richness of vocabulary.
                        When all of these measures are incorporated into a single principal
                        components analysis the genre structure becomes even clearer. Fiction texts
                        are found to the lower left of a plot of the first and second principal
                        component scores, while the other genres are found in the upper right of the
                        graph.</p>
                    <p>Given the structure evident in the principal components analysis, it seems
                        sensible to split the texts by genre and consider each separately. In each
                        case, within fiction, argumentative, and descriptive texts, again the
                        education level is the only factor to be apparent.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Conclusions</head>
                    <p>It is apparent from the results described above that in this study,
                        differences in genre override differences in education level and authorship.
                        The absence of any authorial structure in the analyses shows that it is not
                        the case that each author necessarily has her/his own stylometric
                        fingerprint. Texts can differ in style while originating from the same
                        author (Baayen et al., 1996; Tweedie and Baayen, 1998), and texts can have
                        very similar stylometric properties while being from different authors. Of
                        course, it is possible that larger numbers of texts from our participants
                        might have made it possible to discern authorial structure more clearly.
                        Similarly, it may also be that more fine-grained methods than we have used
                        will prove sensitive enough to consistently cluster texts by author even for
                        the small number of texts in our study. We offer, therefore, our texts to
                        the research community as a methodological challenge. Given what we have
                        seen thus far, we believe our results must alert practitioners of authorship
                        attribution to take extreme care when choosing control texts and drawing
                        conclusions from their analyses.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Baayen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">H.</forename>
                                    <surname>van Halteren</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">F.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Tweedie</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Outside the cave of Shadows. Using syntactic annotation
                                to enhance authorship attribution</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">11</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">121-131</biblScope>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">F.</forename>
                                    <surname>Burrows</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Not Unless You Ask Nicely: The Interpretative Nexus
                                between Analysis and Information</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Literary and Linguisitic Computing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">7</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">91-109</biblScope>
                                <date when="1992">1992</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">I.</forename>
                                    <surname>Holmes</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">The evolution of stylometry in humanities
                                scholarship</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">13</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">111-117</biblScope>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Ledger</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <surname>Merriam</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Shakespeare, Fletcher, and the Two Noble
                                Kinsmen</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">9</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">235-248</biblScope>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">F.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Tweedie</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Baayen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">How Variable May a Constant Be? Measures of Lexical
                                Richness in Perspective</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">32</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">5</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">323-352</biblScope>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
