<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Writing about It: Documentation and Humanities
                    Computing</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Julia</forename>
                        <surname>Flanders</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Brown University</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Text Encoding</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Documentation is arguably the most important part of a humanities computing
                    project's long-term existence, in two senses. First, in the sense that without
                    it a project cannot maintain continuity and consistency; and second, in the
                    sense that without it a project cannot communicate its methods to other members
                    of the larger community, offering them for critique if in need of improvement,
                    and making them known if worthy of emulation.</p>
                <p>Without documentation a project is effectively without "self-knowledge", by which
                    I mean the information which the project itself as an entity needs to know in
                    order to survive and to perpetuate itself. It is crucial to distinguish here
                    between the knowledge belonging to individual participants in the project's
                    work, and the project itself. What individuals know is not necessarily
                    accessible to other project members, and this knowledge is taken away with them
                    when they leave. What the project knows, on the other hand, is an explicit part
                    of its internal and public existence, with several important consequences. It
                    can be found without recourse to private knowledge; it does not depend on any
                    individual and is not vulnerable to changes in staff. And finally, this kind of
                    self-knowledge has a particular rhetorical status within the project and as a
                    public expression of identity, in that it has an understood authority: it is
                    explicitly endorsed by the project and its truth or applicability are not in
                    question.</p>
                <p>This is as much as to say that we need to take documentation seriously not only
                    as a practical matter but also as a question of theory. Producers of
                    documentation must negotiate between different rhetorical scenarios, from the
                    didactic, developmental narrative of a training manual to the encyclopedic
                    granularity of a reference guide. Treating this negotiation as a rhetorical
                    problem seems to locate it in the writing itself. But in fact we can see, once
                    we look more closely, that documentation is a specialized kind of data or
                    content to be purveyed, and that these different scenarios amount to different
                    approaches to data retrieval which must be accommodated. This complexity is
                    compounded by the fact that we are concerned here with humanities computing
                    documentation, to be used by humanists, with humanistic expectations about the
                    relationship between that which is documentable - reproducible, deterministic,
                    normative - and that which is subject to independent judgment and expertise.</p>
                <p>Finally, the challenges documentation poses - its peculiar embodiment of the
                    Arnoldian tension between "Hebraizing" and "Hellenizing", between doing and
                    thinking - also resonate with issues central to humanities computing.
                    Documentation both embodies a project's self-reflection and calls it to a close,
                    requires that reflection conclude in order that action may commence. And yet the
                    normative statements which documentation strives to offer about a project's
                    practice are inevitably, in a project of any scope, the occasion for discovering
                    further issues which have not yet been decided. The perpetually unfinished work
                    of documentation thus holds the project in a state of dynamic suspension, always
                    trying to resolve issues and get back to work, always trying to finish work so
                    that it can be documented.</p>
                <p>Some specific points are worth noting here, to be discussed at greater length in
                    the finished paper. First of all is the issue already mentioned of the
                    relationship between training documentation and reference documentation. The
                    most apparent difference between these two forms is the kind of text being
                    produced: in the first case, a developmental narrative which takes the trainee
                    through the project's methods from basic to advanced in a way which maximizes
                    memorability and comprehensibility; in the second case, a reference work which
                    provides instant access to particular topics discussed as independent items with
                    a high degree of granularity. These two modes are so different that it is often
                    extremely difficult to convert from one to the other, increasingly so in
                    proportion to how successfully the given mode has been realized. They also
                    require quite different kinds of infrastructure to make them useful in the work
                    environment: for instance, the reference model works best when accompanied by
                    good metadata and a good retrieval system. It also requires attention to the
                    level of granularity at which individual instructions are conceptualized, and to
                    how related instructions will be identified and aggregated.</p>
                <p>Producing documentation in either mode requires that one conceptualize the
                    consumer's needs and habits in detail, and this raises a second point which has
                    already been mentioned above. What role do humanists allot to documentation,
                    broadly considered? This question points to a larger issue for humanities
                    computing, namely the role of judgment and interpretation in the creation of
                    humanities data, and in what areas the exercise of these things is appropriate.
                    If the documentation is framed for a workplace in which comparatively unskilled
                    workers require explicit instructions on making absolutely consistent choices,
                    then the documentation itself needs to be equally determinate, authoritative,
                    and exhaustive in the way it communicates. It must anticipate every alternative
                    and leave no opening for variation; from the retrieval standpoint, it must
                    ensure that the correct information is always discovered no matter how inept or
                    tangential the search strategy. In short, it must make the work resemble as
                    little as possible the kind of intellectual environment envisioned by a liberal
                    humanities viewpoint. On the other hand, if the intention is to guide the worker
                    in exercising judgment - that is, to indicate the principles to be applied
                    rather than the act to be performed - then the documentation will necessarily
                    imagine its readers as part of an ongoing investigation into the project's
                    methods and standards.</p>
                <p>To give these reflections some concreteness, the finished paper will also
                    consider an actual documentation system currently in use in a major text
                    encoding project, which has evolved over a period of seven years and is used
                    both for training and reference. Although developed for a particular set of
                    needs and by no means perfect, this system and the process of its development
                    offer an example which may be of use to people currently designing or
                    redesigning documentation systems of their own.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
