<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The MATE Workbench - a Tool for XML Corpus
                    Annotation</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amy</forename>
                        <surname>Isard</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Edinburgh</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">David</forename>
                        <surname>McKelvie</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Edinburgh</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Andreas</forename>
                        <surname>Mengel</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Universitaet Stuttgart</name>, Germany <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Morten</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">Baun</forename>
                        <surname>Moeller</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Odense University</name>, Denmark <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>The MATE workbench is an annotation tool which allows transcription, annotation,
                display and querying of speech and text corpora. It is not tied to any particular
                annotation scheme, and allows users to define interfaces which suit their particular
                needs.</p>
            <p>The main difference between the MATE workbench and other annotation tools is its
                flexibility. Any annotation scheme which can be expressed in XML [7] can be used
                with the workbench (for a discussion of overlapping hierarchies see below), and the
                display and annotation interfaces are defined using a language based on the
                stylesheet language XSLT [8]. The workbench is written entirely in Java and is
                therefore platform independent.</p>
            <p>Annotation can be a very tedious task for humans, and many tools have been developed
                to make it easier. We conducted a review of some existing annotation tools before
                beginning development of the workbench [3], and many of them have in common a fixed
                user interface or a restriction to a particular coding scheme. One tool which has
                some similarities to MATE is GATE [1], which can also be used with any annotation
                scheme, but has a different internal architecture, based on the US Tipster
                architecture rather than XML, and a main aim of making it possible to integrate
                different automatic annotation components within one system. MATE aims to provide a
                framework where stylesheets can be used to provide user-defined annotation and
                display interfaces. Because the stylesheet language is quite high level, it is
                easier to write a stylesheet to provide a given interface than to write an entire
                coding tool from scratch.</p>
            <p>The MATE project has developed annotation schemes for five sets of linguistic
                phenomena, and examples of markup using these schemes will be distributed with the
                workbench, along with stylesheets for their annotation and display. Users of the
                workbench are by no means limited to these schemes, however.</p>
            <p>To display annotated data in the workbench, a user must have a MATE project file,
                which specifies one or more XML annotation or transcription files and sound files if
                appropriate, and a stylesheet which is to be applied to these files. Several
                examples of these will be provided with the workbench. When the workbench is
                started, a corpus folder window appears with a display of all the available project
                files. After selecting a project file, the user clicks on the "run" button, the
                specified files are processed, and one or more display or annotation windows
                appears, depending on what was specified in the stylesheet. A different stylesheet
                can be used with the same files to produce different behaviour.</p>
            <p>The other major use of the workbench is in performing queries over a corpus. A query
                language [4] was developed within the project which is tailored to our internal
                representation of the data, including the treatment of multiple hierarchies as
                defined below. To perform a query, the user first loads in one or more documents,
                then opens a Query Window, which provides support for building complex queries. The
                results of the queries are saved in XML format within the workbench, and are then
                also displayed using a stylesheet, allowing a flexible representation of the
                results.</p>
            <p>One question which often comes up when XML annotation schemes are being developed is
                multiple overlapping hierarchies of markup. The TEI [5] describes several possible
                ways to provide overlapping in SGML. One of these, 'concur', is not possible in XML,
                which was designed to be a less complicated and easier to use version of SGML, and
                therefore left out some features. We have chosen to take a different approach from
                any of these, but one which has been proven to be successful in at least one
                large-scale corpus annotation project [2]. Our solution is to keep each level of
                annotation, and each data-stream (in the case of multi-speaker conversations for
                instance) separate, and to link each level to a common base-level. This base level
                would normally be the smallest unit on which all the other annotations depend. This
                may often be the word level, but could also be phonemes in the case of speech,
                higher level units such as sentences or paragraphs or indeed anything else as
                appropriate. The MATE workbench will therefore deal appropriately with any data
                which are marked up in this way using hyperlinks, as defined in the XLINK proposal
                [6].</p>
            <p>Another advantage of the generality of the MATE workbench is that it makes it easier
                to combine views of annotation done using different schemes on the same corpus.
                These annotations may be done on different sites without any contact, but if both
                use hyperlinks to the same base level, then it is possible to create stylesheets
                which display both the annotations at the same time. It is also possible to write a
                stylesheet which will display one level and allow annotation of another level at the
                same time.</p>
            <p>The MATE workbench has just been completed, and testing and evaluation are about to
                begin. We will be able to provide a section on this evaluation for the final paper.
                We will be asking testers to use the workbench for a variety of different annotation
                tasks, and provide feedback on ease of use and power, and also evaluating whether
                the stylesheet language allows testers to define new annotation and display
                interfaces easily. We will also be submitting a proposal to ALLC/ACH 2000 for a demo
                of the workbench.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct n="[1]">
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">GATE</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr
                                target="http://www.dcs.shef.ac.uk/research/groups/nlp%2Fgate/"
                            />&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="[2]">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Isard</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                /><surname>McKelvie</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">H.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >S.</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Towards a Minimal Standard for Dialogue Transcripts: A
                                New SGML Architecture for the HCRC Map Task Corpus</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Proceedings of the 5th International Conference on
                                Spoken Language Processing, ICSLP98, Sydney</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="[3]">
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">MATE Deliverable D3.1: Specification of Coding
                                Workbench</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.cogsci.ed.ac.uk/~amyi/mate/report.html"
                            />&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="[4]">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Mengel</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first"
                                        >U.</forename><surname>Heid</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Enhancing Reusability of Speech Corpora by Hyperlinked
                                Query Output</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Eurospeech 99, Budapest, September 1999</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="[5]">
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Sperberg-McQueen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Lou</forename>
                                    <surname>Burnard</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">TEI Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding </title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>Lt;<ptr target="http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/TEI.html"/>&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="[6]">
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">XLINK</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink"/></note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="[7]">
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">XML</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml"/>&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="[8]">
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">XSLT</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt"/>&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
