<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Caught in the Decameron Web: New Tools for Scholars and
                    Teachers</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Michael</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Hemment</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Brown University</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Massimo</forename>
                        <surname>Riva</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Brown University</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Giovanna</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">Roz</forename>
                        <surname>Gastald</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Brown University</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Michael</forename>
                        <surname>Papio</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Holy Cross College</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Since 1995, Brown University's Decameron Web has endeavored to assist students
                    with the study of Giovanni Boccaccio's life and works. From its humble
                    beginnings as a series of hyperlinked student essays in a storyspace
                    environment, the site has been in a constant state of regeneration,
                    metamorphosing itself in new directions. Most recently, a National Endowment for
                    the Humanities grant from the Division of Education and Technology has enabled
                    our team to enrich the site with a variety of research and pedagogy tools for
                    students, literary scholars, historians, and teachers, including an SGML-encoded
                    text and correlated Detailed Search, a Pedagogy Module, and an electronic
                    Boccaccio journal.</p>
                <p>The text of the Decameron has been encoded in SGML using a DTD based on TEI-Lite.
                    The software, Dynaweb 4.1, is currently used to deliver the SGML encoded text.
                    The structural encoding embodied in SGML permits searching on selected
                    structural units, such as whole text, frame, and novella. All named characters
                    and geographic locations in the text are tagged and can be retrieved through an
                    advanced search procedure.</p>
                <p>The Decameron Web's new Detailed Search identifies and defines each character and
                    location (both named and unnamed) in Boccaccio's masterpiece using a series of
                    easily searchable encoded attributes. Characters are defined in terms of their
                    age, sex, origin, estate, role, religion, marital status, and disguise; places
                    are encoded to reflect their geographic location (city, region, country) and
                    type (bridge, castle, church, etc.).</p>
                <p>One of our greatest challenges has been to design an HTML interface that is
                    comprehensive in terms of search options, but also intuitive and user-friendly.
                    We settled on a design solution that divides the search into three principle
                    categories: "Characters," "Geographic Locations," and "Single and Multiple
                    Words." Within each of these categories, users may easily define their search by
                    either (1) typing in the name of the character or place they are looking for (if
                    they know it), (2) finding their subject by selecting a combination of
                    attributes from pull-down menus, or (3) viewing the results of our pre-searched
                    lists and tables. The results produced by these searches do more than merely
                    provide researchers with textual references: they bring the user to the exact
                    point in the online text where their character or geographic location appears.
                    Additionally, many characters (for example, all historical characters and
                    members of the brigata) have special philological notes that can be easily
                    accessed through hyperlinks.</p>
                <p>The Decameron Web's Detailed Search allows Boccaccio's text to be searched like
                    never before. Humanities students and scholars will be able to instantly examine
                    Boccaccio's characters based on their social status, sex, and profession, and a
                    series of other attributes. How, for example, do Boccaccio's medieval
                    representations of artists such as Giotto differ from contemporary "portraits of
                    the artist"? What is significant about Boccaccio's depiction of married vs.
                    unmarried women in the text? And is there any correlation between a character's
                    economic status and his/her fortuna?</p>
                <p>Scholars interested in exploring the vast geography of Boccaccio's world will
                    benefit greatly from the detailed geography search. This tool will enable
                    researchers to determine, for instance, what thematic or representational
                    differences exist between the novellas set in Italy and those set in other
                    countries; and what role geography plays in the structure and organization of
                    the Decameron. Having completed, together with STG (Scholarly Technology Group,
                    Brown University), the prototype of our Detailed Search page at the closure of
                    1999, its functionality and design will be rigorously tested and refined by
                    members of our Advisor Board and Brown students taking our Spring semester
                    Boccaccio course. A public release date is expected by early Summer 2000.</p>
                <p>Another recent addition to the Decameron Web has been the creation of a Pedagogy
                    Module, providing high school and university teachers with supplementary
                    classroom materials, including course syllabi, exams, class project ideas, and
                    essay questions. Comprehension exercises and sections dedicated to "Further
                    Research" and "Topics of Discussion" will be integrated with an eye to helping
                    disseminate ideas for successful teaching approaches. These will be contextually
                    linked to all other pertinent modules including Bibliography. There will also be
                    a teacher's forum, where innovative pedagogical approaches to Boccaccio's works
                    can be openly shared and discussed, and student guides to essay writing,
                    Internet research, and classroom presentation. Finally, each semester we will
                    accept nominations for "the best" Boccaccio student essay, which will
                    subsequently be published on the site.</p>
                <p>The Decameron Web's new electronic Boccaccio journal will be of particular
                    interest to medieval literature specialists and students. It will serve as a
                    forum where scholars can publish and debate their latest research on Boccaccio's
                    works, discuss humanities computing initiatives and pedagogy, submit book
                    reviews, and debut new translations of the author's works. The online journal
                    will be multilingual and will accept submissions from an international community
                    of scholars, all contributing their own unique didactic and interpretive
                    perspectives. Unlike traditional print publications, the electronic Boccaccio
                    journal will capitalize on its hypertext nature, facilitating greater editing
                    and publishing efficiently of contributions, allowing users to comment on what
                    they have read, and promoting joint scholarly projects on Boccaccio.</p>
                <p>If properly utilized, we believe that these new research tools can bring a new
                    dimension of excitement to the study and teaching of Boccaccio and his works.
                    The Detailed Search will enable researchers to gain new insights into the
                    complexities of Boccaccio's characters and geography; the Pedagogy Module will
                    provide teachers with a broad range of Boccaccio-related activities and
                    resources intended to challenge and engage their students; and the electronic
                    Boccaccio journal will allow graduate students and literary scholars to publish,
                    research, and discuss the latest advances in Boccaccio studies and humanities
                    computing. Naturally, the success of all of these initiatives is ultimately
                    contingent upon the active collaboration of an international community of
                    Boccaccio students, teachers, and specialists.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
