<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Developing and Teaching with Computer-based Courseware
                    in History: the History Courseware Consortium</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Ian</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Glasgow</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Summary</head>
                    <p>This demonstration illustrates one model developed in the UK for developing,
                        producing and disseminating web-based courseware to enhance the teaching and
                        learning experience of history students in higher education.</p>
                    <p>The demonstration covers the five key areas that the Consortium sought to
                        address in overcoming the under utilisation of computers in history
                        teaching: a pedagogical framework, quality, accessibility, flexibility and
                        support. Examples of the courseware's use in UK Higher Education history
                        teaching are also provided and the demonstration concludes with an
                        assessment of the strengths and weaknesses of the courseware.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Outline</head>
                    <p><emph rend="bold">Pedagogical Framework:</emph> Bridging the gap between
                        'traditional' and computer based methods of teaching meant that the History
                        Courseware Consortium required a conceptual framework that provided both a
                        familiar pedagogical context and incorporated the benefits of computer-based
                        teaching. The metaphor adopted by the Consortium to achieve this was the
                        'Enriched Lecture'.</p>
                    <p><emph rend="bold">Academic Quality:</emph> To ensure the courseware matched
                        accepted standards of academic scholarship the Consortium adopted a unique
                        commissioning system. Editorial panels were established and subject
                        specialists targeted. A key to this was the divorce of authorship from
                        technical production.</p>
                    <p><emph rend="bold">Accessibility:</emph> Another barrier to the widespread use
                        of computers was the technical skills required to operate software. One of
                        the key requirements for the Consortium was that the material should be
                        accessible. Writing the courseware in Hyper-Text Mark-up Language (HTML)
                        permitted the materials to be viewed through a web browser. This minimised
                        the amount of time spent learning 'computing' and maximises the amount of
                        time spent learning 'history'. The consortium format, involving over 80 UK
                        HE institutions, also proved a valuable format for creating a sense of
                        ownership, community and acceptability.</p>
                    <p><emph rend="bold">Flexibility:</emph> In part this was provided by the
                        technical features of HTML, but other aspects of the courseware design had
                        to maximise this feature to help overcome the 'not written here' syndrome.
                        An open-ended system, rich resources and multiple pathways were adopted as
                        key design features. A facility for customisation was also adopted so local
                        lecturers were able to add their own material, sources and evidence.</p>
                    <p><emph rend="bold">Support:</emph> To prevent the courseware 'withering on the
                        vine' on-line, paper-based and staffed support systems were adopted. A
                        particularly distinctive feature was a programme of on-going technical and
                        academic support and training channelled through a 'Users Club'.</p>
                    <p><emph rend="bold">Use in Teaching:</emph> There was a widespread and rapid
                        uptake in UK HE, but the courseware's use was not based on the 'Enriched
                        Lecture' metaphor. This was not unexpected but perhaps an 'Enriched
                        Tutorial' metaphor would have been more appropriate for dissemination.
                        Examples of the courseware's use in teaching, including customisation, are
                        provided from the Universities of Glasgow, Teeside and Sheffield.</p>
                    <p><emph rend="bold">Assessment:</emph> The model adopted by the Consortium was
                        largely successful in UK HE, but the practical limitations of customisation
                        and more recent technical advances must be acknowledged.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
