<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Experience and Expertise: The Humanities Advanced
                    Technology and Information Institute, University of Glasgow</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Ann</forename>
                        <surname>Gow</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Glasgow</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The mission of the Humanities Advanced Technology and Information Institute
                    (HATII) is to encourage actively the use of information technology and
                    information to improve research and teaching in the arts and the humanities.</p>
                <p>The Humanities Advanced Technology and Information Institute builds on over 15
                    years experience in humanities computing at the University of Glasgow. The
                    current expertise advances research and teaching practices through an expanding
                    academic programme in humanities computing at introductory, honours, and
                    postgraduate level. The undergraduate courses include <emph rend="italics"
                        >Introduction to Digitisation for Research and Preservation</emph> and <emph
                        rend="italics">Cultural and Heritage Computing</emph>. </p>
                <p>In addition to supporting collaborative research projects within the Faculty of
                    Arts of the University of Glasgow, the Humanities Advanced Technology and
                    Information Institute manages its own research programme in the area of
                    humanities and heritage computing. Examples of research projects include:<list
                        type="bulleted">
                        <item>Evaluation Strategy for the re-development of the displays and visitor
                            facilities at the Museum and Art Gallery, Kelvingrove</item>
                        <item>Funding Information &amp; Communications Technology in the Heritage
                            Sector</item>
                        <item>Digital Archaeology: Rescuing Neglected and Damaged Data
                            Resources</item>
                        <item>The Wiltshire Wills project</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>HATII also runs a range of conferences, summer schools, and short courses
                    including the very successful International Glasgow Digitisation Summer School. </p>
                <p>The six main areas of activity in HATII are:<list type="bulleted">
                        <item>it runs an academic programme in humanities computing at introductory,
                            honours, and postgraduate level;</item>
                        <item>it has responsibility for overseeing the development and management of
                            the departmentally based teaching laboratories and computer classrooms
                            for the Faculties of Divinity and Arts;</item>
                        <item>it supports and assists in the development and use of computing in
                            teaching within the two Faculties;</item>
                        <item>its technical team supplies a range of network services and desktop
                            support to Faculties of Divinity and Arts staff (~300), postgraduates
                            (~500), and undergraduates (~5000);</item>
                        <item>it acts to promote collaborative research projects within the two
                            Faculties; it manages a research programme;</item>
                        <item>it is organising and developing a range of conferences, summer
                            schools, and short courses.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>See &lt;<ptr target="http://www.hatii.arts.gla.ac.uk"/>&gt; for more information.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>

</TEI>
