<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">An Assistant Tool for Verse-making in Basque-based on
                    Two-Level Morphology</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Bertol</forename>
                        <surname>Arrieta</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of the Basque Country</name>, Spain <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Xavier</forename>
                        <surname>Arregi</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of the Basque Country</name>, Spain <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Iñaki</forename>
                        <surname>Alegria</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of the Basque Country</name>, Spain <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>In this paper we present a specialised word generator, which aims to be an
                        assistant tool for Basque troubadours. Such a tool allows verse-writers to
                        generate all the words that match with a given word termination. We coped
                        with some interesting aspects, i.e. the dimensions of the generated list and
                        the need to establish an order of relevance among the listed items.</p>
                    <p>This work can be seen as a way of re-using computational linguistic tools in
                        the context of the Basque cultural means of expression. The technical
                        foundations of this tool lie in a two-level morphological processor. The way
                        in which words must be generated (starting from the end of the word) leads
                        us to inverse the generation process.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>"Bertsolaritza": What Is It?</head>
                    <p>"Bertsolaritza" (the Basque term for verse-making) is an oral or written
                        literary form with old tradition and great popularity in the Basque Country.
                        Similar forms are manifested in other countries like Cuba.</p>
                    <p>While the written mode is similar to poetry, the oral mode has a peculiarity:
                        troubadours sing verses without previously knowing the theme. In other
                        words, a theme is given to the singers and in a few seconds they have to
                        think of a set of verses adjusted to the theme. These verses must hold to
                        the formal conditions (measurement and rhyme) of the discipline.</p>
                    <p>This verse-making task is quite difficult, so great expertise is required.
                        Because of that, some schools are devoted to teaching how to improvise this
                        type of verses. From our view, the tool we are presenting may be quite
                        useful in the verse-schools. For some decades, an oral verse-making
                        competition has been organised in the Basque Country every four years. The
                        high diffusion of this event (thousand of Basques follow this competition
                        with great interest, live or on TV) is a clear demonstration of the
                        importance of this discipline. From this background was formed the idea of
                        designing the tool here presented. We hope that such an application will be
                        a useful assistance-tool in the task of finding rhymes, namely for those
                        inexperienced troubadours.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Reversing Of The Morphological Description</head>
                    <p>To make this tool we have re-used a morphological analyzer/generator for
                        Basque developed few years before (Alegria et al., 96) and integrated
                        several tools such as spelling correctors and ICALL systems (Maritxalar et
                        al., 97). The morphological description is based on the Koskenniemi's
                        two-level morphology model (Koskenniemi, 83).</p>
                    <p>The two-level system is based on two main components:<list type="bulleted">
                            <item>A lexicon where the morphemes (lemmas and affixes) and the
                                possible links among them (morphotactics) are defined. The lexicon
                                is divided into different sublexicons and each lexicon entry
                                specifies its morphotactical information by means of a continuation
                                class which is a set of sublexicons. Combining sublexicons (nodes)
                                and continuation classes (arcs) the graph of morphotactics is
                                defined.</item>
                            <item>A set of rules which controls the mapping between the lexical
                                level and the surface level (changes at surface level when morphemes
                                are linked) due to the morphophonological transformations
                                (morphophonemics).</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>In order to get our inverted morphological analyser/generator for Basque we
                        needed to reverse this morphological description. The goal is to build an
                        inverted morphological generator for Basque, which will control the order of
                        the proposals according to their suitability for being a rhyme. The inverted
                        morphological generator will obtain all the possible forms corresponding to
                        a known ending, instead of generating the possible forms corresponding to
                        the beginning. We took into account two choices to reverse the morphological description.<list>
                            <item>1. The first one consists of manipulating the automata that is
                                created from the morphological description of the Basque. This
                                option initially looked good because we did not need to manipulate
                                the lexicon and the rules; we only manipulated the automata. But,
                                analysing this option in depth, we realised that our inverted
                                Deterministic Finite Automata (DFA) would actually become a
                                Non-Deterministic Finite Automata (NDFA) in an intermediate state of
                                the transformation process; and trying to re-convert the NDFA in a
                                DFA would cause a combining explosion.</item>
                            <item>2. The second option consists of manipulating and reversing the
                                lexicon and the rules directly, before using the compilers
                                (Karttunen and Beesley, 92)(Karttunen, 93). This approach,
                                therefore, involves the implementation of the programs that invert
                                the lexicon, the morphotactics and the phonological rules
                                automatically.</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>Considering the risks of the first choice, we decided to develop the second
                        method. This process was divided into three steps:<list>
                            <item>1. <emph rend="underscore">Reversing the lexicon:</emph> This task
                                deals with the inversion of all the morphemes. The order of the
                                characters inside the morphemes is inverted. For instance 'big'
                                would be converted to 'gib'.</item>
                            <item>2. <emph rend="underscore">Converting the continuation classes in
                                    "backward classes":</emph> The basis of the morphotactics in the
                                two-level model is the continuation classes (Koskenniemi, 83). We
                                have programmed a script to convert the continuation classes in
                                "backward classes", so that we have a group of morphemes that can go
                                before an inverted morpheme. This looks easy, but it has some
                                problems. Lexicons containing final classes have to be defined as
                                root lexicons, and consequently the backward class of the original
                                root lexicons must be null.<lb/><lb/><eg>For example: Let ADJECT be
                                    the continuation class in adjectives with two syllables or less.
                                    Suppose that this class has a unique lexicon containing the
                                    stems -er, and -est, and that the continuation class of these
                                    stems is null. Once the conversion has been made, -er and -est
                                    will be in the root lexicon and in their backward class will be
                                    included the adjectives with two syllables or less.</eg></item>
                            <item>3. <emph rend="underscore">Reversing the rules:</emph> The rules
                                are expressed as
                                    following:<lb/><lb/><eg>&lt;correspondence&gt;
                                    &lt;operator&gt; &lt;left context&gt; _
                                    &lt;right context&gt;</eg><lb/><lb/>To reverse the rules
                                only contexts have to be changed, interchanging between them and
                                reversing each one. The contexts are regular expressions and it is
                                necessary to distinguish between data (to be reversed) and regular
                                operators and reserved characters.<lb/><lb/><eg>For example, the
                                    rule y:i &lt;=&gt; _ +: s #:; will be converted to y:i
                                    &lt;=&gt; #: s +:_ ; </eg></item>
                        </list></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Application To "Bertsolaritza": Finding Words That Rhyme With An
                        Ending</head>
                    <p>Once the inverted analyser/generator for Basque was developed, we tried to
                        reuse it in an application that got the rhymes based on the final part of a
                        word. We needed to invert the character sequence given by the user and then
                        launch the generation with our inverted morphological generator tool. The
                        output of the generation process - that is, all the words that match with
                        the given ending - must be inverted before showing them to the user in a
                        Tcl-Tk made screen. In this way our tool returns all the Basque words that
                        have the same final sequence of characters as the sequence given by the
                        user. So, the application finds all the words that rhyme with the
                        word-ending given by the user.</p>
                    <p>In order to improve the usefulness of the application, we considered it
                        necessary to face the problem of the huge quantity of generated words that
                        match with the sequence given by the user. Two solutions were implemented: <list>
                            <item>1. Establishing a kind of categorisation or class-partition among
                                the morphemes, so that only one example (representative of the
                                class) is returned when all the elements of the class are suitable
                                to be shown. For instance, if the input is 'est', instead of
                                returning all the adjectives with the superlative form added (too
                                long!) <lb/>
                                <eg>big + est--> biggest 
                                    small + est --> smallest
                                    thin + est --> thinnest 
                                    ...</eg>
                                <lb/>the application will
                                return only one example and a short explanation:<lb/><eg>BIG+ est -->
                                    biggest (ADJECTIVE + est)</eg>
                            </item>
                            <item>2. Returning words sorted in the order that verse- makers
                                appreciate more. The quality of the rhyme is better if the word is
                                not composed or declined. In the example above it would be better to
                                use rhymes like 'guest' than words declined like 'smallest'.</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Conclusions And Future Improvements</head>
                    <p>Basque is a Pre-Indo-European language of unknown origin and quite different
                        from the surrounding European languages. The declension of the Basque
                        language has fourteen different forms for each singular, plural and
                        undefined form. All of these forms are added at the end of the words.
                        Besides, it is an agglutinative language which accepts morphemes being added
                        to other morphemes. These characteristics show us the relevance of the final
                        parts of the Basque words. That reason leads us to think that the inverted
                        morphological analyser/generator would be useful for different applications.
                        We have found an interesting use for such a generator in the world of the
                        "bertsolaritza". Given that final parts of words (rhymes) are very important
                        in verses, the inverted morphological analyser/generator can be an important
                        assistant tool for writing verses. Furthermore, an automatic method for
                        inverting the morphological description has been defined. Such a method can
                        be reused in any other language, always starting from a two-level
                        description.</p>
                    <p>We are considering as future works, (i) returning words with assonance rhyme;
                        (ii) dealing with semantics in the selection module in order to improve the
                        order of presentation, and (iii) publishing the application as a web page.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                    <p>We would like to thank Xerox for letting us use their tools, and specially to
                        Lauri Karttunen.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">I.</forename>
                                    <surname>Alegria</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">X.</forename>
                                    <surname>Artola</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>Sarasola</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Urkia</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Automatic Morphological Analysis of Basque</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">11</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">4</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">193-203</biblScope>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Karttunen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Beesley</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Two-Level Rule Compiler</title>
                            <title level="s">Xerox ISTL-NLTT-1992-2</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>Xerox</publisher>
                                <date when="1992">1992</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Karttunen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Finite-State Lexicon Compiler</title>
                            <title level="s">Xerox ISTL-NLTT-1993-04-02</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>Xerox</publisher>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Karttunen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Constructing Lexical Transducers</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Proc. of COLING«94</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">406-411</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">K.</forename>
                                    <surname>Koskenniemi</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Two-level Morphology: A general Computational Model for
                                Word-Form Recognition and Production</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <edition>Dissertation</edition>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>University of Helsinki, Dept of General
                                    Linguistics</publisher>
                                <date when="1983">1983</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>Publications No. 11</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Maritxalar </surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A></forename>
                                    <surname>Diaz de Ilarraza</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Oronoz</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">From Psycholinguistic Modelling of Interlingua to a
                                Computational Model</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Proc. Of CONLL97 Workshop (ACL Conference)</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Madrid</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name>
                                    <forename type="first"/>
                                    <forename type="middle"/>
                                    <surname>Lekuona</surname>
                                </name> et al</author>
                            <title level="a">Bertsolaritza</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Jakin</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Donostia</pubPlace>
                                <biblScope type="vol">14 eta. 15</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp"/>
                                <date when="1980">1980</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
