<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Modeling the Crystal Palace</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Chris</forename>
                        <surname>Jessee</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Virginia</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Michael</forename>
                        <surname>Levenson</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Virginia</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Will</forename>
                        <surname>Rouk</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Virginia</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Dave</forename>
                        <surname>Cosca</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Virginia</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>The Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities at the University of
                        Virginia is providing historians, architects and students new insights into
                        the history, construction and appearance of the Crystal Palace. These
                        insights are derived from the construction of 3-dimensional computer models
                        and simulations. This project is a small part of the larger "Monuments and
                        Dust". In "Monuments and Dust" an international group of scholars will
                        assemble a complex visual, textual, and statistical representation of
                        Victorian London - the largest city of the nineteenth-century world and its
                        first urban metropolis. A full description of "Monuments and Dust" can be
                        found online. See the "WEB-LINKS" section.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Background</head>
                    <p>Popularly known as the Crystal Palace, the 1851 London Exhibition Building
                        was designed by Joseph Paxton for the Royal Exhibition. On June 20th 1850
                        Paxton delivered his original design to the Industrial Exhibition's
                        executive committee. Only two weeks had passed since the building commission
                        had introduced a clause to allow Paxton to submit a design. Controversy
                        swirled around the exhibition as Col. Charles de L.Waldo Sibthorp's concern
                        over the destruction of elm trees prompted the Times to question the sanity
                        of constructing any permanent structure on the Hyde Park site. The
                        commissioners responded by requesting that Paxton alter his design to
                        include a barrel-vaulted transept that would cover and save the elms. The
                        Industrial Exhibition's opening day was less than a year away on May 1st
                        1851. The Crystal Palace design received popular approval in the press. All
                        other proposed designs for the exhibition building were monolithic masonry
                        and could not be completed in time for the scheduled opening. With no other
                        reasonable plan at hand the building commission accepted Paxton's design
                        with the provision the building be removed from Hyde Park by June 1st 1852.
                        As the foundations were being laid, Paxton's lack of architecture or
                        engineering credentials drew criticism regarding the stability and safety of
                        his design. The design is in essence an elaborately scaled copy of the Duke
                        of Devonshire's Chatsworth Conservatory. Paxton designed the conservatory
                        while employed as the Duke's gardener. In response to the criticism all iron
                        girders were tested on site prior to installation. Wooden cross-bracing was
                        added to visually reassure visitors the wrought iron trusses were sturdy and
                        could withstand the load of the thousands of anticipated visitors. Paxton's
                        reliance on his previous glass-enclosed conservatory design influenced the
                        details of all the Crystal Palace's building systems. The primary role of
                        the building was as exhibit space. The design is composed of a central
                        transept and nave with the nave lined with a series of 24x24 foot structural
                        bays. Second level galleries ring the bays below. The structural bays served
                        to organize the 13,973 exhibitors. Red banners with white letters indicating
                        specific exhibits hung from the 24-foot girders facing the nave. The nave,
                        galleries and transept served as circulation corridors for the exhibition's
                        more than 6 million visitors. The large expanse of overhead glass that
                        serves as the enclosure and lighting systems and gives the building its
                        nickname allowed excessive amounts of light and heat into the exhibit
                        spaces. While this arrangement served Paxton well in the Chatsworth
                        greenhouse, the crowded exhibit spaces quickly overheated. The decision to
                        use extensive amounts of glass without regard to the comfort of the
                        occupants is the primary failure of the design. To remedy this flaw the
                        troughs of the roof system were retrofitted with canvas covers draped
                        between the roof ridges. These tarps shaded the glass and visitors, reduced
                        solar gain and provided a more diffuse and tolerable light in the galleries.
                        The tarps had a seam down the middle to allow rapid water drainage into the
                        Paxton gutters. The secondary role of the building was as exhibit. Initially
                        there was much skepticism, doubt and criticism surrounding the design of the
                        Crystal Palace and the Great Exhibition. But as the building rapidly grew
                        above the trees of Hyde Park the press and public rallied around the
                        glistening structure. The public began to realize and take great pride that
                        the building was revolutionary in every way. The building handily satisfied
                        its most demanding design criteria. It was large enough to accommodate tens
                        of thousands of exhibitors and visitors. It fostered the orderly display of
                        exhibits. It could be manufactured and assembled in a timely manner. It
                        clearly demonstrated the nation's industrial and manufacturing competence.
                        The Crystal Palace was a departure from the past and a vision of the future.
                        The Crystal Palace was designed, manufactured and assembled in less than one
                        year. This feat was made possible by manufacturing technology that should
                        still be considered state of the art. The building is an integrated system
                        or kit of parts, where each part serves multiple functions. The columns
                        support the girders and act as downspouts for the gutters. The Paxton
                        gutters shed rain-water and support the roof gables. The glass roof panels
                        are both building enclosure and lighting system. Each part is machine
                        manufactured by skilled labor under controlled conditions that insure
                        accuracy and high quality. Once a machine or technique is devised to make a
                        specific part, the part can be made very quickly and in large quantity.
                        Parts were delivered to the site and erected as quickly as they were
                        manufactured. The small size and light weight of each part made erection
                        easy. Each structural bay is self-supporting so the 2,000 unskilled workers
                        could assemble parts without waiting for whole systems to be in place. In
                        contrast, other buildings of the time were made of stone and required years
                        to construct. The stone was cut from quarries and transported at great
                        expense to the building site, where skilled masons custom fit one block to
                        another. It is important to study this building in context, as it is
                        evidence of a fundamental cultural shift. As compared to the artifacts in
                        the exhibition the Crystal Palace building has a clean sparse appearance
                        with a minimum of ornament. With the exception of girder connection covers
                        there are few components that could be considered ornamental. The real
                        difference lies in the method of manufacture and the value placed on the
                        resulting product by society. Once Londoners saw the efficiency and grace of
                        its construction the Crystal Palace became a focus of pride. The design
                        marks a cultural shift in values from garish hand made ornament of the past
                        to the clean, streamlined machine-made products of the future. The Crystal
                        Palace is more closely related to buildings of the next century, such as
                        Ludwig Mies van der Rohe's 1929 Barcelona Pavilion and Phillip Johnson's
                        1949 Glass House, than with its monolithic, masonry contemporaries.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Methods</head>
                    <p>Three different types of 3-dimensional computer models are being created for
                        the project. Working from original drawings, a high detail model of each
                        unique building component is constructed in FormZ software. The components
                        are assembled to illustrate the relationship of parts within larger sections
                        of the building. Rendered images of these assemblies and the computer model
                        itself is delivered through the Internet. Rendered orthographic views of the
                        component assemblies are used as texture or image maps on a low detail VRML
                        (virtual reality modeling language) model of the entire building. The VRML
                        model can be viewed through a web browser. Given the state-of-the-art of
                        photography in 1851 and the limits it imposes on our ability to understand
                        and appreciate the lighting in the Crystal Palace our third model is a
                        realistic lighting simulation. Radiance software, running on Supercomputers,
                        enables us to render images and animations of the building's lighting as it
                        existed in 1851. Test images have been rendered on a SGI Power Onyx at the
                        San Diego Supercomputer Center (SDSC) and on SUN workstations at IATH.
                        Additional images and animations will be rendered on a 64-Processor SUN HPC
                        10000 Supercomputer at SDSC.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Use</head>
                    <p>Architects, historians and students can gain a better understanding of the
                        building and its significance by studying the images and models we have
                        created. By freely providing the computer models, variations of the
                        building's structure, lighting and design can be tested and used as a tool
                        for teaching. Exploring the use of realistic lighting simulations (both
                        quantitative and qualitative) on Supercomputers provides not only a new set
                        of tools and methods for the humanities researcher but paves the road for
                        interaction and collaboration with computer scientists.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Web-Links</head>
                    <p>"Modeling the Crystal Palace" &lt;<ptr
                            target="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/london/model/"/>&gt;</p>
                    <p>"Monuments and Dust" &gt;<ptr target="http://www.iath.virginia.edu%2Flondon/"
                        />&gt;</p>
                    <p>The Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities &lt;<ptr
                            target="http://www.iath.virginia.edu/"/>&gt;</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
