<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Teaching Cybertext Writing, Design, and Editing:
                    Language, Image, Linking, Thinking</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Chris</forename>
                        <surname>Funkhouser</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">New Jersey Institute of Technology</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>The Electronic Classroom</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Ira Shor, in <title level="m">Critical Teaching and Everyday Life</title>,
                    proposes a student-centered pedagogy which theorizes that everyone immersed in
                    mass culture is "habituated to a dizzying pace of life." (63) Describing the
                    factors today's teachers face, Shor writes about the "addicting standard of
                    stimulation" set by radio, television and other illuminated media, certifiying
                    that a "hyped use of words in pictures fits into the whole accelerated gestalt
                    of daily life." (63-64)</p>
                <p>Accepting this as contemporary circumstance, methods must be constructed and made
                    readily available to help teachers bridge the gap between past and present in
                    terms of technology and the humanities classroom. Digital technology is changing
                    the whole nature of education in our society. This means that professors and
                    students from all disciplines need to be prepared to read and transmit their
                    work in new ways via the computer.</p>
                <p>My essay will outline, then describe in detail, successful methodology
                    established in teaching "Electronic Publishing" classes to graduate and
                    undergraduate students with interests across multiple disciplines at New Jersey
                    Institute of Technology. The primary objective of "Electronic Publishing" is to
                    enhance a previously untrained student's ability to use computers effectively
                    and intelligently to create and design texts in academic, commercial, or other
                    settings. Projects in this course of study intend to build understanding and
                    functional skills in the visual presentation and online structuring of
                    information. Students learn how to create interactive online documents that
                    incorporate language with visual aspects of computerized text by combining
                    graphics, sound, animation, text, and video into compelling content. The
                    approach to teaching cybertext writing and design I have developed at New Jersey
                    Institute of Technology since 1997 is effective for students presenting research
                    in every area of the humanities, including languages and literature, history,
                    philosophy, music, art, film studies, linguistics, anthropology, archaeology,
                    creative writing, and cultural studies.</p>
                <p>As a pedagogue, I formulate this discipline as an investigative, processual
                    endeavor that demands the understanding and application of two human principles
                    in conjunction with four essential aspects of design. To learn and succeed as
                    online producers of text, students must first embrace and attempt to embody the
                    concepts of patience and organization; the fundamental areas of attention in
                    creating hypertext documents are introduced as: language, image, linking, and
                    thinking. Every technical and aesthetic aspect, or problem, of document
                    construction may be addressed through a series of questions, and a checklist of
                    formal considerations associated with these principles and areas of attention.</p>
                <p>All of the dimensions or elements within the principles and aspects of design
                    highlighted above will be fully addressed and explained in the paper. Among the
                    multiple subjects that arise in this discussion of how to teach students to
                    produce cybertext are: gathering and formatting content, conducting research on
                    the Internet, presenting effective visual communication, strategizing and
                    solving technical problems, interlinking and layering documents, and otherwise
                    establishing objectives and sensible schemes for online documents. In
                    "Electronic Publishing," students are eventually introduced to a completely
                    different language: the relentlessly precise language of computer programming,
                    HTML, which intervenes with content and re-creates sense and vision within
                    cybertext writing and editing. Code is language that handles the work of online
                    producers: writing, image, and sound; sometimes it is relatively easy to
                    understand and use, at others it may also be fearfully complicated. Methods of
                    conceptualizing (for students) what HTML is, and how to make use of it in
                    humanities projects, will be outlined in this presentation.</p>
                <p>This essay will, in addition to covering materials listed above, offer a detailed
                    account of the various components of the "Electronic Publishing" courses which
                    consists of a month of unique design-oriented research followed by two months of
                    "hands-on" work. Students in the course not only study electronic publishing,
                    they do electronic publishing by editing two editions of a journal based on
                    their personal academic or creative pursuits. An electronic portfolio of a
                    student's work in every class they are enrolled in must also be completed as
                    part of "Electronic Publishing."</p>
                <p>The program of "Electronic Publishing" designs a technology plan for other
                    Humanities-oriented departments interested in developing curricula around
                    electronic publishing initiatives, Internet communication, and hardware/software
                    management schematics. Methods of reading and presenting work using
                    technologically sophisticated computers and networks are made clear by my
                    process; students are quickly able to exhibit and exercise their learning in
                    these courses. At the conclusion of my paper, I will present guidelines
                    formulated for the assessment of student generated work.</p>
                <p>For current "Electronic Publishing" course materials on the World Wide Web, see:
                        &lt;<ptr target="http://www-ec.njit.edu/~cfunk/353"/>&gt;,
                        &lt;<ptr target="http://www-ec.njit.edu/~cfunk/605"/>&gt;</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
