<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="panel">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Electronic Resources for Historical Linguists. Part 2:
                    Dictionaries and Related Resources</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Glasgow</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Irené</forename>
                        <surname>Wotherspoon </surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Glasgow</name>, UK<email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Susan</forename>
                        <surname>Rennie</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Scottish National Dictionary Association</name>, UK
                            <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Anne</forename>
                        <surname>McDermott</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Birmingham</name>, UK<email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Computational/Corpus Linguistics</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <p rend="presenter">Chair: Christian Kay</p>
                    <p>The set of papers will be followed by a discussion, which may include points
                        from Part 1: Medieval Studies (session 1.2 on Saturday 22 July).</p>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>Developing a User Interface for the <title level="m">Historical
                                Thesaurus of English</title> Ingres Database</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">Irené Wotherspoon </p>
                        <div>
                            <p>This is effectively a continuation of a paper published in <title
                                    level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> Vol 7, 1992,
                                which described the issues and processes involved in transferring
                                the legacy database of the <title level="m">Historical Thesaurus of
                                    English</title> (HTE) in dBase 11.4 into Ingres 6.1, chosen as
                                being able to support the retrieval of complex information. During a
                                long-term project like HTE, spanning decades rather than years,
                                there will obviously be a huge change in the software available, and
                                software in use will become obsolete. It is therefore vital to
                                transfer the database into new options where feasible. The paper
                                describes the problems encountered in developing a front-end for the
                                Ingres database, now in OpenIngres O.I.2.0, which would cope with
                                the multiple conditions of the queries required in what is
                                essentially a research tool, but which would also be acceptably
                                user-friendly. The user interface now in use is BI/query, the
                                successor to GQL, and this will be described and demonstrated. The
                                complexities of retrieval from the HTE arise from the data concerned
                                with the currency of the words, taken from the <title level="m"
                                    >Oxford English Dictionary</title>. This consists of a) actual
                                starting and finishing dates for periods of currency; b) the
                                qualifiers ante and circa, as in the OED. (These are not used in the
                                OED CD queries, but are necessary for retrieving e.g. words current
                                before a specified date); c) indicators for continuous or
                                discontinuous currency; d) indicator of present currency, e) Old
                                English, covering all dates before 1150; f) style and status labels
                                from the OED attached to periods of currency - a word may be
                                labelled e.g. 'vulgar' for only part of its currency.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>The Electronic Scottish National Dictionary: Work in Progress</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">Susan Rennie</p>
                        <div>
                            <p>The Scottish National Dictionary (SND) is the standard historical
                                dictionary of modern Scots, covering the period from 1700 to the
                                present. This presentation will describe the current project to
                                digitise the SND to produce the eSND, which will eventually be
                                output on the Internet. It will include a brief description of the
                                SND itself, outlining its history, content and structure, and
                                describe how the eSND will differ from the printed text, in
                                particular by integrating the original Supplement and adding new
                                material from the SNDA's ongoing research. The various stages of the
                                eSND project will then be discussed, using examples from the work in
                                progress: <list>
                                    <item>1. the data capture, which is being done through scanning
                                        and OCR of the printed text;</item>
                                    <item>2. the conversion of the OCR data to full XML mark-up,
                                        including details of the actual mark-up scheme (which is
                                        based on the TEI guidelines), and how this has been adapted
                                        to suit the SND text;</item>
                                    <item>3. the integration of the original Supplement and new
                                        material;</item>
                                    <item>4. the development of search tools and a web
                                        interface.</item>
                                </list></p>
                            <p>Details will also be given of the new proposal to combine the eSND
                                with an electronic version of the Dictionary of the Older Scottish
                                Tongue (eDOST), sharing the same mark-up scheme, search software and
                                interface, to produce a comprehensive electronic resource covering
                                Scots from the early medieval period to the present day.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>Early Dictionaries of English and Historical Corpora</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">Anne McDermott</p>
                        <div>
                            <p>This paper discusses the implications for historical corpora of an
                                examination of some early dictionaries of English. Comparison is
                                made between Samuel Johnson's <title level="m">Dictionary of the
                                    English Language</title> (1755) and works such as Thomas
                                Blount's <title level="m">Glossographia</title> (1656), Nathan
                                Bailey's <title level="m">Dictionarium Britannicum</title> (1730),
                                and Robert Ainsworth's influential <title level="m">Linguae Latinae
                                    Compendiarius</title> (1736). The claim that early
                                English-English dictionaries contained many "hard words", i.e.
                                words, often from classical sources, which had infrequent or nil
                                occurrence in the language at the time, is examined by checking the
                                occurrence of such words in historical corpora. This leads to an
                                examination of the corpora themselves and comparison with corpora of
                                modern English. Suggestions are made about how historical corpora
                                might be developed in future, for example by offering
                                domain-specific search facilities. Reference will be made to <title
                                    level="m">A dictionary of the English language on
                                CD-ROM</title>: the first and fourth editions, Samuel Johnson,
                                edited by Anne McDermott (Cambridge : CUP in association with the
                                University of Birmingham, 1996)</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
