<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Collaborative Campus: Rhetoric, Technology and
                    Classroom Re-Composition</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Lissa</forename>
                        <surname>Holloway-Attaway </surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Georgia Institute of Technology</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Patricia</forename>
                        <surname>Worrall</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Gainesville College</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Angela</forename>
                        <surname>Mitchell</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Georgia</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Laura</forename>
                        <surname>Andrews</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Georgia</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christy</forename>
                        <surname>Desmet</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Georgia</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>VanHoosier-Carey</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Georgia Institute of Technology</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Our group proposes to demonstrate the technologies, methodologies, and assessment
                    criteria used to develop a University System of Georgia grant-funded,
                    multi-campus distance education project. The project, initiated in September
                    1999, links faculty and students on three campuses in a collaborative first year
                    writing course through the use of synchronous and asynchronous Internet-based
                    applications. The three schools participating in the project are uniquely
                    diverse in student population and institutional and disciplinary objectives:
                    Gainesville College (a two-year liberal arts school), the University of Georgia
                    (a four-year liberal arts research university), and Georgia Institute of
                    Technology (a four-year technical/engineering institute). The virtual learning
                    community created with the technologies enables students to conduct group
                    discussions, complete critical reading and writing assignments, and design
                    hypertext research projects. The students' practical experience using these
                    collaborative writing tools is reinforced by the course content: a cultural
                    analysis of scientific and technological rhetorical representations. Using
                    fiction, non-fiction, film, and new media, students explore how cultural
                    perceptions of identity and community are transformed by innovative theories of
                    "progress." In our presentation, we will 1) discuss the project's disciplinary
                    and pedagogical objectives, 2) demonstrate the synchronous and asynchronous
                    collaborative environments used to facilitate group discussion, conduct
                    research, and implement hypertext documents, 3) discuss the methods used to
                    promote the desired collaboration via these tools, and 4) present the
                    preliminary results from our assessment of the course.</p>
                <p>Collaborative Campus was motivated by our interest in exploring more efficient
                    and pedagogically effective technologies for hybrid conventional/distance
                    learning education, specifically for technology-infused writing courses.
                    Developed in Fall Semester 1999 and delivered and assessed in Spring and Summer
                    2000, the project is one that promises to extend recent developments in
                    technology and humanities research. Currently, a significant amount of the
                    university interest in educational technology is being directed towards distance
                    education initiatives. This is a mixed blessing for many of us in the computers
                    and writing community. On the one hand, it can mean increased funding for
                    equipment and for teaching initiatives focused on integrating computing
                    technology into current curricula. On the other hand, it often requires
                    vigilance in resisting the delivery-oriented, technology-based format that has
                    become commonplace in many distance education courses. Although many humanities
                    instructors have experience teaching with technology that promotes
                    collaboration, the reality is that much of the current technology is either not
                    technically suited or not sufficiently robust to facilitate distance education
                    writing courses. Furthermore, the relationship between learning and pedagogy in
                    local computer lab classrooms vs. delivery in virtual environments has been
                    insufficiently explored. At present programs, such as Daedalus, are not
                    internet-capable, and text-based environments, such as MOOs, are not conducive
                    to modes of collaboration beyond informal conversation. In order to conduct
                    truly collaborative computer-intensive writing courses in campus labs and in
                    virtual classrooms, we need both tools and methods suited to this more dispersed
                    teaching arrangement.</p>
                <p>Georgia Institute of Technology's School of Literature, Communication, and
                    Culture (LCC) has been committed to researching and developing technologies that
                    will promote collaboration and increase rhetorical skills in both local and
                    distance learning environments. From 1996-1999, the Pilot Writing Program in
                    Electronic Environments enabled faculty and students to explore in increasing
                    depth the use of Internet technologies in the humanities. Faculty working in
                    LCC, including those in the New Media Center for Education and Research and in
                    the Information Design and Technology graduate program, worked in the Pilot
                    Program to develop strategies that combined pedagogical interests with
                    technological development. Using the Pilot Program as a model and extending it
                    to include a larger institutional community, the Collaborative Campus project
                    continues to refine the use and design of educational technologies in computer
                    lab and distance learning settings. Although Gainesville College and the
                    University of Georgia had clearly established technologies in the writing
                    classroom as a priority and had technical/pedagogical support services in place
                    for faculty, our project allows for the continuing development of effective
                    tools and teaching methods for computer-intensive education. The project
                    faculty, teaching a diverse student population on each of the University System
                    of Georgia campuses, is positioned to provide a broad spectrum of experience
                    about the effectiveness of educational technologies in humanities courses and to
                    advise others interested in developing interdisciplinary technology-infused
                    curricula.</p>
                <p>The collaborative writing technologies utilized by project participants (140
                    students and 7 faculty) support a variety of rhetorical and pedagogical
                    purposes, while challenging the students to adapt their communication styles to
                    the distinct capabilities of each. TechLINC, our custom-designed synchronous
                    application, is a virtual campus with classrooms, design studios, and "outdoor"
                    meeting spaces that adapts the Palace software, a popular Internet graphical
                    chat environment, to the educational needs of our project. Like much of the
                    traditional collaboration software used in writing courses, TechLINC allows
                    students to conduct and log synchronous discussions; however, whereas most other
                    programs work only on local-area networks, TechLINC is accessible from any
                    computer on the Internet. Thus it facilitates the multi-campus collaboration
                    necessary among project participants. More importantly, TechLINC radically
                    changes the nature of distance collaboration by augmenting text-based
                    discussions with visual and audio resources. TechLINC's ability to interface
                    with web browsers and multimedia Internet applications allows students
                    simultaneously to access web pages or to hear and see streaming audio and video
                    as they conduct their discussions. These capabilities, in turn, make it possible
                    for students, in real-time and at a distance, to do joint Internet research,
                    collaboratively develop web pages, or listen and discuss a recorded news program
                    or interview. They also provide a means for distance collaboration between
                    instructors and students. Instructors teaching with TechLINC each have a virtual
                    office in which they can meet with students to review assignments. Because of
                    TechLINC's ability to interface with web browsers, instructors and students can
                    also jointly examine and discuss assignments uploaded to the Web, or to Web
                    Crossing, our asynchronous application. Web Crossing allows students to respond
                    in threaded discussions to study questions, post drafts for collaborative
                    peer-review, and link to Internet sites that document their research or preview
                    their own hypertext projects. Because Web Crossing is accessible through a Web
                    Browser, requiring no specialized software, it provides a very cost-efficient
                    means for providing students with collaborative writing and research
                    opportunities. As a counter-point to the more informal discussions generated in
                    TechLINC, Web Crossing archives the real-time discussions of the chat
                    application and provides a more structured electronic environment to post
                    extended responses to critical reading, writing, and design-related issues.</p>
                <p>Successfully integrating technology and teaching is a primary objective for the
                    project participants, and the course content, along with the writing, on-line
                    research, and hypertext design assignments were developed in conjunction with
                    evaluative criteria to measure student learning using different pedagogic modes
                    suited to each technology. Assessment methodologies, including pre- and
                    post-course surveys, focus groups, and independent writing evaluations by
                    non-participating teaching faculty will critique a number of areas relevant to
                    collaborative computing technologies and rhetorical studies: synchronous vs.
                    asynchronous communication styles, the rhetorical capabilities of hypertext vs.
                    conventional essay writing, and student attitudes about technology as a writing
                    and research tool. In general, the project is designed to foster among students
                    a more rigorous imperative for discovering how electronic writing is used to
                    communicate disciplinary content, while providing faculty with precise data to
                    measure student success in diverse electronic environments.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
