<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="panel">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Electronic Resources for Historical Linguists. Part 1:
                    Medieval Studies</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Glasgow</name>
                            <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jeremy</forename>
                        <surname>Smith</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Glasgow</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Simon</forename>
                        <surname>Horobin</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Glasgow</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Laing</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Edinburgh</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Keith</forename>
                        <surname>Williamson</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Edinburgh</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Computational/Corpus Linguistics</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <p rend="presenter">Chair: Christian Kay</p>
                    <p>This session and session 8.1 on Monday 24 July will introduce a range of
                        resources of particular interest to historical linguists and to those
                        concerned with the development of text corpora and databases. Each of
                        today's papers will be followed by discussion, but major issues may also be
                        raised at the group discussion on Monday.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>The Middle English Grammar Project</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">Jeremy Smith</p>
                        <p rend="presenter">Simon Horobin</p>
                        <div>
                            <p>The study of linguistic variation in Middle English has undergone a
                                revolution in recent years, with the publication of the "Linguistic
                                Atlas of Late Mediaeval English" (McIntosh, Samuels and Benskin
                                1986) and other important surveys. However, no thorough-going
                                attempt has as yet been made to harness this new information to a
                                wider programme of linguistic description which is oriented from
                                both structural and variationist perspectives. The Middle English
                                Grammar Project, a British-Academy funded venture now underway at
                                the University of Glasgow and at Stavanger College, Norway, is
                                designed to address this gap, with the production of surveys
                                covering the whole field of ME linguistic studies: spelling,
                                phonology, grammar and lexicology. The Project is currently focused
                                in the UK within the Institute for the Historical Study of Language,
                                a research-centre within Glasgow's Faculty of Arts. The first
                                research area being addressed by the Project is the creation of a
                                new history of ME spelling and phonology. In order to carry out this
                                analysis a corpus of machine-readable texts is currently being
                                assembled. These texts are subsequently classified according to both
                                Present-Day and etymological reflexes and the results of this
                                process are entered in a database. This database includes a variety
                                of extralinguistic information in addition to the classified
                                spelling data, such as genre and script, which allows the corpus to
                                be interrogated according to a number of different factors. This
                                presentation will demonstrate this database and discuss its uses for
                                the study of linguistic variation in Middle English, and historical
                                linguistics more generally.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>Two Historical Linguistic Atlases</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">Margaret Laing</p>
                        <p rend="presenter">Keith Williamson</p>
                        <div>
                            <p>The principal aim of the "Linguistic Atlas of Early Middle English"
                                (LAEME ) and the "Linguistic Atlas of Older Scots" (LAOS) is to
                                produce historical linguistic atlases complementary to "A Linguistic
                                Atlas of Late Mediaeval English" (LALME)<note n="1">McIntosh, Angus,
                                    Samuels, M.L. and Benskin, Michael (1986). <title level="m">A
                                        Linguistic Atlas of Late Mediaeval English</title>, 4 vols.
                                    AUP, Aberdeen.</note>. Computer-based data-processing and
                                analysis have been employed in the projects from their inception in
                                1987 . Their methodology differs radically from that used in LALME.
                                Instead of recording data by a questionnaire of prescribed items,
                                entire texts are diplomatically transcribed and keyed onto disk,
                                where they can be analysed linguistically using programs written
                                in-house. Each word or morpheme in a text is tagged according to its
                                lexical meaning and grammatical function, and each newly tagged text
                                is added to the corpus. The tagging creates a taxonomy of the
                                linguistic material in the texts and permits systematic comparison
                                of their dialects. Information on particular items (defined by one
                                or more tags) may be abstracted from the corpus to identify spatial
                                and/or temporal distributions of the forms associated with the item.
                                The programs generate dictionaries, concordances, chronological
                                charts and input files to mapping software. Maps are produced to
                                show distribution of features or full text forms. This method of
                                analysis has considerable advantages over the questionnaire. Items
                                for study can be selected from a complete inventory of linguistic
                                forms rather than from some predetermined sample. Tagged texts are
                                immediately and constantly available to be processed and compared in
                                whatever ways are desired. While not all the material in the corpus
                                will be useful for dialectal analysis, it remains available for a
                                wide range of future studies: historical phonology, morphology,
                                syntax or semantics. We will demonstrate our method of
                                lexico-grammatical tagging and illustrate how it may be exploited
                                not only for linguistic geography, but also for phonological and for
                                syntactic investigations.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
