<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">New Tools for Learners</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Larry</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
                        <surname>Stewart</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">The College of Wooster</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Peter</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
                        <surname>Havholm</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">The College of Wooster</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>In a recent essay in <title level="j">Salon</title>, Christopher Ott argues that
                    much of educational technology is used in the service of a model of education as
                    "a passive transfer of information ...." As Ott says, "Web sites and CD-ROMs are
                    very good at delivering information, but not so good at teaching what it means
                    or raising difficult questions about it." During the last ten to twelve years,
                    we have assembled a portfolio of technological tools which we believe lead
                    students in the undergraduate classroom to ask those difficult questions and to
                    become active learners rather than passive recipients. We have developed two of
                    these programs, and the others are readily available. This demonstration will
                    allow participants to experiment with several of these tools, to see examples of
                    student work, and to consider how the tools might be used in their own
                    classrooms. Of the tools we use, we propose to have four available for
                    demonstration.</p>
                <p>We will demonstrate the two programs we have developed (and, in earlier versions,
                    discussed at ALLC/ACH '98): the Linear Modeling Kit (LMK) and the Stylistic
                    Analysis Kit (SAK). As well, we have also used and will demonstrate a freeware
                    beta version of PennMUSH and SemNet(r), a tool for creating conceptual networks.
                    The Linear Modeling Kit or LMK is an authoring system which allows users to
                    create applications that generate any kind of text according to principles
                    proposed by the user. For example, a student can use the LMK to create a
                    "tragedy generator" by entering what the student perceives to be the parts or
                    elements of a tragedy, any principles of order among those parts, and
                    characteristic text for each part. Depending on the complexity of the input, the
                    generator will produce hundreds, thousands, or millions of different texts. The
                    task of creating a generator calls for students to think abstractly insofar as
                    they are dealing with stories, not simply a story. That is, students must know
                    well a number of tragedies or romance novels or bildungsroman in order to
                    abstract those qualities or elements that the texts share or that seem central
                    to the genre. However, they must also think very precisely in order to translate
                    their understandings into the unforgiving and unambiguous language of what is
                    essentially computer programming. In essays or articles, we, as well as our
                    students, know how to smooth over those things about which we are not quite
                    sure; we know how either to hide ambiguity or to make it a virtue. Obviously,
                    one cannot do that when creating a generator.</p>
                <p>In short, students have to work at a level both of abstraction and of detail that
                    may be greater than that forced by a paper. The Stylistic Analysis Kit is a
                    combination concordance and counting program. When a text is opened from within
                    the program, the SAK displays basic statistical information about word,
                    sentence, and paragraph lengths and a word list, which can be arranged by
                    frequency or alphabetically or which can show punctuation. Students can learn to
                    use the SAK with less than five minutes of instruction, a significant factor in
                    undergraduate education. In our classes, students have used the SAK to consider
                    both literary texts and their own essays. In either case, students find
                    themselves having to confront and explain the relationship between the abstract
                    and the specific or concrete. When analyzing their own essays, for example,
                    students constantly are driven back to their own texts to account for the
                    statistics they have discovered. Nearly all find themselves, to return to Ott's
                    phrasing, raising difficult questions about information. SemNet(r), by the
                    SemNet Research Group, allows users to create layered and linked conceptual maps
                    or networks. Our use of SemNet(r) has been primarily in writing courses
                    although, again, students have used it both with professional writing and in the
                    creation or analysis of their own essays. We have found that asking students to
                    create Semnet networks causes them to think deeply about the relationships
                    between concepts either in their own papers or in professional essays we have
                    assigned. Creating a visual map of relationships forces students not only to be
                    explicit about the connections between ideas but to recognize when those
                    connections are missing.</p>
                <p>In the demonstration, participants will be able to look at networks created by
                    students and experiment with the program by creating their own networks.
                    Students at our college have also used a MUSH to improvise an on-line serial
                    drama as a laboratory section of an English course in dramatic structure. In the
                    course, students play characters and invent actions on-line, edit the logs of
                    their online sessions into scripts, and then publish a final version on the web.
                    By writing and publishing a play, students in the class are testing the
                    principles of structure they have learned from their reading of a dozen plays
                    and Aristotle's <title level="m">Poetics</title>. They are forced to confront
                    the concrete implications of abstract ideas. While it would be impractical for
                    this demonstration to set up a full-scale MUSH environment (which would require
                    at least two Macintosh machines linked to the internet), we can show samples of
                    student work in our MUSH and the ultimate form of those samples as a drama
                    published on the web. The tools we will demonstrate engage students in making or
                    doing, not in receiving information passively. Using such tools, students learn
                    to use the new technology to explore and test ideas.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
