<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Dating Dickinson: an Experimental Approach to
                    Stylochronometry</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Constantina</forename>
                        <surname>Stamou</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Luton</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Richard</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                        <surname>Forsyth</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Luton</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Stylometry is the statistical analysis of literary style, whose two primary
                    applications are authorship attribution and chronological problems. It
                    originated in 1851 when Augustus de Morgan suggested that it is possible to
                    settle authorship by determining if one text "does not deal in longer words"
                    than another (Holmes, 1998). Stylometry is based upon the notion that it is
                    possible to detect an author's 'signature' by examining quantifiable features of
                    written texts. The only difference between the two applications is that
                    attributional studies claim that certain features in an author's style are
                    manipulated unconsciously and therefore remain fixed, whilst chronological
                    studies support the idea that stylistic fingerprints evolve smoothly throughout
                    an author's life. The contradiction is overridden, though, by the choice of
                    features.</p>
                <p>Stylochronometry, a term used to cover the dating of texts from stylistic
                    evidence, concerns itself with problems of specifying the sequence of
                    composition of the works of a given author. Famous cases are the dating of
                    Plato's dialogues, of certain of Shakespeare's plays, and the dating of the New
                    Testament scriptures, although their true chronology will never be known since
                    there is not enough external evidence to back up such stylometric findings.</p>
                <p>Scientific approaches to chronology begin with the choosing of a group of texts
                    that are more or less securely dated, then proceed with the application of
                    stylometric methods that manipulate the chosen variables which will best
                    correlate with the dates of the texts. Once the methods used assign the correct
                    dates to the initial test set, the final step is to employ the same methods on
                    disputed cases. Such stylometric variables include high frequency words,
                    function and common words, type-token ratio, vocabulary richness measures and
                    others.</p>
                <p>A famous example comes from Brainerd (1980) on the chronology of Shakespeare's
                    plays. Examining the percentage of occurrence of 120 lemmata, which were mainly
                    related to high-frequency lexical items, additionally combined with the
                    investigation of the average verse line length in words, the percentage of split
                    lines and the type-token ratio, he concentrated initially on a group of plays
                    that had fairly accurate dates of composition. Since only 20 out of the 120
                    lemmata proved to be useful discriminators for chronology, he used them in order
                    to construct a function that would predict the dates of the control group. Once
                    his method produced the desired results, the final step was to use it on those
                    of Shakespeare's plays which were of disputed nature in terms of dates.
                    Difficulties arose related to the possibility of multiple authorship in certain
                    cases, authorial revision at some stage, and the status of manuscripts used for
                    the preparation of the basic copy texts. However, multivariate statistics proved
                    useful in order to detect which plays were likely to be products of multiple
                    authorship.</p>
                <p>In poetry though, it has not been possible to date texts of less than 500 words
                    in length until recently. Forsyth (1999) at BSRU investigated a method of dating
                    short pieces of text (averaging 114 words in length) and tested them on W.B.
                    Yeats's work. This method, among others, will be used in our project, which aims
                    at building on collaborative work begun by Dr Forsyth and Prof. Margaret Freeman
                    of Valley College, California, on the investigation of chronological changes in
                    the style of the American poet Emily Dickinson (1830-1886).</p>
                <p>Born in Amherst, Massachusetts, Dickinson lived at her father's house most of her
                    life and in her later years became a recluse. Because of her individualistic
                    style, which, as it is accepted nowadays, set her ahead of her time, only 10 of
                    her poems were published during her lifetime. Moreover, due to her difficult
                    handwriting and her idiosyncratic punctuation, they were heavily edited, since
                    the public was not yet prepared for her eccentric masterpieces. At the time of
                    her death, 1775 poems were discovered arranged in 60 small packets. Following
                    that, efforts were made by her relatives to get all the poems published; still,
                    though, her poetry was heavily edited. Her impact on the American public
                    gradually became intense, and in 1955 a complete edition of her work was
                    published by Thomas H. Johnson, this time using her own punctuation and
                    vocabulary. Today she is known for her startling originality, her bold
                    experiments in prosody, her tragic vision, and the range of her intellectual and
                    emotional explorations.</p>
                <p>Johnson's edition provides approximate dates of composition (Johnson, 1961),
                    according to Theodora Ward's study, who collaborated with Johnson, of the
                    changes in her handwriting, apart from a few poems which have precise dates,
                    either because Dickinson sent them as parts of letters to various friends or
                    because she mentions contemporary events.</p>
                <p>Our investigation will initially concentrate on control authors that have
                    securely dated works, such as Christina Rossetti and W.B. Yeats. Both poets
                    lived in the 19th century as Dickinson did. It is proposed to utilise a
                    feature-finding program developed by Forsyth &amp; Holmes (1996) at BSRU, a
                    tagger such as TOSCA from Nijmegen University, and a content analysis tool. Thus
                    we will tap into linguistic information of different kinds - lexical, syntactic
                    and semantic. Our aim is to detect the type of linguistic information that is
                    useful for discriminating between the early and late works of our poets with the
                    intention of using the techniques applied on the control authors to date
                    Dickinson's work.</p>
                <p>Laan (1995) argues that there is no hard evidence to suggest that authors have
                    both a conscious and an unconscious aspect to their writing style, as stylometry
                    suggests. On the other hand, possibilities such as the existence of a stable and
                    an adaptable part in an author's unconscious style, or the idea that some change
                    their unconscious features of their styles and others do not, also exist as Laan
                    (1995) admits. The question to what extent such claims are true has been
                    investigated by Robinson (1992) and Keyser (1992) who both suggest proceeding
                    from authors with known publication dates to authors with unknown publication
                    dates.</p>
                <p>Initial studies, to be reported at this conference, have investigated the idea
                    that authors generally exhibit a trend towards decreasing complexity as they
                    grow older. Using the Fog Index as a measure of the density of language, based
                    on the proportion of long words and average sentence length, we have found
                    equivocal results. But other measures do seem to show increased simplicity with
                    time. We believe that this brings us a step closer to correct chronology.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">B.</forename>
                                    <surname>Brainerd</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">The Chronology of Shakespeare's Plays: A Statistical
                                Study</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">14</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">4</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">221-230</biblScope>
                                <date when="1980">1980</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >S.</forename><surname>Forsyth</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Stylochronometry with Substrings Or: A Poet Young and
                                Old</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">14</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">4</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">1-11</biblScope>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >S.</forename><surname>Forsyth</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >I.</forename><surname>Holmes</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Feature Finding for Text Classification</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">11</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">4</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">163-174</biblScope>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">D.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >I.</forename><surname>Holmes</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">The Evolution of Stylometry in Humanities
                                Scholarship</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">13</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">111-117</biblScope>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">H.</forename>
                                    <surname>Johnson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">The Complete Poems of Emily Dickinson</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Little, Brown and Company</publisher>
                                <date when="1961">1961</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Keyser</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Stylometric Method and the Chronology of Plato's Works
                                (review article)</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">.Bryn Mawr Classical Review</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">3</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">58-74</biblScope>
                                <date when="1992">1992</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">N.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >M.</forename><surname>Laan</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Stylometry and Method: The Case of Euripides</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">10</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">4</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">271-278</biblScope>
                                <date when="1995">1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >M.</forename><surname>Robinson</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Plato and the Computer</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Ancient Philosophy</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">12</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">375-382</biblScope>
                                <date when="1992">1992</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
