<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Subject Specific Search Engines for the
                    Humanities</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Brian</forename>
                        <surname>Hancock</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Rutgers University</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Internet has proven to be a vast and unruly resource. Students are happy to
                    come to the library and use general engines such as AltaVista and directories
                    such as Yahoo! to do their research on the Web, but often the results they
                    generate are extraneous and from unreliable sources. To make matters worse,
                    recent studies show the major engines index only a portion of the Internet,
                    although Excite claims its recently-announced search engine will reach all the
                    Web's pages. On a more modest scale, to help keep users on track with their Web
                    searches, humanities librarians have begun to use subject-specific engines.</p>
                <p>Subject-specific engines are a good tool for concentrating a search within the
                    parameters of a particular discipline. These parameters naturally define a
                    search and can help users obtain relevant results quickly. To help achieve this,
                    these engines are set up with a variety of automated software packages such as
                    Harvest and Ultraseek server.</p>
                <p>Harvest is an integrated set of tools to gather, extract, organize, search,
                    cache, and replicate relevant information across the Internet. It was developed
                    originally at the University of Colorado by the Internet Task Force Group on
                    Resource Discovery (IRTF-RD) and is maintained by a group of volunteers at the
                    University of Edinburgh. It is used to gather information from selected sites so
                    a user will receive only information relevant to the subject searched. For
                    example, if searched for "Horace," a subject-specific engine for the classics
                    like Index Antiquus will return results relating to the Roman poet. The users of
                    this subject-specific system are assured the hits returned will be relevant.</p>
                <p>Harvest consists of two basic subsystems: the gatherer and the broker. The
                    gatherer collects the information from sites selected by a person (in the case
                    of Index Antiquus, sites relevant to the classics as determined by a librarian).
                    This process is an evaluation using particular criteria - criteria such as
                    accuracy, appropriateness, authority, organization, currency, and relevancy. To
                    this list we must add stability. Even though a robot or link checker will help
                    maintain links to active sites, you don't want the database changing radically
                    every time it's renewed.</p>
                <p>Once the information is returned to the local server, it is summarized and
                    indexed. That is, it is stripped of any HTML code, and a database is created and
                    indexed. The gatherer does not by itself automatically update the database; this
                    is done by running the cron command to resend the gatherer. This can be done at
                    a specified time, every month for instance, and because we are good Net
                    citizens, early in the morning to keep the load down on host servers. The broker
                    is basically the mechanism that accesses the database and returns the results;
                    in other words, the broker is the search engine. The default engine for Harvest
                    is glimpse, but you can use WAIS or Swish if you wish. Because Harvest is open
                    source, you can download the source and compile the software yourself.</p>
                <p>Infoseek has now made its Ultraseek Server port to Linux available. We are
                    currently running Ultraseek 3.1 on on Red Hat Linux 6.1 and have also run it
                    successfully on SuSE Linux 6.3. It's extremely easy to install but because it is
                    a commerical product you are not given the code. It can be used on an Intranet
                    or to collect documents from Web servers.</p>
                <p>The Ultraseek Server automatically sends out its robot to selected sites and
                    creates the index. The search interface is configurable and supports
                    natural-language queries. Once the database is created, you can manage it
                    remotely via your browser. The extensive documentation includes installation,
                    administration, and customization guides. The version for Linux is available in
                    i386.rpm file or tar ball format.</p>
                <p>The presenter will demonstrate Index Antiquus running on Harvest and on Ultraseek
                    server. As indicated, Index Antiquus is a subject-specific search engine for
                    classical and early latin medieval texts. Interested parties will be invited to
                    test Index Antiquus and the presenter will be pleased to answer any questions
                    such as the use of this type of system for other humanities disciplines. The URL
                    for Index Antiquus is &lt;<ptr target="http://harvest.rutgers.edu:8765"/>&gt;
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
