<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Enriching Drawing</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Robin</forename>
                        <surname>Shaw</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Glasgow</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>A three year project to develop a computer based learning package in drawing. </p>
                <p>Until the latest round of funding, United Kingdom Higher Education (UKHE) through
                    the Teaching and Learning Technology Programme (TLTP), despite an overall budget
                    of around £75 million, had not made any sizeable investment in learning
                    technology for art and design. Art schools have always been in the forefront of
                    the use of computers as tools. In design, in layout, in the manipulation of
                    images, and in the creation of art, lecturers and students have possibly formed
                    the most expert group of computer users and their needs have driven some of the
                    most innovative packages.</p>
                <p>However, there has always existed a healthy scepticism as to whether computers
                    have anything to contribute to teaching and learning in art schools. This is not
                    surprising. Apart from the provision of ready access to resources through the
                    internet, learning technology has been dependent on pedagogic situations where
                    new skills or concepts had to be acquired by the student and where the class as
                    a whole would move ahead in expertise which would be tested by the examination.
                    The computer is ideal for a situation where, for example, the student has to
                    learn the basics of a scientific discipline. Information can be given, processes
                    can be simulated and at each stage of the package the student can discover
                    whether they are understanding the material. Questions can be posed and often
                    quite sophisticated feedback given to the student. Contrast that with the
                    situation in art. In art there are few certainties. The emphasis is less on
                    facts, the needs of the student are individual and the assessment of the student
                    is through a piece of work demonstrating creativity and the development of
                    ideas.</p>
                <p>With a grant from TLTP of £300,000 and matching funds to give a budget of around
                    £800,000 a consortium of art schools and universities led by the London
                    Institute is engaged on a three year project to create interactive multimedia
                    learning packages on drawing. Drawing is central to all that is produced within
                    the broadest spectrum of art and design. It is the core around which the
                    conceptual and intellectual development of students takes place. Drawing allows
                    individuals to learn to look, to record what they see, and is used to develop
                    thought and ideas for artwork and for design, in both two and three dimensions. </p>
                <p>In 1995-96 almost 5% of students in UKHE were in art and design. If related
                    subjects with a clear interest in drawing such as architecture, engineering and
                    technology are included the total rises to almost 16%. This growth in numbers
                    has created problems which the package seeks to address.</p>
                <p>The approach adopted by the London Institute and its partners in the Falmouth
                    College of Art, Ravensbourne College of Design and Communication and the
                    Universities of Ulster and Brighton is intended to create materials which give
                    full respect to the richness of the subject. The packages will come at drawing
                    from many different angles and controversy will be welcomed rather than shunned.
                    In addition to a thorough treatment of the basic skills such as drawing on
                    paper, drawing with the computer and draughting, the programs will explore the
                    historical development of our understanding of spatial representation from the
                    origins of perspective, through drawing machines to 3D and computer graphics. In
                    all the work the importance of how to see, how to interpret, and how to innovate
                    will be paramount and due weight will be given to the theoretical, philosophical
                    and contextual elements. Considerable use will be made of video to show
                    practitioners at work and discussing their particular approaches to drawing.</p>
                <p>The project got underway in June 1998 and the initial period was spent in
                    blocking out the areas of drawing we wish to address, and researching our
                    pedagogical approach. The second phase of the project was to write detailed
                    descriptions of the planned modules focusing on the aims and objectives of the
                    module and how the content was to be presented and made interactive. The project
                    is now in the development stage which is using Director.</p>
                <p>There is a considerable body of evidence that in order for learning to take place
                    effectively on the computer, the user has to be involved in tasks where
                    decisions have to be made. The learning should be active and consequently there
                    is a continual pressure to find ways of engaging the student. While assessment
                    within the field of drawing is difficult, we are convinced that the student will
                    gain by reviewing what has been learned and by receiving sensitive feedback on
                    progress, so we are exploring ways in which this can be possible.</p>
                <p>In a project of this nature it is vital to expose ideas to the widest audience
                    before committing them to development and we have been disseminating information
                    about the project to art colleges and other institutions with an interest in
                    drawing. To date, staff from more than ninety institutions in the UK and the USA
                    have expressed an interest and we are allowing them access to our deliberations.
                    We are eager for as wide a participation as possible and interested faculty can
                    sign up to the list from our website at &lt;<ptr
                        target="http://tltp.linst.ac.uk/"/>&gt;.</p>
                <p>The finished package will be distributed on DVD since that medium allows the
                    packaging of the product on one disk with a more than adequate space for high
                    quality graphics. The finished product will be available to UKHE at the
                    beginning of 2001 though beta versions will be widely distributed for testing
                    well before that date. As the project progresses, prototype modules will be
                    trialled in the classroom situation, both in the consortium partners and also in
                    a number of other interested institutions. From the evaluation of these
                    prototypes, which will be carried out by the University of Glasgow, we will make
                    changes to incorporate what we learn from student and staff use. The results of
                    these evaluations will be widely disseminated. The project intends that the
                    package will be made available outside of the United Kingdom though its primary
                    audience is first year degree students in that country.</p>
                <p>Since the project is probably the largest investment ever in learning technology
                    in art it poses a considerable challenge. Its aims are ambitious and
                    wide-ranging and while it in no way seeks to supplant the traditional
                    relationship between staff and student, it intends to make a significant
                    contribution to the richness of the learning environment in the area of drawing.
                    It will do this by producing products which will emphasise the development of
                    observation, skill and accuracy and the understanding of form and space. Though
                    the package will encourage the use of the computer for drawing, the focus of the
                    materials will remain on traditional drawing tools. However, it will certainly
                    promote the new approaches to drawing which are made possible through
                    technology, and will aim to improve the ability to utilise software applications
                    for three-dimensional modelling and to enhance the teaching of formal drawing
                    systems such as projection and perspective. When completed it will be a valuable
                    resource for use in the classroom and for the independent student.</p>
                <p>The proposed presentation will demonstrate examples of the development to date,
                    deal with project management issues and invite discussion and participation from
                    interested faculty.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
