<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">A Comparison of Methods for the Attribution of
                    Authorship of Popular Fiction</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Fiona</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Tweedie</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Glasgow</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Lisa</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">Lena</forename>
                        <surname>Opas-Hänninen</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Joensuu</name>, Finland <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>In this poster we present the stylistic analysis of a number of popular
                        fiction genres. Popular fiction generally receives less academic attention
                        than literature, but its ability to draw the reader into the story is
                        noteworthy. In previous work (Opas and Tweedie, 1999a, 1999b) we have
                        examined measures of stance in an attempt to quantify this degree of reader
                        involvement. In this paper we turn to measures used to discriminate between
                        authors, in order to find consistent differences between genres and authors.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Textual Sources</head>
                    <p>We have taken texts from three distinct sources: romance novels, detective
                        novels and American short stories. Our total corpus is 590,000 words. We
                        have analysed romance novels published between 1990-1996 from the Harlequin
                        Presents and Regency Romance series. We have also analysed Danielle Steel's
                        works, which are classified as women's fiction or 'cross-overs'. The romance
                        texts make up 245,000 words. The detective fiction part of our corpus is
                        made up of popular contemporary female authors published in the 1990s, i.e.
                        Cornwell, Grafton, James, Leon, Peters, and Rendell. Where an author has
                        created many detectives, we chose the most well-known one to represent that
                        author. Some of the detectives are male and others female and we expect them
                        to express stance differently. These texts make up 295,000 words. Short
                        stories were also taken from the works of Carver and Barth. These make up
                        almost 50,000 words.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Methods</head>
                    <p>We will compare and contrast the results from three analyses of these texts.
                        The analyses are based on methods used in determining authorship: the
                        frequency of the most common words, letter frequency and measures of
                        vocabulary richness. The data from each of these procedures is then used in
                        a principal components analysis in order to identify the most important
                        elements.</p>
                    <list>
                        <item><emph rend="bold">1) Word frequencies</emph> The use of principal
                            components analysis of the most common words to determine authorship was
                            proposed by Burrows in 1988 and has become an essential tool for
                            stylistic analysis. Here, the most commonly-occurring forty words were
                            employed. Their frequencies were measured and standardised for text
                            length. A principal components analysis was then carried out and the
                            texts plotted in the principal components space. The first two principal
                            components corresponded to 32.2% of the total variation. The first
                            principal component separates the romantic Steel texts, with high
                            negative scores, from the American short stories which have high
                            positive scores. Detective stories by Sue Grafton and Patricia Cornwell
                            also have high positive scores on this axis. The second principal
                            component appears to act as a rough genre separator; romantic texts tend
                            to have positive scores and all of the detective novels have negative
                            scores. Consideration of a loadings plot indicates that the Steel texts
                            use a high proportion of "she", "her" and "they", while the short
                            stories use "at", "said" and "on". The Grafton and Cornwell texts are
                            written in the first person and this is highlighted by their use of
                            "me", "my" and "I".</item>
                        <item><emph rend="bold">2) Letter frequencies</emph> Ledger and Merriam use
                            letter frequencies in their analysis of Shakespearean texts with
                            remarkable success. Here we consider the relative frequencies of 'A' -
                            'Z', with capital and lower-case letters amalgamated. These 26 variables
                            are then subjected to principal components analysis. The results are
                            plotted in the first two dimensions of the principal components space
                            which account for 34.5% of the total variation. In this analysis the
                            separation is not as good as the word frequency analysis. The American
                            texts tend to have high negative scores on the first principal
                            component, while the texts by P. D. James have very high positive
                            scores.</item>
                        <item><emph rend="bold">3) Measures of Vocabulary Richness</emph> A great
                            number of measures of vocabulary richness have been proposed. Tweedie
                            and Baayen (1998) carry out a review of these measures and find that
                            two, K and Z, contain the vast majority of the information from the
                            author's vocabulary. Yule's K measures the 'repeat-rate' used by the
                            author, while Orlov's Z measures vocabulary richness in the sense of the
                            number of different words used. We therefore plot the texts in the K-Z
                            plane. As might be expected, the American short stories are found to
                            have a low repeat rate and high vocabulary richness. The Steel texts
                            have a higher richness than the other romantic texts, but the detective
                            and romantic fiction texts are not separated by this analysis. </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3. Conclusions</head>
                    <p>These three analyses offer views of different facets of the style of popular
                        romantic and detective fiction. The genres are most clearly separated when
                        the most common words are used as data, while the letter frequency analysis
                        is, not surprisingly, more affected by the particular names of heroes or
                        heroines. The measures of vocabulary richness distinguish clearly between
                        the more popular texts and the short stories. At the conference we shall
                        also present the analysis of markers of stance, used in Opas and Tweedie
                        (1999a, 1999b).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >F.</forename><surname>Burrows</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Word patterns and stay shapes: the statistical analysis
                                of narrative style</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">2</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">61-70</biblScope>
                                <date when="1987">1987</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Ledger</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <surname>Merriam</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Shakespeare, Fletcher and the Two Noble Kinsmen</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">9</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">235-248</biblScope>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >L.</forename><surname>Opas</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">F.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >J.</forename><surname>Tweedie</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">The Magic Carpet Ride: Reader Involvement in Romantic
                                Fiction</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">14</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">89-101</biblScope>
                                <date when="1999">1999a</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">L.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >L.</forename><surname>Opas</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">F.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >J.</forename><surname>Tweedie</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Come into my World: Styles of Stance in Detective and
                                Romantic Fiction</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Abstracts of the ALLC/ACH conference 1999,
                                Virginia</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1999">1999b</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">247</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">F.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >J.</forename><surname>Tweedie</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >H.</forename><surname>Baayen</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">How Variable May a Constant Be? Measures of Lexical
                                Richness in Perspective</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">32</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">5</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">323-352</biblScope>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
