<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Trajan's Column: Building a WWW Image-Database</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Geoffrey</forename>
                        <surname>Rockwell</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">McMaster University</name>, Canada <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Gretchen</forename>
                        <surname>Umholtz</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">McMaster University</name>, Canada <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Michele</forename>
                        <surname>George</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">McMaster University</name>, Canada <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Martin</forename>
                        <surname>Beckmann</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">McMaster University</name>, Canada <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Paul</forename>
                        <surname>Barrette</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">McMaster University</name>, Canada <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Digital Resources</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>One of the challenges when designing image databases in the humanities is to
                    provide interfaces that are drawn from the object being represented rather than
                    from the technology used. In this paper we will discuss an image database of
                    over 400 images that was built by a team of graduate students and faculty at
                    McMaster University. The images relate to carving technique on Trajan's Column,
                    one of the most extensive and important surviving sculptural monuments of
                    ancient Rome. In addition to various text-based search tools, we also created a
                    cartoon sketch interface to the entire frieze of Trajan's Column that allows
                    users to move around a virtual column to access the images and to see them in
                    narrative context. This virtual column is an example of a content driven
                    interface to an image collection that is based on the subject matter of the
                    collection.</p>
                <p>Trajan, Roman emperor from AD 98 to 117, has generally been remembered as a
                    'good' emperor. A gifted general, he was close to his soldiers and led them on a
                    number of campaigns which substantially expanded the Roman empire. Two of these
                    campaigns, the first and second Dacian wars, are commemorated on Trajan's
                    column: a 100 foot tall marble column decorated with a continuous, upwardly
                    spiraling, sculpted frieze. The scenes on this frieze are an invaluable source
                    of information about many aspects of Roman military practice, imperial ideology,
                    and also sculptural technique. The column still stands today in its original
                    place in the Forum of Trajan in Rome, but, due to its great height, visibility
                    of individual scenes from the ground is quite limited; students and scholars
                    must often rely on old photographs and plaster casts for the study of many
                    details.</p>
                <p>In 1997 a team of graduate students and faculty at McMaster University were given
                    access to a unique collection of over 400 slides taken by Peter Rockwell and
                    Claudio Martini when Trajan's Column was being restored and had scaffolding
                    around it. The images are primarily of details that show carving technique. In
                    addition we were given access to a series of cartoon sketches of the entire
                    column that show the narrative of the frieze. The challenge was to create an
                    image database that would provide a context for these photographs so that
                    scholars and students of Roman art could use these resources easily. The WWW
                    site is located at &lt;<ptr
                        target="http://cheiron.humanities.mcmaster.ca/~trajan/"/>&gt;.</p>
                <p>In this paper we will do the following:<list>
                        <item><emph rend="bold">1. Discuss the background of the
                            project.</emph><lb/><lb/>This project was initiated by Peter Rockwell
                            who was looking for a venue for making his collection of slides
                            available to the research and education community. While he had
                            published on the column, the full collection of images on which his
                            research was based could not be published economically. A WWW site
                            seemed the most effective way to make this collection available. The
                            team was limited by the fact that the slide collection was in Rome,
                            Italy and could not be removed to Canada for digitization. In this paper
                            we will discuss the steps taken to digitize the images on site and build
                            the database from information gathered by Peter Rockwell as part of his
                            research.</item>
                        <item><emph rend="bold">2. Discuss the technical design of the WWW
                                site.</emph><lb/><lb/>After initially experimenting with a design
                            that used hundreds of static WWW pages we developed a dynamic database
                            that could generate the pages for the individual images on the fly. This
                            gave us the freedom to easily alter the interface of the image pages and
                            make site-wide changes in real time. This in turn allowed us to refine
                            the design of the site in an interactive fashion as suggestions came in
                            and users reported back. Finally the design of the database allowed
                            editors involved in the project to make corrections over secure
                            connections. In the paper we will comment on the virtues of moving to
                            dynamically generated information for projects that involve teams of
                            people, continuous correction and iterative interface design. We will
                            contrast the development of this site with two previous projects, the
                            Emily Pauline Johnson Archive (<ptr
                                target="http://www.humanities.mcmaster.ca/~pjohnson/home.html"/>)
                            and the Cradle of Collective Bargaining site (<ptr
                                target="http://www.humanities.mcmaster.ca/~cradle/"/>). Both of
                            these other sites use static WWW pages to hold the images. We will also
                            comment on the choice of image resolutions that we settled on. In the
                            Trajan site we make available small thumbnail images within WWW pages
                            for timely access and links to medium and high resolution copies of each
                            image and cartoon. This allows the user to look at and download images
                            suitable for teaching and research.</item>
                        <item><emph rend="bold">3. Discuss the interface problems we faced and the
                                solutions we settled on.</emph><lb/><lb/>The Trajan Project provides
                            three ways for users to navigate the images. The first is to search the
                            image database. The second is by using indexes generated from the
                            database which give the user an overview of the keywords used. The third
                            and most visual is to navigate the column using the cartoon sketches and
                            click on the links to individual images. In effect we have two means of
                            access that are driven by the technology and one that was driven by the
                            content of the database. In the paper we will discuss at length the need
                            for content-driven interfaces that provide access to users to images in
                            ways that correspond to the original artifact. Content-driven interfaces
                            cannot be standardized because they vary according to the artifact(s)
                            represented, but they provide a way of organizing information that the
                            user familiar with the area can use. In our case we used the column as a
                            whole as a visual index to the collection. The visual index not only
                            provides access but creates a context for the images which would be hard
                            to abstract from the database. This visual context augments the
                            interpretative essays that introduce the site.</item>
                        <item><emph rend="bold">4. Conclude by discussing uses and benefits of the
                                site.</emph><lb/><lb/>As part of this project we have been showing
                            the site to interested academics to get their feedback on the interface
                            and to get ideas about how it might be used. As many of the images were
                            taken to document carving techniques used in the sculpting of the
                            frieze, this site is of greatest use to those interested in Roman
                            carving. Many of the images, however, contain enough detail to be useful
                            to those interested in Roman sculpture in general or those interested in
                            studying Roman military equipment and activities. The WWW site provides
                            an economical alternative to print for research image collections to be
                            made available. In addition, the cartoons provide a continuous sketch of
                            the narrative of the column that can be downloaded and annotated by
                            those interested in this depiction of the events around the Dacian wars.
                        </item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Viewers invited to try the site have commented on how they could use the
                    high-resolution images and cartoons for teaching purposes since they are freely
                    available and easily accessed. These types of comments have led us to think
                    about the image database as not only a coherent research and teaching
                    collection, but as an accessible collection of free images that can be mined by
                    those who are shifting to electronic teaching tactics. Whenever you make a
                    digitized collection of images available you are also providing the equivalent
                    to academic clip art which can be reused in ways that are only remotely
                    connected to the original content. This unintended outcome from the digitization
                    of images will be discussed in the conclusion of the paper. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Arnheim</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Visual Thinking</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Berkeley</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1969">1969</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >M.</forename><surname>Baecker</surname></name> et al</author>
                            <title level="a">Vision, Graphic Design, and Visual Display</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Ronald</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">M.</forename>
                                    <surname> Baecker</surname>
                                </name> et al </editor>
                            <title level="m">Human-Computer Interaction: Toward the Year
                                2000</title>
                            <edition>2nd ed.</edition>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>San Francisco</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1995">1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Bertin</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Semiology of Graphics: Diagrams, Networks, Maps</title>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp>Trans.</resp>
                                <name><forename type="first">W.</forename><forename type="middle"
                                        >J.</forename><surname>Berg</surname></name>
                            </respStmt>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Madison, Wisconsin</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1983">1983</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Cichorius</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Die Reliefs der Trajanssäule</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Berlin</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1896">1896</date>
                                <date when="1900">1900</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">F.</forename>
                                    <surname>Lepper</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Frere</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Trajan's Column</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Gloucester</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1988">1988</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Marcus</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Graphic Design for Electronic Documents and User
                                Interfaces</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1991">1991</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">W.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">j.</forename>
                                    <surname>Mitchell</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">The Reconfigured Eye: Visual Truth in the
                                Post-Photographic Era</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Cambridge, Massachusetts</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1992">1992</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">P.</forename><forename type="middle"
                                        >M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Monti</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">La Colonna Traiana</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Rome</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1980">1980</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>

                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Settis</surname>
                                </name> et al </author>
                            <title level="m">La Colonna Traiana</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Rome</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1988">1988</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Rockwell</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Prelimary Study of the Carving Techniques on the Column
                                of Trajan</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Marmi Antichi</title>
                            <title level="s">Studi Miscellanei</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">26</biblScope>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1985">1985</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">101-111</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Rockwell</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">The Art of Stoneworking: a Reference Guide</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Tufte</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">The Visual Display of Quantitative Information</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Cheshire, CT</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1983">1983</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Tufte</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Envisioning Information</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Cheshire, CT</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1990">1990</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
