<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Shouting and Screaming: Manner and Noise Verbs in
                    Communication</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Urban</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of California, Berkeley</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Josef</forename>
                        <surname>Ruppenhofer</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of California, Berkeley</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>In many languages, words can be used in different domains from those in which
                    they originated. In English, sound verbs are commonly used in the context of
                    human communication (1-4).</p>
                <eg>(1) ('Shut up, Doreen,'[MESSAGE]) (Silas[SPEAKER]) barked, his face contorted by
                    a scowl.</eg>
                <eg>(2) ('Darling,'[MESSAGE]) (Conrad[SPEAKER]) cooed as Lee entered the living
                    room.</eg>
                <eg>(3) ('He's a thief, Hilary,'[MESSAGE])(he[SPEAKER]) grated almost savagely.</eg>
                <eg>(4) (Grandson Richard[SPEAKER]) rumbled (a reply[MESSAGE]).</eg>
                <p>However, not all sound verbs have communication uses; the ones that do are
                    restricted as to the type of message and/or speaker they can occur with. The
                    syntactic patterns of sound verbs used for communication are not the same
                    patterns found with true communication verbs. Several researchers (Goossens
                    1995, Miller &amp; Johnson-Laird 1976, Levin et al. 1997) have explored these
                    phenomena, paying particular attention to which verbs have or lack communication
                    uses. Here we propose a unified and expanded corpus-based account of these
                    cross-domain extensions in terms of Frame Semantics (Fillmore 1982) and with
                    reference to theories of metaphor. This analysis has implications for the
                    further description of the relationships between frames (e.g., inheritance and
                    blending), and the development of cross-domain uses of words.</p>
                <p>The FrameNet Project (P.I. Charles J. Fillmore) is creating a lexical database
                    with 3 linked components: the expanded lexicon, the Frame Database, and
                    annotated example sentences (Baker et al. 1998). Files which represent senses of
                    lexical items within a particular domain and frame (represented as domain/frame)
                    are created, and constituents are annotated with the Frame Elements which are
                    realized with respect to the target word. This annotation, and subsequent
                    marking of phrase type and grammatical function, is further analyzed for the
                    combinations of syntactic and semantic patterns realized in various senses. Even
                    while still in progress, this project has become a valuable resource for lexical
                    and other linguistic analysis. The authors, both researchers involved in all
                    stages of the project, have examined annotated files for 201 verbs in
                    perception/noise, 23 verbs in communication/manner, and 60 verbs in
                    communication/noise (there are 314 communication verb files overall).</p>
                <p>Sound originates in the domain and frame of perception/noise. Since communication
                    involves human verbal interaction, it necessarily overlaps with the sound
                    domain. Two criteria determine which noise verbs can have communication uses.
                    First, a noise verb is usable as a communication verb if the sound is produced
                    by animate beings, especially animals (e.g. bark, yelp), but not when it is
                    produced by objects (e.g. clink, thud). Nevertheless, some inanimate noises,
                    such as rumble, are used for communication. It is possible that the physical
                    profile of these sounds lends itself to a communication construal. Secondly,
                    among animal sounds, imitative sounds (e.g. oink, quack) have no uses as
                    communication verbs; the exact specification of the sound blocks the expression
                    of a message (5).</p>
                <eg>(5) *(Mr. Baker[SPEAKER]) oinked (an invitation[MESSAGE]) across the table.</eg>
                <p>The noise verbs with communication uses (e.g. scream, bellow) do not behave like
                    genuine manner of speech verbs (e.g. shout, whisper), differing from them both
                    syntactically and semantically. We argue that this reflects the differences in
                    the structure of the two domains and frames. In their home domain, noise verbs
                    are usually intransitive, taking the sound SOURCE as subject (6-8).</p>
                <eg>(6) Somewhere behind her (a horn[SOURCE]) blared.</eg>
                <eg>(7) (The long blades[SOURCE]) clashed and rang, their movement too fast for the
                    eye to follow.</eg>
                <eg>(8) The ducks began quacking and (the frogs[SOURCE]) croaking.</eg>
                <p>By comparison, communication verbs are normally transitive, with a SPEAKER
                    subject and a MESSAGE object. ADDRESSEE and TOPIC prepositional phrases and
                    MANNER adverbs frequently appear (9-11).</p>
                <eg>(9) ('How's the shop?[MESSAGE]) mumbles (one balding sweating man[SPEAKER]) (to
                    another[Addressee]).</eg>
                <eg>(10) One of his body squires heard (him[SPEAKER]) whispering (about it[TOPIC])
                    (to his Gascon favourite[Addressee]).</eg>
                <eg>(11) 'If (you[SPEAKER]) so much as whisper (a word[MESSAGE]) (about Dame
                    Agatha[TOPIC])(to the Lady Maeve[ADDRESSEE]), you will regret the day I ever
                    plucked you out of Newgate!.'</eg>
                <p>Consider a communication use of the sound verb 'snarl' (`Do you have to?' she
                    snarled at him as he took out a cigarette). Whereas `Do you have to?' [MESSAGE]
                    and she [SPEAKER] look like canonical communication frame elements, (at him) is
                    not a typical encoding of ADDRESSEE; compare the oddness of (I talked at John).
                    The effect of (at him) is to make him seem more like the target of a directed
                    sound emission as in (The dog barked at me). The difference between real manner
                    of speech verbs and communication uses of noise verbs can also be observed in
                    terms of complementation patterns and their frequencies. For example, more
                    quoted MESSAGEs are found with noise verbs than with manner of speech verbs. The
                    pattern is the reverse for that-clause MESSAGEs. ADDRESSEEs are less common with
                    noise verbs used for communication than with regular manner of speech verbs
                    (12).</p>
                <eg>(12) (The housekeeper[SPEAKER]) left the room, muttering (about
                    ingratitude[TOPIC]).</eg>
                <p>This difference can be exemplified statistically by the analysis of proportional
                    samples of representative verbs from each domain and frame.</p>
                <p>Noise verbs used for communication do not only differ from manner of speech verbs
                    as a class, but also exhibit interesting differences among themselves. For
                    instance, many verbs are specialized as to what kinds of speakers they accept:
                    older people and females are better cacklers, while men and people in positions
                    of authority are more likely to rumble, bellow, or grunt (13-15).</p>
                <eg>(13) ('I'll warrant he is!'[MESSAGE]) (the old lady[SPEAKER]) cackled
                    unexpectedly.</eg>
                <eg>(14) We passed (the police sentry who[SPEAKER]) grunted (a sleepy
                    greeting[MESSAGE]).</eg>
                <eg>(15) ('Off now then?'[MESSAGE])chirped (the woman[SPEAKER]), dropping another
                    sock.</eg>
                <p>Also, inasmuch as the manner of the speech act is being emphasized, the quoted
                    [MESSAGE] component frequently contains an alphabetic representation supporting
                    that emphasis (16).</p>
                <eg>(16) ('Th-that's b-blackmail,'[MESSAGE]) (she[SPEAKER]) spluttered.</eg>
                <p>This analysis shows that in these cross-domain uses, semantic and syntactic
                    factors from both source and target domains play a role in determining the
                    structure of the utterance. While the target domain supplies a syntactic
                    structure, the source domain's semantics constrain the degree to which that
                    syntactic structure can be exploited. Although some of the domains' interactions
                    resemble metaphorical mappings, e.g. the SPEAKER-SOURCE correspondence, the
                    relationship between the domains is not that of metaphor. Both domains are
                    concrete, rather than one being concrete and one abstract. Instead of being
                    discrete domains, they have something in common, i.e. the presence of a sound
                    source. Nor are they simple cases of situational metonymy between speaking and
                    producing sound. This kind of evidence and data can be used to describe more the
                    complex interactions of frames which are evidenced in natural language: frame
                    blends and inheritance, metaphor, complex frames, and other cross-domain uses.
                    The synthesis of linguistic theory, lexicography, and work with large-scale
                    corpora is necessary for significant coverage of the data. The frame semantic
                    approach, with detailed lexical analysis, provides a semantically and
                    syntactically informative account.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Collin</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">F.</forename>
                                    <surname>Baker</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Charles</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Fillmore</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">John</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">B.</forename>
                                    <surname>Lowe</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">The Berkeley FrameNet Project</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">COLING-ACL '98 Proceedings of the Conference, held
                                August 10-14, 1998, in Montreal, Canada</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Charles</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Fillmore</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Frame Semantics</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name type="org">Linguistic Society of Korea</name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Linguistics in the Morning Calm</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Seoul</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Hanshin</publisher>
                                <date when="1982">1982</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">111-138</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Louis</forename>
                                    <surname>Goossens</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Metaphtonymy: The Interaction of Metaphor and Metonymy
                                in Figurative Expressions for Linguistic Action</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Louis</forename>
                                    <surname>Goossens</surname> et al </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">By Word of Mouth</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Amsterdam/Philadelphia</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>John Benjamins Publishing Co.</publisher>
                                <date when="1995">1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">George</forename>
                                    <surname>Lakoff</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Mark</forename>
                                    <surname>Johnson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Metaphors We Live By</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Chicago/London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1980">1980</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Beth</forename>
                                    <surname>Levin</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Grace</forename>
                                    <surname>Song</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">B.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">T.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Atkins</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Making Sense of Corpus Data: A Case Study of Verbs of
                                Sound</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">International Journal of Corpus Linguistics</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">2</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">23-64</biblScope>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">George</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Miller</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Philip</forename>
                                    <surname>Johnson-Laird</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Language and Perception</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Cambridge, Mass.</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1976">1976</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
