<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.3.0.0/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ab-142">

<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>Juxta Commons</title>
<author>
<name>
<surname>Wheeles</surname>, <forename>Dana</forename>
</name>
<affiliation>University of Virginia, United States of America</affiliation>
<email>dana@nines.org</email>
</author>
<author>
<name><surname>Jensen</surname>, <forename>Kristin</forename></name>
<affiliation>Performant Software, United States of America</affiliation>
<email>kristin@performantsoftware.com</email>
</author>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority/>
<publisher>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</publisher>
<distributor>
<name>Center for Digital Research in the Humanities</name>
<address>
<addrLine>319 Love Library</addrLine>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska&#8211;Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
<addrLine>cdrh@unl.edu</addrLine>
</address>
</distributor>
<pubPlace>Lincoln, Nebraska</pubPlace>
<address>
<addrLine>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</addrLine>
<addrLine>Lincoln, NE 68588-4100</addrLine>
</address>
<availability>
<p/>
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<notesStmt>
<note type="abstract">Juxta Commons is the new destination site for textual collation and
visualization online. The original desktop application has been transformed into a web service by
the NINES R&amp;D team and an interface has been added to streamline the user&#039;s workflow. On
the web, Juxta Commons refines and expands the original analytical potential of the tool, and adds
to it a rhetorical facet, by enabling sharing and embedding whole comparison sets in blogs, articles
and other online publications.</note>
</notesStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<profileDesc>
<textClass>
<keywords scheme="original" n="category">
<term>Poster</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="keywords">
<term>collation</term>
<term>visualization</term>
<term>textual analysis</term>
</keywords>
<keywords scheme="original" n="topic">
<term>scholarly editing</term>
<term>software design and development</term>
<term>xml</term>
<term>bibliographic methods/textual studies</term>
<term>visualisation</term>
</keywords>
</textClass>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date when="2013-04-09"/>
<name>Matthew Lavin</name>
<desc>Initial encoding</desc>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text type="poster">
<body>
<div>
<p>Free and open source, Juxta Commons (juxtacommons.org) is an online workspace for comparing
multiple witnesses to a single textual work, privately storing collations, and sharing
visualizations.</p>
<p>Originally offered as a downloadable Java-based application developed by the Applied Research in
'Patacriticism group at the University of Virginia in 2005, Juxta was taken up by NINES
(http://nines.org) and transformed into a web service. This open-source API modularizes the sequence
of steps required for digital collation and offers more options for working with XML documents. In
addition, the NINES R&amp;D team created the interface for Juxta Commons, a destination site for
collation on the web. </p>
<p>Juxta Commons offers three visualizations of the differences between a group of texts: the heat
map (an overlay of the texts with differences highlighted by color), the side-by-side view (two
texts visualized with lines connecting the sites of difference) and the histogram (a global view of
the text illustrating the portions with the most change across versions). It is also compatible with
TEI Parallel Segmentation, so that users can upload their encoded files and make use of Juxta’s
visualizations, or those with text or XML files can export their collations as a digital critical
apparatus. </p>
<p>The interface streamlines the workflow of the original desktop application, and allows the user
to edit their sources, filter the XML content included in a given collation, and share their results
in a number of different ways. Even though the tool provides sophisticated options for working with
texts (XML and TXT), our goal in designing Juxta Commons was to allow teachers, scholars,
programmers and any other users curious about variants between documents the ability to create,
collate and share their findings with others without requiring any extra software downloads or
logins. </p>
<p>In taking Juxta to the web, NINES has transformed the tool into a rhetorical as well as
analytical tool, enabling initial discoveries to be interrogated, explored, and ultimately offered
as a new kind of evidence for scholarly arguments. Instead of relying upon footnotes or links in a
digital edition, a scholar can embed their collations within the argument itself, targeting sites of
interest, and encouraging readers to explore the full visualizations on their own. </p>
<p>Even as it presents some exciting opportunities for students of book history and textual
criticism, Juxta Commons also broadens the scope of interest in collation to the many different
kinds of texts on the web. Speeches and transcriptions, Wikipedia article versions, news releases,
Google Books and HATHI Trust texts: all these require the kind of authentication and analysis that
Juxta Commons makes possible. </p>
<p>Please visit the site juxtasoftware.org to learn more, and to find sample sets to spark your
creativity. </p>
</div>

</body>

</text>
</TEI>
