<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-589">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The TEI's Extramural Journal Project: Exploring New Digital Environments
                    and Defining a New Genre in Academic Publishing</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Schlitz, Stephanie A.</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Bloomsburg University</orgName><reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>sschlitz@bloomu.edu</email>
                </author>
               </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-03-18</date>
                <name>CD</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The Text Encoding Initiative’s (TEI) Extramural Journal (EJ) project was
                    conceived early in 2009 when the conveners of the TEI Education Special Interest
                    Group (SIG) proposed, as a matter of urgency, the development of an online
                    publishing suite to address the shortage of TEI educational resources.<note>Two
                        of the notable TEI teaching resources which are available include the Women
                        Writers Project’s NEH-funded series of “Advanced Seminars on Scholarly Text
                        Encoding” (see &lt;<ref type="external"
                            target="http://www.wwp.brown.edu/encoding/seminars/neh_advanced.html"
                            >http://www.wwp.brown.edu/encoding/seminars/neh_advanced.html</ref>&gt;)
                        and TEI by Example (see &lt;<ref type="external"
                            target="http://www.kantl.be/ctb/project/2006/tei-ex.htm"
                            >http://www.kantl.be/ctb/project/2006/tei-ex.htm</ref>&gt; and
                        Terras et al.).</note> Following approval by the TEI Board and Council and
                    the receipt of a small SIG grant in support of the project, TEI-EJ advanced into
                    development.</p>
                <p>Because TEI-EJ is being researched and developed in an era where “print is no
                    longer the exclusive or the normative medium in which knowledge is produced
                    and/or disseminated” (“A Digital Humanities Manifesto”) and where electronic
                    publication is increasingly common (see Waltham; Maron and Smith; Willett), it
                    is crucial to point out that typologically, TEI-EJ is positioned outside of two
                    disparate points on the web publishing continuum, media-driven journals which
                    are designed primarily for the publication of media-driven content (e.g. <hi
                        rend="italic">Vectors Journal</hi> &lt;<ref type="external"
                        target="http://www.vectorsjournal.org/"
                    >http://www.vectorsjournal.org/</ref>&gt;, <hi rend="italic">Southern
                        Spaces</hi> &lt;<ref type="external"
                        target="http://www.southernspaces.org/"
                    >http://www.southernspaces.org/</ref>&gt;; also see Toton and Martin) and
                    text-driven journals which are designed to reproduce the print journal model in
                    a web publication (e.g. <hi rend="italic">Journal of Writing Research</hi>
                        &lt;<ptr type="external" target="http://www.jowr.org"
                    ></ptr>&gt;, <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Teaching
                        and Learning in Higher Education</hi> &lt;<ref type="external"
                        target="http://www.isetl.org/ijtlhe/"
                    >http://www.isetl.org/ijtlhe/</ref>&gt;).</p>
                <p>Although TEI-EJ’s ‘journal’ designation is suggestive of a single aim, from the
                    outset, project objectives have been defined as both experimental and
                    extramural, and TEI-EJ has been envisaged not only as a publishing venue but
                    also as a community-driven online forum that offers members of the TEI, whether
                    novice or expert, as well as the broader DH community new educational insights
                    into the TEI. Significantly, the steps being taken to achieve these objectives
                    contribute to a newly emerging body of scholarship which explores the
                    development of new digital environments and which defines a new genre in
                    academic publishing.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>The first stage of the project has been the development of TEI-EJ as a born
                    digital, open access, peer reviewed scholarly journal where communicative modes
                    are bidirectional rather than exclusively unidirectional, articles are
                    media-driven (including video, audio, and image) as well as text-driven, and
                    where the aims of publication extend beyond print journal mimesis to include
                    education and community building.</p>
              <p>Given the hybrid nature of the project’s goals (publishing and learning
                    community; see Dal Fiore, Koku and Wellman) and the novel design for implementation, TEI-EJ’s site infrastructure
                    (see <hi rend="bold">Fig. 1</hi>) was designed to be extensible, capable of
                    managing text articles (e.g. TEI-XML as well as formats such as .txt and .doc
                    which are converted to TEI-XML), multimedia articles (e.g. video, audio, image),
                    moderated responses to articles, and community-driven communications (e.g. forum
                    and blog) (see <hi rend="bold">Fig. 2</hi>). This is achieved through Drupal,<note>For a good, comparative discussion of content management systems, see
                        “Comparing Open Source Content Management Systems: WordPress, Joomla,
                        Drupal, and Plone,” available at &lt;<ref type="external"
                            target="http://idealware.org/comparing_os_cms/"
                            >http://idealware.org/comparing_os_cms/</ref>&gt;. TEI-XML content
                        is being handled by the Drupal XML Content module, and the journal’s
                        publishing workflow is being handled by the Drupal E- Journal
                    module.</note> a customizable, open source content management system, which
                    facilitates the social media as well as the publishing and educational aspects
                    of the project.<note>A preview of the publishing website and a fully functional
                        mock journal issue are being presented at the TEI Members’ Meeting in
                        November 2009.</note></p>
                <p>
                    <figure xml:id="fig1">
                        <head>Fig. 1. <hi rend="italic">Schlitz TEI-EJ project planning
                                'mindmap'</hi></head>
                        <graphic url="589_Fig1.jpg" xmt:type="full"
                            rend="left-img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <figure xml:id="fig2">
                        <head>Fig. 2. <hi rend="italic">Screenshot of TEI-EJ website</hi></head>
                        <graphic url="589_Fig2.jpg" xmt:type="full"
                            rend="left-img" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>This paper will introduce the TEI-EJ project, describing the <hi rend="italic"
                        >why</hi> and <hi rend="italic">how</hi> of the key theoretical,
                    technological and editorial decisions that drove development as we advanced from
                    theory into practice. In doing so, it aims to establish the project as a new
                    model for academic publishing which is designed to harness emerging
                    technologies, to leverage the fact that “Open access is changing the public and
                    scholarly presence of the research article” (Willinsky), to promote learning
                    objectives beside dissemination of scholarship, and to elevate the role of
                    reader/end-user to the position of chief stakeholder.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title level="m">A Digital Humanities Manifesto</title>
                        <date type="other">15 Dec. 2008</date>
                        <date type="other">23 July 2009</date>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://dev.cdh.ucla.edu/digitalhumanities/2008/12/15/digital-humanities-manifesto/"
                            type="external"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Dal Fiore, Filippo</author>
                        <title level="a">Communities Versus Networks: The Implications on Innovation
                            and Social Change</title>
                        <title level="j">American Behavioral Scientist</title>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <biblScope type="issue">(50)7</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">857-866</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Koku, Emmanuel F.</author>
                        <author>Wellman, Barry</author>
                        <title level="a">Scholarly Networks as Learning Communities: The Case of
                            TechNet</title>
                        <title level="m">Designing Virtual Communities in the Service of
                            Learning</title>
                        <editor>Sasha Barab</editor>
                        <editor>Rob Kling</editor>
                        <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                        <date>2002</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Maron, Nancy L.</author>
                        <author>Kirby Smith, K.</author>
                        <title level="a">Current Models of Digital Scholarly Communication: Results
                            of an Investigation Conducted by Ithaka Strategic Services for the
                            Association of Research Libraries</title>
                        <title level="j">The Journal of Electronic Publishing</title>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <biblScope type="issue">12(1)</biblScope>
                        <ptr type="external"
                            target="http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/text- idx?c=jep;view=text;rgn=main;idno=3336451.0012.105"
                        />
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title level="m">TEI: Text Encoding Initiative</title>
                        <date type="visited">7 July 2009</date>
                        <ptr type="external" target="http://www.tei-c.org/index.xml"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Terras, Melissa</author>
                        <author>Van den Branden, Ron</author>
                        <author>Vanhoutte, Edward</author>
                        <title level="a">Teaching TEI: The Need for TEI by Example</title>
                        <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <biblScope type="issue">24(3)</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">297-306</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Toton, Sarah</author>
                        <author>Martin, Stacey</author>
                        <title level="a">Teaching and Learning from the U.S. South in Global
                            Contexts: A Case Study of Southern Spaces and Southcomb</title>
                        <title level="j">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <biblScope type="issue"> 3(2)</biblScope>
                        <ptr type="external"
                            target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/3/2/000047.html"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Waltham, Mary</author><date>12 Oct. 2009</date>
                        <title level="a">The Future of Scholarly Journals Publishing</title>
                        <ptr type="external" target="http://www.nhalliance.org/bm~doc/hssreport.pdf"
                        />
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Willett, Perry</author>
                        <title level="m">Electronic Texts: Audiences and Purposes</title>
                        <title level="a">A Companion to Digital Humanities</title>
                        <editor>Schreibman, Susan </editor>
                        <editor>Siemens, Ray </editor>
                        <editor>Unsworth, John </editor>
                        <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Blackwell</publisher>
                        <date>2004</date>
                        <ptr type="external" target="http://digitalhumanities.org/companion/"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Willinsky, J.</author>
                        <title level="a">9 Flavors of Open Access</title>
                        <title level="j">E-MEDICINE</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">49 (3)</biblScope>
                        <date>25 Sept. 2009</date>
                        <ptr type="external"
                            target="http://cssp.us/pdf/9%20Flavors%20of%20Open%20Access.pdf"/>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
