<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-623">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>A Tale of Two Cities: Implications of the Similarities and Differences in
                    Collaborative Approaches within the Digital Libraries and Digital Humanities
                    Communities</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Siemens, Lynne</name>
                    <affiliation>Faculty of Business/School of Public Administration, <orgName>University of
                        Victoria</orgName> <reg><country>Canada</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>siemensl@uvic.ca</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Cunningham, Richard</name>
                    <affiliation>Acadia Digital Culture Observatory, <orgName>Acadia University</orgName> <reg><country>Canada</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>richard.cunningham@acadiau.ca</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Duff, Wendy</name>
                    <affiliation>Faculty of Information, <orgName>University of Toronto</orgName> <reg><country>Canada</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>wendy.duff@utoronto.ca</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Warwick, Claire</name>
                    <affiliation>Department of Information Studies, <orgName>University College
                        London</orgName> <reg><country>UK</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>c.warwick@ucl.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-03-30</date>
                <name>NG</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>Besides drawing on content experts, librarians, archivists, developers, programmers,
                managers, and others, many emerging digital projects also pull in disciplinary
                expertise from areas that do not typically work in team environments. To be
                effective, these teams must find processes – some of which are counter to natural
                individually-oriented work habits – that support the larger goals and group-oriented
                work of these digital projects. This paper will explore the similarities and
                differences in approaches within and between members of the Digital Libraries (DL)
                and Digital Humanities (DH) communities by formally documenting the nature of
                collaboration in these teams. The objective is to identify exemplary work patterns
                and larger models of research collaboration that have the potential to strengthen
                this positive aspect of these communities even further, while exploring the key
                differences between them which may limit digital project teams’ efforts. Our work is
                therefore designed to enable those who work in such teams to recognise factors that
                tend to predispose them to success, and perhaps more importantly, to avoid those
                that may lead to problematic interactions, and thus make the project less successful
                than it might otherwise have been.</p>
            <div>
                <head>Context</head>
                <p>Traditionally, research contributions in the humanities field have been felt to
                    be, and documented to be, predominantly solo efforts by academics involving
                    little direct collaboration with others, a model reinforced through doctoral
                    studies and beyond (See, for example, Cuneo 2003; Newell and Swan 2000).
                    However, DL and DH communities are exceptions to this. Given that the nature of
                    digital projects involves computers and a variety of skills and expertise,
                    collaborations in these fields involve individuals within their institutions and
                    with others nationally and internationally. Such collaboration typically must
                    coordinate efforts between academics, undergraduate and graduate students,
                    research assistants, computer programmers and developers, librarians, and other
                    individuals as well as financial and other resources. Further, as more digital
                    projects explore issues of long term sustainability, academics and librarians
                    are likely to enter into more collaborations to ensure this objective
                    (Kretzschmar Jr. and Potter 2009).</p>
                <p>Given this context, some research has been done on the DL and
                    DH (See, for example Liu and Smith 2007; Ruecker and Radzikowska 2008; Siemens
                    2009) communities as separate entities (See, for example
                    Johnson 2009; Liu, Tseng and Huang 2005; Johnson 2005; Siemens et al. 2009b), but little has been done on the
                    interaction between these two communities when in collaboration. Tensions can
                    exist in academic research teams when the members represent different
                    disciplines and approaches to team work (Birnbaum 1979; Fennel and Sandefur
                    1983; Hara et al. 2003). Collaborations can be further complicated when some
                    team members have more experience and training in collaboration than other
                    members, a case which may exist with digital projects involving librarians and
                    archivists, who tend to have more experience, and academics, who have tend to
                    have less. Ultimately, too little is known about how these teams involving DL and
                    DH members collaborate and the types of support needed to ensure project
                    success.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Methods</head>
                <p>This paper is part of a larger project examining research teams within the DH and
                    DL communities, led by a team based in Canada and England (For more details, see
                    Siemens et al. 2009a; Siemens et al. 2009b). It draws upon results from
                    interviews and two surveys of the communities exploring the individuals’
                    experiences in digital project teams. The findings include a description of the
                    communities’ work patterns and relationships and the identification of supports
                    and research preparation required to sustain research teams (as per Marshall and
                    Rossman 1999; McCracken 1988). A total of seven individuals were interviewed and
                    another 69 responded to the two surveys.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Preliminary Findings</head>
                <p>At the time of writing this proposal, final data analysis of the surveys and
                    interviews is being completed. However, some preliminary comparisons between the
                    two communities can be reported.</p>
                <p>As a starting point, similarities exist among DL and DH projects. First, digital
                    projects are being accomplished within teams, albeit relatively small ones, as
                    defined by budget and number of individuals involved. Both communities report
                    that the scale and scope of digital projects require individuals with a variety
                    of skills and expertise. Further, these collaborations tend to operate without
                    formal documentation that outline roles, responsibilities, decision making
                    methods, and conflict resolution mechanisms. The survey and interview
                    respondents from both communities report similar benefits and challenges within
                    their collaborations. Finally, these teams rely heavily on email and
                    face-to-face interaction for their project communications.</p>
                <p>Some interesting differences between DL- and DH-based teams exist and may
                    influence a digital project team’s effectiveness. First, the DL respondents seem
                    to have a greater reliance on email as opposed to face-to-face communications
                    and tend to rate the relative effectiveness of email higher than the DH
                    respondents. Several explanations may be offered for this. According to survey
                    results, DL teams appear more likely to be located within the same institution,
                    which means that casual interpersonal interaction may be more likely to occur
                    between team members than with groups that are geographically dispersed, as many
                    DH teams are. For dispersed teams, meetings need to be more deliberately
                    planned, which may mean a higher consciousness about the importance of this kind
                    of interaction and the necessity to build this into project plans. Also, given
                    that many of the DL teams are within the same organization, team members may be
                    more familiar with each other in advance of a project start, meaning that more
                    communication can be done by email. Less time may need to be spent in formal
                    meetings developing work processes as is the case with those teams whose members
                    may not have worked together on previous projects.</p>
                <p>Second, a greater percentage of respondents (42%) within the DH community
                    indicated that they “enjoyed collaboration” than the DL respondents (18%).
                    Comprising of more academics, the DH community tends to undertake more solitary
                    work, and therefore collaboration may be seen as a welcomed change and may be a
                    deliberate choice that they have made to undertake this type of work. In
                    contrast, team work is more the norm for librarians and archivists, and thus
                    they may feel it is an expected part of their jobs, rather than a choice and
                    welcomed activity. As a result, members of these two communities approach
                    collaboration from two fundamentally different positions, which must be
                    understood from the outset of a digital project in order to reduce challenges
                    and ensure success.</p>
                <p>Further, differences in roles and perceived status may complicate collaboration.
                    Often, tensions may exist between service departments, such as libraries and
                    computer support, and the researcher, who is perceived to have higher status
                    (Warwick 2004). These differences in perceived status can complicate work
                    process as those with lower status may have difficultly directing those with
                    perceived higher status (Hagstrom 1964; Ramsay 2008; Newell and Swan 2000).</p>
                <p>The benefits to the DL and DH communities will be several. First, the study
                    contributes to an explicit description of these communities’ work patterns and
                    inter-relationships. Second, it designed to enable those who work in such teams
                    to recognise factors that tend to predispose them to success, and perhaps more
                    importantly, to avoid those that may lead to problematic interactions, and thus
                    make the project less successful than it might otherwise have been.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Birnbaum, Philip H.</author>
                        <date>1979</date>
                        <title level="a">Research Team Composition and Performance</title>
                        <title level="m">Interdisciplinary Research Groups: Their Management and
                            Organization</title>
                        <editor>Richard T. Barth and Rudy Steck</editor>
                        <publisher>International Research Group on Interdisciplinary
                            Programs</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Vancouver, British Columbia</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Cuneo, Carl</author>
                        <date>November 2003</date>
                        <title level="a">Interdisciplinary Teams - Let's Make Them Work</title>
                        <title level="j">University Affairs</title>
                        <biblScope type="pp">18-21</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Fennel, Mary, and Gary D. Sandefur</author>
                        <date>1983</date>
                        <title level="a">Structural Clarity of Interdisciplinary Teams: A Research
                            Note</title>
                        <title level="j">The Journal of Applied Behavioral Science</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">19.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">193-202</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hagstrom, Warren O.</author>
                        <date>1964</date>
                        <title level="a">Traditional and Modern Forms of Scientific Teamwork</title>
                        <title level="j">Administrative Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">9</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">241-63</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hara, Noriko, et al.</author>
                        <date>2003</date>
                        <title level="a">An Emerging View of Scientific Collaboration: Scientists'
                            Perspectives on Collaboration and Factors That Impact
                            Collaboration</title>
                        <title level="j">Journal of the American Society for Information Science and
                            Technology</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">54.10</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">952-65</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Johnson, Ian M.</author>
                        <date>2005</date>
                        <title level="a">In the Middle of Difficulty Lies Opportunity" - Using a
                            Case Study to Identify Critical Success Factors Contributing to the
                            Initiation of International Collaborative Projects</title>
                        <title level="j">Education for Information</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">23. 1/2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">9-42</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Johnson, Ian M</author>
                        <title level="a">International Collaboration between Schools of
                            Librarianship and Information Studies: Current Issues</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Asia-Pacific Conference on Library &amp;
                            Information Education &amp; Practice</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kretzschmar Jr., William A., and William G. Potter</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Library Collaboration with Large Digital Humanities
                            Projects</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Digital Humanities</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Liu, Jyi-Shane, Mu-Hsi Tseng, and Tze-Kai Huang</author>
                        <date>2005</date>
                        <title level="a">Building Digital Heritage with Teamwork Empowerment</title>
                        <title level="j">Information Technology &amp; Libraries</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">24.3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">130-40</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Liu, Yin, and Jeff Smith</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">Aligning the Agendas of Humanities and Computer Science
                            Research: A Risk/Reward Analysis</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings"> SDH-SEMI</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Marshall, Catherine, and Gretchen B. Rossman</author>
                        <date>1999</date>
                        <title level="m">Designing Qualitative Research</title>
                        
                        <publisher>SAGE Publications</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Thousand Oaks, CA</pubPlace>
                        <edition>3rd edition</edition>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>McCracken, Grant</author>
                        <date>1988</date>
                        <title level="m">The Long Interview. Qualitative Research Methods</title>
                        
                        <publisher>SAGE Publications</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Newbury Park, CA</pubPlace><biblScope type="vol">13</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Newell, Sue, and Jacky Swan</author>
                        <date>2000</date>
                        <title level="a">Trust and Inter-Organizational Networking</title>
                        <title level="j">Human Relations</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">53.10</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">1287-328</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kretzschmar Jr., William A., and William G. Potter</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">Rules of the Order: The Sociology of Large,
                            Multi-Institutional Software Development Projects</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Digital Humanities</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Ruecker, Stan, and Milena Radzikowska</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">The Iterative Design of a Project Charter for
                            Interdisciplinary Research</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">DIS</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Siemens, Lynne</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">It's a Team If You Use &quot;Reply All&quot;: An
                            Exploration of Research Teams in Digital Humanities Environments</title>
                        <title level="j">Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">24.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">225-33</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Siemens, Lynne, et al.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Able to Develop Much Larger and More Ambitious Projects: An
                            Exploration of Digital Projects Teams</title>
                        <title level="m">DigCCurr 2009: Digital Curation: Practice, Promise and
                            Prospects</title>
                        <editor>Helen R. Tibbo, et al.</editor>
                        <publisher>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</publisher>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Siemens, Lynne, et al.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Building Strong E-Book Project Teams: Processes to Maximize
                            Success While Drawing on Essential Academic Disciplinary
                            Expertise</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">BooksOnline &apos;09: 2nd Workshop on
                            Research Advances in Large Digital Book Collections</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Warwick, Claire</author>
                        <title level="a">No Such Thing as Humanities Computing? An Analytical
                            History of Digital Resource Creation and Computing in the
                            Humanities</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Joint International Conference of the
                            Association for Computers and the Humanities and the Association for
                            Literary &amp; Linguistic Computing</title>
                    </bibl>

                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
