<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-697">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letters, Ideas and Information Technology: Using digital corpora of letters
                    to disclose the circulation of knowledge in the 17th century</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Roorda, Dirk</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Data Archiving and Networked Services</orgName>,  <country>Netherlands</country></affiliation>
                    <email>dirk.roorda@dans.knaw.nl</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Bos, Erik-Jan</name>
                    <affiliation>Department of Philosophy, 
                        Utrecht University, Netherlands </affiliation>
                    <email>erik-jan.bos@phil.uu.nl</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>van den Heuvel, Charles</name>
                    <affiliation>Virtual Knowledge Studio,
                        Netherlands</affiliation>
                    <email>charles.vandenheuvel@vks.knaw.nl</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-05-01</date>
                <name>NG</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Circulation of Knowledge and Letters</head>
                <p>The scientific revolution of the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century was driven by
                    countless discoveries in Europe and overseas in the observatory, in the library,
                    in the workshop and in society at large. There was a dramatic increase in the
                    amount of information, giving rise to new knowledge, theories and world images.
                    But how were new elements of knowledge picked up, processed, disseminated and –
                    ultimately – accepted in broad circles of the educated community? A consortium
                    of universities, research institutes and cultural heritage institutions has
                    started a project called CKCC<note>Circulation of Knowledge and Learned
                        Practices in the 17th-century Dutch Republic. A Web-based Humanities’
                        Collaboratory on Correspondences. Participants: Descartes Centre for the
                        History and Philosophy of the Sciences and the Humanities, Utrecht
                        University; National Library of the Netherlands; Huygens Institute, <ptr
                            target="http://www.huygensinstituut.knaw.nl/__eng/"/> (accessed
                        2010-03-19); DANS; Virtual Knowledge Studio. Start date: November 2008.
                        Duration: 4 years. Budget: 1 M€. </note> to meet this research question,
                    building a multidisciplinary collaboratory to analyze a machine-readable and
                    growing corpus of letters of scholars who lived in the 17th-century Dutch
                    Republic. Until the publication of the first scientific journals in the 1660s,
                    letters were by far the most direct and important means of communication between
                    intellectuals. Therefore the 17th-century Republic of Letters offers an ideal
                    case for exploring the answers to this question. </p>
                <p>Researchers want to uncover patterns in letters that are indicative for the
                    circulation of knowledge, patterns that reveal the emergence of complex,
                    collective phenomena in modern science. However, they face some fundamental
                    problems with finding such patterns in letters. One cannot know in advance the
                    nature of these patterns, and only few categorical hypotheses can be tested by
                    simply data mining the letters. Purported patterns cannot be tested against the
                    letters, because the heterogeneous information on which these patterns are based
                    cannot be gleaned from the texts, but need considerable interpretation and
                    contextualization.</p>
                <p>Here is a short list of the problems: (i) the letters are not uniformly
                    available; (ii) the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century language varieties are not
                    standardised and pose a challenge for language technology; (iii) much
                    interpretation is needed to resolve references to people, places, dates, ideas
                    and instruments; interpretations are complicated by the heterogeneity of
                    annotations; (iv) it is not clear how to set up visualisations of patterns that
                    are really informative to the historian of science. These four types of problems
                    will be used to report on the methodology of the project and on its results so
                    far. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Information technology as a humanities’ observatory</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Availability of the Letters</head>
                    <p>CKCC limits itself to the ca. 20,000 letters written by scholars that were
                        active in the Netherlands: René Descartes, Hugo Grotius, Constantijn
                        Huygens, Christiaan Huygens, Caspar Barlaeus, Jan Swammerdam and Anthony van
                        Leeuwenhoek. Modern editions of these correspondences—already published or
                        in an advanced state of production by members of CKCC—form the basis of the
                        digitised texts. The letters, once converted to a minimal TEI format, will
                        then be made available through e-Laborate,<note>e-Laborate, <ptr
                                target="http://www.e-laborate.nl/en/"/> (accessed 2010-03-19),
                            Huygens Instituut.</note> a web-based philological annotation tool that
                        will be transformed into a collaboratory for the history of science and the
                        humanities in general. It serves three purposes: (a) providing scholarly
                        access to the letters; (b) allowing researchers to enrich existing datasets
                        and annotate the letters; (c) using the letters and the input of researchers
                        to visualise patterns meaningful for the circulation of knowledge.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Use of other datasets</head>
                    <p>We will incorporate a particular database of (meta)data, the<hi rend="italic"
                            > Catalogus Epistularum Neerlandaricum</hi> (CEN), or the Catalogue of
                        letters in Dutch repositories. It is a relatively old database, already
                        available via Telnet in the early 1990s, before the world wide web came into
                        being. </p>
                    <p>CEN is an exhaustive database of letters in the collections of five Dutch
                        university libraries, the Royal Library, and four other important libraries.
                        It contains more than 265,000 descriptions of approximately 1,000,000
                        letters, dating from 1600 until the present day (of which ca. 100,000 from
                        the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century). It supplies the following metadata:
                        sender, recipient, place of sending, year, language, repository and shelf
                        mark. </p>
                    <p>The format in which this database will be made available to the project is to
                        be negotiated with the owner, OCLC.<note>Online Computer Library Center,
                                <ptr target="http://www.oclc.org"/> (accessed
                        2010-03-19).</note></p>
                    <p>Usage of this database will enable us to make assertions about the fraction
                        of the selected letters with respect to the total body of letters. Moreover,
                        it allows us to increase the density of the networks we are interested in,
                        leading to unprecedented research opportunities.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Language technology</head>
                    <p>In order to find meaningful patterns in social networks of scholars and in
                        circulation of knowledge language technology is needed. For this, CKCC is
                        cooperating with CLARIN.<note>Common Language Resources and Technology
                            Infrastructure, <ptr target="http://www.clarin.eu/"/> (accessed
                            2010-03-19). CKCC is on the list of supported projects by which CLARIN
                            is reaching out to the humanities, <ptr
                                target="http://www.clarin.eu/wp3/wp3/wp3-documents/call-for-full-proposals-for-collaboration-with-humanities-and-social-sciences"
                            /> (accessed 2010-03-19).</note> The mission of CLARIN is to make
                        language technology interoperable and to make linguistic resources
                        accessible on a European infrastructure, so that all the arts and humanities
                        can make use of it. The Netherlands pillar of CLARIN,
                            CLARIN-NL,<note>CLARIN-NL (Netherlands), <ptr
                                target="http://www.clarin.nl/node/2"/> (accessed 2010-03-19).</note>
                        has already obtained funding for constructing such infrastructure, and has
                        issued a call for proposals for adding existing resources to this
                        infrastructure and writing demonstrator services. Aided by expertise
                        provided by CLARIN members, in particular by the University of
                            Lancaster,<note>University Centre for Computer Corpus Research on
                            Language, <ptr target="http://ucrel.lancs.ac.uk/"/> (accessed
                            2010-03-19), in particular Paul Rayson, <ptr
                                target="http://www.comp.lancs.ac.uk/~paul/"/> (accessed
                            2010-03-19).</note> CKCC is developing such a demonstrator. A proposal
                        to this end has been accepted by CLARIN-NL. The demonstrator, comprising the
                        correspondences of Grotius, Const. Huygens and Descartes (ca. 15,000 letters
                        in all), is planned to be completed by October 2010. It will perform a
                        time-sensitive keyword extraction, which can be visualised by means of a
                        dynamic word cloud. As the source languages are 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                        century Dutch, French and Latin, one needs at least spelling normalisation
                        and harmonisation of keywords across languages.</p>
                </div>
                <div>

                    <head>Interpretation and Enrichment</head>
                    <p>References to people, places and times are often implicit and can only be
                        retrieved by studying contextual material or by using secondary sources.
                        Named Entity Recognisers are helpful, but it is not possible to rely on
                        technology alone. In order to get an accurate picture in sufficient
                        resolution, interplay between manual work and automatic tools is needed. The
                        collaboratory based on e-Laborate gives researchers the opportunity to
                        collect their interpretations of the texts, compare them to others and to
                        annotate them with their insights. Over time, the results of this hand/mind
                        work might be automatically gathered and incorporated in enriched
                        transcriptions of the texts.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Visualisation</head>
                    <p>By offering meaningful visualizations of the data, the CKCC will enable
                        humanities researchers in a wider context to use the tools and the results
                        yielded. Not only the relationships between corresponding authors will be
                        made visible in time and space, but CKCC also aims at visualizing the
                        dynamics of knowledge production by focusing on the emergence of themes in
                        scholarly debates and social networks of 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century
                        natural philosophers.</p>
                    <p>The dynamic word clouds based on keyword extraction is just a first step.
                        CKCC will subsequently explore several approaches of gathering and
                        visualising meaningful patterns, which are deliberately different in nature.
                        The first approach (a) is a sophistication of keyword extraction, and the
                        second one (b) is based on associations in text. Both methods can be used to
                        evaluate the results of each other.</p>
                    <p>(a) Concept analysis. This requires considerable more analysis than keyword
                        extraction. For example: the many surface expressions of a concept must be
                        linked into one entity, preferably part of an ontology or thesaurus.
                        Existing subject indices and reference corpora will be used. Visualising the
                        behaviour of concepts over time will yield a good approximation of knowledge
                        circulation.</p>
                    <p>(b) Associative neural network technology. This is an application of a recent
                        effort, ANNH,<note>Associative Neural Networks for the Humanities. An
                            application developed by the Department of Philosophy (P. Ziche, E.-O.
                            Onnasch, E.-J. Bos), Utrecht University, and Dr. Holthausen GmbH,
                            Bocholt. See (Holthausen et al., 2007).</note> to apply the idea of
                        neural networks to the humanities. This approach enables the automatic
                        comparison of texts, based on the degree of associative similarity. Concepts
                        or themes occurring in the letters could thus be made visible, either by
                        focussing on single terms (e.g. ‘observations’) or word pairs (e.g. ‘soul’
                        and ‘matter’). Moreover, it is possible to query for letters associated to a
                        given one, and rank the results by the degree of association. The facility
                        to track the circulation of knowledge will then be within reach. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>An infrastructure for the digital humanities</head>
                <p>Infrastructure is of particular interest in view of current developments in
                    Europe as testified by the ESFRI roadmap.<note>European Roadmap for Research
                        Infrastructures, <ptr target="http://cordis.europa.eu/esfri/roadmap.htm"/>
                        (accessed 2010-03-19).</note> The roadmap funds the preparation for several
                    research infrastructures in the humanities, among which CLARIN, as demonstrated
                    above, is most relevant for the CKCC project. CKCC will take care that the
                    materials residing in the collaboratory can be exported in such a way that it is
                    available on the CLARIN infrastructure, thus contributing to the much grander
                    vision to have all scholarly letters of the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century
                    uniformly available for research, including the results of related
                        work.<note>Mapping the Republic of letters, <ptr
                            target="http://shc.stanford.edu/collaborations/supported-projects/mapping-republic-letters"
                        /> (accessed 2010-03-19). Cultures of Knowledge, <ptr
                            target="http://www.history.ox.ac.uk/cofk/"/> (accessed
                        2010-03-19).</note></p>
                <p>In due course, CKCC will not only contribute to the understanding of the
                    circulation of knowledge in the 17th century, but also generate useful
                    technologies for cross-disciplinary collaborations involving data-sharing and
                    data-enrichment in the Humanities. As such, this web-based humanities
                    collaboratory on correspondences is a valuable prototype for possible future
                    research collaborations focusing on large, heterogeneous datasets in the
                    Humanities.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Holthausen, K and Ziche, P.</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">Neuronale Netze für die Geisteswissenschaften</title>
                        <title level="j">Akademie Aktuell</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">20</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">32-35</biblScope>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://www.badw.de/aktuell/akademie_aktuell/2007/heft1/10_Holthausen.pdf"
                        />
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
