<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-637">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Detection of Citations and Textual Reuse on Ancient Greek Texts and its
                    Applications in the Classical Studies: eAQUA Project</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Büchler, Marco</name>
                    <affiliation>Natural Language Processing Group, Institute of Mathematics and
                        Computer Science, <orgName>University of Leipzig</orgName>, <country>Germany</country></affiliation>
                    <email>mbuechler@eaqua.net</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Geßner, Annette</name>
                    <affiliation>Ancient Greek Philology Group, Institute of Classical Philology and
                        Comparative Studies, <orgName>University of Leipzig</orgName>, <country>Germany</country></affiliation>
                    <email>agessner@eaqua.net</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Heyer, Gerhard</name>
                    <affiliation>Natural Language Processing Group, Institute of Mathematics and
                        Computer Science, <orgName>University of Leipzig</orgName>, <country>Germany</country></affiliation>
                    <email>gheyer@eaqua.net</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Eckart, Thomas</name>
                    <affiliation>Natural Language Processing Group, Institute of Mathematics and
                        Computer Science, <orgName>University of Leipzig</orgName>, <country>Germany</country></affiliation>
                    <email>teckart@eaqua.net</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-03</date>
                <name>GF</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
           </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                
                <p>&quot;Users of this or any edition are warned that the textual variants presented
                    by citations from Plato in later literature have not yet been as fully
                    investigated as is desirable&quot;. This shortcoming, characterized by Kenneth
                    Dover (Dover, 1980) is still existent and is unlikely to be corrected quickly by
                    traditional research techniques. Textual reuse plays an important role in
                    Classical Studies research. Similar to modern publications, classical authors
                    used the texts of others as sources for their own work. In ancient texts,
                    however, a less stronger form of word by word citation can be observed.
                    Additionally, the complexity of ancient resources disallows fully manual
                    research.</p>
                <p>From a bird&apos;s eye view there are different points of view to the problem of
                    textual reuse implying different research interests (Büchler and Geßner, 2009): <xmt:uList>
                        <item>A <hi rend="bold">Computer Science</hi> perspective focuses on
                            algorithms (<hi rend="italic">technical view</hi>): Which algorithm is
                            better than others? The scope of this research is wide ranging and also
                            relates to plagiarism detection in modern texts like theses at
                            universities (Potthast et al., 2009).</item>
                        <item>A <hi rend="bold">Historian</hi> is interested in more complex
                            correlations (<hi rend="italic">macro view</hi>). For this kind of work
                            a dedicated user interface is necessary to figure out relations between
                            e.g. chapters of a book and their citation usage on a timeline.</item>
                        <item>The research interests of a <hi rend="bold">Classical Philologist</hi>
                            focus on the textual differences between the original text and its
                            variants in citations (<hi rend="italic">micro view</hi>). These varying
                            requirements necessitate designing different user interfaces for these
                            three kinds of researchers.</item>
                    </xmt:uList>
                </p>
                <p>Within the eAQUA project we are investigating the reception of Plato as a case
                    study of textual reuse in ancient Greek texts. Our research is carried out in
                    two steps. On the <hi rend="italic">technical level</hi>, we firstly extract
                    word by word citations. This is achieved by combining syntactical ngram
                    overlappings (Hose, 2009 and Büchler, 2008) and significant terms for several of
                    Plato&apos;s works. In the second step the constraints on syntactic word order
                    are relaxed. This is done by combining text mining and information retrieval
                    techniques. A graph based approach is then introduced that can deal with free
                    word order citations. The key concept is not syntactically based, but focuses on
                    the semantic level to extract the relevant <hi rend="italic">core
                        information</hi> of a used citation. Then the information is represented as
                    a formal graph that is similar to the <hi rend="italic">Lexical Chaining</hi>
                    approach (Waltinger et al. 2008) that is often used for text summarisation (Yu
                    et al. 2007). On the one hand syntactical and semantic approaches are only used
                    to select reuse candidates with a small set of uncommon matching words within a
                    citation. On the other hand, a complete pairwise comparison of all of the nearly
                    5.5 million sentences in the TLG corpus would require approximately 1000 years
                    due to the squared complexity of O(n<hi rend="sup">2</hi>) that was used for
                    example to compare the Dead Sea Scrolls with the Hebrew Bible (Hose, 2009). For
                    this reason, an intelligent pre-clustering of relevant reuse candidates is
                    needed. Such a divide and conquer strategy reduces the complexity dramatically.
                    Whilst the second step only increases the degree of free word order, in the
                    third step the algorithm is expanded by similarly used words like <hi
                        rend="italic">go</hi> and <hi rend="italic">walk</hi>. Those candidates are
                    computed by similar cooccurrence profiles. The three levels briefly described
                    above are only one dimension of reuse exploration. Other relevant dimensions
                    that will be discussed are the <hi rend="italic">degree of preprocessing</hi> as
                    well as the <hi rend="italic">visualisation</hi> of textual reuse in terms of
                    citations. </p>
                <p>In the field of preprocessing the main focus lies on <hi rend="italic"
                        >tokenisation</hi> (more active tokenisation is needed with ancient texts
                    than on modern languages), <hi rend="italic">normalisation</hi> (reducing all
                    words internally to a lower-case representation without diacritics) and <hi
                        rend="italic">lemmatisation</hi> (reducing all words internally to a
                    word&apos;s base form). This dimension can speed up the algorithm and also
                    improves the results for strongly inflected languages like Ancient Greek. </p>
                <p>Leaving the technical point of view of computer scientists, the research of
                    Classicists includes both an application of a <hi rend="italic">macro view</hi>
                    for Historians as well as one for the <hi rend="italic">micro view</hi> of
                    Classical Philologists. The visualisation dimension of textual reuse is
                    important since text mining approaches typically generate a huge amount of data
                    that can&apos;t be explored manually. This is shown in Fig. 1. Whilst the light grey
                    area marks Neoplatonism (about 5. AC) the grey ranges highlight Middle
                    Platonism (about 2. AC). Taking Plato&apos;s <hi rend="italic">Timaeus</hi>, one
                    can clearly identify that both phases of Plato&apos;s reception (see Fig. 1 –
                    top) are based on different &quot;chapters&quot; of <hi rend="italic">Timaeus</hi> (bottom).</p>
                <p>
                    <figure>
                       <graphic url="637_Fig1a.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Fig. 1. Macro view: Screen of an interactive visualisation for citation
                            usage. Citation distribution by Stephanus pages of Plato&apos;s Timaeus.
                            The highest peak of the first picture is strongly correlated with the
                            citation usage of the pages 27 to 42 of the second picture: Neo
                            Platonism.</head>
                        <graphic url="637_Fig1b" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>As Fig. 1 is of stronger interest for Historians, there is also a requirement for
                    a visualisation for researchers from the field of Classical Greek Philology. As
                    shown in Fig. 2, a visualisation highlighting the differences in citation usage
                    is necessary. This is especially important if longer citations are investigated. </p>
                <p>
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="637_Fig2a" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/></figure>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Fig. 2. Micro view: Highlighted differences of citations (green, orange) in
                            relation to original text of Plato (blue). Top: The orange word highlights
                            the same word but including a language evolution of about 10
                            centuries. Bottom: An included word (orange) in
                            the citation is shown.</head>
                        <graphic url="637_Fig2b" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>Additionally, it will be demonstrated how to detect different editions of the
                    same original text. Such completely unsupervised approaches are important to
                    investigate the scientific landscape of text digitisation. Furthermore, the
                    relation to modern plagiarism detection will be given as well as the importance
                    of building modern representative corpora since especially web corpora typically
                    contain several duplicates of the same text. </p>
                <p>In the evaluation section different results related to the comparison of various
                    approaches on several text genres will be shown. An example of those results is
                    given by contrasting citations of Plato&apos;s work with the textual reuse of
                    the Atthidographers. Whilst citations of Plato can be extracted quite well by
                    the syntactical approach even with very low similarity thresholds, the same
                    approach works with an accuracy smaller than 20% for textual reuse of the
                    Atthidographers. </p>
                <p>Finally, results of a still in progress manual evaluation will be presented
                    relating to the question of how and why a passage was cited.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Büchler, M.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="m">Medusa: Performante Textstatistiken auf großen Textmengen:
                            Kookkurrenzanalyse in Theorie und Anwendung</title>
                        <publisher>VDM Verlag Dr. Müller</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Saarbrücken</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Büchler, M. and Geßner, A.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Citation Detection and Textual Reuse on Ancient Greek
                            texts</title>
                        <title level="m">2009 Chicago Colloquium on Digital Humanities and Computer
                            Science</title>
                        <editor>Argamon, S.</editor>
                        <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Dover, K.</author>
                        <date>1980</date>
                        <title level="m">Plato: Symposium</title>
                        <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hose, R.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="m">CS490 Final Report: Investigation of Sentence Level Text Reuse
                            Algorithms</title>
                        <date type="visited">29 October 2009</date>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://www.cs.cornell.edu/BOOM/2004sp/ProjectArch/DeadSea/index.html"
                        />
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Potthast, M., Stein, B., Eiselt, A., Barrón-Cedeño, A. and Rosso,
                            P.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Overview of the 1st International Competition on Plagiarism
                            Detection</title>
                        <title level="m">SEPLN 2009 Workshop on Uncovering Plagiarism, Authorship,
                            and Social Software Misuse (PAN 09)</title>
                        <editor>Stein, B., Rosso, P., Stamatatos, E. Koppel, M. and Agirre,
                            E.</editor>
                        <publisher>CEUR-WS.org</publisher>
                        <biblScope type="pp">1-9</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Waltinger, U., Mehler, A. und Heyer, G.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">Towards Automatic Content Tagging: Enhanced Web Services in
                            Digital Libraries Using Lexical Chaining</title>
                        <title level="m">4th Int. Conf. on Web Information Systems and Technologies
                            (WEBIST '08), 4-7 May, Funchal, Portugal</title>
                        <editor>Cordeiro, J. and Filipe, J. and Hammoudi, S.</editor>
                        <publisher>INSTICC Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Barcelona</pubPlace>
                        <biblScope type="pp">231-236</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Yu L., Ma, J., Ren, F. and Kuroiwa, S.</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">Automatic Text Summarization Based on Lexical Chains and
                            Structural Features</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Eighth ACIS International Conference on
                            Software Engineering, Artificial Intelligence, Networking, and
                            Parallel/Distributed Computing (SNPD 2007)</title>
                       
                        <biblScope type="vol">2</biblScope> <biblScope type="pp">574-578</biblScope>
                        
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
