<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<teiCorpus xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-673">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Networks of Stories, Structures and Digital Humanities</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Akdag Salah, Almila</name>
                    <affiliation>KNAW <orgName>Royal Netherlands Academy of Arts and Sciences</orgName>,
                        <country>Netherlands</country></affiliation>
                    <email>almila.akdagsalah@vks.knaw.nl </email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>De Nooy, Wouter</name>
                    <affiliation>UVA, Faculty of Social and Behavioral Sciences,
                        <reg><orgName>University of Amsterdam</orgName></reg>
                        <country>Netherlands</country></affiliation>
                    <email>w.denooy@uva.nl</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Borovsky, Zoe</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>UCLA</orgName>, ATS, LA, <country>USA</country></affiliation>
                    <email>zoe@ats.ucla.edu</email>
                </author>


            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2009-04-29</date>
                <name>JL</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <TEI>
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title/>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College
                        London</publisher>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>

        <text>
            <body>
                <div>
                    <p>In March 2004, Slashdot, the online news aggregator 'for nerds', cited a web
                        page featuring animated network visualizations of the relationships between
                        characters in Shakespeare’s plays.<note><ptr
                                target="http://www.jibble.org/shakespeare/"/></note> The Shakespeare
                        site began getting hits at a rate of 250,000 hits per hour. Programmer Paul
                        Mutton created the diagrams by feeding Shakespeare’s plays into an IRC
                        (Internet Relay Chat) bot designed to visualize social networks. The
                        Slashdot story promised that the diagrams would allow users to “see
                        Shakespeare in an entirely new light”.<note>
                            <ptr
                                target="http://tech.slashdot.org/story/04/03/11/0151256/Tracking-Social-Networking-In-Shakespeare-Plays?art_pos=24"
                            /> Mutton also presented his work at a conference on Information
                            Visualization in 2004. See <ptr
                                target="http://www.cs.kent.ac.uk/pubs/2004/1931/content.pdf"
                            /></note>
                    </p>
                    <p>Social network analysis, the mapping of relationships as networks, has truly
                        provided new insights in the social and life sciences with increasing
                        participation from mathematicians and computer scientists. The idea that
                        there are laws that govern networks--such as the notion that everyone is at
                        most six steps away from any other person on earth, and that networks evolve
                        in predictable ways--has led to remarkable discoveries in fields from
                        sociology to biology. These insights furthered publications such as Six
                        Degrees (by sociologist Duncan Watts)<note>Watts, D.J. (2003). Six Degrees:
                            The Science of a Connected Age 1st ed., W. W. Norton &amp;
                            Company</note> presenting these discoveries (and the science behind
                        them) to a more general audience. In addition, online communities such as
                        Facebook, Twitter, MySpace, etc., have demonstrated the utility and power of
                        network theory in our daily lives.</p>
                    <p>With popular awareness of these tools and techniques, combined with the
                        promise of new insights into ever-increasing amounts of data, network
                        analysis has significant appeal to digital humanities scholars. However,
                        these investigations call for tools and software to gather and clean large
                        amounts of data, even when the researcher opts for analyzing only a tiny
                        fraction of these vast data sets. Moreover, to interpret these datasets, a
                        good understanding of network analysis, as well as other visualization means
                        is necessary. Overcoming the hurdle of handling complicated technological
                        tools and acquisition of the necessary expertise in network theory both
                        demand investment on the side of researchers, a risky investment that only a
                        handful of humanities scholars are willing to make.<note>Social network
                            analysis is a more popular tool among social scientist then humanities
                            scholars. A search at Web of Science for the search term returns around
                            150 hits for social sciences, whereas if the search is refined to arts
                            and humanities only, it has less than 30 results.</note> Typically,
                        researchers familiar with the tools perform these analyses, posing the
                        questions and interpreting the results. In this session, we will first
                        provide a brief overview of social network analysis and related tools. Then,
                        we will focus on three examples of how we, as humanities scholars, have made
                        use of network analysis tools and techniques in our research, both to
                        illustrate the potential of these approaches, and to discuss some common
                        problems and their possible solutions.</p>
                    <p>The names and affiliation of confirmed authors are as follows: <xmt:uList>
                            <item>Zoe Borovsky, Academic Technology Services and the Center for
                                Digital Humanities, University of California, Los Angeles</item>
                            <item>Wouter de Nooy, Amsterdam School of Communication Research
                                (ASCoR), University of Amsterdam, The Netherlands </item>
                            <item>Loet Leydesdorff, Amsterdam School of Communication Research
                                (ASCoR), University of Amsterdam, The Netherlands</item>
                            <item>Andrea Scharnhorst, Virtual Knowledge Studio of the Netherlands
                                Royal Academy of Arts and Sciences, The Netherlands</item>
                            <item>Almila Akdag Salah, Virtual Knowledge Studio of the Netherlands
                                Royal Academy of Arts and Sciences, The Netherlands</item>
                        </xmt:uList></p>
                </div>
            </body>
        </text>

    </TEI>

</teiCorpus>
