<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-626">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Specimen Case and the Garden: Preserving Complex Digital Objects,
                    Sustaining Digital Projects </title>
                <author>
                    <name>Schlosser, Melanie</name>
                    <affiliation>University Libraries, <orgName>The Ohio State University</orgName> <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>schlosser.40@osu.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Ulman, H. Lewis</name>
                    <affiliation>Department of English, <orgName>The Ohio State University</orgName> <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>ulman.1@osu.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-03-19</date>
                <name>GF</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>In a recent article entitled &quot;Innkeeper at the Roach Motel&quot;, Dorothea
                    Salo worries that focusing exclusively on preservation when designing
                    institutional repositories leads to a situation in which documents are placed
                    into repositories but never come out (Salo 2009). In this conceit, a
                    &quot;live&quot; project gets placed in a repository and &quot;dies&quot; from
                    lack of use. However, when attempting to preserve distributed, dynamic
                    electronic textual editions, a somewhat different metaphor is needed. Like items
                    in a specimen case, &quot;live&quot; digital projects must be &quot;killed&quot;
                    before they are added to a conventional institutional repository such as DSpace.
                    In such applications, they must be removed from the dynamic ecology of their
                    production environments (the garden of our title) and frozen in a snapshot form
                    that is substantially different in appearance and functionality. In our
                    presentation, we will outline our own efforts to construct a preservation and
                    sustainability plan for a multi-format, distributed, dynamic electronic textual
                    edition that involves both the creation of a preservation &quot;specimen&quot;
                    and the careful tending of the edition in the &quot;garden&quot;. We will also
                    share the general tools and workflows developed by the project that can help
                    others tackle the same challenges.</p>
                <p>Due to their innovative nature and the environments in which they are created,
                    Digital Humanities projects are often dynamic and distributed. In other words,
                    they often exist in multiple parts maintained on distributed hardware (which
                    itself is supported by multiple organizations), and are often compiled for
                    viewing on the fly in response to readers&apos; actions. The typical
                    preservation strategy of frequent offsite backups is inadequate for these
                    projects. The user or manager must to be able to find the backups (including all
                    of the constituent parts of a complex project, wherever they reside) and
                    recognize what they are; the backups must be in usable condition; and their
                    contents need to be understandable to the people who want to use them. Moreover,
                    if backup files are to be used in any way similar to their original use, the
                    files must be (1) compatible with current hardware and software, (2) translated
                    into formats that are compatible with current hardware and software, or (3) used
                    on reconstructed or emulated hardware and software that match the environment in
                    which the project was originally developed.</p>
                <p>Digital Humanities projects created by faculty often have the added vulnerability
                    of relying on the creator&apos;s university computing accounts. Absent special
                    accommodations, these accounts usually expire on a set schedule once the
                    individual has moved on, taking with them information that often exists nowhere
                    else. </p>
            <div>
                <head>Cultures of Preservation</head>
                <p>In short, digital materials require a culture of description, preservation, and
                    access every bit as robust as the practices and institutions that allow us to
                    preserve manuscript and print materials. The devil of preservation — whether of
                    print, digital, or other material artifacts — lies in the details of production,
                    use, description, storage, conservation, and access. This holds true whether we
                    are talking about acidic paper disintegrating on library shelves, digital files
                    in obsolete formats, or media spread across computer systems whose links to one
                    another have been broken. Preservation is further complicated by the distinction
                    between preserving physical artifacts (books, manuscripts, floppy disks, flash
                    drives) and preserving the information contained on those media in a useful
                    format. </p>
                <p>&quot;The Specimen Case and the Garden: Preserving Complex Digital Objects,
                    Sustaining Digital Projects&quot; focuses on the preservation challenges posed
                    by complex digital humanities projects, which present unique challenges to
                    libraries and repositories charged with accessioning, describing, and preserving
                    the scholarly record. Our work, funded by the U. S. National Endowment for the
                    Humanities, takes a two-pronged approach to the problem, developing technologies
                    for preserving digital <hi rend="italic">objects</hi> — and the relationships
                    among them — that constitute complex projects, and establishing institutional
                    structures for sustaining digital humanities <hi rend="italic">projects</hi>
                    after their creators are no longer actively involved in their development and
                    maintenance. Over the course of more than a year, we have interviewed faculty
                    involved in digital humanities projects, library professionals, and information
                    technology professionals; assessed the need for new practices adapted to digital
                    preservation at our institution; and documented the resources and workflows
                    currently available for, or adaptable to, long-term preservation of digital
                    objects. We have also begun to develop tools, institutional structures, and
                    workflows for describing and archiving complex digital objects, as well as
                    sustaining distributed digital production environments.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Preservation and Sustainability Tools and Workflows</head>
                <p>Our presentation will outline the problems associated with preserving and
                    sustaining complex digital projects, review the data we collected during our
                    interviews, literature review, and environment scan, and share the tools that we
                    have developed, including the following: <xmt:uList>
                        <item>a lifecycle map of complex digital projects that represents
                            development and preservation milestones as interactions among scholars,
                            library professionals, and IT professionals;</item>
                        <item>a visual content manifest for complex digital projects that represents
                            assets, the hardware on which those assets rely, and entities that
                            enable the collaborative work of developing and preserving digital
                            humanities projects;</item>
                        <item>a Metadata Encoding and Transmission Standard (METS) profile for
                            creating archival packages of complex digital projects;</item>
                        <item>a visual representation of the roles of the scholars, library
                            professionals, and IT professionals on our campus in the long-term
                            preservation of digital humanities projects;</item>
                        <item>a proposal for a Digital Humanities Network that could sustain
                            selected distributed digital projects, without requiring that they
                            sacrifice functionality for centralization.</item>
                    </xmt:uList>
                </p>
                <p>Some of these tools and workflows will be easier to adapt to different projects,
                    institutions, and cultural settings than others: for example, any library system
                    should be able to adapt the METS profile to their needs, while our proposed
                    Digital Humanities Network will serve mostly as a heuristic. Indeed, we hope to
                    initiate a fruitful conversation about how to build cultures of preservation for
                    complex digital projects among scholars, librarians, and IT professionals in a
                    variety of institutional settings.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Blue Ribbon Task Force on Sustainable Digital Preservation and
                            Access</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">Sustaining the Digital Investment: Issues and Challenges of
                            Economically Sustainable Digital Preservation</title>
                        <ptr target="http://www.citeulike.org/user/AlisonBabeu/article/3801593"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Cundiff, M. V.</author>
                        <date>2004</date>
                        <title level="a">An Introduction to the Metadata Encoding and Transmission
                            Standard (METS)</title>
                        <title level="j">Library Hi Tech</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">22.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">52-64</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Dobreva, M.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="m">Digitisation of Special Collections: Mapping, Assessment,
                            Prioritisation, Final Report</title>
                        <publisher>Centre for Digital Library Research (CDLR)</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>University of Strathclyde</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Knight, G.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="m">SHERPA Digital Preservation 2: Developing Services for
                            Archiving and Preservation in a Distributed Environment, Final
                            Report</title>
                        <publisher>JISC; Centre for e-Research, King's College London</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>The Library of Congress</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <ptr target="http://www.loc.gov/standards/mets/mets-home.html"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Maron, N. L., Smith, K. K., and Loy, M.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="m">Sustaining Digital Resources: An on-the-Ground View of
                            Projects Today</title>
                        <publisher>Ithaka Case Studies in Sustainability</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>London: JISC</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Rieger, O. Y., and Kehoe, B.</author>
                        <date>DATE</date>
                        <title level="a">Enduring Access to Digitized Books: Organizational and
                            Technical Framework</title>
                        <title level="m">The Fifth International Conference on Preservation of
                            Digital Objects. Joined Up and Working: Tools and Methods for Digital
                            Preservation</title>
                        <editor>Farqhar, Adams</editor>
                        <publisher>The British Library</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                       
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Robertson, R. J., Mahey, M., and Allinson, J.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="m">An Ecological Approach to Repository and Service
                            Interactions</title>
                        <publisher>JISC Centre for Educational Technology &amp; Interoperability
                            Standards</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Strathclyde, Scotland</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Salo, D.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">Innkeeper at the Roach Motel</title>
                        <title level="j">Library Trends</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">57</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">2</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Skinner, K., and M. Halbert (eds)</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="m">Strategies for Sustaining Digital Libraries</title>
                        <publisher>Emory University</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Atlanta, GA</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Thompson, D.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">Archiving Web Resources</title>
                        <title level="m">DCC Digital Curation Manual</title>
                        <editor>Ross, S. and Day, M.</editor>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
