<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<teiCorpus xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-673">
    
    <TEI>
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title>Network analysis of story structure</title>
                    <author>
                        <name>de Nooy, Wouter</name>
                        <affiliation>Amsterdam School of Communication Research (ASCoR), University
                            of Amsterdam, The Netherlands</affiliation>
                        <email>w.denooy@uva.nl</email>
                    </author>

                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College
                        London</publisher>
                    <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change>
                    <date>2009-04-30</date>
                    <name>JL</name>
                    <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <body>
                <div>
                    <head/>
                    <p> Relations and structure play an important role in the humanities. Language
                        is structured at the word, sentence, text levels, and beyond. Literary texts
                        contain implicit references to one another and artists are linked by lines
                        of influence or artistic descent. In some branches of structuralism, meaning
                        is inextricably intertwined with the relations among linguistic elements
                        (signifiers). In this paper, I extend the idea that structure is the carrier
                        of meaning to stories. I submit that story structure conveys meaning.
                        Patterns of interactions among the characters of a story are meaningful in
                        the sense that they represent roles with moral connotations.</p>
                    <p>Structure quickly becomes complex if the number of elements and relations
                        increases. Then, network analysis is an indispensable tool. In a network,
                        entities such as characters in a story are represented by nodes (vertices)
                        and lines embody links between these characters. There is no limitation to
                        the kinds of links that can be represented by lines as long as each link
                        connects two entities. Durable ties, for example, family relations among
                        characters, can be expressed in this way just as easily as incidental events
                        or interactions. Lines can be symmetric, for example, being siblings, or
                        asymmetric, such as an action from one character directed towards another
                        character in the story. Lines can have attributes and they can be of
                        different kinds, for example, positive versus negative lines (this is called
                        a signed network). Finally, each line can be time-stamped to indicate the
                        onset and expiration of ties. With this formalization of structure as a
                        network, we can use computers to quickly and correctly identify structural
                        patterns. Software that is able to analyze large and complicated networks is
                        widely available.</p>
                    <p> If network analysis yields a tool for finding patterns, does it also tell us
                        which patterns to look for? In an analysis of story structure understood as
                        the interactions among characters, it makes sense to borrow from the
                        tradition of social network analysis. In this paper, I use the theory of
                        structural balance, which originated in (social) psychology and was adopted
                        in social network analysis. Based on simple premises like ‘the friend of my
                        friend is my friend,’ this theory predicts that people favour balanced
                        networks. A network is balanced if the positive (friendship) and negative
                        (antagonism) ties display specific, easily recognizable patterns.</p>
                    <p> Balance theory has been applied to the affective ties among characters in
                        stories: tales, opera, and movies. The general finding is that balance among
                        the story’s protagonists is restored at a story’s resolution. Stories
                        develop from unbalanced towards balanced networks. In this paper, I focus
                        on another important role of time. I show that the time order and direction
                        of positive and negative actions between two protagonists defines the roles
                        they play in the story. I use the seminal work of Vladímir Propp—Morphology
                        of the Folktale (1928)—which inspired most of the later work on story
                        grammars and narratology. Propp offers a concise set of propositions on the
                        basic form and plot of a corpus of Russian fairytales, distinguishing
                        between several roles of protagonists, such as the hero, the villain, and
                        the donor. I demonstrate that each role is associated with a unique sequence
                        of positive and negative actions. In other words, one can tell a fairytale
                        character’s role from the interaction sequence it is involved in.</p>
                    <p> A formal focus on structure, which is needed for computerized network
                        analysis, entails that attributes of the characters, such as a hut on
                        chicken legs indicating that a character is a witch, and detailed content of
                        interactions are not taken into account. Instead, the focus is on an
                        abstract schema that can be fleshed out in any number of ways in a story.
                        Notwithstanding their abstract character, I contend that the schemata have
                        moral implications. Attacking the story’s hero out of the blue, which is a
                        characteristic of the structural pattern associated with the villain, has a
                        negative moral connotation, which is also linked to the last step in the
                        villain’s structural pattern, namely that the villain is defeated by the
                        hero at the end of the story. Undesirable properties of the villain, such as
                        ugliness, may help to reinforce the moral depreciation of the role but they
                        are not essential to it.</p>
                    <p>Tales and other stories socialize children into a culture of appreciating
                        some sequences of interaction and depreciating other sequences. Authors may
                        play with these conventions by combining structural role patterns with
                        attributes of the character that are usually associated with other roles. In
                        a more fundamental way, authors may turn structural patterns upside down,
                        for example, a woman accepting to live with the man who raped her (a typical
                        villain role) in Coetzee’s Disgrace or the protagonist in Houellebecq’s
                        Elementary Particles, who turns his back on his most important ‘donor.’
                        Fairy tale structure is probably quite straightforward in comparison to
                        stories read by adults. A systematic analysis of more complicated stories
                        requires formal network analysis and so does the detection of conventional
                        role patterns in sets of stories, differences in this regard between story
                        genres, and development over time.</p>
                    <p> If the role patterns in stories are instruments of socialization, we may
                        expect to find them in real-life interactions. Because role patterns and
                        network analysis are purely structural, it is straightforward to compare the
                        structure of interactions within stories to interactions among humans. In
                        this paper, I will apply network analysis to evaluations among a set of
                        literary authors and critics to show that fairytale roles can be
                        distinguished and help to explain what happens. In this way, the social
                        sciences benefit from the analysis of story structure just like social
                        theory and social network analysis may advance the analysis of story
                        structure.</p>
                </div>

            </body>

        </text>
    </TEI>

</teiCorpus>
