<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<teiCorpus xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-630">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Origins and Current State of Digitization of Humanities in Japan</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Muller, A. Charles</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of Tokyo</orgName> <reg><country>Japan</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>acmuller@jj.em-net.ne.jp</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Hachimura, Kōzaburō</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Ritsumeikan University</orgName> <reg><country>Japan</country></reg></affiliation>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Hara, Shoichiro</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Kyoto University</orgName> <reg><country>Japan</country></reg></affiliation>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Ogiso, Toshinobu</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>National Institute for Japanese Language and
                        Linguistics</orgName> <reg><country>Japan</country></reg></affiliation>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Aida, Mitsuru</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>National Institute for Japanese Literature</orgName> <reg><country>Japan</country></reg></affiliation>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Yasuoka, Koichi</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Kyoto University</orgName> <reg><country>Japan</country></reg></affiliation>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Akama, Ryo</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Ritsumeikan University</orgName> <reg><country>Japan</country></reg></affiliation>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Shimoda, Masahiro</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of Tokyo</orgName> <reg><country>Japan</country></reg></affiliation>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Tabata, Tomoji</name>
                    <affiliation>University of Osaka <reg><orgName>Osaka University</orgName></reg> <reg><country>Japan</country></reg></affiliation>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Nagasaki, Kiyonori</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>International Institute for Digital Humanities</orgName> <reg><country>Japan</country></reg></affiliation>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-27</date>
                <name>GF</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <TEI>
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title/>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College
                        London</publisher>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <body>
                <div>
                    <p>Digital Humanities in Japan has been in progress since an early period.
                        Recently, due to the spread and the development of advanced digital
                        environments, individual humanities researchers are coming to use digital
                        materials in various forms, and according to the continually growing needs
                        of users, cooperation and organization between projects has steadily
                        increased. However, there is some extent to which the large framework known
                        Humanities Computing in Japan has lagged behind in its efforts to develop
                        cooperation with similar projects overseas. Therefore, this panel aims to
                        take a step in the right direction by introducing the origins and current
                        state of Humanities Computing in Japan on digitization by featuring the
                        reflections of the representatives of the projects and organizations that
                        have worked in this area from a relatively early time. </p>
                    <p>Humanities digitization projects in Japan, being developed by various
                        research centers and research organizations, have already garnered over 3.5
                        billion yen in the form of known large-scale grants which were funded by
                        Japanese Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology.
                        This does not include the numerous small grants that have been received for
                        various digitization projects by individual researchers and small groups and
                        budgets which were assigned by each organization itself which was promoting
                        such projects. In order to provide a venue for the presentation and
                        publication of the results of these funded projects, a number of groups and
                        associations engaged in this work were established. One of the more
                        prominent is Special Interest Group for Computers and Humanities (SIG-CH),
                        which was established in 1989 under the auspices of the Information
                        Processing Society of Japan which is the largest society of informatics in
                        Japan. SIG-CH has served as the major organ for communication among
                        researchers interested in these projects. </p>
                </div>
            </body>
        </text>
    </TEI>
    <TEI>
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title>Kōzaburō Hachimura, Ritsumeikan University, representing SIG-CH</title>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College
                        London</publisher>
                    <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <body>
                <div>
                    <p>The meetings of SIG-CH have been held on a regular basis, about four times a
                        year since 1989. At each meeting approximately 8 research papers are
                        presented, with the proceedings being been published as the “IPSJ SIG Notes”
                        series. Up to the present, we have held 84 meetings, which have included a
                        total of 720 paper presentations. The group consists of over 200 researchers
                        belonging to the academic organizations of informatics or humanities. </p>
                    <p>Here, processing, analysis or mining of texts, images, digital archiving of
                        texts, bibliographies or other digitized materials, and especially 3-D
                        motion capture, etc. are the major themes. The technique, tools or study
                        results in which they are applied etc. are presented. In recent years, study
                        results that use GIS have been increasing in number. The various Humanities
                        fields in Japan are represented by literature, linguistics, history,
                        archeology, museum studies, anthropology, dance studies, and Buddhist
                        Studies, etc. In earlier periods, system-oriented thought was dominant, but
                        recently, presentations tend to be characterized by an increase in content
                        orientation, as well as on local and international cooperation between
                        projects. </p>
                </div>
            </body>
        </text>
    </TEI>
    <TEI>
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title>Toshinobu Ogiso, representing the National Institute for Japanese
                        Language and Linguistics NINJAL)</title>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College
                        London</publisher>
                    <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <body>
                <div>
                    <p>NINJAL, established in 1948, has created various Japanese corpora. One
                        example is the &quot;<hi rend="italic">Taiyō</hi> Corpus,&quot; which is the
                        first major Humanities database in Japan created using XML. It is a
                        tag-structure rendition of the 19-20th century magazine <hi rend="italic"
                            >Taiyō</hi>, in which tags created for the purpose of linguistic
                        research applied to about 14.5 million text characters. <hi rend="italic"
                            >Taiyō</hi> was a typical magazine in Japan during the period of its
                        publication from 1895 to 1925, and thus is an invaluable resource for
                        understanding the foundations of the modern Japanese language which were
                        formed during that period. </p>
                    <p>Also underway at this institute is the KOTONOHA plan, which seeks to
                        integrate various corpora (including the <hi rend="italic">Taiyō</hi>
                        corpus). One part of this effort is the presently-underway project of the
                        &apos;Balanced Contemporary Corpus of Written Japanese&apos; (BCCWJ),
                        containing 100 million words. In addition to this, the construction of a
                        corpus is planned aimed at compiling premodern data. This project must
                        especially address the peculiarities of written Japanese, which does not
                        include spaces between words, and includes Chinese characters, <hi
                            rend="italic">hiragana</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">katakana</hi>, making
                        it very difficult to indicate word information with pauses between phrases,
                        parts of speech, etc. </p>
                </div>
            </body>
        </text>
    </TEI>
    <TEI>
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title>Mitsuru Aida, representing the National Institute for Japanese Literature
                        (NIJL)</title>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College
                        London</publisher>
                    <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <body>
                <div>
                    <p>NIJL was established in 1972, making one of the earliest efforts to digitize
                        Japanese literature. Researchers there have worked at converting the
                        research information into database format, and in its inclusion of words,
                        text descriptions, and literary indexes, has become Japan&apos;s prototype
                        textual research database. In the early 1990&apos;s, NIJL defined an
                        original standard for tagging Japanese literatures based on SGML, and upon
                        this built a large full-text database. It has played a major role as the
                        mechanism for a general database of the human culture research. </p>
                </div>
            </body>
        </text>
    </TEI>
    <TEI>
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title>Koichi Yasuoka, Kyoto University, Institute for Humanities Research (Jinbunken)</title>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College
                        London</publisher>
                    <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <body>
                <div>
                    <p>In 1980 the Jinbunken began the digitization of the <hi rend="italic">Ming
                            Dynasty Civil Examination Index</hi>. The following year, the institute
                        initiated the digitization of the <hi rend="italic">Index of Shanwen
                            Liyi</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Catalog for the Study of East Asian
                            Documents</hi>. Moreover, the Institute has held an Annual Workshop for
                        Oriental Studies Computing (ORICOM) every year in 1990. The research
                        conducted here for the past 20 years extends to many areas, including
                        multilingual text processing, character-code issues, digital catalogs, and
                        GIS. Most notably, the Jinbunken has been actively engaged in critique and
                        development of Japanese <hi rend="italic">kanji</hi> character sets, dealing
                        with issues concerning the relationship between ancient characters, JIS X
                        0213, Unicode and so forth. </p>
                </div>
            </body>
        </text>
    </TEI>
    <TEI>
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title>Ryo Akama, representing the Ritsumeikan University Art Research Center
                        (ARC)</title>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College
                        London</publisher>
                    <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <body>
                <div>
                    <p>The extensive works of ARC have their origins in the digitization of the <hi
                            rend="italic">kabuki</hi> material that Prof. Akama initiated in the
                        Waseda University Theater Museum in 1988. This approach led to the
                        establishment of the ARC in 1998. The ARC has worked on the digitization of
                        various material and intangible Japanese cultural treasures through the aid
                        of the Ministry of Education. The research is carried out making good use of
                        various information technology skills, which include not only text and
                        images, but also 3D images and motion capture, etc. At present, they have
                        received a Global COE grant from the Ministry of Education, whereby they are
                        serving as a base for Digital Humanities intended for Japanese culture as a
                        whole. </p>
                </div>
            </body>
        </text>
    </TEI>
    <TEI>
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title>Masahiro Shimoda, representing The University of Tokyo Center for
                        Evolving Humanities (CEH)</title>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College
                        London</publisher>
                    <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <body>
                <div>
                    <p>One of the major aims of the CEH is, along with the development of its own
                        Buddhist texts information system, to bring about cooperation with a wide
                        range of digital projects related to the study of Indian Philosophy and
                        Buddhism, and in so doing, to demonstrate a solid example of the
                        possibilities of digital humanities studies to the Japanese academic world.
                        The project includes the development of an extensive bibliographical
                        database for the field of Buddhist Studies in Japan, which now includes
                        about 70,000 entries. In addition, the Daizōkyō Text Database Research
                        Committee, established in 1994, has completed and released a set of highly
                        accurate text data of 600MB, covering the major portion of the East Asian
                        Buddhist canon. This is known as the SAT Database, which is now fully
                        interactive with the above mentioned article database, as well as the online
                        reference work, the <hi rend="italic">Digital Dictionary of Buddhism</hi>.
                        The project is working toward further expansion of cooperation with other
                        data bases in the field. </p>
                </div>
            </body>
        </text>
    </TEI>
    <TEI>
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title>Conclusion</title>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College
                        London</publisher>
                    <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <body>
                <div>
                    <p>The projects represented here constitute only a very small portion of what is
                        going on in Japan. For example, on the educational front, the Faculty of
                        Culture and Information Science of Doshisha University, established in 2005,
                        is aiming to teach methods of research for the analysis of cultural
                        information at both the undergraduate and graduate levels, and in the future
                        is expected to be a major source for the development of talented researchers
                        in the digitization of humanities. A few decades have now passed for
                        Humanities Computing in Japan, and a wealth of data, tools, and techniques
                        have been produced as a result. We are convinced that this panel we be an
                        important step for locating digitization of humanities in Japan in the flow
                        of worldwide Digital Humanities, and in charting our own future. </p>
                </div>
            </body>
        </text>
    </TEI>
</teiCorpus>
