<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-696">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Digital Mediation of Modernist Literary Texts and their Documents</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Byron, Mark</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of Sydney</orgName>
                        <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>mark.byron@sydney.edu.au</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-03-22</date>
                <name>NG</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>This paper will demonstrate an advanced work in progress, the digitised manuscript
                and transcription of Samuel Beckett’s novel <hi rend="italic">Watt</hi> (composed in
                1941-45 and first published in 1953). Discussion of the project will centre upon the
                digital resources buttressing the presentation of manuscript material and a range of
                related analytic features, and will outline some of the more significant ways in
                which specifically digital treatment of the material opens up new lines of literary
                and textual analysis. Indeed, some foundational concepts of textuality come into
                sharp focus by virtue of digital treatment of textual materials. Some of these
                concerns will be illustrated by way of examples taken from the <hi rend="italic"
                    >Watt</hi> project, and by a fuller view of the complex relationship between
                text and manuscript arising from the project.</p>
            <div>
                <head>SBDMP and the Digitised Edition of the <hi rend="italic">Watt</hi>
                    Notebooks</head>
                <p>The digital and scholarly resources required to produce a digitised literary
                    transcription are not trivial. Two related questions must frame any such
                    project: what scholarly need is being met by the production of such an edition?
                    What specific innovations are made available by virtue of its digital
                    delivery?</p>
                <p>The digital transcription of Beckett’s <hi rend="italic">Watt</hi> is an
                    instalment of a larger international project – the Samuel Beckett Digital
                    Manuscript Project – which aims to have all of Beckett’s literary manuscripts
                    transcribed and represented in digital form. This initiative responds to a
                    profound deepening of scholarly interest in modernist manuscripts as potential
                    sources of literary hermeneutic attention, and in concert with this focal shift,
                    a renewed interest in theories of textuality and textual criticism. The specific
                    (and heightened) relevance to this particular text in Beckett’s oeuvre is
                    immediately apparent on viewing the complex series of heavily revised and
                    illustrated notebooks that constitute the manuscript of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Watt</hi>. The primary materials do not lend themselves easily to
                    conventional print publication, and indeed several dominant textual features
                    would be lost or deeply submerged within any codex structure. For example, the
                    relationships between dispersed narrative episodes and fragments within the
                    manuscripts cannot be represented adequately in the linear structure of the
                    codex, nor the complex patterns of transmitted, dispersed and submerged material
                    between the manuscript and the published editions of <hi rend="italic"
                    >Watt</hi>.</p>
                <p>Of all of Beckett’s major texts, <hi rend="italic">Watt</hi> has received the
                    least critical attention, despite significant scholarly curiosity regarding the
                    deep ambiguity of the published narrative and the baroque nature of its
                    manuscript archive.<note>J. M. Coetzee described the <hi rend="italic">Watt</hi>
                        manuscript material and hypothesised its stages of composition in his PhD
                        dissertation over thirty years ago at the University of Texas at Austin. An
                        epitome of this description and analysis was published in his essay,
                        &quot;The Manuscript Revisions of Beckett's <hi rend="italic"
                        >Watt</hi>,&quot; <hi rend="italic">JML</hi> 2.4 (1972): 472-480. Other
                        discussions include: Sighle Kennedy, &quot;‘Astride of the Grave and a
                        Difficult Birth’: Samuel Beckett’s <hi rend="italic">Watt</hi> Struggles to
                        Life,&quot; <hi rend="italic">Dalhousie French Studies</hi> 42 (1998):
                        115-147; David Hayman, &quot;Beckett's <hi rend="italic">Watt</hi> – the
                        Graphic Accompaniment: Marginalia in the Manuscripts,&quot; <hi
                            rend="italic">Word &amp; Imag</hi>e 13.2 (1997): 172-182 and &quot;Nor
                        Do My Doodles More Sagaciously: Beckett Illustrating <hi rend="italic"
                            >Watt</hi>,&quot; in Lois Oppenheim, ed., <hi rend="italic">Samuel
                            Beckett and the Arts: Music, Visual Arts, and Non-Print Media</hi> (New
                        York and London: Garland, 1999), pp. 199-215; and John Pilling,
                        &quot;Beckett’s English Fiction,&quot; in Pilling, ed., <hi rend="italic"
                            >The Cambridge Companion to Beckett</hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge UP,
                        1994), pp. 17-42.</note> One reason for this oversight pertains directly to
                    the digitised manuscript project: the materials extend to nearly a thousand
                    pages of autograph manuscript in Beckett’s notoriously difficult hand. Few
                    scholars have read any of the primary materials, and only a very few have read
                    them completely. The well-known hermeneutic difficulties presented by the
                    published narrative are thus in no way adequately understood in relation to the
                    primary materials, because they themselves constitute a kind of <hi
                        rend="italic">terra nullius</hi>. By representing and transcribing the
                    manuscript archive of this pivotal text in digital form, such relations between
                    the archive and publication can begin to proceed in an informed way, and more
                    adequate editorial and hermeneutic strategies can be brought to bear on this
                    most inscrutable of Beckett’s texts.</p>
                <p>The difficulties of reading Beckett’s manuscript and text are, in part,
                    aesthetic. The manuscript was composed during the Second World War, when its
                    author was displaced in the south of France, at a time when reflections upon the
                    efficacy of literary expression were most acute. In addition, the fragments,
                    riddles, and non sequiturs in the published novel (first published in 1953)
                    strongly imply a process of archivisation of fuller manuscript material, or more
                    accurately, providing keys by which to unlock abundant manuscript contents. By
                    providing coherent and searchable access to such a large and complex document,
                    the digitised manuscript project provides the grounds for extensive
                    investigation into hitherto inscrutable textual features in the published text,
                    and provides space for reflection on variant narrative structures and the
                    evolution of literary works more generally.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Digital Technology and Editorial Practice</head>
                <p>The presence of digital technology in scholarship has become increasingly
                    prominent in recent years. Digital aides to scholarship (online library
                    catalogues, concordances, etc.) provide extensions to existing scholarly tools
                    and practices, facilitating certain kinds of scholarship. Primary sources can be
                    identified by means of web-based archive catalogues, and online digital
                    representations of manuscripts allow scholars to conduct particular kinds of
                    work at geographical distance. Whilst access to the physical document may be
                    desirable or even critical in the final event, several stages of a research
                    project can be accomplished prior to such access. Digital extensions of
                    traditional analogue research tools are perfectly commonplace in most
                    disciplines, and (in theory) are not particularly difficult to integrate into a
                    disciplinary mentality.</p>
                <p>Recent innovative approaches to scholarly editing tend to imply or assert the
                    relevance of a wider array of documentary sources: genetic editions seek to
                    incorporate all manuscript material and published versions of a text, as well as
                    a rationale of any stemmatic relationship between them, in an attempt to provide
                    a &quot;total&quot; text; social text methods seek to integrate erstwhile
                    secondary documents and materials into the very conceptual fabric of a text, as
                    constituent parts of a text’s identity. These more aggregative models of text
                    identity, and more specifically the texts to which they pertain, are clearly
                    conducive to presentation as digital scholarly editions. Conversely, digital
                    modes of representing literary texts can bring questions of a text’s identity
                    into sharp focus. For example, the representation of multiple textual witnesses
                    in collation software such as Juxta<note>Juxta was originally developed as a
                        collation tool for Jerome J. McGann’s digital Rossetti Archive &lt;<ref
                            type="external" target="http://www.rossettiarchive.org/"
                            >www.rossettiarchive.org</ref>&gt; and is now housed under the auspices
                        of the Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities and NINES (a
                        digital research environment for nineteenth century studies), Alderman
                        Library, University of Virginia.</note> or Versioning Machine<note>Susan
                        Schreibman began developing Versioning Machine &lt;<ref type="external"
                            target="http://v-machine.org/">v-machine.org</ref>&gt; in 2000. It is
                        housed at the University of Maryland Libraries and the Maryland Institute
                        for Technology in the Humanities.</note> alters rather profoundly the
                    reader’s apprehension of the textual matter at hand. The text is digitally
                    mediated and may be represented by transposed digital reproductions and
                    transcriptions suitably marked up for digital display. But this mediation can go
                    to the very heart of what is considered to be the text.</p>
                <p>Digital scholarly editions can do two things that seem fundamentally new:
                    firstly, a potentially large corpus of material can be represented in one space,
                    and manipulated in ways simply not possible in the world of physical manuscripts
                    and codex editions: a basic premise of the digitised manuscript of <hi
                        rend="italic">Watt</hi>. Secondly, digital collations allow for
                    manipulations of the text material that are visually straightforward and
                    intuitively intelligible, whilst bearing profound implications for the text’s
                    identity and the authority of textual evidence. The digital manuscript of <hi
                        rend="italic">Watt</hi> deploys an interface powered by the Apache Tomcat
                    servlet container, which represents files marked up in XML, in a streamlined
                    version of the TEI5 protocols. A high-resolution digital image of the manuscript
                    page appears alongside the marked-up transcription and attendant tools for
                    analysing the transcribed document. In the case of this particular project, the
                    use of Juxta collation software is not a straightforward choice, given that the
                    manuscripts accord very closely to the published text in many places but diverge
                    almost absolutely in many others. The relationship between text and archive is
                    by no means self-evident, or even chronologically linear, witnessed by the
                    density of cryptic allusions and riddles in the published narrative: many of
                    these may only be understood following a close reading of the more expansive
                    manuscripts episodes from which they are sedimented.</p>
                <p>The application of the Juxta software to such an editorial project as the digital
                    variorum edition of Ezra Pound’s <hi rend="italic">Cantos</hi> offers an
                    instructive counterpoint, providing a view of the way in which a well-developed
                    and intuitively graspable digital aid offers new opportunities for new
                    documentary and analytic research. These two examples provide one aspect by
                    which to view the question of digital tools for literary research: does each
                    project in the field of digital humanities require custom digital tools, or are
                    there ways to engineer convergences that continue to provide each project with
                    the specific resources it needs? This remains an open question, inspiring in
                    equal parts an anxiety of resource-intense customisation, on the one hand, and
                    the very exciting prospect of powerful convergences of digital tools in literary
                    research on the other. One critical implication for literary studies is that
                    wherever this question may lead, the nature and status of text identity will
                    demand radical investigation.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>The Digital-Textual-Literary Future</head>
                <p>Recent advances in digital scholarly tools present exciting possibilities for
                    scholarship and for reconsiderations of the paradigms of scholarship. They also
                    present a basic challenge to the work undertaken in literary studies, by calling
                    into question some of the most fundamental conceptual paradigms. The opportunity
                    exists for significant developments in the theory of textual criticism. Whilst
                    it is critical not to overstate the kinds of change made possible by digital
                    scholarship – some apparent paradigm shifts are simply incremental changes to
                    concepts and methods that remain integral to literary scholarship – it seems
                    clear that we are only beginning to understand just what may be possible in the
                    digital domain.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Coetzee, J.M</author>
                        <date>1972</date>
                        <title level="a">The Manuscript Revisions of Beckett's "Watt"</title>
                        <title level="j">JML</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">2,4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">472-480</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hayman, D</author>
                        <date>1997</date>
                        <title level="a">Beckett's "Watt" – the Graphic Accompaniment: Marginalia in
                            the Manuscripts</title>
                        <title level="j">Word &amp; Image</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">13.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">172-182</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hayman, D.</author>
                        <date>1999</date>
                        <title level="a">Nor Do My Doodles More Sagaciously: Beckett Illustrating
                            "Watt"</title>
                        <title level="m">Samuel Beckett and the Arts: Music, Visual Arts, and
                            Non-Print Media</title>
                        <editor>Oppenheim, L.</editor>
                        <publisher>Garland</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>New York and London</pubPlace>
                        <biblScope type="pp">199-215</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kennedy, S.</author>
                        <date>1998</date>
                        <title level="a">"Astride of the Grave and a Difficult Birth": Samuel
                            Beckett’s "Watt" Struggles to Life</title>
                        <title level="j">Dalhousie French Studies</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">42</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">115-147</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Pilling, J.</author>
                        <date>1994</date>
                        <title level="a">Beckett’s English Fiction</title>
                        <title level="m">The Cambridge Companion to Beckett</title>
                        <editor>Pilling, J.</editor>
                        <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                        <biblScope type="pp">17-42</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
