<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-601">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Modes of Seeing: Case Studies on the Use of Digitized Photographic
                    Archives</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Conway, Paul</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of Michigan</orgName><reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>pconway@umich.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-22</date>
                <name>AC</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>Digital humanities scholarship has expanded beyond its deep foundations in text
                analysis to find new meaning and knowledge through the creative reuse of historical
                photographs and other visual resources. Visual studies scholars in the humanities
                who wish to work primarily in the digital domain face a fundamental dilemma in the
                choice either to create “purpose-built” thematic collections tailored to specific
                studies (Palmer, 2008) or to make use of collections digitized for general purposes
                by an archives, a library, or other cultural heritage organization.
                “General-purpose” digital library collections are simultaneously mechanisms for
                delivering digital surrogates of archival holdings and new archival collections in
                their own right that reflect the decisions that digital curators make throughout the
                digitization process (Ross, 2007; Conway, 2008). The research issues associated with
                the actual use in humanities contexts of these large-scale general-purpose
                collections of digital images are profound and as yet largely unexplored (Saracevic,
                2004). Concluding an important study establishing a typology of use in image
                retrieval, Graham (2004, p. 324) observes that “these <hi rend="italic">uses</hi> do
                not tell us what was actually done with the images once they had been found.” </p>
            <p>This paper reports on a multi-case study of the use of general purpose digitized
                photographic archives. The paper’s title is a play on John Berger’s somewhat
                forgotten pre-digital argument in <hi rend="italic">Ways of Seeing</hi> that
                reproductions transform art (including of photographs and other graphical materials)
                into information, and in doing so expose original material objects to new uses not
                imagined by either the artist or, especially, the museums and archives that collect
                these artifacts. “It is not a question of reproduction failing to reproduce certain
                aspects of an image faithfully; it is a question of reproduction making it possible,
                even inevitable, that an image will be used for many different purposes and that the
                reproduced image, unlike the original work, can lend itself to them all” (Berger,
                1972, p. 24). In suggesting that the post-modern critique has outlived its
                usefulness in the arena of visual studies, Mitchell calls for moving beyond Walter
                Benjamin’s skepticism of the reproduction by embracing digital image surrogacy as
                superior. “In a world where the very idea of the unique original seems a merely
                nominal or legal fiction, the copy has every chance of being an improvement or
                enhancement of whatever counts as the original” (Mitchell, 2003, p. 487).</p>
            <p>Efforts to extract evidence and meaning from the digitized photographic image extend
                well beyond the disciplines of art and art history to encompass history, a range of
                other social sciences, and increasingly the humanities. Humanists with a propensity
                toward visual studies run the gamut from skepticism to enthusiasm about the
                processes that digitally transform the material properties of original photographs
                and camera negatives. Koltun (1999, p. 124) claims that a digitized photograph
                “leaves behind another originating document whose disposal or retention can inspire
                other archival debates focused around original attributes and meanings not
                ‘translated’ into, even distorted by, the new medium.” Sassoon (2004, p. 199)
                largely sees diminished meaning (“an ephemeral ghost”) through digitization, whereas
                Cameron (2007, p. 67) projects archival properties onto the “historical digital
                object” that are distinctive and original. Skeptics and enthusiasts on both sides of
                this argument stake their claims with little regard for the actual uses of digitized
                historical photographs. </p>
            <p>This paper exposes varying perspectives on “modes of seeing” by synthesizing case
                studies of seven deeply experienced researchers both within and outside the academy,
                ranging from scholars to serious avocational users to people whose livelihood
                depends on finding and using high quality representations of historical photographs.
                The group of study participants is broadly (but not statistically) representative of
                the variety of sophisticated humanities-oriented uses to which general purpose
                collections are put. The participants in the seven case studies vary widely in terms
                of demographic characteristics. Three are female; four are male. Their ages range
                from 30 to 67. The participants work and live east of the Mississippi River in five
                separate communities. Each case study revolves around a specific tangible product
                that was in some stage of completeness at the time of the interviews. The form of
                the products ranged from books and a dissertation, a complex and dynamic website, to
                a database for a membership organization. For their projects, participants made use
                of digitized photographs delivered from either the Library of Congress’s American
                Memory collection or the online catalog of the Prints and Photographs Division. Each
                of the five collections consulted is discrete within its particular delivery system.
                The Civil War Photographs collection is available through interfaces to both the
                American Memory and the PPD databases. A 1872 Turkestan photographic album and
                photographs from the National Child Labor Committee are available in digital form
                only through the online catalog. Portions of the extensive Farm Security
                Administration/Office of War Information collection are distributed through the
                American Memory interface, but the entire digitized collection is fully available
                only through the online catalog. Finally, the Bain photograph collection, including
                a sizable sub-collection on American baseball, is fully available digitally through
                the online catalog and selectively through the American Memory interface. </p>
            <p>The paper frames the findings on the use of digitized photographs in digital
                humanities scholarship within new theoretical perspectives on visual literacy
                (Elkins, 2008) and remediation (Bolter and Grusin, 1996), and the practical aspects
                of imaging for humanities scholarship (Deegan and Tanner, 2002). The case studies
                are constructed using an innovative multi-method qualitative approach that
                encompasses archival research in photo archives combined with a two-stage
                qualitative investigation. Stage one gathers background information and an
                assessment of expertise from interview subjects. Stage two consists of in-depth,
                semi-structured, in-situ interviews and observations. A three-part “thinking out
                loud” protocol extracts extensive commentary on the nature of individual and
                community expertise, on macro decision making strategies for creating the research
                product, and the character of micro-decisions on the choice and use of individual
                photographs. The descriptive evidence of “modes of seeing” is derived from a
                “grounded theory” analysis of interview transcripts.</p>
            <p>Using extracted quotations and extensive visual examples, the paper presents an
                original typological model on the ways that perspectives of users on visual content,
                archival properties, and technical characteristics of digitized photographic
                archives combine to produce distinctive, but often intersecting “modes of seeing.”
                One mode, “Discovering,” takes maximum advantage of the visual detail discernable in
                high-resolution digital copies of camera negatives to find and contextualize new
                knowledge. A second mode, “Storytelling,” has a point of departure in the emotion
                evoked by wholly composed photographic images, seeking hidden narratives surrounding
                the subjects of the images, much in the way that textual archives yield their
                stories through the power of provenance. A third mode, “Landscaping,” finds meaning
                through the geospatial and temporal contexts of the images and the circumstances of
                their existence, sometimes providing a portal on technologically mediated power
                relations. All three modes carry either a “materialist” or “anti-materialist” stance
                that circumscribes the intimacy of original source and digital surrogate. The two
                stances have much to say about trust, integrity, and the archival nature of digital
                collections for humanities scholarship.</p>
            <p>The findings have at least three important implications for the use of general
                purpose collections of digitized photographs in a digital humanities context. First,
                the study demonstrates the relationship between the technical characteristics of
                digitally transformed photographs and the construction of visual narrative. Second,
                the study exposes how hidden archival properties embedded in the transformed
                archival photographic record create the context of use for scholars who privilege
                digital surrogacy over the material nature of original sources. Third, the study’s
                model of “modes of seeing” diversifies our understanding of how humanists interpret
                the visual order on, beneath, and beyond the visual plane of the photographic
                object.</p>
            <p><hi rend="bold">Funding</hi><lb/>This work was supported by the U. S. National
                Science Foundation [IIS-0733279]. Ricardo Punzalan provided valuable assistance in
                conducting the phase-one interviews.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Berger, J.</author>
                        <author> et al.</author>
                        <date>1972</date>
                        <title level="m">Ways of Seeing</title>
                        <publisher>Penguin Books and British Broadcasting Corporation</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bolter, J.</author>
                        <author>Grusin, R.</author>
                        <date>1996</date>
                        <title level="a">Remediation</title>
                        <title level="j">Configurations</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">4 (3)</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">311-358</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Cameron, F.</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">Beyond the Cult of the Replicant: Museums and Historical
                            Digital Objects – Traditional Concerns, New Discourses</title>
                        <title level="m">Theorizing Digital Cultural Heritage: A Critical
                            Discourse</title>
                        <editor>Cameron, F.</editor>
                        <editor>Kenderdine, S.</editor>
                        <publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                        <biblScope type="pp">49-75</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Conway, P.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Building Meaning in Digitized Photographs</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Proceedings of the Chicago Colloquium on
                            Digital Humanities and Computer Science 1</title>
                        <name type="venue">Chicago</name>
                        <ptr
                            target="https://letterpress.uchicago.edu/index.php/jdhcs/article/viewFile/12/61"/>
                        <date type="visited">3 March 2010</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Deegan, M.</author>
                        <author>Tanner, S.</author>
                        <date>2002</date>
                        <title level="m">Digital Futures: Strategies for the Information Age</title>
                        <publisher>Library Association Publishing</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <editor>Elkins, J.</editor>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="m">Visual Literacy</title>
                        <publisher>Routledge</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Graham, M.</author>
                        <date>2004</date>
                        <title level="a">Enhancing Visual Resources for Searching and
                            Retrieval</title>
                        <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">321-333</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Koltun, L.</author>
                        <date>1999</date>
                        <title level="a">The Promise and Threat of Digital Options in an Archival
                            Age</title>
                        <title level="j">Archivaria</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">47 (Spring)</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">114-135</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Mitchell, W.J.T.</author>
                        <date>2003</date>
                        <title level="a">The Work of Art in the Age of Biocybernetic
                            Reproduction</title>
                        <title level="j">Modernism/modernity</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">10 (3)</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">481-500</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Palmer, C.</author>
                        <date>2004</date>
                        <title level="a">Thematic Research Collections</title>
                        <title level="m">A Companion to Digital Humanities</title>
                        <editor>Schreibman, S.</editor>
                        <editor>Siemens, R.</editor>
                        <editor>Unsworth, J.</editor>
                        <publisher>Blackwell</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <biblScope type="pp">348-365</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Ross, S.</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">Digital Preservation, Archival Science and Methodological
                            Foundations for Digital Libraries</title>
                        <title level="m">Keynote Address at the 11th European Conference on Digital
                            Libraries (ECDL)</title>
                        <name type="venue">Budapest </name>
                        <date type="conference">17 September 2007</date>
                        <ptr target="http://www.ecdl2007.org/Keynote_ECDL2007_SROSS.pdf"/>
                        <date type="visited">3 March 2010</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Saracevic, T. </author>
                        <date>2004</date>
                        <title level="a">How Were Digital Libraries Evaluated?</title>
                        <title level="m">DELOS WP7 Workshop on the Evaluation of Digital
                            Libraries</title>
                        <name type="venue">Padova, Italy </name>
                        <date type="conference">4-5 October 2004</date>
                        <ptr target="http://comminfo.rutgers.edu/~tefko/DL_evaluation_LIDA.pdf"/>
                        <date type="visited">3 March 2010</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Sassoon, J.</author>
                        <date>2004</date>
                        <title level="a">Photographic Materiality in the Age of Digital
                            Reproduction</title>
                        <title level="m">Photographs, Objects, Histories</title>
                        <editor>Edwards, E.</editor>
                        <publisher>Routledge</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <biblScope type="pp">196-212</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
