<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-688">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Deeper Delta Across Genres and Languages: Do We Really Need the Most Frequent
                    Words?</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Rybicki, Jan</name>
                    <affiliation>Pedagogical University, Krakow, <reg><orgName>Pedagogical University of Krakow</orgName></reg> <country>Poland</country></affiliation>
                    <email>jkrybicki@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Eder, Maciej</name>
                    <affiliation>Pedagogical University, Krakow, <reg><orgName>Pedagogical University of Krakow</orgName></reg> <country>Poland</country></affiliation>
                    <email>maciej_eder@poczta.onet.pl</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-07</date>
                <name>CD</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>In 2007, John Burrows identified three regions in word frequency lists of corpora
                    in authorship attribution and stylometry. The first of these regions consists of
                    the most frequent words, for which his Delta has become the best-known method of
                    study. This is evidenced by a varied body of research with interesting
                    modifications of the method (e.g. Argamon 2008; Hoover 2004, 2004a). At the
                    other end of the frequency list, Iota deals with the lowest-frequency words,
                    while &quot;the large area between the extremes of ubiquity and
                    rarity&quot; (Burrows, 2007) is now the target of many studies employing
                    Zeta (e.g. Craig, Kinney, 2009; Hoover, 2007).</p>
                <p> Due to the popularity of the three methods it was only a matter of time before
                    Delta (and, to a lesser extent, Zeta and Iota) were applied to texts in
                    languages other than Modern English: Middle Dutch (Dalen-Oskam, Zundert, 2007),
                    Old English (Garcìa, Martìn 2007) and Polish (Eder, Rybicki 2009). Delta has
                    also been used in translation-oriented papers, including Burrowsís own work on
                    Juvenal (Burrows, 2002) and Rybicki's attempts at translator attribution
                    (2009).</p>
                <p> It has been generally - and mainly empirically - assumed that the use of methods
                    relying on the most frequent words in a corpus should work just as well in other
                    languages as it did in English; this question was approached in any detail only
                    very recently (Juola, 2009). We could not fail to observe that its success rates
                    in Polish, although still high, fell somewhat short of its guessing rate in
                    English (Rybicki 2009a). Also, the already-quoted study by Rybicki (2009) seemed
                    to suggest that, in a corpus of translated literary texts, Delta was much better
                    at recognising the author of the original than the translator. This justified a
                    more in-depth look at the workings of Burrowsís method both in its
                    &quot;original&quot; English and in a variety of other languages.</p>
           <div>
                <head>Methods</head>
                <p>In this study, a single major modification has been applied to the usual Delta
                    process. Each analysis was made for the top 50-5000 most frequent words in the
                    corpus - but then the 50 most frequent words would be omitted and the next
                    50-5000 words taken for analysis; then the first 100 most frequent words would
                    be omitted, and so on. This was done with a single R script written by Eder; the
                    script produced word frequency tables, calculated Delta and produced
                    &quot;heatmap&quot; graphs of Delta&apos;s success rate for each of
                    the frequency list intervals, showing the best combinations of initial word
                    position in wordlist and size of window, including variations of pronoun
                    deletion and culling parameters. Thus, in the resulting heatmap graphs, the
                    horizontal axis presents the size of each wordlist used for one set of Delta
                    calculations; the vertical axis shows how many of the most frequent words were
                    omitted. Each of the runs of the script produced an average of ca. 3000 Delta
                    iterations.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Material</head>
                <p>The project included the following corpora (used separately); each contained a
                    similar number of texts to be attributed.</p>
                <table>
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell role="label" rend="1cm">Code</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Language</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Texts</cell>
                        <cell role="label">Attribution</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>E1</cell>
                        <cell>English</cell>
                        <cell>65 novels from Swift to Conrad</cell>
                        <cell>Author</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>E2</cell>
                        <cell>English</cell>
                        <cell>32 epic poems from Milton to Tennyson</cell>
                        <cell>Author</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>E3</cell>
                        <cell>English</cell>
                        <cell>35 translations of Sienkiewicz&apos;s novels</cell>
                        <cell>Translator</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>P1</cell>
                        <cell>Polish</cell>
                        <cell>69 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>- and early 20<hi rend="sup"
                            >th</hi>-century novels from Kraszewski to Øeromski</cell>
                        <cell>Author</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>P2</cell>
                        <cell>Polish</cell>
                        <cell>95 translations of 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>- and 20<hi rend="sup"
                                >th</hi>-century novels from Balzac to Eco</cell>
                        <cell>Author</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>P3</cell>
                        <cell>Polish</cell>
                        <cell>95 translations of 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>- and 20<hi rend="sup"
                                >th</hi>-century novels from Balzac to Eco</cell>
                        <cell>Translator</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>F1</cell>
                        <cell>French</cell>
                        <cell>71 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>- and 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>-century
                            novels from Voltaire to Gide</cell>
                        <cell>Author</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>L1</cell>
                        <cell>Latin</cell>
                        <cell>94 prose texts from Cicero to Gellius </cell>
                        <cell>Author</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>L2</cell>
                        <cell>Latin</cell>
                        <cell>28 hexameter poems from Lucretius to Jacopo Sannazaro</cell>
                        <cell>Author</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>G1</cell>
                        <cell>German</cell>
                        <cell>66 literary texts from Goethe to Thomas Mann</cell>
                        <cell>Author</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>H1</cell>
                        <cell>Hungarian</cell>
                        <cell>64 novels from Kemèny to Bródy</cell>
                        <cell>Author</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>I1</cell>
                        <cell>Italian</cell>
                        <cell>77 novels from Manzoni to D&apos;Annunzio</cell>
                        <cell>Author</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Results</head>
                <p>The English novel corpus (E1, <ref type="internal" cRef="fig1">Fig. 1</ref>) was
                    the one with the best attributions for all available sample sizes starting at
                    the top of the reference corpus word frequency list; it was equally easy to
                    attribute even if the first 2000 most frequent words were omitted in the
                    analysis - or even the first 3000 for longer samples. The English epic poems
                    (E2, <ref type="internal" cRef="fig2">Fig. 2</ref>) had their area of best
                    attributive success removed away from the top of the word frequency list, into
                    the 1000<hi rend="sup">th</hi>-2000<hi rend="sup">th</hi> most-frequent-word
                    region. Some successful attributions could also be made with a variety of
                    wordlists around the 2000 mark, starting at the 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> most
                    frequent word.</p>
                <p>
                    <figure xml:id="fig1">
                        <head>Figure 1. Heatmap of 65 English novels (percentage of correct attributions).
                            Colour coding is from low (white) to high (black)</head>
                        <graphic url="688_Fig1.jpg" rend="left" 
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="fig2">
                        <head>Figure 2. Heatmap of 32 English epic poems</head>
                        <graphic url="688_Fig2.jpg" rend="right" 
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>The final &quot;specialist&quot; corpus in the English section of the
                    project - 32 works by Polish novelist Henryk Sienkiewicz, translated into
                    English by a number of translators (<ref type="internal" cRef="fig3">Fig.
                        3</ref>) - showed Delta's expected problems in translator attribution;
                    however, for a variety of culling/pronoun deletion parameters, a small yet
                    fairly consistent hotspot would appear for small samples if the first 2000-3000
                    words were deleted from the frequency wordlist. The first Polish corpus, that of
                    69 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>- and early 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>-century classic
                    Polish novels (P1, <ref type="internal" cRef="fig4">Fig. 4</ref>), showed marked
                    improvement in Delta success rate when the wordlist taken for attribution
                    started at some 450 words down the frequency list; the most successful sample
                    sizes were relatively small: no more than 1200 words long. </p>
                <p>When the corpus of Polish translations was studied for original authorship (P2,
                        <ref type="internal" cRef="fig5">Fig. 5</ref>), the results were quite
                    accurate for many sample sizes up to 1800 from the very top of the frequency
                    list. Delta was equally successful for samples of up to 1400 words beyond the
                    800th most-frequent-word mark. The same corpus yielded lower attribution success
                    when studied for translator recognition (P3, <ref type="internal" cRef="fig6"
                        >Fig. 6</ref>). In fact, it resembled somewhat the graph for Polish
                    classics: a small range of passable attributions, usually for samples below
                    1000, and usually better when starting a hundred or so words down the frequency
                    rank list.</p>
                <p>
                    <figure xml:id="fig3">
                        <head>Figure 3. Heatmap of 35 English translations of Sienkiewicz&apos;s
                            works</head>
                        <graphic url="688_Fig3.jpg" rend="left" 
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="fig4">
                        <head>Figure 4. Heatmap of 69 Polish novel classics</head>
                        <graphic url="688_Fig4.jpg" rend="right" 
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <figure xml:id="fig5">
                        <head>Figure 5. Heatmap of 95 Polish translations from Balzac to Eco (autorship
                            attribution)</head>
                        <graphic url="688_Fig5.jpg" rend="left" 
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="fig6">
                        <head>Figure 6. Heatmap of 95 Polish translations from Balzac to Eco (translator
                            attribution)</head>
                        <graphic url="688_Fig6.jpg" rend="right" 
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>The French corpus proved almost equally difficult (F1, <ref type="internal"
                        cRef="fig7">Fig. 7</ref>): Delta was very successful mainly for small-sized
                    samples from the top of the overall frequency wordlist. In contrast, the graph
                    for the German corpus (G1, <ref type="internal" cRef="fig8">Fig. 8</ref>)
                    presented a success rate akin to that for the English novels, with a
                    consistently high correct attribution in most of the studied spectrum of sample
                    size and for samples beginning anywhere between the 1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> and
                    the 1000<hi rend="sup">th</hi> word in the corpus frequency list.</p>
                <p>
                    <figure xml:id="fig7">
                        <head>Figure 7. Heatmap of 71 French novels</head>
                        <graphic url="688_Fig7.jpg" rend="left" 
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="fig8">
                        <head>Figure 8. Heatmap of 66 German texts</head>
                        <graphic url="688_Fig8.jpg" rend="right" 
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>Of the two Latin corpora, the prose texts (L1, <ref type="internal" cRef="fig9"
                        >Fig. 9</ref>) could serve as excellent evidence for a minimalist approach
                    in authorship attribution based on most frequent words, as the best (if not
                    perfect) results were obtained by staying close to the axis intersection point:
                    no more than 750 words, taken no further than from the 50<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
                    place on the frequency rank list.</p>
                <p>
                    <figure xml:id="fig9">
                        <head>Figure 9. Heatmap of 94 Latin prose texts</head>
                        <graphic url="688_Fig9.jpg" rend="left" 
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="fig10">
                        <head>Figure 10. Heatmap of 28 Latin hexameter poems</head>
                        <graphic url="688_Fig10.jpg" rend="right" 
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>The other Latin corpus, that of hexameter poetry (L2, <ref type="internal"
                        cRef="fig10">Fig. 10</ref>), paints a much more heterogeneous picture: Delta
                    was only successful for top words from the frequency list at rare small (150),
                    medium (700) and large (1700) window sizes, and for a few isolated places around
                    the 1000/1000 intersection point in the graph.</p>
                <p>The corpus of 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi>-century Hungarian novels (H1, <ref
                        type="internal" cRef="fig11">Fig. 11</ref>) exhibited good success for much
                    of the studied spectrum and an interesting hotspot of short samples at ca. 4000
                    words from the top of the word frequency list.</p>
                <p>
                    <figure xml:id="fig11">
                        <head>Figure 11. Heatmap of 64 Hungarian novels</head>
                        <graphic url="688_Fig11.jpg" rend="left" 
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="fig12">
                        <head>Figure 12. Heatmap of 77 Italian novels</head>
                        <graphic url="688_Fig12.jpg" rend="right" 
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>With the Italian novels (I, <ref type="internal" cRef="fig12">Fig. 12</ref>),
                    Delta was at its best for a broad variety of sample sizes, but only when some
                    1000 most frequent words were eliminated from the reference corpus.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusions</head>
                <p>
                    <xmt:oList rend="arabic">
                        <item> Standard Delta (i.e. applied to the most frequent words) provides the
                            best results for authorial attribution in English and German
                            prose.</item>
                        <item> The same procedures still yield acceptable results in other languages
                            and in translator attribution. The success here can be improved by
                            manipulating the number of words taken for analysis and by selecting the
                            reference wordlists at various distances from the top of the overall
                            frequency rank list.</item>
                        <item>The differences in attributive success could be partially explained by
                            the differences in the degree of inflection/agglutination of the
                            languages studied, the strongest evidence of this being the relatively
                            highest success rate in English and German.</item>
                    </xmt:oList>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Argamon, S.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">Interpreting Burrows&apos;s Delta: Geometric and
                            Probabilistic Foundations</title>
                        <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">23(2)</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">131-147</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Burrows, J.F.</author>
                        <date>1987</date>
                        <title level="m">Computation into Criticism: a Study of Jane Austen's Novels
                            and an Experiment in Method</title>
                        <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher></bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Burrows, J.F.</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">All the Way Through: Testing for Authorship in Different
                            Frequency Strata</title>
                        <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">22(1)</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">27-48</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Burrows, J.F.</author>
                        <date>2002</date>
                        <title level="a">The Englishing of Juvenal: Computational Stylistics and
                            Translated Texts</title>
                        <title level="j">Style</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">36</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">677-99</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Burrows, J.F.</author>
                        <date>2002a</date>
                        <title level="a">Delta: A Measure of Stylistic Difference and a Guide to
                            Likely Authorship</title>
                        <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">17</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">267-287</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hoover, D.L.</author>
                        <date>2003</date>
                        <title level="a">Frequent Collocations and Authorial Style</title>
                        <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">18</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">261-286</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hoover, D.L.</author>
                        <date>2004</date>
                        <title level="a">Testing Burrows&apos;s Delta</title>
                        <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">19</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">453-475</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hoover, D.L.</author>
                        <date>2004a</date>
                        <title level="a">Delta Prime?</title>
                        <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">19</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">477-495</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Hoover, D.L.</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">Corpus Stylistics, Stylometry, and the Styles of Henry
                            James</title>
                        <title level="j">Style</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">41(2)</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">174-203</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Rybicki, J.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Translation and Delta Revisited: When We Read Translations,
                            Is It the Author or the Translator that We Really Read?</title>
                        <name type="venue">College Park</name>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Digital Humanities</title>
                        <date type="conference">2009</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Rybicki, J.</author>
                        <date>2009a</date>
                        <title level="a">Liczenie krasnoludków. Trochę inaczej o polskich
                            przekładach trylogii Tolkiena</title>
                        <name type="venue">Warszawa</name>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Po co ludziom krasnoludki?</title>
                        <date type="conference">2009</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title level="m">Shakespeare, Computers, and the Mystery of
                            Authorship</title>
                        <editor>Craig, H.</editor>
                        <editor>Kinney, A.F.</editor>
                       
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author> Dalen-Oskam, K. van</author>
                        <author>Zundert, J. van</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">Delta for Middle Dutch–Author and Copyist Distinction in
                            Walewein</title>
                        <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">22</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">345-362</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Eder, M.</author>
                        <author>Rybicki, J.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">PCA, Delta, JGAAP and Polish Poetry of the 16th and the
                            17th Centuries: Who Wrote the Dirty Stuff?</title>
                        <name type="venue">College Park</name>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Digital Humanities</title>
                        <date type="conference">2009</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Garcìa, A.M.</author>
                        <author>Martìn, J.C.</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">Function Words in Authorship Attribution Studies</title>
                        <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">22</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">49-66</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Jockers, M.L.</author>
                        <author>Witten, D.M.</author>
                        <author>Criddle, C.S.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">Reassessing Authorship in the Book of Mormon Using Delta
                            and Nearest Shrunken Centroid Classification</title>
                        <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">22</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">465-491</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Mosteller, F.</author>
                        <author>Wallace, D.L.</author>
                        <date>1964</date>
                        <title level="m">Inference and Disputed Authorship: The Federalist</title>
                        <note>Reprinted with a new introduction by John Nerbonne</note>
                        <publisher>CSLI Publications</publisher>
                        <date>2007</date>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
