<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-663">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Two representations of the semantics of TEI Lite</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Black Mesa Technologies LLC</orgName>, <country>USA</country></affiliation>
                    <email>cmsmcq@blackmesatech.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Marcoux, Yves</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Université de Montréal</orgName>, <country>Canada</country></affiliation>
                    <email>yves.marcoux@umontreal.ca</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Huitfeldt, Claus</name>
                    <affiliation>Department of Philosophy, <orgName>University of Bergen</orgName> <reg><country>Norway</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>Claus.Huitfeldt@uib.no</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-03-29</date>
                <name>JL</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2010-06-09</date>
                <name>JL</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <!-- or poster -->
        <body>
            <div>

                <p>Markup languages based on SGML and XML provide reasonably fine control over the
                    syntax of markup used in documents. Schema languages (DTDs, Relax NG, XSD, etc.)
                    provide mature, well understood mechanisms for specifying markup syntax which
                    support validation, syntax-directed editing, and in some cases query
                    optimization. We possess a much poorer set of tools for specifying the <hi
                        rend="italic">meaning</hi> of the markup in a vocabulary, and virtually no
                    tools which could systematically exploit any semantic specification. Some
                    observers claim, indeed, that XML and SGML are “just syntax”, and that SGML/XML
                    markup has no systematic semantics at all. Drawing on earlier work (Marcoux et
                    al., 2009), this paper presents two alternative and complementary approaches to
                    the formal representation of the semantics of TEI Lite: <hi rend="italic"
                        >Intertextual semantics</hi> (IS) and <hi rend="italic">Formal tag-set
                        descriptions</hi> (FTSD).</p>
                <p>RDF and Topic Maps may appear to address this problem (they are after all
                    specifications for expressing “semantic relations,” and they both have XML
                    transfer syntaxes), but in reality their focus is on generic semantics —
                    propositions about the real world — and not the semantics of markup
                    languages.</p>
                <p>In practice, the semantics of markup is most of the time specified only through
                    human-readable documentation. Most existing colloquial markup languages are
                    documented in prose, sometimes systematically and in detail, sometimes very
                    sketchily. Often, written documentation is supplemented or replaced in practice
                    by executable code: users will understand a given vocabulary (e.g., HTML, RSS,
                    or the Atom syndication format) in terms of the behavior of software which
                    supports or uses that vocabulary; the documentation for Docbook elevates this
                    almost to a principle, consistently speaking not of the meaning of particular
                    constructs, but of the “processing expectations” licensed by those
                    constructs.</p>
                <p>Yet a formal description of the semantics of a markup language can bring several
                    benefits. One of them is the ability to develop provably correct mappings
                    (conversions, translations) from one markup language to another. A second one is
                    the possibility of automatically deriving facts from documents, and feeding them
                    into various inferencing or reasoning systems. A third one is the possibility of
                    automatically computing the semantics of part or whole of a document and
                    presenting it to humans in an appropriate form to make the meaning of the
                    document (or passage) precise and explicit.</p>
                <p>There have been a few proposals for formal approaches to the specification of
                    markup semantics. Two of them are <hi rend="italic">Intertextual Semantic
                        Specifications</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Formal Tagset
                    Descriptions</hi>.</p>
                <p>Intertextual semantics (IS) (Marcoux, 2006; Marcoux &amp; Rizkallah, 2009) is a
                    proposal to describe the meaning of markup constructs in natural language, by
                    supplying an IS specification (ISS), which consists in a pre-text (or
                    text-before) and a post-text (or text-after) for each element type in the
                    vocabulary. When the vocabulary is used correctly, the contents of each element
                    combine with the pre- and post-text to form a coherent natural-language text
                    representing, to the desired level of detail, the information conveyed by the
                    document. Although based on natural language, IS differs from the usual
                    prose-documentation approach by the fact that the meaning of a construct is
                    dynamically assembled and can be read sequentially, without the need to go back
                    and forth between the documentation and the actual document.</p>
                <p>Formal tag-set descriptions (FTSD) (Sperberg-McQueen et al., 2000)
                    (Sperberg-McQueen &amp; Miller, 2004) attempt to capture the meaning of markup
                    constructs by means of “skeleton sentences”: expressions in an arbitrary
                    notation into which values from the document are inserted at locations indicated
                    by blanks. FTSDs can, like ISSs, formulate the skeleton sentences in natural
                    language prose. In that case, the main difference between FTSD and ISS is that
                    an IS specification for an element is equivalent to a skeleton sentence with a
                    single blank, to be filled in with the content of the element. In the general
                    case, skeleton sentences in an FTSD can have multiple blanks, to be filled in
                    with data selected from arbitrary locations in the document (Marcoux et al.,
                    2009). It is more usual, however, for FTSDs to formulate their skeleton
                    sentences in some logic notation: e.g., first-order predicate calculus or some
                    subset of it.</p>
                <p>Three other approaches, though not directly aimed at specifying markup semantics,
                    use RDF to express document structure or <hi rend="italic">some</hi> document
                    semantics, and could probably be adapted or extended to serve as markup
                    semantics specification formalisms. They are <hi rend="italic">RDF Textual
                        Encoding Framework</hi> (RDFTef) (Tummarello et al., 2005) (Tummarello et
                    al., 2006), EARMARK (<hi rend="italic">Extreme Annotational RDF Markup</hi>) (Di
                    Iorio et al., 2009), and GRDDL (<hi rend="italic">Gleaning Resource Descriptions
                        from Dialects of Languages</hi>) (Connolly, 2007).</p>
                <p>RDFTef and EARMARK both use RDF to represent complex text encoding. One of their
                    key features is the ability to deal with non-hierarchical, overlapping
                    structures. GRDDL is a method for trying to make parts of the meaning of
                    documents explicit by means of an XSLT translation which transforms the document
                    in question into a set of RDF triples. GRDDL is typically thought of as a method
                    of extracting meaning from the markup and/or content in a particular document or
                    set of documents, rather than as a method of specifying the meaning of a
                    vocabulary; it is often deployed for HTML documents, where the information of
                    most immediate concern is not the semantics of the HTML vocabulary in general,
                    but the implications of the particular conventions used in a single document.
                    However, there is no reason in principle that GRDDL could not be used to specify
                    the meaning of a markup vocabulary apart from any additional conventions adopted
                    in the use of that vocabulary by a given project or in a given document.</p>
                <p>If proposals for formal semantics of markup are scarce, their application to
                    colloquial markup vocabularies are even scarcer. Most examples found in the
                    literature are toy examples. A larger-scale implementation of RDFTef for a
                    subset of the TEI has been realized by Kepler (Kepler, 2005). However, as far as
                    we know, no complete formal semantics has ever been defined for a real-life and
                    commonly used colloquial vocabulary. This paper reports on experiments in
                    applying ISSs and FTSDs to an existing and widely-used colloquial markup
                    vocabulary: TEI Lite.</p>
                <p>Developing an ISS and an FTSD in parallel for the same vocabulary is interesting
                    for at least two reasons. First, it is an opportunity to verify the intuition
                    expressed in Marcoux et al., 2009 that working out ISSs and FTSDs involves much
                    the same type of intellectual effort. Second, it can give insight into the
                    relative merits and challenges of natural-language vs logic-based approaches to
                    semantics specification.</p>
                <p>The full paper will focus on the technical and substantive challenges encountered
                    along the way and will describe the solutions adopted.</p>
                <p>An example of a challenge is the fact that TEI Lite documents can be either
                    autonomous or transcriptions of existing exemplars. Both cases are treated with
                    the same markup vocabulary, but ultimately, the meaning of the markup is quite
                    different: in one case, it licences inferences about the marked-up document
                    itself, while in the other, it licences inferences about the exemplar. The work
                    reported in Sperberg-McQueen et al., 2009 on the formal nature of transcription
                    is useful here to decide how to represent statements about the exemplar, when it
                    exists. However, the problems of determining whether any particular document is
                    a transcription or not, and of putting that fact into action in the generation
                    of the semantics remain. One possible solution is to consider as external
                    knowledge the fact that the document is a transcription. In the FTSD case, that
                    external knowledge would be represented as a formal statement that could then
                    trigger inferences about an exemplar. In the ISS case, it would show up as a
                    preamble in the pre-text of the document element. Another solution is to
                    consider the transcription and autonomous cases as two different application
                    contexts of the vocabulary, and define two different specifications. The
                    benefits and disadvantages of the two solutions will be discussed.</p>
                <p>Follow-on work will include developing a GRDDL specification of TEI Lite, and
                    comparing it to the ISS and FTSD. It will also include the elaboration of tools
                    to read TEI Lite-encoded documents and generate from them either a prose
                    representation of the meaning of the markup (from the ISS) or a set of sentences
                    in a formal symbolic logic (from the FTSD). We also expect to induce a formal
                    ontology of the basic concepts appealed to by the three formalisms and attempt
                    to make explicit some of the essential relations among the concepts in the
                    ontology: What kinds of things exist in the world described by TEI Lite markup?
                    How are they related to each other?</p>
            </div>

        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>

                    <bibl>
                        <author>Connolly, Dan</author>
                        <title level="m">Gleaning Resource Descriptions from Dialects of Languages
                            (GRDDL)</title>
                        <ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/grddl/"/>
                    </bibl>

                    <bibl><author>Di Iorio, A.</author><author>Peroni, S.</author><author>Vitali,
                            F.</author><date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Towards markup support for full GODDAGs and beyond: the
                            EARMARK approach</title><title level="m" type="proceedings">Balisage:
                            The Markup Conference</title><name type="venue">Montréal,
                            Canada</name><date type="conference">August 2009</date>
                        <title level="s">Balisage Series on Markup Technologies</title><biblScope
                            type="vols">3 vols</biblScope>
                        <ptr target="doi:10.4242/BalisageVol3.Peroni01"/></bibl>

                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kepler, F. N</author>
                        <title level="m">RDF Textual Encoding Framework</title>
                        <ptr target="http://sourceforge.net/projects/rdftef/"/>
                    </bibl>

                    <bibl>
                        <author>Marcoux, Y.</author>
                        <date>2006</date>
                        <title level="a">A natural-language approach to modeling: Why is some XML so
                            difficult to write?</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Extreme Markup Languages</title>
                        <name type="venue">Montréal, Canada</name>
                        <date type="conference">August 2006</date>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://conferences.idealliance.org/extreme/html/2006/Marcoux01/EML2006Marcoux01.htm"
                        />
                    </bibl>

                    <bibl>
                        <author>Marcoux, Y.</author>
                        <author>Rizkallah, É.</author><date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Intertextual semantics: A semantics for information
                            design</title>
                        <title level="j">Journal of the American Society for Information Science
                            &amp; Technology</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">Volume 60, Issue 9</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">1895-1906</biblScope>
                        <ptr target="doi:10.1002/asi.21134"/>
                    </bibl>

                    <bibl><author>Marcoux, Y.</author>
                        <author>Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.</author>
                        <author>Huitfeldt, C.</author><date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Formal and informal meaning from documents through skeleton
                            sentences: Complementing formal tag-set descriptions with intertextual
                            semantics and vice-versa</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Balisage: The Markup
                            Conference</title><name type="venue">Montréal, Canada</name>
                        <date type="conference">August 2009</date>) <biblScope type="issue">Balisage
                            Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 3</biblScope>
                        <ptr target="doi:10.4242/BalisageVol3.Sperberg-McQueen01"/></bibl>

                    <bibl><author>Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.</author><author>Huitfeldt, C.</author>
                        <author>Marcoux, Y.</author><date>2009</date><title level="a">What is
                            transcription? (part 2) (abstract)</title><title level="m">Digital
                            Humanities 2009 Conference Abstracts, June 2009</title><biblScope
                            type="pp">257-260</biblScope>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://www.mith2.umd.edu/dh09/wp-content/uploads/dh09_conferencepreceedings_final.pdf"
                        /></bibl>

                    <bibl><author>Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.</author>.<author>Huitfeldt, C.</author>
                        <author>Renear, A.</author><date>2000</date><title level="a">Meaning and
                            Interpretation of Markup: Not as Simple as You Think</title><title
                            level="m" type="proceedings">Extreme Markup Languages 2000</title><name
                            type="venue">Montréal, Canada</name>
                        <date type="conference">August 2000</date>)</bibl>

                    <bibl>
                        <author>Sperberg-McQueen, C. M.</author>
                        <author>Miller, E.</author><date>2004</date>
                        <title level="a">On mapping from colloquial XML to RDF using XSLT</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Extreme Markup Languages 2004</title>
                        <name type="venue">Montréal, Canada</name>
                        <date type="conference">August 2004</date>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://conferences.idealliance.org/extreme/html/2004/Sperberg-McQueen01/EML2004Sperberg-McQueen01.html"
                        />
                    </bibl>

                    <bibl>
                        <author>Tummarello, G.</author>
                        <author>Morbidoni, C.</author>
                        <author>Kepler, F.</author>
                        <author>Piazza, F.</author>
                        <author>Puliti, P.</author><date>2006</date>
                        <date type="conference">May 2006</date>
                        <title level="a">A novel Textual Encoding paradigm based on Semantic Web
                            tools and semantics</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">5th edition of the International
                            Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation</title>
                        <name type="venue">Genoa, Italy</name>
                        <ptr target="http://www.sdjt.si/bib/lrec06/pdf/225_pdf.pdf"/>
                    </bibl>

                    <bibl>
                        <author>Tummarello, G.</author>
                        <author>Morbidoni, C.</author>
                        <author>Pierazzo, E.</author>
                        <date>2005</date>
                        <title level="a">Toward Textual Encoding Based on RDF</title>
                        <title level="m">9th ICCC International Conference on Electronic
                            Publishing</title>
                        <name type="venue">Leuven-Heverlee, Belgium</name>
                        <date type="conference">June 2005</date>
                        <ptr target="http://elpub.scix.net/data/works/att/206elpub2005.content.pdf"
                        />
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
