<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<teiCorpus xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-673">
   
    <TEI>
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title>Mapping the Flow of “Digital Humanities”</title>
                    <author>
                        <name>Akdag Salah, Alkim Almila</name>
                        <affiliation>Virtual Knowledge Studio of the Netherlands Royal Academy of
                            Arts and Sciences, The Netherlands</affiliation>
                        <email>almila.akdagsalah@knaw.vks.nl</email>
                    </author>
                    <author>
                        <name>Loet Leydesdorff</name>
                        <affiliation>Amsterdam School of Communications Research (ASCoR), University
                            of Amsterdam, The Netherlands</affiliation>
                        <email>loet@leydesdorff.net</email>
                    </author>
                    <author><name>Andrea Scharnhorst</name>
                        <affiliation>Virtual Knowledge Studio of the Netherlands Royal Academy of
                            Arts and Sciences, The Netherlands</affiliation>
                        <email>andrea.scharnhorst@vks.knaw.nl</email></author>

                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College
                        London</publisher>
                    <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change>
                    <date>2009-04-30</date>
                    <name>JL</name>
                    <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <body>
                <div>

                    <p> In this paper, we propose novel ways of charting out activity in digital
                        humanities research. In particular, we apply a combination of classic
                        bibliometric analysis<note>‘Scientometrics’ or ‘bibliometrics’ is a research
                            venue specialized in evaluating growth, relations and interactions in
                            scientific fields with the help of citation data collected above all
                            from journal papers. Scientometrics is traced back to the beginnings of the
                            1900s, but the more official start can be settled to 1964, when Garfield
                            founded Institute for Scientific Information; today it is a product of
                            Thompson ISI and called Web of Science. From the 80’s onwards, the research in
                            this area accelerated with the advancement of computers and various
                            combinations of statistical methods used to extract and evaluate
                            information such as citations, cocitations with reference of various
                            bibliometric data. The end-results are usually rendered as so-called
                            ‘citation networks’ which are a variation of social networks. Now it is
                            a common practice to evaluate a scholar or a journal according to how
                            many times it/he/she is cited. To read more on the history of
                            scientometrics see Katy Börner, Jeegar T. Marus, and Robert L.
                            Goldstone. (2004). The Simultaneous Evolution Of Author And Paper
                            Networks, PNAS 101 (suppl.1): 5266-5273. For more information on
                            citation networks, please see Doreian Patrick. (1985). A Measure Of
                            Standing Of Journals in Stratified Networks. Journal of the American
                            Society for lnformation Science, 8(5/6): 341-363. For a critique of
                            bibliometric analysis see Lindsey D. (1989). Using Citation Counts As A
                            Measure Of Quality In Science Measuring What's Measurable Rather Than
                            What's Valid., Scientometrics, Vol. 15, No 3-4: 189-203; Leydesdorff L.
                            (2006). Can Scientific Journals Be Classified in Terms of Aggregated
                            Journal-Journal Citation Relations Using the Journal Citation Reports?
                            Journal Of The American Society For Information Science And
                            Technology—March: 601-614.</note> focusing on citation patterns and a
                        broader text and actor network analysis based on various data sets collected
                        from different sources, such as standardized scientific information
                        databases and web data in general.</p>
                    <p>"Digital humanities" is the latest term for "humanities computing", almost a
                        century old enterprise that made use of computational methods and tools in
                        humanities research. Today, this enterprise has become a hot topic supported
                        by significant government funding agencies like National Endowment in
                        Humanities (NEH) in the United States<note>NEH has an office dedicated for
                            Digital Humanities research: <ptr
                                target="http://www.neh.gov/whoweare/divisions/DigitalHumanities/index.html"
                            />
                        </note> and the European Framework programs of EU.<note>One of the FP7
                            projects is titled PREPARINGDARIAH (Preparing for the construction of
                            the Digital Research Infrastructure for the Arts and Humanities) and is
                            devoted to enriching DH: <ptr target="http://www.dariah.eu"/></note> The
                        topic attracts attention from scholars coming from a wide range of
                        disciplines like computer science and art history, and its future is the
                        focus of a heated debate on certain weblogs dedicated to this research
                        initiative. Depending on the research environment, the idea of Digital
                        Humanities (DH) is envisioned in diverse ways; some research institutes or
                        universities view it as a methodology, others incorporate it into their
                        research agendas as a tool for analysis. Others view it as a discourse,
                        investigating how knowledge is produced with new media technologies, while
                        at the same time making use of these technologies in humanities research
                        itself.</p>
                    <p>Usually, the applications and methodology of DH ask for a collaborative
                        commission, and these interdisciplinary collaborations forge beneficial
                        links that enable the use of technological tools in a way to serve
                        humanities research questions. However, recent findings (Leydesdorff &amp;
                        Akdag Salah, in preparation)<note>Leydesdorff L., Akdag Salah, A.
                            (forthcoming). Maps on the basis of the Arts &amp; Humanities Citation
                            Index: the journals Leonardo and Art Journal¸ and “Digital Humanities”
                            as a topic, Journal of the American Society for Information Science and
                            Technology, available at <ptr
                                target="http://www.leydesdorff.net/ahci/ahci.pdf"/></note> show that
                        the scholarly activities around DH are less broad than one could expect. One
                        might even say that DH falls short of reaching out to an interdisciplinary
                        audience. A bibliometric study of the citation patterns of papers that are
                        tagged in Web of Science’s all three databases under the topic of "digital
                        humanities" reveals that the knowledge base of DH is confined to two groups
                        of journals, namely the ones that are dedicated to humanities computing, and
                        the others dealing with library and information sciences (see Figures 1
                        &amp; 2). This outcome should not be surprising, as research in the arena of
                        humanities computing was centered upon text mining and analysis of
                        humanities literature, and the publication of these research results were
                        confined to specialized journals such as Humanities Computing. Beside text
                        analysis, a main focus of DH activities was the digitization of archives and
                        libraries, hence the second group of journals are specialized in this area. </p>


                    <p>
                        <figure>
                            <head/>
                            <graphic url="673_fig2.png" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                                mimeType="image/png"/>
                            <head>Figure 1: Journal co-citation patterns of 33 documents citing
                                46 documents about “Digital Humanities” in 2008; threshold 0.5%;
                                cosine ≥ 0.0; N = 15, from Leydesdorff &amp; Akdag Salah
                                (forthcoming).</head>
                        </figure>
                        <figure>
                            <head/>
                            <graphic url="673_fig3.png" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                                mimeType="image/png"/>
                            <head>Figure 2: k-core group of 36 journals bibliographically coupled
                                in 46 documents about “digital humanities”; threshold 0.5%; cosine >
                                0.2, from Leydesdorff &amp; Akdag Salah (forthcoming).</head>
                        </figure>
                    </p>

                    <p>Currently, it is not clear whether DH is in the first formations of either
                        becoming a discipline on its own, or whether it will become merged into the
                        infrastructure of future humanities departments by offering a platform for
                        collaborative research environment enriched by media technologies of today.
                        In either case, our initial findings on DH’s position and its present
                        inability to reach an interdisciplinary audience led us to conclude that
                        policy makers and scholars, both of whom contribute to the development of DH
                        could benefit from an expansion of our analysis.</p>
                    <p>We assume that DH activities that are very innovative and still in an
                        emergent state might not be fully reflected by the journals sampled in <hi
                            rend="italic">Web of Science</hi>. We furthermore suppose that a more
                        in-depth analysis that goes beyond journal-journal citation networks will
                        reveal interesting patterns. We will present the results of a social network
                        analysis and a semantic map of DH based on a dataset extracted from papers
                        published on leading DH journals such as <hi rend="italic">Humanities
                            Computing</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Calica</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi>, as well as papers retrieved
                        from online publication venues such as <hi rend="italic">Text
                            Technology</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Digital Studies</hi>, <hi
                            rend="italic">Digital Medievalist</hi>. We believe that online journals
                        will alter the recent findings of the knowledge dissemination of DH to a
                        considerable extend. Here one should not be limited with classical database
                        providers like <hi rend="italic">Web of Science</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                            >Scopus</hi>, but also make full use of Google Scholar search-engine.
                        Even then, a bibliometric study of the topic confined to journal-journal
                        citation maps will not deliver a complete picture of the flux of DH. To
                        capture this change and the debate around it, we propose a methodology that
                        will incorporate different type of social networks in rendering and
                        interpreting this new research area.</p>
                    <p> DH scholars can use virtual research environments for collaboration and
                        production of knowledge, as well as for publication of their results. Hence,
                        information retrieval from online communities, mailing lists, discussion
                        forums and blogs dedicated to DH research is crucial for understanding the
                        state of the art in projects, programs, and research done in the name of DH.
                        A social network based on the shared keywords of such a dataset reveals what
                        topics are of recent interest to DH scholars. Furthermore, this dataset is
                        used in preparing a second network that shows the links of websites and
                        blogs (in and out), which facilitates the drawing of information flow inside
                        DH community, as well the community's relation to other scholarly
                        communities.</p>
                    <p> A very interesting extension is a map that depicts the connection between
                        institutions and the resources they draw upon. As we have already mentioned,
                        the structural formation of DH is different in every institution. Thus,
                        every DH research environment is built on different premises, and the
                        development of each of these settings is mainly based on internal resources
                        (which are usually delivered in terms of equipment or the availability of
                        technical staff and scholars) and on external support (governmental or
                        private agencies). Today, when the main attention of DH scholars are on
                        combining their past experience and their ideas about DH to create a better
                        platform for humanities departments in general, to depict the flow of
                        resources, financial and otherwise, is as vital as following the flow of
                        information in DH. </p>

                </div>

            </body>

        </text>
    </TEI>

</teiCorpus>
