<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<teiCorpus xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-673">
        <TEI>
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title>Dickens' Double Narrative: Network Analysis of Bleak House</title>
                    <author>
                        <name>Borovsky, Zoe</name>
                        <affiliation>Academic Technology Services and the Center for Digital
                            Humanities, University of California, Los Angeles</affiliation>
                        <email>zoe@ats.ucla.edu</email>
                    </author>

                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College
                        London</publisher>
                    <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change>
                    <date>2009-04-30</date>
                    <name>JL</name>
                    <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <body>
                <div>


                    <p>My presentation extends Masahiro Hori’s collocational analysis of Dickens’
                        style (2004) <note>Hori, M. (2004). Investigating Dickens' style, Palgrave
                            Macmillan.</note> using network content analysis tools. Because DH2010
                        will be held in London, and since Hori devotes a chapter in his book to
                        Dickens’ novel, <hi rend="italic">Bleak House</hi>, I will focus the
                        presentation on this novel. My goals are three-fold: First, I will show how
                        network analysis provides additional insights and metrics for studying the
                        collocational patterns in texts. Secondly, I will demonstrate how this
                        analysis provides new insights into the gender issues in Dickens’ novel.
                        Finally, I will extend my analysis to the field of Digital Humanities and
                        reflect on how it, too, can be read as a “double-narrative” with a deep
                        structure similar to the one Dickens depicts in <hi rend="italic">Bleak
                            House</hi>.</p>
                    <p> Network Analysis has been applied to many different types of systems:
                        sociological, biological, ecological, as well as the Internet. In addition,
                        human language has been examined for evidence of network behavior—the laws
                        that have been shown to govern other complex systems. Beginning with the
                        2001 publication of “The Small World of Human Language”.<note>Cancho, R.F.I.
                            &amp; Solé, R.V. (2001). The Small World of Human Language. Proceedings
                            of the Royal Society of London. Series b, biological sciences, 268,
                            2261--2266.</note> I will present a brief overview of scholarship on
                        network analysis to provide some background. Typically, humanities scholars
                        have used network analysis to model networks described in texts (e.g. the
                        characters in Shakespeare’s plays).<note>Stiller, J., Nettle, D. &amp;
                            Dunbar, R. (2003). The small world of Shakespeare’s plays. Human Nature,
                            14(4): 397-408.</note> However, the main purpose of this paper is to
                        demonstrate the implications of these more theoretical studies upon text
                        analysis.</p>
                    <p> Having provided the context for my analysis, I will show how
                            Wordij,<note>Danowski, J., WORDij, Chicago: University of Illinois at
                            Chicago. Available at: <ptr target="http://wordij.net/"/></note> a suite
                        of network content analysis tools designed to analyze unstructured texts,
                        can be used to extend Hori’s analysis of the collocates<note>Collocates, or
                            word-pairs, have been defined and analyzed in various ways. Hori
                            provides a useful short history in his book. Wordij generates collocates
                            or pairs of words that occur within a user-specified span of surrounding
                            text. See Danowski, J. (2009). Network analysis of message content. In
                            Krippendorff, K &amp; Bock, M. (eds), The content analysis reader. Sage
                            Publications, pp. 421-430 for a detailed description of how Wordij
                            generates and ranks collocates.</note> of the two narrators in Dickens’
                        text. Against the prevailing view that the first-person narrative of the
                        central female character, Esther, is plain and boring, Hori compares the
                        unusual collocates of both narrators. His careful analysis reveals that
                        Esther’s narrative is “linguistically experimental and satisfactorily
                        creative” (Hori 2004, p. 206). My analysis builds upon Hori’s and
                        illustrates that through the course of the novel, the narrative of the
                        anonymous third-person narrator becomes “tainted” with collocates that have
                        led scholars to judge Esther’s narrative as overly sentimental and
                        boring.</p>
                    <p> Because Wordij allows us to analyze texts as a network, with links created
                        between collocates, we can use it to calculate the distance between concepts
                        that are connected through other links. Using the network diagrams produced
                        from collocates of both these narrative sections, I will demonstrate how
                        this type of “semantic map” can be used to compare the distance between
                        words. As examples, I compare the distance between the words “man” and
                        “woman” in each narrator’s section. Opticomm (one of the programs in Wordij)
                        measures the distance between nodes (the words) by counting the number of
                        links between words and calculating the distance or path and the average
                        pair frequency.</p>
                    <!-- use of rightarrow symbol -->
                    <p> For example, one of the shortest paths from the word “man” to “woman” in
                        Esther’s text takes the following route:
                            man<foreign>→</foreign>said<foreign>→</foreign>woman. Opticomm
                        calculates the “distance” using the frequency of the pairs. The pair
                            “man<foreign>→</foreign>said” occurs 27 times (1/27 = .0370), and the
                        pair “said<foreign>→</foreign>woman” occurs 19 times (1/19 =.0526). The sum
                        of the distances equals .0897. The average pair frequency of the path is
                        low: 23. A higher frequency path takes advantage of more frequently used
                        pairs. One of the “hubs” (a word that has many connections) in Esther’s
                        narrative is the word “little”. By adding the word “little” to the path
                            (man<foreign>→</foreign>said<foreign>→</foreign>little<foreign>→</foreign>woman), the
                        distance between “man” and “woman” becomes shorter (.0673) and more frequent
                        (53.6667) [See Figure 1]. </p>

                    <p>
                        <figure>
                            <head/>
                            <graphic url="673_fig1.png" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                                mimeType="image/png"/>
                            <head>Figure 1: Network of collocates of Esther's narrative, Dickens,
                                Bleak House. Visualization is created with NetDraw 2.087 using
                                collocates and distances generated with Wordij. Frequencies of the
                                pairs (shown by weighted lines) are greater than or equal to
                                18.</head>
                        </figure>
                    </p>

                    <p>The results of this analysis show how the third-person narrator’s change in
                        style (employing collocate patterns used in Esther’s text) reflects and
                        mirrors the character development in the novel—the rezoning of the
                        hyper-masculine characters: Sir Leicester Dedlock and Mr. George. I will
                        argue that the deep structure of the novel hinges on this “rezoning” of the
                        masculine-- a plot structure that is remarkably similar to the occult horror
                        films analyzed by Carol Clover in her book: <hi rend="italic">Men, Women and
                            Chainsaws: Gender in the Modern Horror Film</hi>.<note>Clover, C.J.
                            (1993). Men, Women, and Chain Saws: Gender in the Modern Horror Film.
                            Princeton University Press.</note> Like occult films, I will present
                        that the aim of Bleak House is a reconstruction of the masculine, a process
                        that typically takes place almost invisibly, as the texts foregrounds the
                        excesses of the female characters. Thus the narrative technique, one that
                        “opens up” to the sentimental expressions characteristic of Esther’s
                        narrative, reflects the deep-structure “rezoning” on the periphery of Bleak
                        House; George’s Shooting Gallery and Sir Leicester’s Chesney Wold are
                        radically transformed in the novel.</p>
                    <p>Finally, I will draw comparisons between the cultural conditions that evoke
                        these types of structures and double narratives, and reflect on how the
                        field of Digital Humanities can be read in this light. Scholarship in
                        Digital Humanities is a “double-narrative” brought about by the rezoning of
                        hard and soft sciences, a project similar to the reconstruction undertaken
                        by Dickens’ <hi rend="italic">Bleak House</hi>.</p>

                </div>
            </body>
        </text>
    </TEI>
    
</teiCorpus>
