<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-620">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Pointless Babble or Enabled Backchannel: Conference Use of Twitter by Digital
                    Humanists</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Ross, Claire</name>
                    <affiliation>Department of Information Studies, <orgName>University College
                        London</orgName> <reg><country>UK</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>claire.ross@ucl.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Terras, Melissa</name>
                    <affiliation>Department of Information Studies, <orgName>University College
                        London</orgName> <reg><country>UK</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>m.terras@ucl.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Warwick, Claire</name>
                    <affiliation>Department of Information Studies, <orgName>University College
                        London</orgName> <reg><country>UK</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>c.warwick@ucl.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Welsh, Anne</name>
                    <affiliation>Department of Information Studies, <orgName>University College
                        London</orgName> <reg><country>UK</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>a.welsh@ucl.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-14</date>
                <name>JL</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2010-06-10</date>
                <name>JL</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
           <p>Microblogging, a variant of a blogging which allows users to quickly post short
                    updates to websites such as twitter.com, has recently emerged as a dominant form
                    of information interchange and interaction for academic communities. To date,
                    few studies have been undertaken to make explicit how such technologies are used
                    by and can benefit scholars. This paper considers the use of Twitter as a
                    digital backchannel by the Digital Humanities community, taking as its focus
                    postings to Twitter during three different international 2009 conferences. This
                    paper poses the following question: does the use of a Twitter enabled
                    backchannel enhance the conference experience, collaboration and the
                    co-construction of knowledge, or is it a disruptive, disparaging and a
                    inconsequential tool full of ‘pointless babble’?</p>
           <p>Microblogging, with special emphasis on Twitter.com,<note>Twitter was created by
                        a San Francisco based privately funded startup and launched publicly in
                        August 2006. <ref target="http//:twitter.com/about" type="external"
                            >http//:twitter.com/about</ref></note> the most well known microblogging
                    service, is increasingly used as a means of extending commentary and discussion
                    during academic conferences. This digital “backchannel” communication
                    (non-verbal, real-time, communication which does not interrupt a presenter or
                    event, Ynge 1970) is becoming more prevalent at academic conferences, in
                    educational use, and in organizational settings. Frameworks for understanding
                    the role and use of digital backchannel communication, such as that provided by
                    Twitter, in enabling a participatory conference culture are therefore
                    required.</p>
                <p>Formal conference presentations still mainly occur in a traditional setting; a
                    divided space with a ‘front’ area for the speaker and a larger ‘back’ area for
                    the audience. Implying a single focus of attention. There is a growing body of
                    literature describing problems with a traditional conference setting; lack of
                    feedback, nervousness about asking questions and a single speaker paradigm
                    (Anderson et al 2003, Reinhardt et al 2009). The use of a digital backchannel
                    such as Twitter, positioned in contrast with the formal or official conference
                    programme, can address this, providing an irregular, or unofficial means of
                    communication (McCarthy &amp; Boyd, 2005). Backchannel benefits include
                    being able to ask questions, or provide resources and references, changing the
                    dynamics of the room from a one to many transmission to a many to many
                    interaction, without disrupting the main channel communication. Negatives
                    include a cause of distraction, disrespectful content and creating cliques
                    amongst participants (Jacobs &amp; Mcfarlane 2005, McCarthy and Boyd 2005). 
                    Nevertheless research consistently shows the digital backchannel as a valuable
                    way for active participation (Kelly 2009) and that it is highly appropriate for
                    use in learning based environments (Reinhardt et al. 2009). Recently
                    microblogging has been adopted by conferences such as DH2009 to act as a
                    backchannel as it allows for the ‘spontaneous co-construction of digital
                    artefacts’ (Costa et al 2008). Such communication usually involves note taking,
                    sharing resources and individuals real time reactions to events.</p>
                <p>This paper presents a study that analyses the use of Twitter as a backchannel for
                    academic conferences, focusing on the Digital Humanities community in three
                    different physical conference settings held from June to September 2009. During
                    three key conferences in the academic field (Digital Humanities 2009, That Camp
                    2009 and Digital Resources in the Arts and Humanities 2009), unofficial Twitter
                    backchannels were established using conference specific hashtags (#dh09,
                    #thatcamp and #drha09, #drha20091<note>The community aspect of Twitter means
                        that participants self organize, instigating tags themselves, hence the
                        participants of Digital Resources in the Arts and Humanities used two
                        different hashtags to discuss the conference depending on the twitter
                        user.</note>) to enable visible commentary and discussion. The resulting
                    corpus of individual “tweets” provides a rich dataset, allowing analysis of the
                    use of Twitter in an academic setting, and specifically presenting how the
                    Digital Humanities community has embraced this microblogging tool.</p>
            <div>
                <head>Method</head>
                <p>Data from the three conferences was collected by archiving tweets which used the
                    four distinct conference hashtags.  (These hashtags were used prior to and after
                    the conferences, and have been reused by other conferences, therefore the corpus
                    was limited to tweets posted during the span of each conference). This provided
                    a data set of 4574 tweets from 326 distinct Twitter users, resulting in a corpus
                    of 77308 tokens, which were analysed using various quantitative and qualitative
                    methods which allowed us to understand and categorize the resulting corpus
                    effectively.</p>
                <p> Quantitative measures were used such as identifying prominent tweeters,
                    analysing the frequency of conversations between users and the frequency of
                    reposting messages (“retweeting”), and the differing use of Twitter at the three
                    separate events. Text analysis tools were also used to interrogate the corpus. </p>
                <p> Tweets were then categorized qualitatively using open coded content analysis
                    where each post was read and categorized, determining the apparent intention of
                    each twitter post.  It was necessary to develop our own categories: although
                    Java et al (2007) present a brief taxonomy of Twitter user intentions (daily
                    chatter, conversations, sharing information and reporting news)  they are based
                    on general Twitter use and were too imprecise for our needs. Ebner (2008)
                    discovered four major categories in his study of the use of Twitter during the
                    keynote presentation at the Ed-Media 2008 conference, but this is a small study
                    limited to 54 posts made by ten distinct users, whereas the DH conferences
                    involved a much larger user population. Through our analysis, Tweets were
                    divided into seven categories: comments on presentations; sharing resources;
                    discussions and conversations; jotting down notes; establishing an online
                    presence; and asking organizational questions.  Tweets which were highly
                    ambiguous were placed in an Unknown category. </p>

            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Findings</head>
                <p>Conference hashtagged Twitter activity does not constitute a single distributed
                    conversation but, rather multiple monologues and a few intermittent, loosely
                    joined dialogues between users. The majority of the activity was original
                    tweeting (93%): only 6.7% were re-tweets (RT) of others’ ideas or comments. The
                    real time interchange and speed of review of shared ideas appears to create a
                    context of users offering ideas and summaries and not spreading the ideas of
                    others verbatim. 45% of the tweets during the conference proceedings included
                    direct references to others’ Twitter IDs, using the ‘@’ sign, as the source of a
                    quote, object of a reply or debate. This implies a form of collaborative writing
                    activity, driving a conference community of practice (Wenger 1998) who are
                    involved in shared meaning making and the co-construction of knowledge (McNely
                    2009). However, the content of the tweets indicate that the discussion was
                    between a few Twitter users rather than mass collaboration and was not
                    necessarily focused on conference content.</p>
                <p>Jacob and Mcfarlane (2005) discuss polarization in digital backchannels,
                    highlighting a conflict between an inclusive and participatory conference
                    culture and a fragmentation of conference participants into cliques only
                    intermittently engaged with the main presentations. This, in some instances
                    seems to be the case during the Digital Humanities conferences, suggesting that
                    newer members of the discipline or newer uses to Twitter may be excluded from
                    the discussion. This also raises the question about official and unofficial
                    backchannels. When communication is digitally mediated, backchannels may not be
                    obvious. That is, even if participants know who else is participating in an
                    interaction, this doesn’t guarantee (as it does in the front channel) that it is
                    an accessible backchannel. Therefore by its nature an unofficial backchannel
                    does not enable active participation. Further research is currently being
                    undertaken on this corpus, which will be presented fully in the paper. </p>
                <p>Most tweets in the corpus fell into the category of jotting down notes, triggered
                    predominately by the front channel presentation, suggesting that participants
                    are sharing experiences and to a degree co-constructing knowledge. What is
                    surprising is the lack of direct commentary on presentations. Although Reinhardt
                    et al (2009) argue that Twitter enables thematic debates and offers a digital
                    backchannel for further discussion and commentary, the tweet data suggests that
                    this does not appear to have happened to a significant extent at the digital
                    humanities conferences. This raises the question of whether a Twitter enabled
                    backchannel promotes more of an opportunity for users to establish an online
                    presence and enhance their digital identity rather than encouraging a
                    participatory conference culture. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>This study of digital humanities conference tweets provides an insight into the
                    Digital Humanities community of practice. The Twitter enabled backchannel
                    constitutes a complex multidirectional discursive space in which the conference
                    participants make notes, share resources, hold discussions and ask questions as
                    well as establishing a clear individual online presence. While determining
                    individual user intentions in Twitter in a conference setting is challenging, it
                    is possible to describe broad behavioral trends of tweeting during Digital
                    Humanities conferences. The predominance of note taking suggests that the DH
                    community could be classed as social reporters, commenting on the conference
                    presentations for outsiders, rather than collaborating during the conference.
                    There was also a tendency for a small group of users to produce the majority of
                    tweets, interacting with each other about other matters. This suggests the small
                    friendly nature of the DH researcher community, but may also be somewhat
                    intimidating for those new to the field or conference. The Twitter enabled
                    backchannel thus raises some interesting questions about the nature of
                    conference participation and whether or not it is helped or hindered by a
                    digital backchannel. Rather than pointless babble, the twitter record produced
                    at each conference provides important evidence regarding how Digital Humanities,
                    as a community of practice, functions and interacts. </p>
            </div>

        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>

                    <bibl><author>Anderson, R.J.</author>,<author>Anderson, R.</author>,
                            <author>Vandergrift, T.</author>
                        <author>Wolfman, S.</author>
                        <author>Yasuhara, K.</author>
                        <date>2003</date>
                        <title level="a">Promoting Interaction in Large Classes with Computer
                            Mediated Feedback</title><title level="m" type="proceedings">Designing
                            for Change in Networked Learning Environments. Proceedings of
                            CSCC</title><name type="venue"
                                >Bergen</name>
                        <biblScope type="pp">119-123</biblScope></bibl>

                    <bibl>
                        <author>Barnes, S.J.</author>
                        <author>Böhringer, M.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Continuance Usage Intention in Microblogging services: The
                            Case of Twitter</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Proceedings of the 17th European
                            Conference on Information Systems (ECIS)</title>
                        <ptr target="http://www.ecis2009.it/papers/ecis2009-0164.pdf"/>
                    </bibl>

                    <bibl>
                        <author>Costa, C.</author>
                        <author>Beham, G.</author>
                        <author>Reinhardt, W.</author>
                        <author>Sillaots, M.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">Microblogging In Technology Enhanced Learning: A Use-Case
                            Inspection of PPE Summer School 2008</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Microblogging in technology enhanced
                            learning conferences: A use case Inspection Workshop at the European
                            Conference on Technology Enhanced Learning</title>
                        <date type="conference">2008</date>
                        <name type="venue">Maastricht, the Netherlands</name>
                    </bibl>

                    <bibl>
                        <author>Ebner, M.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Introducing Live Microblogging: How Single Presentations
                            Can Be Enhanced by the Mass</title>
                        <title level="j">Journal of Research in Innovative Teaching</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue"> Volume 2, Issue 1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">91-100</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Ebner, M.</author>
                        <author>Schiefner, M.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">Microblogging - more than fun?</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Proceedings of IADIS Mobile Learning
                            Conference</title>
                        <date type="conference">2008</date>
                        <name type="venue">Algarve, Portugal</name>
                        <biblScope type="pp"> 155-159</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Jacobs, N.</author>
                        <author>Mcfarlane, A.</author>
                        <date>2005</date>
                        <title level="a">Conferences as Learning Communities: Some early lessons in
                            using ‘back-channel’ Technologies at an Academic Conference - Distributed
                            Intelligence or Divided Attention</title>
                        <title level="j">Journal of Computer Assisted Learning</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">21 (5)</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">317-329</biblScope>
                    </bibl>

                    <bibl>
                        <author>Java, A.</author>
                        <author>Song, X.</author>
                        <author>Finin, T.</author>
                        <author>Tseng, B.</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">Why we twitter: understanding microblogging usage and
                            communities</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">International Conference on Knowledge
                            Discovery and Data Mining Proceedings of the 9th WebKDD and 1st SNA-KDD
                            2007 workshop on Web mining and social network analysis</title>
                        <date type="conference">2007</date>
                        <name type="venue">New York</name>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Karger, D. R.</author>
                        <author>Quan, D</author>
                        <date>2005</date>
                        <title level="a">What would it mean to blog on the semantic Web?</title>
                        <title level="j">Web Semantics: Sciences, Services and Agents on the World
                            Wide Web</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">147-157</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kelly, B.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="m">(TwitterFall) Your’re My Wonder Wall. UK Web Focus:
                            Reflections on the Web and Web 2.0</title>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://ukwebfocus.worpress.com/2009/04/20/twiterfall-youre-my-wonder-wall/"
                        />
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Krishnamurthy, B.</author>
                        <author>Gill, P.</author>
                        <author>Arlitt, M.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">A few Chirps about Twitter</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">WOSP 08: Proceedings of the first
                            workshop on online social networks</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>McCarthy, J.F.</author>
                        <author>Boyd, D.</author>
                        <date>2005</date>
                        <title level="a">Digital backchannels in shared physical spaces: Experiences
                            at an academic Conference</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Proceedings of the Conference on Human
                            Factors in Computing Systems</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>McFedries, P.</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">All a-twitter</title>
                        <title level="j">IEE Spectrum</title>
                        <biblScope type="pp">84</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>McNely, B.J.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Backchannel Persistence and Collaborative Meaning
                            Making</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Proceedings of the 27th ACM
                            international conference on Design of communication</title>
                        <name type="venue">Bloomington, Indiana</name>
                    </bibl>

                    <bibl><author>Reinhardt, W.</author><author>Ebner M.</author>, <author>Beham
                            G.</author>, <author>Costa, C.</author>
                        <date>2009</date><title level="a">How People are using Twitter during
                            Conferences</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Creativity and Innovation Competencies
                            on the Web. Proceeding of 5. EduMedia conference</title></bibl>

                    <bibl><author>Wenger, E.</author>
                        <date>1998</date> <title level="m">Communities of practice: learning,
                            meaning, and identity</title><publisher>Cambridge University
                            Press</publisher></bibl>

                    <bibl>
                        <author>Ynge, V.</author>
                        <date>1970</date>
                        <title level="a">On Getting a Word in Edgewise</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Papers from the Sixth Regional Meeting
                            of the Chicago Linguistic Society</title>
                        <biblScope type="pp">567-577</biblScope>
                    </bibl>

                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
