<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-722">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Graceful Degradation Survey: Managing Digital Humanities Projects Through
                    Times of Transition and Decline</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Nowviskie, Bethany</name>
                    <affiliation>Scholars' Lab, <orgName>University of Virginia</orgName> Library
                                <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email> bethany@virginia.edu </email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Porter, Dot</name>
                    <affiliation>Digital Humanities Observatory, <orgName>Royal Irish Academy</orgName> <reg><country>Ireland</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>dot.porter@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2009-04-23</date>
                <name>JL</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>2009-06-11</date>
                <name>JL</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <!-- or poster -->
        <body>


            <p>Transition and decline are pressing issues for scholars in the digital humanities, as
                our projects tend to be both collaborative and open-ended. Project staff relocate,
                reestablish themselves in new areas, or retire, even as funding and institutional
                support comes and goes. How are projects to be designed so that they can be
                maintained, or maintain themselves, through periods of change? How might projects be
                designed in a way that takes periods of transition and possible decline into account
                from the very start?</p>

            <p>These are some of the issues we sought to explore in undertaking "Graceful
                Degradation: Managing Digital Projects in Times of Transition and Decline," a
                wide-ranging survey of the digital humanities community, in the summer of 2009. Our
                intent was to investigate how the community currently deals with these problems and,
                using our survey data – which also included some demographic information and
                measures of perceived levels of support and impact of various kinds of change – to
                make recommendations on how we, as a community, might improve the current
                approach.</p>

            <p> This presentation will provide a detailed look at the outcomes of the "Graceful
                Degradation" survey, and propose some initial recommendations. (Full recommendations
                will be published in a separate article.)</p>

            <p> The survey was designed in consultation with statistical analysis staff at the
                Scholars' Lab, University of Virginia Library and unveiled at Digital Humanities
                2009 in College Park, Maryland and at Digital Resources for the Humanities and Arts
                (DRHA 2009) in Belfast, Northern Ireland. It was conducted online between July and
                September 2009. There were 102 completed surveys, representing 114 discrete
                projects. Some of our findings are presented below.</p>

            <p> The vast majority (76%) of Graceful Degradation respondents come from "large
                universities with a research emphasis," but teaching colleges, cultural heritage
                institutions, and commercial ventures were also represented. Most respondents have
                worked in project management or digital research and development efforts in the
                humanities for 2-10 years, but 35% of respondents have been engaged in this activity
                for more than a decade.</p>

            <p> Respondents were asked to rate perceived levels of support for the digital
                humanities at their home institutions, including (as separate queries) general
                support, support for collaborative activities, local funding and cost-share
                opportunities, support by higher administration, department-level or local support,
                and support for project management and grant-writing.</p>

            <p> 64% of respondents had experienced the decline of a project or had weathered a
                period of difficult transition. 29% of respondents indicated a sense that digital
                humanities projects are more likely to decline or suffer these difficult transitions
                at their institutions than at others.</p>

            <p> Participants were asked to respond in detail regarding their experiences with a
                particular project that suffered decline or a difficult transition. The following
                percentages apply to the primary or to the single project which survey participants
                addressed. 37% of respondents identified themselves as project lead or principal
                investigator (PI) for the project they discussed in depth. 29% of respondents
                self-identified as project managers, and other respondents fell into categories such
                as "dedicated, project-specific support staff," "support staff on loan from other
                units," "graduate or undergraduate research staff," "post-docs or faculty
                collaborators."</p>

            <p> 38% of projects discussed fell into the category of "content creation, digitization,
                and archive-building," but other categories (including software development, online
                community-building activities, online journals and other publications, and creation
                of support infrastructure for digital scholarship) were also represented.
                Predominant disciplines and time periods addressed were literary and textual studies
                and digital history, from the modern or early modern era. More projects (31% and 24%
                respectively) identified an academic department and a library or museum as their
                primary institutional home, with 23% primarily housed in a digital humanities
                center.</p>

            <p>Of projects that had experienced decline or difficult transition, most were
                identified as still "ongoing and active" (51%), with 26% abandoned or dormant, and
                15% and 8% either complete or "just getting started," respectively.</p>

            <p> Participants were asked about funding sources for these projects (generally via
                institutional support or "external public funding") and understood length of funding
                or support. Projects treated were generally funded for 2-3 years, with no
                possibility of renewal, but often (in 21% of cases) the length of funding or support
                was "unclear." That said, 75% of respondents considered their project's funding to
                be "reliable and clear in scope."</p>

            <p> Most respondents undertook the treated project with clear plans for supporting it
                beyond an initial funding period, but most projects also ultimately "differed in
                scope or definition from early plans." In 68% of cases, participants had identified
                both short-term and long-term goals for their projects, but conscious use of
                "specific project management techniques or tools" and "risk management strategies"
                was a rarity. Anecdotal responses treated the impact of varying levels of planning
                or lack of planning on digital projects.</p>

            <p> The majority of projects (55%) experienced no negative impact due to staff overturn
                whatsoever. For projects that did, we asked participants to rate the negative impact
                of overturn of six different categories of staff members and collaborators. Survey
                participants also rated the broad impact of their projects in a dozen areas, such as
                "scholarly inquiry in a particular field," "my own pedagogical practice," and "the
                professional advancement of my collaborators."</p>

            <p> Participants were additionally given the opportunity to respond to several prose
                prompts, and to add more contextual information to many of the questions for which
                we had devised statistical measures. They summarized the reasons for the project
                decline or difficult transitions they experienced, and offered formulae for their
                successes. Some respondents identified nuanced issues with intellectual property and
                open source as contributing factors. We plan to summarize these rich responses and
                reveal the results of qualitative data analysis at the conference.</p>

            <p> 67% of respondents indicated that their personal views and practices have evolved as
                a result of experiencing a period of difficult transition or the decline of digital
                humanities project, but in only 32% of cases did they feel that the views or
                practices of their local institutions or the larger academic community have evolved
                in response to such experiences like these.</p>

            <p> 67% of respondents also indicated that they had experienced what they would consider
                a "phase of successful transition" in their digital projects, and offered anecdotal
                advice as to what made that possible.</p>

            <p> At Digital Humanities 2010, we will summarize and offer some visualizations and
                analysis of these findings and others, and we will address the extensive qualitative
                data that were collected from participants in free-form text responses. (Several
                participants granted us permission to quote their responses directly. We will
                anonymize and summarize responses from others.) We will also draw conclusions about
                avenues for future research and – more importantly – identify areas for future
                action on the part of institutions supporting digital humanities projects and
                professional societies representing the digital humanities community.</p>



        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <!-- Note: use of 'et al' -->
                    <bibl><author>Matthew Kirschenbaum et al</author>
                        <title level="a">Done: 'Finished' Projects in the Digital Humanities</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Digital Humanities</title>
                        <date type="conference">2007</date>
                        <name type="venue">Urbana-Champaign, Illinois</name></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Daniel Pitti</author><title level="a">Designing Sustainable
                            Projects and Publications</title><title level="m">A Companion to Digital
                            Humanities</title><editor>Susan Schreibman</editor>
                        <editor>Ray Siemens</editor>
                        <editor>John Unsworth</editor>
                        <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Blackwell</publisher>
                        <date>2004</date><ptr target="http://digitalhumanities.org/companion/"/>
                        <date type="visited">13 November 2009</date></bibl>

                    <!-- Note: use of 'et al' -->
                    <bibl><author>Stephen Ramsay et al</author>
                        <title level="a">Innovations in Interdisciplinary Research Project
                            Management</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Digital Humanities</title>
                        <date type="conference">2008</date>
                        <name type="venue">Oulu, Finland</name></bibl>

                    <bibl><author>Geoffrey Rockwell</author><author>Shawn Day</author><title
                            level="a">Burying Dead Projects: Depositing the Globalization
                            Compendium</title><title level="m" type="proceedings">Digital
                            Humanities</title>
                        <date type="conference">2009</date>
                        <name type="venue">College Park, Maryland</name></bibl>

                    <bibl><editor>Siemens, Lynne</editor><title level="m" type="proceedings">Issues
                            in Large Project Planning and Management. Digital Humanities Summer
                            Institute</title><name type="venue">Victoria</name>, <date
                            type="conference">2009</date></bibl>

                    <!-- advcance access -->
                    <bibl><author>Siemens, Lynne</author><title level="a">It's a team if you use
                            "reply all": An exploration of research teams in digital humanities
                            environments</title>
                        <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing Advance Access</title>
                        <date>June 1, 2009</date>
                        <biblScope type="issue">24</biblScope><biblScope type="pp"
                            >225-233</biblScope>
                        <ptr target="DOI 10.1093/llc/fqp009"/><title level="j">Literary and
                            Linguistic Computing</title>
                    </bibl>

                    <bibl><author>Siemens, L.</author>
                        <author>Cunningham, R.</author>
                        <author>Duff, W.</author>
                        <author>Warwick, C.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">More minds are brought to bear on a problem: Methods of
                            Interaction and Collaboration within Digital Humanities Research
                            Teams</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Society for Digital Humanities/Société
                            pour l'étude des  médias interactifs</title></bibl>

                    <!-- CLIR Reports - journa? Series? How to mark up? -->
                    <bibl><author>Diane Zorich</author>
                        <title level="m">A Survey of Digital Humanities Centers in the United
                            States</title> CLIR Reports, <date>November 2008.</date>
                        <ptr target="http://www.clir.org/pubs/reports/pub143/contents.html"/><date
                            type="accessed">13 November 2009</date></bibl>

                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
