<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-731">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>A corpus approach to cultural keywords: a critical corpus-based analysis of
                    ideology in the Blair years (1998-2007) through print news reporting</title>
                <author>
                    <name> Jeffries, Lesley</name>
                    <affiliation> The <orgName>University of Huddersfield</orgName>, <country>UK</country></affiliation>
                    <email>l.jeffries@hud.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name> Walker, Brian David</name>
                    <affiliation> The <orgName>University of Huddersfield</orgName>, <country>UK</country></affiliation>
                    <email>b.d.walker1@lancaster.ac.uk</email>
                </author>


            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-29</date>
                <name>JL</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>This paper will report on a corpus-based study of the cultural keywords (in the
                Raymond Williams’ sense) via the analysis of key-words (in the corpus/statistical
                sense) of newspaper reporting in the years since Labour came to power. The project
                demonstrates that certain lexemes (or lexical strings) gain currency in relatively
                short historical periods and may take on political importance.</p>
            <p>This project assesses the ideological landscape during the years of the New Labour
                project by extracting the cultural keywords of the time, and demonstrating their
                evolving meanings in the commentary provided by the print media.</p>
            <p>The project takes inspiration from Raymond Williams’ book ([1975] 1983) <hi
                    rend="italic">Keywords</hi> which attempted to sum up the ideology of the
                post-war years. Williams chose a set of words which he thought had taken on
                particular meanings in that period, and wrote an informed but ultimately anecdotal
                commentary on each one. Like Williams, we begin with a hypothesis that some words
                (such as, for example, <hi rend="italic">radicalisation</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                    >choice</hi>) have both increased in usage and polarised in their meaning since
                1998.</p>
            <p>Unlike Williams, this project pursues a rigorous approach to the discovery of <hi
                    rend="italic">which</hi> words characterise the period under investigation,
                using two corpora of newspaper data and computer tools. This enables us to make a
                comprehensive investigation and an objective assessment, including use and meaning,
                of the cultural keywords of the Blair years</p>
            <p>The project is primarily corpus-based, but with a strong qualitative focus, using an
                approach to studying textually-constructed meanings of words and other linguistic
                items which recognises both their place in a relatively stable system of language,
                and their capacity to take on additional meaning in specific contexts of time and
                place.</p>
            <div>
                <head>Background</head>
                <p>Our project links the corpus linguistic notion of key-words to earlier work into
                    the ‘emergent meaning’ of individual lexical items (see Jeffries 2003, 2006 and
                    2007). </p>
                <p>Jeffries (2003) investigated the meaning of water, in the context of the
                    Yorkshire water crisis of 1995. Jeffries (2006) investigated the speech act of
                    apology, in particular news commentators’ view of Blair’s putative apology for
                    the Iraq war. Jeffries (2007) was a much more extensive consideration of the way
                    in which the female body was constructed by women’s magazines in 2004. This
                    larger study developed a system of describing textual meaning which draws on
                    Hallidayan approaches to systems of linguistic form and meaning applying his
                    combined semantic and syntactic view of textual meaning to other functions such
                    as the construction of opposites.</p>
                <p>The current project was designed in the spirit of Critical Discourse Analysis, in
                    particular the work of Fairclough whose work on ideology in language, and
                    specifically the language of New Labour (Fairclough 2000) influences the
                    approach taken here. However, the methods used in this project are closer to
                    corpus stylistics in that they are text-analytic and at least in some of the
                    stages, computer-assisted and corpus-driven. Work already carried out in this
                    area (see for example McIntyre and Walker 2010) showed that corpus approaches
                    and tools, in particular Wmatrix, can successfully be applied to textual
                    analysis. Baker and McEnery (2005) and Baker and Gabrielatos (2008) are also
                    influential on this project because this work has paralleled Jeffries’ work in
                    looking at sets of texts from a particular time period to demonstrate political
                    ideologies in news texts.</p>
                <p>The project also reflects renewed interest in cultural keywords in the Williams
                    sense, with a recent special issue of Critical Quarterly (2007) devoted to the
                    subject, and Durant’s (2006) related article which suggests that “[…] the
                    development of electronic search capabilities applied to large corpora of
                    language use […] encourages renewed attention to cultural keywords.” (Durant
                    2006). This project effectively takes up that suggestion.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Research questions</head>
                <p>
                    <xmt:oList rend="arabic">
                        <item>What are the key-words for the years 1998–2007, as evidenced in the
                            British press and can they be identified as cultural keywords?</item>
                        <item>Have they developed meanings specific to this period and have these
                            meanings evolved within the period?</item>
                    </xmt:oList>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Methodology</head>
                <p>The project focuses on news texts from 1998 to the end of 2007. A corpus of
                    comparable data from three national daily newspapers (The Guardian, The
                    Independent, and The Times) was assembled from a large, on-line newspaper
                    database. This database represents a very rich and potentially overwhelming
                    amount of data (100s of millions of words). However, our project had very
                    limited timescales and we found it necessary to carefully control the amount of
                    data that we collected. This was because: (i) downloading selected articles from
                    the database is largely a manual and fairly time consuming process; and (ii) in
                    its raw form each downloaded article contained structured extra-textual details
                    (headers containing titles, dates and so forth), random intra-textual
                    information (such as journalist’s email addresses) and corruptions. This extra
                    text and corrupted data had to be removed from and amended in each of the
                    downloaded files: a laborious process which consumed a lot of project time. We
                    also found that the corpus tools we used for data manipulation struggled when
                    presented with files of more than one million words. Consequently, we took a
                    structured sampling approach, choosing a week from the politically ‘busy’ month
                    of September (party conferences), and collected selected news-related items from
                    these weeks. The resulting corpus was approximately 2.3 million words, which we
                    anticipated would be sufficient to answer our research questions. A comparison
                    corpus was built along similar lines using newspaper data from the five year
                    period prior to 1997 (the Major years).</p>
                <p>The corpus was automatically analysed, in the first instance, using Wmatrix
                    (Rayson 2008), which is a relatively new corpus tool that can calculate keyness
                    (using Log-likelihood) at the word level (key-words), at the grammatical level
                    (key-POS), and the semantic level (key-concepts). The present study uses just
                    the key-word output.</p>
                <p>To address the qualitative aspect of the research questions, this investigation
                    included the following considerations: <xmt:uList>
                        <item>Do the collocations of the key-word demonstrate particular nuances of
                            meaning?</item>
                        <item>How does the semantico-syntactic behaviour of the key-word demonstrate
                            meaning specific to the context?</item>
                        <item>Does the key-word enter into any unconventional lexical relations
                            (e.g. of opposition)?</item>
                        <item>Is the key-word associated with any modal or negated text
                            worlds?</item>
                    </xmt:uList></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Results</head>
                <p>The key-words, generated from the comparison of our corpora, that we consider to
                    be the important cultural keywords from the Blair years are as follows: <table>
                        <row role="label">
                            <cell role="label" rend="1cm"> No.</cell>
                            <cell role="label" rend="1.5cm"> Keyword</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Associated key-words</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="data">1</cell>
                            <cell role="data"> Terror</cell>
                            <cell role="data"> Terrorism, terrorist(s), attacks, atrocities,
                                threat</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="data"> 2</cell>
                            <cell role="data"> Global</cell>
                            <cell role="data"> Globalisation, world, international</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="data"> 3</cell>
                            <cell role="data"> Spin</cell>
                            <cell role="data"> spun</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="data"> 4</cell>
                            <cell role="data"> Reform</cell>
                            <cell role="data"> progressive, radical, modernise(d) / er(s) /
                                ation</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell role="data"> 5</cell>
                            <cell role="data"> Choice</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>

                            <cell role="data"> 6</cell>
                            <cell role="data"> Respect</cell>

                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>
                <p>Items in the ‘keyword’ column are the main items used in our investigation and
                    the terms that we consider to be culturally significant. The items in the third
                    column are key-words resulting from our corpus comparison which are related to
                    individual (cultural) keywords and which, we hypothesise, form a network of
                    meaning. These are still to be fully investigated and we do not report on them
                    in this paper.</p>
                <p>For each keyword we provide a more detailed quantitative commentary using
                    concordance and collocation data. Our major findings, though rigorous and
                    replicable, are qualitative, and provide the basis of both detailed linguistic
                    commentaries on each key-word and could also provide the foundation for more
                    general popular essays not dissimilar to those provided by Williams, but with
                    more clarity about their provenance. There will not be time to discuss all our
                    findings, but our paper will report on some of the quantitative data and focus
                    qualitatively on ‘spin’.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>


                    <bibl><author>Adamson, S.</author>
                        <author>Durant, A</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="j">Critical Quarterly</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">49,1</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Baker, P.</author><author>McEnery, A.</author><date>2005</date>
                        <title level="a">A corpus-based approach to discourses of refugees and
                            asylum seekers in UN and newspaper texts</title>
                        <title level="j">Language and Politics</title><biblScope type="issue"
                            >4:2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">197-226(30)</biblScope></bibl>
                    <!-- bib entry has accepted for publication -->
                    <bibl><author>Baker, P.</author><author>Gabrielatos,
                            C.</author><date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">Fleeing, sneaking, flooding: a corpus analysis of
                            discursive constructions of refugees and asylum seekers in the UK Press
                            1996-2005</title>
                        <title level="j">Journal of English Linguistics</title>
                        <edition>Forthcoming</edition></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Durant, A.</author><date>2006</date><title level="a">Raymond
                            Williams’s Keywords: Investigating Meanings ‘‘offered, felt for, tested,
                            confirmed, asserted, qualified, changed’’</title><title level="j"
                            >Critical Quarterly</title><biblScope type="issue"
                            >48:1</biblScope><biblScope type="pp"> 1–26</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Fairclough, N.</author>
                        <date>2000</date>
                        <title level="m">New Labour, New Language</title>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Routledge</publisher>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Jeffries, Lesley</author>
                        <date>2003</date>
                        <title level="a">Not a drop to drink: Emerging meanings in local newspaper
                            reporting of the 1995 water crisis in Yorkshire</title>
                        <title level="j">Text - Interdisciplinary Journal for the Study of
                            Discourse</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">23 (4)</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">513-538</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Jeffries, Lesley </author><date>2006</date>
                        <title level="a">Journalistic Constructions of Blair's 'Apology' for the
                            Intelligence Leading to the Iraq War</title>
                        <title type="m">Language in the Media: Representations, Identities,
                            Ideologies. Advances in Sociolinguistics</title>
                        <publisher>Continuum</publisher><pubPlace> London</pubPlace>
                        <biblScope type="pp">48-69</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Jeffries, Lesley</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="m">Textual Construction of the Female Body A Critical
                            Discourse Approach</title>
                        
                        <pubPlace>Basingstoke</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>McIntyre, D.</author><author>Walker, B.</author>
                        <date>2010</date>
                        <title level="a">‘How can corpora be used to explore the language of poetry
                            and drama?’</title>
                        <editor>McCarthy, M.</editor>
                        <editor>O’Keefe, A.</editor><title level="m">The Routledge Handbook of
                            Corpus Linguistics</title><pubPlace> Abingdon</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Routledge</publisher></bibl>
                    <!-- Gives details of website - how to mark up? -->
                    <bibl><author>Rayson, P.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="m">Wmatrix: a web-based corpus processing environment,</title>
                        Computing Department, Lancaster University <ptr
                            target="http://www.comp.lancs.ac.uk/ucrel/wmatrix/"/></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Williams, R.</author>
                        <date>1983</date>
                        <title level="m">Keywords (2nd Ed.)</title>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Fontana</publisher></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
