<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-763">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>“Quivering Web of Living Thought”: Mapping the Conceptual Networks of
                    Swinburne's <hi rend="italic">Songs of the Springtides</hi></title>
                <author>
                    <name>Walsh, John A.</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Indiana University</orgName> <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>jawalsh@indiana.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Foong, Pin Sym</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Indiana University</orgName> <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Anand, Kshitiz</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Indiana University</orgName> <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Ramesh, Vignesh</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Indiana University</orgName> <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-28</date>
                <name>AC</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Our paper will discuss conceptual networks present in Victorian poet Algernon
                    Charles Swinburne's mid-career collection <hi rend="italic">Songs of the
                        Springtides</hi> (1880) and how those networks may be represented in TEI P5
                    XML markup and graphic visualizations driven by the encoded text.</p>
                <p>Swinburne’s work is full of familiar signposts and nodes, such as his trademark
                    binary oppositions and pairings: pain/pleasure, life/death, love/hate,
                    hope/fear, sleep/death. An incredibly learned poet with an extensive range of
                    form and allusion, Swinburne’s poems are packed with often obscure references to
                    the Bible, classical mythology, and Arthurian legend. He wrote a number of
                    political poems addressing contemporary events. He wrote parodies of other
                    contemporary poets, including Tennyson, Browning, and Rossetti. And as Jerome
                    McGann has noted, “No English poet has composed more elegies than Swinburne”
                    (McGann 293). These binary oppositions; the many biblical, mythical and
                    legendary references; the historical and contemporary figures who are eulogized
                    in the elegies and praised in the many tributes and dedications; the pervasive
                    symbols of song and the sea: these elements of Swinburne’s verse all serve as
                    familiar, easily identifiable nodes of information, laden with meaning acquired
                    through strategic repetition and structural integration into the intellectual
                    networks of Swinburne’s work. We will examine these nodes, structures and
                    architectonic forms in one of Swinburne’s most artfully crafted and carefully
                    designed collections, <hi rend="italic">Songs of the Springtides</hi>.</p>
                <p>The mid-career <hi rend="italic">Songs of the Springtides</hi> is a particularly
                    interesting volume in the context of inter- and intra-textual networks. For <hi
                        rend="italic">Songs of the Springtides</hi>, Swinburne originally planned “a
                    little volume containing three poems upwards of 500 lines each in length, all of
                    them in a sense sea-studies” (Swinburne <hi rend="italic">Uncollected
                        Letters</hi> 2:181). The three poems are: “Thalassius,” “On the Cliffs,” and
                    “The Garden of Cymodoce.” To this “triad of sea-studies” Swinburne added the
                    “Birthday Ode” to Victor Hugo. Unannounced but also present in the volume are
                    three short poems: the fifteen-line “Dedication” to Edward John Trelawny,
                    Swinburne’s “old sea king” and a friend of Shelley’s (Swinburne <hi
                        rend="italic">Uncollected Letters</hi> 2:181); an untitled sonnet, with the
                    first line “Between two seas the sea-bird’s wing makes halt;” and another
                    sonnet, buried in the notes to the ode for Hugo, “On the proposed desecration of
                    Westminster Abbey by the creation of a monument to the son of Napoleon III.”</p>
                <p>This small volume is an artful example of a deliberately fashioned and
                    architected whole connected by complex discourse networks of key concepts that
                    operate within, across, and beyond the individual poems. Familiarity with the
                    poems of <hi rend="italic">Songs of the Springtides</hi> reveals a few key
                    concepts, figures, or images of particular import and penetration: Swinburne's
                    pantheon of literary heroes; song and music; the natural world, especially the
                    sea; the poet; the text.</p>
                <p>In many cases occurrences of these concepts may be identified algorithmically.
                    However, one cannot rely on string pattern matching to find all words and
                    phrases related to a particular concept. In the case of <hi rend="italic"
                        >song</hi>, for instance, automated processes may be used to identify the
                    many clear and obvious occurrences of this concept, phrases including words such
                    as <hi rend="italic">song</hi>, <hi rend="italic">songs</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >sing</hi>, <hi rend="italic">singer</hi>, <hi rend="italic">music</hi>,
                    etc. However, the poems also contain phrases such as the following: “lutes and
                    lyres of milder and mightier strings,” which is obviously related to music, but
                    less susceptible to automated identification. A combination of automated and
                    manual markup then has been used to identify and encode words and phrases
                    related to the concepts of interest in the texts.</p>
                <p>This notion of the text as a self-constituted network or as a part of a larger
                    inter-textual network is found in influential writings of the major sages of
                    poststructuralism and postmodernism. In <hi rend="italic">S/Z</hi>, Roland
                    Barthes writes about the text as <q rend="block">an entrance into a network with
                        a thousand entrances; to take this entrance is to aim, ultimately, not at a
                        legal structure of norms and departures, a narrative or poetic Law, but at a
                        perspective (of fragments, of voices from other texts, other codes), whose
                        vanishing point is nonetheless ceaselessly pushed back, mysteriously opened;
                        each (single) text is the very theory (and not the mere example) of this
                        vanishing, of this difference which indefinitely returns, insubmissive.
                        (12)</q>
                </p>
                <p>Michel Foucault, in <hi rend="italic">The Archaeology of Knowledge</hi> writes,
                        <q rend="block">The frontiers of a book are never clear-cut: beyond the
                        title, the first lines, and the last full stop, beyond its internal
                        configuration and its autonomous form, it is caught up in a system of
                        references to other books, other texts, other sentences: it is a node within
                        a network. And this network of references is not the same in the case of a
                        mathematical treatise, a textual commentary, a historical account, and an
                        episode in a novel cycle; the unity of the book, even in the sense of a
                        group of relations, cannot be regarded as identical in each case. The book
                        is not simply the object that one holds in one's hands; and it cannot remain
                        within the little parallelepiped that contains it: its unity is variable and
                        relative. As soon as one questions that unity, it lows its self-evidence; it
                        indicates itself, constructs itself, only on the basis of a complex field of
                        discourse. (23)</q>
                </p>
                <p>More recently, Friedrich Kittler in Discourse Networks 1800/1900, building on and
                    synthesizing the work of Barthes, Foucault, Derrida, and others, writes about
                    literature as an information system supported and shaped by the available
                    technologies of discourse: <q rend="block">An elementary datum is the fact that
                        literature (whatever else it may mean to readers) processes, stores, and
                        transmits data, and that such operations in the age-old medium of the
                        alphabet have the same technical positivity as they do in computers.
                        (370)</q>
                </p>
                <p>These theories of the text as constituting and constituted by information
                    networks have obvious relevance and resonance for digital humanities
                    scholarship, much of which is engaged in explicitly identifying, encoding, and
                    otherwise representing the information structures in texts of all kinds.</p>
                <p>By encoding the individual information nodes, one can generate new interfaces and
                    mechanisms for reading and navigating the text and for visualizing the patterns
                    and interactions of the information networks operating throughout Swinburne's
                    volume.</p>
                <p>The authors have been working on a specific web-based visualization to represent
                    graphically the conceptual networks at play across a series of literary texts,
                    in this case Swinburne's <hi rend="italic">Songs of the Springtides</hi>, and to
                    allow users to view and browse these networks from a distance and to zoom in and
                    focus on local clusters and concentrations of the conceptual nodes.</p>
                <p>Our presentation will include a detailed discussion of <hi rend="italic">Songs of
                        the Springtides</hi> as a carefully designed information system, supported
                    by a framework of internal and external discourse networks. Following this more
                    theoretical discussion of Swinburne's volume, we will review and illustrate the
                    TEI P5 mechanisms used to encode the networks and demonstrate the web-based
                    visualization of the text.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Barthes, Roland</author>
                        <date>1974</date>
                        <title level="m">S/Z</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Miller, Richard</editor>
                        <publisher>Hill and Wang</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Foucault, Michel</author>
                        <date>1972</date>
                        <title level="m">The Archaeology of Knowledge and the Discourse on Language</title>
                        <publisher>Pantheon</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Kittler, Friedrich A.</author>
                        <date>1990</date>
                        <title level="m">Discourse Networks 1800 / 1900</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Cullens, Chris</editor>
                        <editor role="translator">Metteer, Michael</editor>
                        <publisher>Stanford University Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Stanford</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>McGann, Jerome</author>
                        <date>1972</date>
                        <title level="m">Swinburne: An Experiment in Criticism</title>
                        <publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Swinburne, Algernon Charles</author>
                        <date>2004</date>
                        <title level="m">Uncollected Letters of Algernon Charles Swinburne</title>
                        <biblScope>3 vols.</biblScope>
                        <editor>Meyers, Terry L.</editor>
                        <publisher>Pickering &amp; Chatto</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Swinburne, Algernon Charles</author>
                        <date>1880</date>
                        <title level="m">Songs of the Springtides</title>
                        <publisher>Chatto</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
