<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<teiCorpus xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-769">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Standards, Specifications, and Paradigms for Customized Video
                    Playback</title>
                <author>
                    <name>McDonald, Jarom Lyle </name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Brigham Young University</orgName>, <country>USA</country></affiliation>
                    <email>jarom_mcdonald@byu.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Melby, Alan K.</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Brigham Young University</orgName>, <country>USA</country></affiliation>
                    <email>melbyak@yahoo.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Hendricks, Harold </name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Brigham Young University</orgName>, <country>USA</country></affiliation>
                    <email>harold_hendricks@byu.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-05-01</date>
                <name>NG</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <TEI>
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title/>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College
                        London</publisher>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <body>
                <p>Culture is fully inundated with video--from the ubiquitous DVD and succeeding
                    optical media formats, to locally stored digital bits passed between DVRs and
                    video iPods, to over a billion Internet-streamed videos a day. Unfortunately,
                    while those involved in humanities education and research know how widespread
                    video usage is and are attempting to integrate such a rich medium into what they
                    do, they are more often than not struggling, fighting against the medium and
                    associated baggage rather than using video for their own purposes.</p>
                <p>For all of the ways in which video differs from other forms of media, perhaps the
                    most challenging obstacle to effectively utilizing video assets as objects of
                    teaching and research is their inflexibility. Because of the complexity of video
                    technologies and the pressure of external interests, video is an incredibly
                    closed medium, especially when compared to text, image, or even audio. In many
                    ways video resists fundamental activities of digital humanities inquiry such as
                    metadata, structural, and segment analysis and annotation. What's more, video
                    also is, technologically speaking, a linear medium; it is (as much as if not
                    more than other media) architected to proceed continuously from point A to point
                    B, serving up bits in order and only responding to very limited, legacy
                    interface controls. Even the &quot;interactivity&quot; touted by content holders
                    (such as DVD &quot;extras&quot;) is a rigid, linear interactivity, designed to
                    keep the control of playback under the stewardship and limited scope of the
                    video producer rather than the needs of the learner, the desires of the scholar,
                    or the tastes of the consumer. To encourage collaborative, resuable approaches
                    to video (while avoiding legal pitfalls or isolationist tendencies that come
                    with an extracted clip approach), we need to incorporate a more thorough,
                    flexible, and widespread  method of <hi rend="italic">customized</hi> video
                    playback.</p>
                <p>The papers in this panel will focus on data-driven customized video playback
                    (CVP), from theory and methodology to real-world use cases that are evolving and
                    practical implementations that are both already in use as well as under
                    development to meet the needs of the Humanities today. The first presentation
                    will make the case for the fundamental groundwork for video asset analysis and
                    eventual customized video playback, the Multimedia Content Description Interface
                    (also known as MPEG-7). This XML standard for describing (both globally and in
                    timecode-associated ways) video assets offers a markup solution that is
                    complementary to common video encoding containers (such as MPEG-2 and MPEG-4),
                    and, as XML, can be easily coupled with other relevant data and metadata
                    standards as well. The second paper will present an argument for ways to take
                    these video asset descriptions and use them to enable both people and technology
                    to better facilitate customized video playback using a videoclip playlist
                    specification (serializable as plain text, as XML, as JSON, or as any other data
                    exchange format). With the segment descriptions of a thorough video asset
                    description, a videoclip playlist can then define custom playback operations.
                    The final presentation will demonstrate several use cases of customized video
                    playback, along with working models for achieving the type of interactivity we
                    desire with the technologies we have today, including demonstration of a CVP
                    system in use at several university campuses. </p>
                <p>The panel as a whole will seek to argue a unified justification and methodology
                    of customized video playback, and invite future collaboration from the Digital
                    Humanities community who can, if they desire, push these ideas further towards
                    making our proposed standards, specifications, and paradigms as widespread,
                    useful, and effective as possible. </p>
            </body>
        </text>
    </TEI>
    <TEI>
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title>Finding the Best in Approaches to Video Asset Description</title>
                    <author>
                        <name>McDonald, Jarom Lyle </name>
                        <affiliation>Brigham Young University, USA</affiliation>
                        <email>jarom_mcdonald@byu.edu</email>
                    </author>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College
                        London</publisher>
                    <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change>
                    <date>2010-05-01</date>
                    <name>NG</name>
                    <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <body>
                <p>From Google's Web Services to Wikipedia's DBPedia project to the underlying
                    architecture of modern digital libraries, our notion of how to make data more
                    semantic is moving (slowly but persistently) towards ideal principles that the
                    W3C lays out for what is commonly called &quot;the Semantic Web.&quot; This is
                    even true for the subject of my study, video data, albeit with much less of a
                    semantically-inflected critical mass. There are a few solid, innovative
                    investigations (such as the BBC's video portal and the many incarnations of the
                    Joost video platform) that are or have been working to bring technologies such
                    as metadata, RDF/RDFa, and SPARQL to the storage and dissemination of video
                    (especially online video); but there is still a lot of work that needs to be
                    done in order to make today's video assets truly useful in a way that Tim
                    Berners-Lee would approve, a world &quot;in which information is given
                    well-defined meaning, better enabling computers and people to work in
                    cooperation&quot; (Scientific American).</p>
                <p>While the Semantic Web includes a large number of topics too broad to cover in
                    this proposal, I will focus on one particular aspect of semantic markup that
                    does apply to video data. It is vital to underscore the unique nature of video
                    as an object of<hi rend="italic"> perception</hi>--that is, video is meant to be
                    played for a viewer with the linear, temporal nature in the forefront of
                    experiencing the video. Thus to describe the data of a video asset, as a whole,
                    in a useful way would necessarily require a structured analysis of more than
                    just the metadata<hi rend="italic"> about</hi> the video that you might be able
                    to achieve with Dublin Core, IEEE-LOM, or RDF; the most significant need is a
                    system that can connect such semantic vocabularies to a thorough, analytic
                    description of the video content itself in as close an approximation to the
                    playback act as might be reasonably able to achieve--in other words, a workable
                    time-coded markup language. This isn't to say that a video must be necessarily
                    viewed chronologically; rather, given that video exists as bits served from time
                    point A to time point B, it must be described that way in order to make use of
                    the data encoded there. If a video asset has the right description of its
                    segmented, time-coded parts (of which, naturally, there may be many versions
                    based on who is doing the markup or who is using the materials), it will
                    eventually allow for more than just watching the video; a segmentation model of
                    video markup is essential for enabling a system of interactive, customized video
                    playback. </p>
                <p>Several options for such a language to use are available and have been somewhat
                    explored both commercially and academically, but none are completely
                    satisfactory. Naturally, given the success of the Text Encoding Initiative, it
                    makes sense to consider its ability to function as a time-coded video markup
                    system. In fact, Reside (2007) and Arneil and Newton (2009) have presented just
                    such an idea at recent Digital Humanities conferences. The flexibility and
                    thoroughness of the TEI makes it an attractive option; however, while the speech
                    transcription models can potentially provide time-coded descriptions of spoken
                    elements of a video (and even be retrofitted to other elements of video
                    content), because the TEI is a text-encoding framework, it lacks a temporal
                    segmentation scheme designed specifically for existing models of video encoding
                    and playback (for example, referring to multiple video or audio tracks,
                    multiplexing metadata with the binary streams, etc.). Most projects exploring
                    video markup descriptions also mention the W3C's Synchronized Multimedia
                    Integration Language (SMIL). Since version 3.0, SMIL integrates a temporal
                    segmentation model with one for spatial fragmentation, allowing semantic
                    relationships both within and between video elements. What's more, SMIL is a W3C
                    recommendation, offering the potential for tighter integration with web
                    delivered video as it continues to mature. Several commercial endeavors
                    (including the streaming platform Hulu) have incorporated SMIL into their
                    playback process, allowing for a sophisticated combination of video annotation
                    (for example, Hulu uses it for their advertisements and upcoming social viewing
                    features) and search/retrieval (combining the time-coded markup with RDF
                    metadata). Yet SMIL provides no scope for how to implement various temporal
                    segment references, instead leaving that task up to playback mechanisms (of
                    which there are currently very few for SMIL). More significantly, SMIL provides
                    no way to refer to described segments out of the context of the document, making
                    it difficult to design a URI scheme for accessing the various clips, something
                    integral to having true semantic web functionality or building video players
                    that can interpret the descriptions consistently. Video streaming servers such
                    as those provided by Apple, Microsoft, and Adobe have all developed their own
                    model for segmenting (either in markup or in actual bits) video data and serving
                    it with instructions for playback, but in these cases the systems very heavily
                    limit the metadata that can be included, and the resulting descriptions are
                    completely coupled to the proprietary vendor technologies (for example, a set of
                    Flash Streaming Media Server cue points is not portable to other systems without
                        intervention).<note>It's notable to also mention MIT's Cross Media
                        Annotation System (XMAS), a project developed over the last decade to
                        incorporate time-aligned video annotation and commentary into Shakespeare
                        classes at MIT. The approach that XMAS takes is much more in line with what
                        we see as the proper way to annotate video; however, theirs is a closed
                        system very tightly coupled to their specific Shakespeare needs, so it isn't
                        known what technologies they're using or how portable those technologies
                        might be.</note></p>
                <p>For the past 10 years, the Moving Picture Experts Group has defined and refined
                    what they've formally titled the &quot;Multimedia Content Description
                    Interface,&quot; also known as MPEG-7. MPEG-7, an XML-based, ISO/IEC standard,
                    is an expansive, far-reaching specification that does many, many things
                    (including defining itself and defining the language by which it defines itself
                    and its various parts); what is of particular interest to this proposal is Part
                    9, &quot;Profiles and Levels.&quot; Recognizing that there are many approaches
                    and viewpoints surrounding video asset description (those mentioned above, plus
                    such systems at TV-Anytime, the SMPTE Metadata Dictionary, and even extensions
                    to the Dublin Core standard), MPEG-7 seeks to be a superset of video markup, and
                    the concept of &quot;profiles&quot; as laid out in Part 9 of the spec offers
                    various focused schemas and methodologies that conform to the MPEG-7 spec but
                    serve unique needs. Seeing a need for a general purpose, video-specific
                    description language, Brigham Young University has collaborated with Motorola
                    and the Japanese National Broadcasting Corporation to publish a &quot;Core
                    Description Profile&quot; (CDP), a framework that utilizes MPEG-7 descriptions
                    and provides all the necessary tools for time-coded, segmented, video
                    annotation. </p>
                <p>Every file that conforms to the CDP schema (a schema now included directly as
                    part of the MPEG-7 specification and which has been released as open-source by
                    ISO) must also conform to the MPEG-7 super-schema. In addition to the MPEG-7
                    root element and any necessary header information, a CDP document has a series
                    of &lt;description&gt; elements that contain &lt;MultimediaContent&gt;; a simple
                    example of such an element might look something like this: </p>
                <code xml:space="preserve">
&lt;MultimediaContent xsi:type=&quot;VideoType&quot;&gt;   
 &lt;Video id=&quot;MainTitle&quot;&gt;   
  &lt;TemporalDecomposition&gt;
   &lt;VideoSegment id=&quot;chapter1&quot;&gt;
     &lt;TemporalDecomposition&gt;       
       &lt;VideoSegment id=&quot;chapter1scene1&quot;&gt;
          &lt;TextAnnotation type=&quot;description&quot;&gt;
           &lt;FreeTextAnnotation&gt;opening credits; 
            music; village aerial view
            &lt;/FreeTextAnnotation&gt;
          &lt;/TextAnnotation&gt;
          &lt;MediaTime&gt;
           &lt;MediaTimePoint&gt;T00:00:00
            &lt;/MediaTimePoint&gt;
           &lt;MediaDuration&gt;PT1M24S
            &lt;/MediaDuration&gt;
          &lt;/MediaTime&gt;
       &lt;/VideoSegment&gt;
       &lt;VideoSegment id=&quot;chapter1scene2&quot;&gt;
          &lt;TextAnnotation type=&quot;description&quot;&gt;
          &lt;!-- other types of annotations are 
           possible as well --&gt;
          &lt;FreeTextAnnotation&gt;entering church; 
           bells; Count introduced
           &lt;/FreeTextAnnotation&gt;
          &lt;/TextAnnotation&gt;
          &lt;MediaTime&gt;
          &lt;MediaTimePoint&gt;T00:01:24
           &lt;/MediaTimePoint&gt;
          &lt;MediaDuration&gt;PT0M20S&lt;/MediaDuration&gt;
          &lt;/MediaTime&gt;
       &lt;/VideoSegment&gt;
  &lt;!-- remaining scenes go here --&gt;
    &lt;/TemporalDecomposition&gt;
 &lt;/VideoSegment&gt;
&lt;!-- Remaining chapters go here --&gt;
&lt;/TemporalDecomposition&gt;
&lt;/Video&gt;
&lt;/MultimediaContent&gt;
                </code>
                <p>Having been designed as a general-purpose video asset description schema, the CDP
                    is the most promising format for defining video clip boundaries, including
                    metadata and annotations. On the surface it may not seem much different from
                    other markup schemas such as SMIL; however, the real power of the approach lies
                    in combining a CDP-conformant description with other parts of the MPEG-7
                    specification. First of all, because MPEG-7 is the data description framework
                    for the same group behind the MPEG-2 and MPEG-4 video encoding containers and
                    codecs, MPEG-7 can be easily multiplexed directly into a video container.
                    Additionally, as XML, a CDP video asset description can incorporate any other
                    relevant data through namespacing, including TEI, Dublin Core, RDF
                    relationships, or future information schemas. And finally, because it is a
                    general purpose description framework, it can also be serialized into any needed
                    format such as SMIL, IEEE-LOM (a Learning Object Metadata standard) or CMML (the
                    Continuous Media Markup Language), an XML schema defined by the organization
                    behind the Ogg media formats and promising tight integration with emerging HTML5
                    video technologies. To project this even further, imagine a robust, RDF-aware
                    repository (such as FEDORA) full of digital video objects that connect video
                    streams to valid MPEG-7 video asset descriptions, making videos easily
                    discoverable, easily searchable, and ultimately, truly semantic. And finally,
                    this approach to video asset description lays the foundation for, to return to
                    Tim Berners-Lee's comment,  enabling us to make video playback from computer to
                    person customizable, flexible, and just what we need it to be. </p>
            </body>
            <back>
                <div>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <author>Berners-Lee, Tim, James Hendler and Ora Lassila</author>
                            <title level="m">The Semantic Web. Scientific American May, 2001</title>
                            <ptr
                                target="http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=the-semantic-web"
                            />
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <author>Bush, Michael D., Alan K. Melby, Thor A. Anderson, Jeremy M.
                                Browne, Merrill Hansen, and Ryan Corradini</author>
                            <date>2004</date>
                            <title level="a">Customized Video Playback: Standards for Content
                                Modeling and Personalization</title>
                            <title level="j">Educational Technology</title>
                            <biblScope type="issue">44.4 </biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="pp">5-13</biblScope>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <title level="m">MPEG-7 Overview</title>
                            <ptr
                                target="http://www.chiariglione.org/mpeg/standards/mpeg-7/mpeg-7.htm"
                            />
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <title level="m">W3C Semantic Web Frequently Asked Questions</title>
                            <ptr target="http://www.w3.org/2001/sw/SW-FAQ#What1"/>
                        </bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
            </back>
        </text>
    </TEI>
    <TEI>
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title>Videoclips as Playlists in Customized Video</title>
                    <author>
                        <name>Melby, Alan K.</name>
                        <affiliation>Brigham Young University, USA</affiliation>
                        <email>melbyak@yahoo.com</email>
                    </author>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College
                        London</publisher>
                    <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change>
                    <date>2010-05-01</date>
                    <name>NG</name>
                    <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <body>
                <p>The video interface that we are all familiar with has garnered universal
                    acceptance. This is true both of the iconic symbols of playback control, as well
                    as the actual functions of control that are allowed. Since the days of very
                    early analog playback, media consumers have been allowed to do pretty much just
                    the following:</p>
                <p>
                    <xmt:uList>
                        <item>Insert (or open) media</item>
                        <item>Play</item>
                        <item>Pause</item>
                        <item>Stop</item>
                        <item>Fast-forward</item>
                        <item>Rewind</item>
                        <item>Volume control (including muting)</item>
                    </xmt:uList>
                </p>
                <p>There have been a few additions to the list as media (especially video)
                    technology has evolved; for example, with the introduction of laserdisc and
                    subsequently DVD, &quot;return to menu,&quot; &quot;next/previous chapter,&quot;
                    and &quot;go to title&quot; controls have entered the collective interface.
                    Streaming media has also invoked the need for a &quot;fullscreen toggle&quot;
                    control. And many playback systems are now allowing for the display of certain
                    content-provider defined metadata or even a &quot;scrub&quot; bar for more
                    flexible time placement. But such change comes slowly, and all of these playback
                    controls are very simple, require a good deal of user intervention, and truly
                    limit the video asset's effectiveness as a learning object.</p>
                <p>
                    <figure xml:id="fig1">
                        <graphic url="769_Fig1.png" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                            mimeType="image/png"/>
                        <head>Image 1: A current video playback interface, offering only standard,
                            simple user controls (source: <ptr type="external"
                                target="http://commons.wikimedia.org"/>)</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>To provide an example of the limitations of commonly accepted playback, let me
                    briefly describe what happened this semester in a Hebrew class at our
                    university. The instructor wanted to use several clips from a commercial Israeli
                    movie to help the students with their vocabulary. With current US laws and
                    technological learning curves making it unreasonable to rip the clips from the
                    DVD and edit them for her class's needs, she instead instructed them to check
                    out the DVD from the reserve library, start playing it, jump to chapter 14,
                    watch for 4 minutes and 17 seconds (rewinding if necessary to fully understand
                    the dialogue), jump to 2 minutes into chapter 31, watch for 3 minutes, pause the
                    DVD and go look at some of the resources she'd posted on her course website,
                    return to the DVD, etc. etc. etc. This is an extremely ineffective way to use
                    the video in a learning environment, but unfortunately, it's really the only
                    methodology that is widely available right now.</p>
                <p>Historically, this hasn't always been the case. Laserdisc technology provided
                    unprecedented control for both users and instructional designers over the video
                    asset, and a large number of rich learning experiences were created and shared
                    on laserdisc. More recently, the concept of &quot;WebDVD&quot; seemed poised to
                    recover some of the lost functionality when laserdisc didn't emerge outside of a
                    niche market; but WebDVD didn't catch on, either. Technologies of streaming
                    media (such as Youtube annotations or bookmark-driven systems in place at CNN,
                    ABC, Hulu, and other commercial streaming media institutions) have some
                    potential, but they are still in their infancy, aren't widely used, and don't
                    allow for anything other than an editorial overlay; the content itself is still
                    played back under very strict control that the user can only pause, stop,
                    rewind, etc.</p>
                <p>What we propose, then, and what is so desparately needed, is a completely
                    different playback system that allows for true interactivity for instructional
                    designers, teachers, and viewers. Bush et al. propose two models for customizing
                    video playback that seek to alleviate the sort of haphazard &quot;playback
                    list&quot; illustrated earlier. One, of course, would be to strip the digital
                    bits onto a local filesystem, edit the content as needed, add in annotations
                    (subtitles, links, external info), and share the new video with all students to
                    view in traditional playback systems, repeating the process when the video
                    content might need to be viewed in a different way. But this (as the authors
                    point out) is time consuming and expensive, not to mention the unfortunate
                    copyright implications of such an approach.</p>
                <p>The other model for enabling customized video playback, and what we are currently
                    developing, is to combine a data-driven, &quot;descriptive&quot; approach with a
                    &quot;selective playback mechanism&quot;, software specifically built for
                    customized video playback according to a robust, standardized specification for
                    delineating the different actions that the designer/instructor might want to
                    have students experience. The most promising form of video description is the
                    Video Asset Description (VAD), an XML encoding of clip boundaries, video
                    content, and other metadata that is isomorphic with the MPEG-7, part 9 core
                    description profile and which is described in another paper on this panel. When
                    a video asset is associated with a full VAD (or several of them), an
                    instructor--or in many cases even automated software--can use that description
                    to generate a playlist. When I say &quot;playlist,&quot; I'm not referring to
                    the common usage of the term as a description of a media collection (a list
                    which describes what assets to play and in what order), but it is similar; what
                    I propose is a notion of a video clip playlist (VCP), a description of timecoded
                    clips within a video asset. A collection of these clips, along with the actions
                    to take for each clip, could be fed directly into the queue of selective
                    playback software, software that would be programmed to know how to read the
                    instructions and present the new playback session.<note>Some might ask why it's
                        necessary to go to the trouble of having a markup layer associated with
                        time-aligned video segments at all; why not use extracted clips? However,
                        the legal and technical obstacles involved in extracting segments of video
                        are far greater problems than those experienced through the copy/paste of
                        small snippets of text, making clip extraction unfeasible for most cases
                        (not to mention the fact that clips themselves are just as rigid, and must
                        be re-extracted if the use cases change). Moreover, extracted clips are
                        difficult to share and collaborate on, and would still need some sort of
                        annotation layer associated with them for editorial commentary, additional
                        subtitles, etc. Our proposed methodology can handle annotation,
                        collaboration, modification, re-use, and legal restrictions all with one
                        approach.</note></p>
                <p>Each instruction in a videoclip playlist would be a triple that would consist of
                    a framecode number, an operation, and an operand. The framecode is not a direct
                    representation of either human perception of time or of frame count, but is
                    instead a convenient fiction that allows for the most effective and standardized
                    accuracy in calculating either time or frame. The operation, most easily
                    represented as a numeric opcode, would be one of a number of operations that a
                    playback system might encounter. Of course there would be the standard
                    &quot;play, pause, stop, mute&quot; controls, but they would be under the
                    stewardship of the instructional designer who is authoring the videoclip
                    playlist. There would also be codes for jumping to a new timecode (not just a
                    chapter, not just an approximate location on a scrub bar, but a frame-accurate
                    location), for displaying annotations (subtitles, scholar-composed notations,
                    instructor comments, etc.), displaying &quot;wrap&quot; data (for example,
                    material retrieved from web services and displayed in an additional pane of the
                    selective viewer at the precise moment the playlist instructs), and so forth.
                    The operand would be a piece of data that makes the op code intelligible; if a
                    command instructed the player to jump to a new time code, the operand would be
                    the time code to jump to. If a command instructed the player to start playing a
                    clip, the operand might be the number of frames to play.</p>
                <p>We have designed a simple RNG schema for encoding these clips in an XML file that
                    is both machine and human readable. The file would have some header information
                    that identifies the videoclip playlist, associated video asset descriptions, and
                    references to wrap data and other annotations, as well as an instructionList of
                    the commands that the player would need to perform the custom playback. The
                    instructionList looks like this:</p>
                <code xml:space="preserve"> 
  &lt;instructionList&gt;
    &lt;instruction trigger=&quot;0&quot; opCode=&quot;68&quot; operand=&quot;60&quot;&gt;show &apos;skipping&apos; message for 2
        seconds&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction trigger=&quot;0&quot; opCode=&quot;0&quot; operand=&quot;0&quot;&gt;pause before seeking&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction trigger=&quot;0&quot; opCode=&quot;65&quot; operand=&quot;52164&quot;&gt;seek to frame 52164&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction trigger=&quot;52164&quot; opCode=&quot;75&quot; operand=&quot;32&quot;&gt;new clip [32] begins&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction trigger=&quot;52164&quot; opCode=&quot;85&quot; operand=&quot;0&quot;&gt;show wrapData #0&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction trigger=&quot;52164&quot; opCode=&quot;85&quot; operand=&quot;1&quot;&gt;show wrapData #1&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction trigger=&quot;52164&quot; opCode=&quot;85&quot; operand=&quot;2&quot;&gt;show wrapData #2&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction trigger=&quot;53753&quot; opCode=&quot;68&quot; operand=&quot;60&quot;&gt;show &apos;skipping&apos; message for 2
        seconds&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction trigger=&quot;53753&quot; opCode=&quot;0&quot; operand=&quot;0&quot;&gt;pause before seeking&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction trigger=&quot;53753&quot; opCode=&quot;65&quot; operand=&quot;99926&quot;&gt;seek to frame 99926&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction trigger=&quot;99926&quot; opCode=&quot;75&quot; operand=&quot;57&quot;&gt;new clip [57] begins&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction trigger=&quot;99926&quot; opCode=&quot;85&quot; operand=&quot;3&quot;&gt;show wrapData #3 &lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction trigger=&quot;99926&quot; opCode=&quot;85&quot; operand=&quot;4&quot;&gt;show wrapData #4 &lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction trigger=&quot;99926&quot; opCode=&quot;85&quot; operand=&quot;5&quot;&gt;show wrapData #5 &lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction trigger=&quot;100911&quot; opCode=&quot;75&quot; operand=&quot;58&quot;&gt;new clip [58] begins&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction trigger=&quot;100911&quot; opCode=&quot;85&quot; operand=&quot;6&quot;&gt;show wrapData #6 &lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction trigger=&quot;100911&quot; opCode=&quot;85&quot; operand=&quot;7&quot;&gt;show wrapData #7&lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction trigger=&quot;100911&quot; opCode=&quot;85&quot; operand=&quot;8&quot;&gt;show wrapData #8 &lt;/instruction&gt;
    &lt;instruction trigger=&quot;103033&quot; opCode=&quot;99&quot; operand=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;end of playlist -- indefinite pause
    &lt;/instruction&gt;
&lt;/instructionList&gt;
                </code>
                <p>A player, of course, would only need to be passed the triples represented by the
                    integer values of each instruction's attributes, and in fact a videoclip
                    playlist could be serialized in any necessary data exchange format, whether it
                    be JSON (for building a browser-based player for customizing streaming media
                    playback), plain text (that might include just tab-delimited integers easily
                    consumable by an appliance with an embedded selective player), and so forth.</p>
                <p>Obviously, one key to such an approach to facilitating customized video playback
                    is the creation of the selective players themselves. We are currently undergoing
                    development on specifications that would allow anyone to build such a player.
                    With the combination of robust video asset descriptions, shareable, thorough
                    videoclip playlists, and intelligent, VCP-aware players, customized video
                    playback is once again a reality.</p>
            </body>
        </text>
    </TEI>
    <TEI>
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title>Customized Video Playback; Where We've Come From, Where We're
                        Going</title>
                    <author>
                        <name>Hendricks, Harold </name>
                        <affiliation>Brigham Young University, USA</affiliation>
                        <email>harold_hendricks@byu.edu</email>
                    </author>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College
                        London</publisher>
                    <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
            <revisionDesc>
                <change>
                    <date>2010-05-01</date>
                    <name>NG</name>
                    <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
                </change>
            </revisionDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <body>
                <p>When we talk about customized video playback, it's important to recognize that
                    the actual playing back of the video is paramount; theories of how to mark up
                    the video's content or describe the desired playback are significant only
                    insofar as they can lead to actual implementations that satisfy some of the use
                    cases that we might envision for a customizable video playback system. These use
                    cases generally fall into three types: one-on-one interactivity, classroom
                    lecture, and large audience presentations, such as annotated cinema. I hope to
                    move the locus of attention from CVP theory to practice in three ways: by
                    discussing some of our historical attempts to achieve such an implementation, by
                    demonstrating a current, working system for customized video playback in use in
                    several academic institutions today, and by outlining where our work is moving
                    next (and how we envision collaborating with others outside our project who have
                    so much to contribute).</p>
                <p>The introduction of videodisc technology in the mid 1970s provided the first
                    practical method for inexpensive video storage and random-access playback,
                    especially in the realm of academic instruction. <hi rend="italic">Macario</hi>,
                    a repurposed Mexican motion picture, was issued as a custom videodisc pressing
                    with interactive menus and annotations coded to the linear playback of the
                    video. When a student would pause the video, the interactive materials would
                    appear, allowing for commentary, instruction, thought-questions tied directly to
                    individual scenes being watched, and even replay of selected video with choice
                    of audio track.  </p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Macario</hi>'s model of annotated video playback offered some
                    innovative learning opportunities to, for example, intermediate Spanish language
                    and culture classes, but it was still a fairly simplistic model, one built upon
                    and improved over the next few years. Projects such as the German Video Enhanced
                    Learning, Video Enhanced Teaching (VELVET) program empowered students with more
                    custom tools, such as the ability to filter out or select particular types of
                    annotations (both text and image), highlight keywords in accompanying
                    transcriptions, or even perform intricate searching through accompanying
                    materials to narrow in on particular scenes (replaying them as needed) of use to
                    the student. These types of activities demonstrated how useful customized video
                    playback could be, focusing the viewing experience and tailoring it to
                    particular educational needs.</p>
                <p>In the late 1980s, Junius Bennion and Glen Probst modified some of these previous
                    models of interactive video to allow more control of video assets within
                    targeted learning experiences. Having first created a methodology for an Apple
                    II-controlled videodisc of <hi rend="italic">Raiders of the Lost Ark</hi>,
                    Bennion, Probst and James Taylor reprogrammed the content to work with
                    Hazeltine's Time-shared, Interactive, Computer-Controlled, Information
                    Television (TICCIT) System at BYU.  Within this modal the motion picture is
                    divided into scenes with light-pen interactivity with annotations,
                    transcriptions, questions, text and audio commentary, and instructional drills.
                    Examples of these TICCIT programs include versions of<hi rend="italic"> Black
                        Orpheus</hi>, <hi rend="italic">The Seventh Seal</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >C'eravamo tanto amati</hi>. With the TICCIT modified model, customized,
                    interactive video instruction moved from research projects to the language
                    lab.</p>
                <p>The ideas underlying some of these models of customized video playback are the
                    same principles expounded upon in the other sessions of this panel, implemented
                    in the best possible way using the technology available at the time. But they
                    were all inextricably linked to the technology itself, needing custom produced
                    videodiscs or a complex networked computer system to run. When videodisc
                    technology never caught on (for a number of reasons), these innovative products
                    were made obsolete. Likewise our attempts to achieve robust customized video
                    playback through such frameworks as HyperCard, ToolBook, and &quot;WebDVD&quot;
                    have struggled for much the same reason. Recently, however, we have been able to
                    achieve quite functional and effective CVP through an existing system entitled
                    &quot;Electronic Film Review&quot; (EFR), a methodology for controlling video
                    playback of DVDs.</p>
                <p>The EFR approach, demonstrated as a poster session at the 2006 Digital Humanities
                    Conference, is based on the MPEG-7 and VideoClip Playlist open standards
                    discussed earlier, and is designed to be implementable in any media player for
                    time-coded video that supports playing a segment of video based on time codes.
                    The current implementation of the EFR approach runs on Windows XP computers that
                    have decoders suitable for watching DVDs through shared, DirectShow DVD decoders
                    (the current EFR software does not include its own DVD decoders). For individual
                    language study, each user-defined clip of a film can be annotated with
                    vocabulary, culture, and other notes. The EFR player itself includes the video
                    window, the common media interface controls, custom &quot;playlist
                    controls&quot; (for navigating between pre-defined clips), and areas to display
                    the annotations. the EFR system also includes an authoring tool, EFR Aid, as
                    well as a compiler to generate the playlist format, to ease the definition and
                    annotation of various segments of a particular video. </p>
                <p>Because the EFR system is based on open standards, any learning materials created
                    for particular video assets are shareable; video asset descriptions and
                    playlists can be transferred from one user to another. What's more, these
                    resources that the EFR system helps create are not coupled to the video asset
                    itself; they are a form of meta-annotation (hence the title of &quot;film
                    review&quot;) that do not interfere with a single bit of the video data, thus
                    respecting any copyright laws that might exist. As plain-text (serializable as
                    XML), they are also fully searchable, allowing for discovery of relationships
                    between videos that may not have been previously known. Most importantly, the
                    EFR system makes video much more than just watchable; it makes video useable. </p>
                <p>
                    <figure xml:id="fig2">
                        <graphic url="769_Fig2.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>Image 2: A screenshot of the EFR video player</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>By useable, once again we mention the three primary use cases: individual
                    interactivity, classroom interactions, and annotated cinema. Both our historical
                    efforts and the current EFR implementation have focused primarily on a single
                    user interacting with a computer, with some efforts made to enhance classroom
                    presentation. However, the EFR program has successfully been used in all three
                    of these cases, providing the means for enhanced comprehension, vocabulary
                    building, speech modelling, and cultural awareness for individuals, a means to
                    integrate these same video-based activities into the classroom, and also a tool
                    for modifying the playback of full-length feature films with content filtering
                    and additional subtitles without modifying the copyrighted and encrypted video. </p>
                <p>Now, as mentioned earlier, several universities (Brigham Young University, the
                    University of Hawaii at Manoa) have used or are currently using a Windows-XP
                    based EFR system for DVD playback. However, once again the evolution of
                    technology is forcing change in our approach to customized video playback. With
                    the introduction of Blu-Ray, the explosive growth of online, streaming video,
                    and constant legal and political fighting between content providers and content
                    consumers, we see it necessary to broaden the scope of the EFR project to allow
                    for all possible use-cases that we might imagine. We are currently undergoing a
                    project, a collaboration between academic institutions and commercial
                    enterprises, to define open specifications for building a CVP system for any
                    technology. Our goal is to create content and meta-data that can be used on any
                    machine without worry that the necessary technology might not be available.
                    Though still in their nascent stages, these specifications will build on the
                    principles outlined throughout this session--reusable, robust XML markup of
                    video assets, clip divisions, annotations, and playback instructions. If we are
                    successful, we hope to end up with standards that can be used regardless of the
                    video encoding format or delivery system. We invite suggestions and
                    participation from the community as we move forward from the historical and
                    current availability of customized video playback towards an approach that works
                    for all time-based media now and in the future. </p>
            </body>
            <back>
                <div>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <author>Hendricks, Harold.</author>
                            <date>1993</date>
                            <title level="a">Models of Interactive Videodisc Development</title>
                            <title level="j">CALICO Journal</title>
                            <biblScope type="issue">11.1</biblScope>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl>
                            <author>Melby, Alan</author>
                            <date>2004</date>
                            <title level="a">The EFR (Electronic Film Review) Approach to Using
                                Video in Education</title>
                            <title level="m">Proceedings of World Conference on Educational
                                Multimedia, Hypermedia and Telecommunications 2004</title>
                            <editor>L. Cantoni &amp; C. McLoughlin </editor>
                            <publisher>AACE</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>Chesapeake, VA</pubPlace>
                            <biblScope type="pp">593-597</biblScope>
                        </bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
            </back>
        </text>
    </TEI>
</teiCorpus>
