<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-770">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Reading Darwin Between the Lines: A Computer-Assisted Analysis of the Concept
                    of Evolution in <hi rend="italic">The Origin of Species</hi></title>
                <author>
                    <name>Sainte-Marie, Maxime B. </name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Université du Québec à Montréal</orgName>, <country>Canada</country></affiliation>
                    <email>msaintemarie@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Meunier, Jean-Guy</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Université du Québec à Montréal</orgName>, <country>Canada</country></affiliation>
                    <email>meunier.jean-guy@uqam.ca</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Payette, Nicolas </name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Université du Québec à Montréal</orgName>, <country>Canada</country></affiliation>
                    <email>nicolaspayette@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Chartier, Jean-François </name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Université du Québec à Montréal</orgName>, <country>Canada</country></affiliation>
                    <email>chartier.jf@gmail.com</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-05-01</date>
                <name>NG</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Whereas Darwin is nowadays considered the founder of the modern theory of
                    evolution, he wasn't the first to use this word in a biological context: indeed,
                    the word &quot;evolution&quot; already had two distinct biological uses at the
                    time the <hi rend="italic">Origin of Species</hi> was first published (Bowler,
                    2003; Huxley, 1897): &quot;initially, to refer to the particular embryological
                    theory of preformationism; and later, to characterize the general belief that
                    species have descended from one another over time&quot; (Richards, 1998: 4).</p>
                <p>Deriving from the Latin <hi rend="italic">evolutio</hi>, which refers to the
                    scroll-like act of unfolding or unrolling, the word «evolution» was first used
                    in biology to refer to the development of the embryo, mainly through the
                    formulation, promulgation, and justification of preformationist and epigenetical
                    theories. Embryological evolution would receive its fullest, most modern
                    experimental and theoretical account in the works of Karl Ernst von Baer:
                    characterizing embryological development as a gradual differentiation process
                    leading from homogeneous matter to the production of heterogeneity and
                    complexity of structure, von Baer would usually use the word <hi rend="italic"
                        >Entwickelung</hi> to refer to this dynamic phenomenon, often followed by
                    the Latin <hi rend="italic">evolutio</hi> in parentheses. The ground-breaking
                    importance of von Baer’s work, as well as its diffusion in the scientific
                    community through numerous translations, commentaries, and appropriations,
                    significantly contributed to consecrate the embryological use of the word
                    &quot;evolution&quot;.</p>
                <p>As for the use of the word evolution to describe specific development, its
                    emergence is closely tied to Lamarckism: even though Lamarck never used the word
                    ‘evolution’ himself to refer to the transformation of species over time and
                    generations, his commentators, detractors, readers and followers often did
                    however, thus contributing to the semantic alteration of the term. Indeed,
                    &quot;by the 1830s, the word &quot;evolution&quot; had shifted 180 degrees from
                    its original employment and was used to refer indifferently to both
                    embryological and species progression&quot; (Richards, 1992: 15): Étienne Renaud
                    Serres used the expression <hi rend="italic">théorie des evolutions</hi> in his
                    1827 article<hi rend="italic"> Théories des formations organiques</hi> to refer
                    both &quot;to the recapitulational <hi rend="italic">métamorphoses</hi> of
                    organic parts in the individual and the parallel changes one sees in moving
                    (intellectually) from one family of animals to another and from one class to
                    another&quot; (Richards, 1992: 69); von Baer, in rejecting the possibility of
                    transmutation and the popular idea that embryological development recapitulates
                    the progression of the species, used the word «evolution» to refer to both
                    processes; in England, naturalists such as Charles Lyell, Joseph Henry Green,
                    Robert Grant and Richard Owen also used the word &quot;evolution&quot; to both
                    comment and reject Lamarckism (Bowler, 2003; Richards, 1993).</p>
                <p>While this dual usage of the word and its most common synonyms at the time
                    (transformation, development, transmutation…) has been confirmed in the works of
                    the most important biologists and naturalists of the first half of the 19<hi
                        rend="sup">th</hi> century, little is known about Darwin’s own stance on
                    this matter: did he or not use the word ‘evolution’ or any other word to refer
                    both to embryological and specific development? This question, however crucial
                    it may appear, proves very difficult to answer: while the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Origin of Species</hi> is generally considered as the birth document of the
                    theory of evolution, studies on and around this book often overlook the fact
                    that the word itself is rarely used by Darwin, the sole and slight exception
                    being the sixth and last edition (1872) of the work.</p>
                <table>
                    <head>Occurrences of &quot;evolution&quot;, &quot;evolve&quot;, and
                        &quot;evolved&quot; in the Origin of Species</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="2.5cm">1<hi rend="sup">st</hi> Edition (1)</cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">evolved</hi>: XV (490)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2<hi rend="sup">nd</hi> Edition (1)</cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">evolved</hi>: XV (490)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>3<hi rend="sup">rd</hi> Edition (1)</cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">evolved</hi>: XV (525)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition (1)</cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">evolved</hi>: XV (577)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition (2)</cell>
                        <cell><hi rend="italic">evolved</hi>: XV (573), XV (579)</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Edition (14)</cell>
                        <cell>
                            <hi rend="italic">evolution</hi>: (VII:201(2), 202), VIII (215), X
                            (282), XV (424 (3)) <hi rend="italic">evolve</hi>: VII (191) <hi
                                rend="italic">evolved</hi>: VII (191, 202(2)), XV (425, 429) </cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>This lexical scarcity doesn’t necessarily mean however that the concept of
                    evolution isn’t present elsewhere in the text, where the words ‘evolution’,
                    ‘evolved’, and ‘evolve’ don’t appear. According to distributional semantics
                    theory, meaning can be more easily stated as a property of word combinations
                    than of words <hi rend="italic">per se</hi>: in every sentence and paragraph,
                    each word brings its own constraints to the whole, reduces the sets of possible
                    words that could fit with it, therefore increasing the total information
                    conveyed and structuring the semantic dimension of each word thus combined. In
                    short, this theory holds that &quot;similarities and patternings among the
                    co-occurrence likelihoods of various words correlate with similarities and
                    patternings in their types of meaning&quot; (Harris, 1991: 341). In this sense,
                    if concepts are thought of as networks of such meaning-bearing word
                    combinations, then, conceptual structures can determine the semantic dimension
                    of a text without being properly lexicalized; in other words, such
                    considerations, while emphasizing the distinction between the semantic
                    associations of specific concepts and their embodiment in natural language, also
                    seem to imply the possibility of &quot;reading between the lines&quot;, that is,
                    of identifying and analyzing concepts on the sole basis of their relations with
                    other words and concepts and independently of any proper designation.</p>
                <p>In view of this, the fact that the word &quot;evolution&quot; itself is rarely
                    found in the sixth edition of the <hi rend="italic">Origin of Species</hi>
                    doesn't necessarily imply that the lexical and inferential network it refers to
                    and that constitutes its conceptual dimension isn’t present elsewhere in the
                    text and can't be studied in its stead. In this sense, taking into account word
                    combinations similar to those where the word 'evolution' occurs instead of
                    focusing solely on the latter might be the most reliable way to determine
                    whether or not Darwin’s concept of evolution in the <hi rend="italic">Origin of
                        Species</hi> refers to both embryological and specific development, like
                    most biological theories of the same period. However, dealing with word
                    combinations manually might prove difficult, if not impossible. In light of
                    this, a new computer-assisted conceptual analysis tool has been developed by the
                    LANCI laboratory, one which aims to &quot;read Darwin between the lines&quot;,
                    that is to identify where the author &quot;conceptually&quot; refers to
                    evolution, regardless of the presence or the absence of the word itself.</p>
                <p>Theoretically speaking, this new approach is based on two fundamental
                    assumptions: 1) The inferential nature and dimension of a concept are
                    linguistically expressed in a differentiated, contextualized and regularized
                    manner; 2) these regularities and patterns can be identified or distinguished
                    using algorithmic, iterative and automatic clustering methods. Concretely, the
                    algorithm aims at &quot;digging deeper into data&quot; by means of an iterative
                    clustering process. Following an initial clustering of the analyzed corpus (in
                    this case, the 974 paragraphs of the sixth edition of the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Origin of Species</hi>), the iterative concordance clustering process
                    starts by retrieving the most characteristic word of each cluster containing the
                    word(s) to be analyzed, that is, the word that has the higest TF.IDF rating
                    (Term Frequency – Inverted Document Frequency) for each of these clusters. Then,
                    the concordance of each of these characteristic words is extracted from the
                    corpus, and the same process of clustering, cluster selection, TF.IDF rating and
                    ranking, word selection and concordance extraction is performed on each of those
                    new concordances, until no new characteristic word is found or no more clusters
                    containing the word(s) to be analyzed are found.</p>
                <table>
                    <head>Iterative Concordance Clustering Algorithm</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell rend="2.3cm">1. Concordance extraction:</cell>
                        <cell>For each cluster containing the word(s) to be analyzed, extract the
                            concordance of the highest-TF.IDF-ranked word.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2. Concordance clustering:</cell>
                        <cell>For each previously unselected word, proceed to the clustering of its
                            concordance.</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>3. Iteration:</cell>
                        <cell>Return to step 1, unless 1) no new highest-TF.IDF-ranked word is
                            found, or 2) no clusters containing the word(s) to be analyzed are
                            found.</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>In order to identify the principal lexical constituents of the concept of
                    evolution and determine whether or not this underlying conceptual structure
                    includes references to both embryological and specific processes,two different
                    extraction procedures were made: the first one only aimed at the word
                    &quot;evolution&quot;, while the second one also added &quot;evolve&quot; and
                    &quot;evolved&quot;. Figures 1 and 2 show the results of the two analyses. </p>
                <p>
                    <figure xml:id="fig1">
                        <graphic url="770_Fig1.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>Figure 1: Conceptual analysis of &quot;evolution&quot;</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <figure xml:id="fig2">
                        <graphic url="770_Fig2.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                            mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <head>Figure 2: Conceptual analysis of &quot;evolution&quot;,
                            &quot;evolve&quot;, and &quot;evolved&quot;</head>
                    </figure>
                </p>
                <p>In addition to new and unforeseen methodological discoveries, interpretation of
                    both conceptual analyses seems to bring the sixth edition of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Origin of Species</hi> closer to the contemporary works of the
                    more mature Herbert Spencer, who began to de-emphasize the connection between
                    embryology and the general process of &quot;evolution&quot; and thus contributed
                    to forge the present, strictly specific and most commonly known biological use
                    of the word &quot;evolution&quot;.</p>
                <p>These results, along with the method that made them possible, are not in any way
                    definitive, and further improvements and modifications of the iterative
                    concordance clustering process are to be expected. Upon completion, this rather
                    new and original approach, while hoping to bring new insights in the
                    understanding of the <hi rend="italic">Origin of Species</hi>, also aims at
                    underlining the pertinence and usefulness of text mining methods and
                    applications for expert and specialized text reading and analysis, as well as
                    their importance for the future development of philology, hermeneutics, social
                    sciences and humanities in general.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Bowler, P.J. </author>
                        <date>2003</date>
                        <title level="m">Evolution: the History of an Idea</title>
                        <publisher>University of California Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title level="m">The Complete Works of Charles Darwin Online</title>
                        <date type="visited">25 February 2010</date>
                        <ptr target="http://darwin-online.org.uk "/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Harris, Z.</author>
                        <date>1991</date>
                        <title level="m">A Theory of Language and Information: A Mathematical
                            Approach</title>
                        <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Huxley, T.H.</author>
                        <date>1894</date>
                        <title level="a">Evolution in Biology</title>
                        <title level="m">Collected Essays, vol II: Darwiniana</title>
                        <publisher>Macmillan</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <biblScope type="pp">187-226</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>MacQueen, J. B. </author>
                        <date>1967</date>
                        <title level="a">Some Methods for classification and Analysis of
                            Multivariate Observations</title>
                        <title level="m">Proceedings of 5th Berkeley Symposium on Mathematical
                            Statistics and Probability</title>
                        <publisher>University of California Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berkeley</pubPlace>
                        <biblScope type="pp">281–297</biblScope>
                        <ptr target="http://projecteuclid.org/euclid.bsmsp/1200512992"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Meunier, J.G., Forest D. and Biskri, I. </author>
                        <date>2005</date>
                        <title level="a">Classification and Categorization in Computer-Assisted
                            Reading and Text Analysis</title>
                        <title level="m">Handbook of Categorization in Cognitive Science</title>
                        <editor>Cohen, H. and Lefebvre, C. </editor>
                        <publisher>Elsevier</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>The Hague</pubPlace>
                        <biblScope type="pp">955-978</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <title level="m">Network Workbench Tool</title>
                        <ptr target="http://nwb.slis.indiana.edu"/>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Richards, R.J. </author>
                        <date>1992</date>
                        <title level="m">The Meaning of Evolution: the Morphological Construction
                            and Ideological Reconstruction of Darwin's Theory</title>
                        <publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
