<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-795">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Mapping the World of an Ancient Greek Historian: The HESTIA Project</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Barker, Elton</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Open University</orgName>, <country>UK</country></affiliation>
                    <email>e.t.e.barker@open.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Pelling, Chris</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of Oxford</orgName>, <country>UK</country></affiliation>
                    <email>chris.pelling@chch.ox.ac.uk</email>
                    <email/>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Bouzarovski, Stefan</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of Birmingham</orgName>, <country>UK</country></affiliation>
                    <email>BuzarS@adf.bham.ac.uk</email>
                    <email/>
                </author>
                <author><name>Isaksen, Leif</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of Southampton</orgName>, <country>UK</country></affiliation>
                    <email>l.isaksen@soton.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-20</date>
                <name>CD</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="bold">HESTIA</hi> (the <hi rend="bold">Herodotus Encoded
                        Space-Text-Imaging Archive</hi>) is an interdisciplinary project, sponsored
                    by the AHRC and involving the collaboration of academics from Classics,
                    Geography and Archaeological Computing, that aims to enrich contemporary
                    discussions of space by developing an innovative methodology to the study of an
                    ancient narrative, Herodotus’ <hi rend="italic">Histories</hi>. Using the latest
                    ICT, it investigates the ways in which space is represented in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Histories</hi>, and develops visual tools to capture the
                    ‘deep’ topological structures of the text, extending beyond the usual
                    two-dimensional Cartesian maps of the ancient world. In addition to exploring
                    the network culture that Herodotus represents, one of its stated outcomes is to
                    introduce Herodotus’ world to new audiences via the internet. This paper will
                    set out in more detail that methodology, paying particular attention to the
                    decisions that we have made and the problems that we have encountered, in the
                    hope that our project can contribute not only to offering a more complex picture
                    of space in Herodotus but also to establishing a basis for future digital
                    projects across the humanities which deal with large text-based corpora.</p>
                <p>For the purposes of a twenty minute presentation, we address three key areas of
                    interest: <xmt:oList rend="arabic">
                        <item>To provide the background to the data capture and digital mark-up of
                            the <hi rend="italic">Histories</hi>. Our project differs from many by
                            utilizing a digital resource already in the public domain: the text of
                            Herodotus freely available from Perseus (<ref type="external"
                                target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/"
                                >http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/</ref>). Though the capture of
                            the digital text from Perseus (version P4) gave our project a welcome
                            initial boost, a number of issues have had to be overcome including
                            procedural conversion, which involves handing back a P5 text to
                            Perseus.</item>
                        <item>To sketch out the the type, structure and categorization of our
                            spatial database. A PostgreSQL database was chosen because its PostGIS
                            extension provides excellent functionality for spatial data and is
                            widely supported by other applications: one key principle of HESTIA has
                            been to use open source software in order to maximize its potential
                            dissemination and reusability of its data. By storing information about
                            references, locations and the text in the database, it has been possible
                            to provide it to both a Desktop GIS system and Webmapping server
                            simultaneously (<ref type="internal" cRef="fig1">see figure 1</ref>). </item>
                        <item>To present a sample set of results of the maps that we have been able
                            to generate using the geo-referenced database. While sections 1 and 2
                            will be of particular concern to anyone wishing to understand how one
                            may interrogate spatial data using the digital resources available, this
                            last stage holds the greatest interest for the non ICT expert since it
                            demonstrates the use to which data in this form can be employed: hence
                            the main focus of this paper will be on explaining the five kinds of map
                            that we have been able to generate: <xmt:oList rend="lower_roman">
                                <item xml:id="i"><hi rend="italic">Geographical Information System
                                        (GIS) maps</hi>. The most basic maps that are generated
                                    simply represent a ‘flat’ image of the spatial data: that is to
                                    say, they mark all the places that Herodotus mentions over the
                                    course of his work with a single point, thereby providing a
                                    snapshot of the huge scope of his enquiry. In this way one is
                                    able to gain an overview of the places mentioned in Herodotus
                                    and divide them according to three different kinds of spatial
                                    category: settlement, territory and physical feature (<ref
                                        type="internal" cRef="fig2">see figure 2</ref>). A variation
                                    on this basic model depicts places according to the number of
                                    times they are mentioned (<ref type="internal" cRef="fig3">see
                                        figure 3</ref>).</item>
                                <item xml:id="ii"><hi rend="italic">GoogleEarth</hi>. In order to
                                    start experimenting with public dissemination it was decided to
                                    expose the PostGIS data as KML: a mark-up format that can be
                                    read by a variety of mapping applications including GoogleEarth.
                                    With this ‘Herodotus Earth’ application, users will be able to
                                    construct ‘mashups’ of visual and textual data. So, for example,
                                    since all places are linked to entries in the database, when one
                                    clicks on a particular location in GoogleEarth, it will be
                                    possible to bring up a dialog box containing Herodotus’ text (in
                                    both English and Greek) for that particular location for every
                                    occasion when it is mentioned in the narrative (<ref
                                        type="internal" cRef="fig4">see figure 4</ref>).</item>
                                <item xml:id="iii"><hi rend="italic">TimeMap</hi>. Whilst it is
                                    possible to visualise narrative change using graphs, and static
                                    differences using GIS, it is more difficult to visualize spatial
                                    changes throughout the narrative; GIS does not have useful
                                    functionality in this regard except for the ability to turn
                                    layers on and off, a process which becomes impractical beyond
                                    book level. The most likely candidate to provide this kind of
                                    functionality is an Open Source JavaScript project called
                                    TimeMap, developed by Nick Rabinowitz, which draws on several
                                    other technologies in order to allow data plotted on GoogleMaps
                                    to appear and disappear as a timeline is moved. In collaboration
                                    with the project’s IT consultant Leif Isaksen, Nick Rabinowitz
                                    has adapted his schema in order to represent the book structure
                                    of Herodotus’ narrative in a similar way (<ref type="internal"
                                        cRef="fig4">see figure 5</ref>).</item>
                                <item xml:id="iv"><hi rend="italic">Database-generated network
                                        maps</hi>. Since the GIS maps outlined in <ref
                                        type="internal" cRef="i">i.</ref> have little to say per se
                                    regarding Herodotus’ organization of space, a key next step has
                                    been to explore rapidly-generated networks based on the simple
                                    co-presence of terms within sections of the text. The purpose of
                                    producing networks of this kind is to start exploring the
                                    connections that Herodotus himself makes between places, seeing
                                    how strongly the narrative is bound to geographical regions, and
                                    flagging up potential links between particular locations (<ref
                                        type="internal" cRef="fig6">see figure 6</ref>). <ref
                                        type="internal" cRef="fig7">Figure 7</ref> illustrates one
                                    such simple network, that for “territories” across the entire
                                        <hi rend="italic">Histories</hi>. It shows a series of links
                                    connecting Greece to other areas within the Mediterranean world:
                                    but the territory that has the strongest connections in this
                                    basic network culture is Egypt. While surprising, it does make
                                    sense on reflection, since for a better part of one book
                                    Herodotus uses Egypt as the touchstone against which other
                                    cultures, including Persia and his own, Greece, are compared. It
                                    is as a tool of comparison, then, that Egypt appears to be the
                                    centre of Herodotus’ network picture of the Mediterranean. <ref
                                        type="internal" cRef="fig8">Figure 8</ref> complements this
                                    picture by presenting the networks of physical features, which
                                    envelop the comparison between Greece and Egypt.</item>
                                <item xml:id="v"><hi rend="italic">Manual network maps</hi>. The
                                    automated maps outlined in <ref type="internal" cRef="iv"
                                        >iv.</ref> rely on ‘counting’ the number of times two or
                                    more places are connected to each other: they have little to say
                                    about the kind of connection being drawn. We end our
                                    presentation, then, with a brief comparison to text-based
                                    qualitative analysis, which attempts to categorize relationships
                                    according to fundamental geographical concepts of movement or
                                    transformation, based on the close reading of one book (<ref
                                        type="internal" cRef="fig5">5</ref>). Our different
                                    approaches are intended to complement, challenge and inform each
                                    other with a view also to suggest ways by which the automated
                                    process may be extended, such as by adopting text-mining
                                    procedures. </item>
                            </xmt:oList></item>
                    </xmt:oList>
                </p>
                <p>In sum, this paper aims to meet three outcomes: <xmt:oList rend="arabic">
                        <item>To outline a methodology for dealing with digital data that may be
                            transferred, adapted and improved upon in other fields of digital
                            humanities.</item>
                        <item>To demonstrate the value of digital projects within the humanities for
                            helping to achieve ‘impact’ by bringing the world of a fifth-century BC
                            Greek historian into everyone’s home.</item>
                        <item>To show the potential for the digital manipulation of data in posing
                            new kinds of research questions.</item>
                    </xmt:oList>
                </p>
            </div>            <div>
                <figure xml:id="fig1">
                    <head>Fig. 1</head>
                    <graphic url="795_Fig1.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                        mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="fig2">
                    <head>Fig. 2</head>
                    <graphic url="795_Fig2.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                        mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="fig3">
                    <head>Fig. 3</head>
                    <graphic url="795_Fig3.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                        mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="fig4">
                    <head>Fig. 4</head>
                    <graphic url="795_Fig4.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                        mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="fig5">
                    <head>Fig. 5</head>
                    <graphic url="795_Fig5.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                        mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="fig6">
                    <head>Fig. 6</head>
                    <graphic url="795_Fig6.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                        mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="fig7">
                    <head>Fig. 7</head>
                    <graphic url="795_Fig7.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                       mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="fig8">
                    <head>Fig. 8</head>
                    <graphic url="795_Fig8.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                        mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>

            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Berman, M. L.</author>
                        <title level="a">Boundaries or Networks in Historical GIS: Concepts of
                            Measuring Space and Administrative Geography in Chinese History</title>
                        <title level="j">Historical Geography</title>
                        <date>2005</date>
                        <biblScope type="issue">33</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">118-33</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Crampton, J.W.</author>
                        <author>Krygier, J.</author>
                        <title level="a">An introduction to critical cartography</title>
                        <title level="j">ACME: An International E-Journal for Critical
                        Geographies</title>
                        <date>2006</date>
                        <biblScope type="issue">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">11-33</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Harley, J.B.</author>
                        <title level="a">Deconstructing the map</title>
                        <title level="j">Cartographica: The International Journal for Geographic
                        Information and Geovisualization</title>
                        <date>1989</date>
                        <biblScope type="issue">26.2</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">1-20</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Horden, J.</author>
                        <author>Purcell, N.</author>
                        <title level="m">The Corrupting Sea</title>
                        <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                        <date>2000</date></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Jackson, P.</author>
                        <title level="m">Maps of Meaning: An Introduction to Cultural
                            Geography</title>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <date>1994</date></bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Janni, P.</author>
                        <title level="m">La Mappa e il Periplo. Cartografia antica e spazio
                            odologico</title>
                        <pubPlace>Marcerata</pubPlace>
                        <date>1984</date></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Kwan, M.-P.</author>
                        <author>Ding, G.</author>
                        <title level="a">Geo-Narrative: Extending Geographic Information Systems for
                            Narrative Analysis in Qualitative and Mixed-Method Research</title>
                        <title level="j">The Professional Geographer</title>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <biblScope type="issue">60.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">443-65</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Lefebvre, H.</author>
                        <title level="m">The Production of Space</title>
                        <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                        <date>1991</date></bibl>
                    <bibl>
                        <author>Lloyd, C. D.</author>
                        <author>Lilley, K. D.</author>
                        <title level="a">Cartographic Veracity in Medieval Mapping: Analyzing
                            Geographical Variation in the Gough Map of Great Britain</title>
                        <title level="j">Annals of the Association of American Geographers</title>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <biblScope type="issue">99.1</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">27-48</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Purves, A. C. </author>
                        <title level="m">Telling Space: Topography, Time and Narrative from Homer to
                            Xenophon</title>
                        <publisher>University of Pennsylvania</publisher>
                        Ph.D. Dissertation<date>2002</date></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Romm, J.S.</author>
                        <title level="m">The Edges of the Earth in Ancient Thought: Geography,
                            Exploration, and Fiction</title>
                        <pubPlace>Princeton</pubPlace>
                        <date>1994</date></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Sheppard, E.</author>
                        <title level="a">Knowledge Production through Critical GIS: Genealogy and
                            Prospects</title>
                        <title level="j">Cartographica: The International Journal for Geographic
                        Information and Geovisualization</title>
                        <date>2005</date>
                        <biblScope type="issue">40.4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">5-21</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl><author>Tuan, Y.-F. </author>
                        <title level="a">Literature and geography: implications for geographical
                            research</title>
                        <editor>Ley</editor>
                        <editor>Samuels</editor>
                        <title level="m">Humanistic Geography</title>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <date>1978</date>
                        <biblScope type="pp">194-206</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
