<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-856">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Crossing the Boundary: Exploring the Educational Potential of Social
                    Networking Sites</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Lang, Anouk</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Queen Mary, University of London</orgName> <reg><country>UK</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>a.lang@qmul.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-19</date>
                <name>CD</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>To date, the scholarship on social networking sites (SNSs) such as Facebook and
                    MySpace has focused largely on areas other than pedagogy, with <ref
                        type="internal" cRef="bibl1">Boyd and Ellison (2007)</ref> observing that so
                    far, most SNS research has centred on “impression management and friendship
                    performance, networks and network structure, online/offline connections, and
                    privacy issues”. Some work has been done on the effect of instructor presence on
                    Facebook (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl4">Hewitt and Forte, 2006</ref>; <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl5">Mazer et al., 2007</ref>; <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl10">Szwelnik, 2008</ref>), the
                    creation of MySpace pages in terms of the acquisition of new forms of digital
                    literacy (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl8">Perkel, 2008</ref>), and some of the difficulties and benefits of SNSs for
                    university students (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl11">Thelwall, 2008</ref>). Aside from this, however, there is little
                    scholarship on the educational uses and potential of SNSs at university level.
                    As <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl10">Szwelnik (2008)</ref> comments, ‘Facebook has attracted a lot of attention from
                    media and business but not yet a lot of attention from educational researchers’. </p>
                <p>It is perhaps not surprising that it is the social aspects of these sites that
                    have attracted the most critical attention, given that their central purpose is
                    understood to be the management and navigation of (often pre-existing)
                    relationships, rather than a means by which to share interests, complete tasks,
                    or simply communicate with others (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl1">Boyd and Ellison, 2007</ref>; <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl6">OFCOM, 2008</ref>).
                    However, given that the social dimension of education is a fundamental to
                    learning, it is worth exploring how SNSs may be used to pedagogical advantage.
                    This is particularly the case given the large proportion of university students
                    that access the sites: <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl3">Ellison et al. (2007)</ref> found that 94% of the undergraduate
                    population at Michigan State University were members, while a 2007 Ipsos Mori
                    poll found that 95% of British undergraduates are regular users (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl9">Shepherd,
                    2008</ref>). SNSs, it would seem, are a resource not yet being used to their full
                    potential for university teaching. </p>
                <p>This paper reports on the findings of a research project designed to address the
                    under-utilisation of SNSs at university level and the corresponding gap in the
                    literature. Undertaken with students in the School of Languages, Linguistics and
                    Film at Queen Mary, University of London, it investigates the educational
                    potential of Facebook for facilitating informal learning with students on their
                    year abroad, particularly in the domain of intercultural awareness and
                    communication. Events held in previous years demonstrated the usefulness of
                    bringing language students together in face-to-face contexts to reflect on their
                    own and others’ diverse experiences of the year abroad. This project set up an
                    online space on an SNS to facilitate this kind of learning through a peer
                    mentoring framework, and to allow discussions of this sort to occur regularly
                    during the students’ time abroad, rather than after it was over. </p>
                <p>Undergraduate students in their second and final year of a language course were
                    surveyed about their attitude towards the year abroad, their use of technology
                    and SNSs, and, following <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl3">Ellison et al. (2007)</ref>, their affective investment in
                    SNSs. Two different populations were surveyed: second year students organising
                    their year abroad for the following year, and final year students who had
                    returned from their year abroad. The results were used to develop focus group
                    protocols to gauge students’ receptivity to the idea of using Facebook to carry
                    out course-related discussions, to judge the extent to which Facebook was a
                    hospitable environment for peer mentoring to occur, and to determine which
                    Facebook applications would best assist with educational objectives. Students
                    were also asked about which aspects of the year abroad they were already using
                    Facebook to engage with, and which elements of their time away could be
                    ameliorated through provision of a virtual meeting place for discussion. Several
                    peer mentors were then chosen from the cohort who had already completed a year
                    abroad, and these students were trained in online moderating and mentoring. A
                    Facebook group was set up for the student mentors to use, and this was observed
                    over a period of three months. Following this, four methods of evaluation were
                    used to measure the effectiveness of the Facebook group: a) an online survey for
                    third-year students currently on their year abroad; b) informal discussions with
                    academic staff in modern languages; c) interviews with the peer mentors held at
                    a computer; and d) close analysis and corpus analysis of the text of the online
                    discussions.</p>
                <p><ref type="internal" cRef="bibl7">Paul and Brier (2001)</ref> and <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl2">Cummings et al. (2006)</ref> have explored how students of
                    university age use Facebook and other internet technologies to alleviate the
                    “friendsickness” brought about by moving away from one’s friends. This project
                    aimed to capitalise on the powerful ability of SNSs to address this relational
                    need by drawing students into online conversations and collaborations that not
                    only helped them to sustain relationships but also to use those relationships to
                    learn from one another. However, existing research points to a strong resistance
                    from university students to academics occupying “their” space on an SNS,
                    something Szwelnik terms “crossing the boundary” (2008). <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl4">Hewitt and Forte (2003)</ref>
                    observe that identity management is a significant concern for SNS users when the
                    roles they occupy cross perceived social boundaries and bring organizational
                    power relationships into visibility, citing one student’s fears that Facebook
                    could “unfairly skew a professor's perception of a student in a student
                    environment”. Given that both social boundaries and uneven power relationships
                    both come into play in the context of teacher-led discussions around
                    course-related material, the project sought to find a way to build a learning
                    community without infringing on a space perceived not to belong to academic
                    staff, and to shift the discursive content from social to educational without
                    forcing students to “cross the boundary”. In working with peer mentors, the
                    project aimed not only to avoid these boundary-crossing problems but also to
                    work intentionality into the fabric of the Facebook group. As <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl12">Woods and Ebersole
                    (2003)</ref> observe, transforming textual exchanges into a learning community with a
                    positive social dynamic requires intentional decisions in the realm of both
                    verbal and nonverbal communication, so student mentors needed to be made
                    acquainted with the learning objectives for the educational context, and
                    carefully trained in techniques of e-moderation to overcome the challenges a
                    mediated environment can pose to productive discussions. This approach also had
                    the advantage of being, to an extent, futureproofed: students were more likely
                    than academic staff to know which technologies are most popular with their
                    peers, and once a framework for online mentoring is established, this could be
                    moved in future years to different sites or applications as students’ usage
                    patterns change. A further advantage of this model is that it equips the student
                    mentors with the digital literacy and communication skills to operate in the
                    kinds of virtual environments that, as knowledge workers, they are likely to
                    inhabit in their careers. </p>
                <p>In summarising the results of this study, this paper will report on the benefits
                    of using an SNS to support informal learning in the context of students on a
                    year abroad, and set out approaches that universities can take to promote
                    learning more generally through the use of SNSs. It uses tools from the Internet
                    Community Text Analyzer (<ref type="external" target="http://textanalytics.net/"
                        >http://textanalytics.net/</ref>) to visualise the networks that developed
                    between students on the site, and to identify productive models of SNS-mediated
                    student mentoring behaviour.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl1"><author>Boyd, D. M.</author>
                        <author>Ellison, N. B.</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">Social Network Sites: Definition, History, and
                            Scholarship</title>
                        <title level="j">Journal of Computer-Mediated Communication</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">13(1)</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">210-230</biblScope>
                        <ptr target="http://jcmc.indiana.edu/vol13/issue1/boyd.ellison.html"/>
                        <date type="visited">19 September 2008</date></bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="bibl2"><author>Cummings, J.</author>
                        <author>Lee, J.</author>
                        <author>Kraut, R.</author>
                        <date>2006</date>
                        <title level="a">Communication Technology and Friendship During the
                            Transition from High School to college</title>
                        <editor>Kraut, R. E.</editor>
                        <editor>Brynin, M.</editor>
                        <editor>Kiesler, S.</editor>
                        <title level="m">Computers, Phones, and the Internet: Domesticating
                            Information Technology</title>
                        <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
                        <biblScope type="pp">pp. 265-278</biblScope></bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="bibl3"><author>Ellison, N. B.</author>
                        <author>Steinfield, C.</author>
                        <author>Lampe, C.</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">The Benefits of Facebook "Friends:" Social Capital and
                            College Students' Use of Online Social Network Sites</title>
                        <title level="j">Journal of Computer-Mediated Communication</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">12(4)</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">1143–1168</biblScope>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://www3.interscience.wiley.com/cgi-bin/fulltext/117979349/HTMLSTART"/>
                        <date type="visited">30 October 2008</date></bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="bibl4"><author>Hewitt, A.</author>
                        <author>Forte, A.</author>
                        <date>2006</date>
                        <title level="a">Crossing Boundaries: Identity Management and
                            Student/Faculty Relationships on the Facebook</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">CSCW'06</title>
                        <name type="venue">Banff, AB</name>
                        <date type="conference">November 2006</date>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://www-static.cc.gatech.edu/~aforte/HewittForteCSCWPoster2006.pdf"/>
                        <date type="visited">19 September 2008</date></bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="bibl5"><author>Mazer, J.</author>
                        <author>Murphy, R.</author>
                        <author>Simonds, C.</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">I'll See You On "Facebook": The Effects of
                            Computer-Mediated Teacher Self-Disclosure on Student Motivation,
                            Affective Learning, and Classroom Climate</title>
                        <title level="j">Communication Education</title><biblScope type="issue"
                            >56(1)</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">1-17</biblScope></bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="bibl6"><author>OFCOM [Office of Communication]</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="m">Social Networking: A Quantitative and Qualitative Research
                            Report into Attitudes, Behaviours and Use</title>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://www.ofcom.org.uk/advice/media_literacy/medlitpub/medlitpubrss/socialnetworking/report.pdf"/>
                        <date type="visited">22 September 2008</date></bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="bibl7"><author>Paul, E. L.</author>
                        <author>Brier, S.</author>
                        <date>2001</date>
                        <title level="a">Friendsickness in the Transition to College: Precollege
                            Predictors and College Adjustment Correlates</title>
                        <title level="j">Journal of Counseling &amp; Development</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">79(1)</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">77-89</biblScope></bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="bibl8"><author>Perkel, D.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">Copy and Paste Literacy? Literacy Practices in the
                            Production of a MySpace Profile</title>
                        <editor>Drotner, K.</editor>
                        <editor>Jensen, H.S.</editor>
                        <editor>Schroeder, K.</editor>
                        <title level="m">Informal Learning and Digital Media: Constructions,
                            Contexts, Consequences</title>
                        <pubPlace>Newcastle, UK</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>Cambridge Scholars Press</publisher>
                        <biblScope type="pp">203-224</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl9"><author>Shepherd, J.</author>
                        <date>30 September 2008</date>
                       <title level="a">Make Friends Before you Start</title>
                        <title level="j">The Guardian</title>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://www.guardian.co.uk/education/2008/sep/30/students.facebook"
                        />
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl10"><author>Szwelnik, A.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="m">BMAF Project Report: Embracing the Web 2.0 Culture in
                            Business Education – The New Face of Facebook</title>
                        <ptr
                            target="http://www.heacademy.ac.uk/assets/bmaf/documents/projects/TRDG_projects/trdg_0708/finalreports_0708/Alice_Szwelnik_OBU_web.doc"/>
                        <date>11 November 2008</date></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl11"><author>Thelwall, M.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="a">MySpace, Facebook, Bebo: Social Networking Students</title>
                        <title level="j">Association for Learning Technology Online
                            Newsletter</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">11</biblScope>
                        <date>25 January 2008</date>
                        <ptr target="http://newsletter.alt.ac.uk/e_article000993849.cfm"/></bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="bibl12"><author>Woods, R.</author>
                        <author>Ebersole, S.</author>
                        <date>2003</date>
                        <title level="a">Using Non-Subject-Matter-Specific Discussion Boards to
                            Build Connectedness in Online Learning</title>
                        <title level="j">American Journal of Distance Education</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">17(2)</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">99-118</biblScope>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
