<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-867">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Using Wikipedia to Enable Entity Retrieval and Visualization Concerning the
                    Intellectual/Cultural Heritage</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Athenikos, Sofia J.</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Drexel University</orgName>, Philadelphia, <country>USA</country></affiliation>
                    <email>sofia.j.athenikos@acm.org</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-28</date>
                <name>CD</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>At the 2009 Digital Humanities conference I presented my paper on the
                    WikiPhiloSofia (<ref type="external"
                        target="http://research.cis.drexel.edu:8080/sofia/WPS/"
                        >http://research.cis.drexel.edu:8080/sofia/WPS/</ref>) project (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl1">Athenikos
                    and Lin, 2009</ref>), which was concerned with extraction and visualization of facts,
                    relations, and networks concerning philosophers using Wikipedia (<ref
                        type="external" target="http://www.wikipedia.org/"
                        >http://www.wikipedia.org/</ref>) as the data source. In this proposal, I
                    present a related, extended project in progress, entitled PanAnthropon, which
                    incorporates the problems of retrieving entities in response to a query and
                    retrieving entities related to a given entity and which extends the scope of
                    application to domains other than philosophy. </p>
            <div>
                <head>Background</head>
                <p>Traditional information retrieval is concerned with retrieving documents that are
                    potentially relevant to a user’s query. The relevance of a document to a given
                    query is usually measured by lexico-syntactic matching between the terms in the
                    query and those in the document (title). Familiar Web search engines, such as
                    Google and Yahoo, for example, return a ranked list of Web pages that contain
                    all or some of the keywords in the query entered by a user. The Semantic Web
                    (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl3">Berners-Lee et al., 2001</ref>) initiative aims at transforming the Web of pages
                    (documents) into the Web of entities (things in the broadest sense) (cf. OKKAM
                    project (<ref type="external" target="http://www.okkam.org/"
                        >http://www.okkam.org/</ref>) (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl4">Bouquet et al., 2007</ref>)). Information retrieval
                    on the Semantic Web is no longer a matter of retrieving documents via
                    semantics-unaware keyword matching but a matter of retrieving entities that
                    satisfy the semantic constraints imposed by the query, i.e. those that are of
                    specific semantic type and that satisfy the given semantic conditions. Wikipedia
                    has become an important semantic knowledge resource (cf. <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl8">Zesch et al., 2007</ref>)
                    thanks to its unique set of semi-structured semantic features and the huge
                    amount of content covering a wide range of topics. What renders Wikipedia more
                    interesting is the fact that it can be considered as a self-contained web of
                    entities. Each Wikipedia article is concerned with one entity, and the given
                    entity is connected to other entities via explicit semantic relations as in
                    infoboxes and wikitables or via implicit semantic relations as in hyperlinks.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Motivation</head>
                <p>Through the WikiPhiloSofia project I demonstrated extracting, retrieving, and
                    visualizing specific facets of information, not documents, concerning entities
                    of a selected type, namely, philosophers, by exploiting the hyperlinks,
                    categories, infoboxes, and wikitables contained in Wikipedia articles. The
                    interface that I created enables the users to select a focus of query in the
                    form of an entity (philosopher) or a pair of entities (philosophers) and then to
                    retrieve entities that satisfy specified conditions with respect to the given
                    entity or pair of entities. However, the project did not consider the problems
                    of retrieving entities as answers to queries, semantically typing entities, or
                    retrieving related entities by type and condition. </p>

                <p>The proposed PanAnthropon project takes up the aforementioned problems left out
                    of the WikiPhiloSofia project. The dual objective is to enable retrieval of
                    entities that directly answer a given semantics-based query and to enable
                    retrieval of related entities by semantic type, subtype (role), and relation, by
                    using information extracted/integrated from Wikipedia. The project applies the
                    approach to the entities concerning the intellectual/cultural heritage – people,
                    works, concepts, etc. The Web portal interface thereby constructed will allow
                    the users to retrieve entities that directly answer their queries as well as to
                    explore people, works, concepts, etc. <hi rend="italic">in relation to</hi>
                    other people, works, concepts, etc. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conceptualization</head>
                <p>In the proposed project, “entities” are conceived of as things of all kinds that
                    have certain properties (or attributes). The “type” of an entity is considered
                    as a generic kind (or class or category) into which the given entity is
                    classified, e.g., person, work, etc. In general, the type of an entity is fixed
                    and exclusive in the sense that an entity that belongs to one type does not or
                    cannot belong to other types. The “subtype” of an entity refers to a subclass or
                    subcategory into which the entity can be classified, under a given type. The
                    subtype of an entity is fluid and non-exclusive in the sense that an entity may
                    belong to more than one subtype (under a given type). This is especially so in
                    the case of person-type entities, and thus a subtype may better be understood as
                    a “role” in this case. In general, there are multiple subtypes under a given
                    type, and the former can be further classified into still more specific
                    subtypes. A type or subtype of an entity can be considered as a special kind of
                    property. A “fact” concerning an entity refers to a tuple consisting of
                    &lt;entity, attribute, value, [context]&gt;, which adds the optional
                    “context” element to the &lt;subject, predicate, object&gt; triple
                    model. An entity can have “relations” to other entities, given its properties.
                    The kinds of properties and relations that are relevant or of interest
                    concerning an entity, except certain basic facts, depend on the domain at issue.
                    An entity may belong to multiple domains, but not every subtype, property, or
                    relation is relevant or equally important in one domain as in another domain.
                    The project therefore intends to build a portal consisting of sub-portals
                    representing different domains.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Methodology</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Data Extraction and Processing</head>
                    <p>The pre-processing stage of the project (for each domain) concerns: (1)
                        compiling a seed list of entities of interest by extracting names from
                        various lists and categories in Wikipedia, (2) downloading Wikipedia article
                        pages for each entry on the list, and (3) inspecting typical attributes and
                        (types/subtypes of) values contained in infoboxes, wikitables, etc. The main
                        processing stage concerns extracting information on an entity and related
                        entities from each Wikipedia page. The semantic type/subtypes of a given
                        entity are extracted and/or assigned. Semi-structured templates and portions
                        of the article are processed so as to extract attribute–value (or
                        predicate–object or relation–entity) pairs. The related entities are matched
                        to the entities on the seed entity list. Additional Wikipedia pages are
                        downloaded for entities not matched on the list, and the information on
                        those entities is extracted. The (optional) post-processing stage concerns
                        converting the data stored in a MySQL database to XML files and RDF triples,
                        thereby creating a semantic data repository that can be linked to other
                        resources involved in the Linked Data (<ref type="external"
                            target="http://linkeddata.org/">http://linkeddata.org/</ref>) initiative
                        in the latter case. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Semantic Search Interface</head>
                    <p>The semantic search interface created will support three types of query and
                        retrieval. The first type of query/retrieval concerns retrieval of entities
                        that correspond to queries the expected answers of which are entities. The
                        second type of query/retrieval concerns retrieval of entities related to an
                        entity, according to type/subtypes and specified properties/values. The
                        third type of query/retrieval concerns retrieval of facts concerning an
                        entity. The interface will also incorporate some of the visualization
                        features available in the WikiPhiloSofia portal interface. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Current Application</head>
                <p>The film domain has been chosen as the initial proof-of-concept domain of
                    application. In my presentation I will demonstrate the entity retrieval functionalities with 1.5+ million (and growing) facts about 11370 films, 69545 persons, 74545 film roles, 253 places, 6033 dates, etc.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Related Work</head>
                <p>The task of retrieving entities in response to user queries using the information
                    in Wikipedia has since 2007 been the focus of the INEX (Initiative for the
                    Evaluation of XML Retrieval) XML Entity Ranking (XER) Track (de Vries et al.,
                    2008; Demartini et al., 2009). Unlike in the INEX XER Track, the proposed
                    project addresses the task by extracting information from the HTML Wikipedia
                    files and building a knowledge base based on it. The task of constructing a
                    knowledge base by extracting information from templates in Wikipedia such as
                    infoboxes has been attempted in large scale by, e.g., <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl2">Auer and Lehmann (2007)</ref>
                    and <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl7">Suchanek et al. (2007)</ref>. There is also the DBpedia (<ref type="external"
                        target="http://dbpedia.org/">http://dbpedia.org/</ref>) knowledge base,
                    which contains the information extracted from Wikipedia. The proposed project,
                    however, utilizes the information in the main content of Wikipedia articles, as
                    well as templates, to enable and enhance entity retrieval. It will also provide
                    a more flexible working search interface for both general and entity-specific
                    queries. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion</head>
                <p>The PanAnthropon project utilizes Wikipedia as a semantic knowledge source for
                    entity retrieval and applies the approach to materials concerning the
                    intellectual/cultural heritage. The semantic search interface created will allow
                    the users to retrieve entities that directly answer their queries as well as to
                    explore various semantic facets concerning those entities. As such, it will
                    provide a useful resource for digital humanities.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl1">
                        <author>Athenikos, S.J.</author>
                        <author>Lin, X.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">WikiPhiloSofia: Extraction and Visualization of Facts,
                            Relations, and Networks Concerning Philosophers Using Wikipedia</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Conference Abstracts of Digital Humanities 2009</title><biblScope type="pp">56-62</biblScope>
                        </bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="bibl2"><author>Auer, S.</author>
                        <author>Lehmann, J.</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">What Have Innsbruck and Leipzig in Common? Extracting
                            Semantics from Wiki Content</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Proceedings of 4th European Semantic Web
                            Conference (ESWC 2007)</title>
                        <name type="venue">Innsbruck, Austria</name>
                        <date type="conference">June 2007</date></bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="bibl3"><author>Berners-Lee, T.</author>
                        <author>Hendler, J.</author>
                        <author>Lassila, O.</author>
                        <date>2001</date><title level="a">The Semantic Web</title> <title level="j">Scientific
                            American</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">5 (May 2001)</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl4"><author>Bouquet, P.</author>
                        <author>Stoermer, H.</author>
                        <author>Giacomuzzi, D.</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">OKKAM: Enabling a Web of Entities</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Proceedings of the 16th International
                            World Wide Web Conference (WWW 2007)</title>
                        <name type="venue">Banff, Alberta, Canada</name><date type="conference">
                            8-12 May 2007</date>. </bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="bibl5"><author>Demartini, G.</author>
                        <author>de Vries, A.P.</author>
                        <author>Iofciu, T.</author><author>Zhu, J.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="m">Overview of the INEX 2008 Entity Ranking Track, INEX
                            2008</title>
                        <title level="s">LNCS</title>
                        
                        <publisher>Springer-Verlag, Berlin</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Heidelberg</pubPlace><biblScope type="vol">5631</biblScope><biblScope type="pp"
                        >243-252</biblScope></bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="bibl6"><author>de Vries, A.P.</author>
                        <author>Vercoustre, A.-M.</author>
                        <author>Thom, J.A.</author>
                        <author>Craswell, N.</author><author>Lalmas, M.</author>
                        <date>2008</date>
                        <title level="m">Overview of the INEX 2007 Entity Ranking Track, INEX
                            2007</title>
                        <title level="s">LNCS</title>
                        
                        <publisher>Springer-Verlag, Berlin</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Heidelberg</pubPlace><biblScope type="vol">4862</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">245-251</biblScope></bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="bibl7"><author>Suchanek, F.M.</author>
                        <author>Kasneci, G.</author>
                        <author>Weikum, G.</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">YAGO: A Core of Semantic Knowledge Unifying WordNet and
                            Wikipedia</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Proceedings of the 16th International
                            World Wide Web Conference (WWW 2007)</title>
                        <name type="venue">Banff, Alberta, Canada</name>
                        <date type="comference">8-12 May 2007</date>
                        <biblScope type="pp">697-706</biblScope></bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="bibl8">
                        <author>Zesch, T.</author>
                        <author>Gurevych, I.</author>
                        <author>Mühlhäuser, M.</author>
                        <date>2007</date>
                        <title level="a">Analyzing and Accessing Wikipedia as a Lexical Semantic
                            Resource</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Proceedings of the Biannual Conference
                            of the Society for Computational Linguistics and Language
                            Technology</title>
                        <name type="venue">Tübingen, Germany</name>
                        <date type="conference">April 2007</date>
                    </bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
