<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-808">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Digitizing the Act of Papyrological Interpretation: Negotiating Spurious
                    Exactitude and Genuine Uncertainty</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Tarte, Ségolène M.</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of Oxford</orgName>, <country>UK</country></affiliation>
                    <email>segolene.tarte@oerc.ox.ac.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-20</date>
                <name>CD</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Digitization is a sampling process</head>
                <p>The act of papyrological interpretation is a continuous thought process that
                    unravels non-linearly (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl11">Youtie, 1963</ref>; <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl10">Terras, 2006</ref>). Throughout this sense-making
                    process, ancient and scarcely legible documents progress from the status of pure
                    physical objects to that of meaningful historical artefacts. Within the
                    e-Science and Ancient Documents project,<note>Project website: <ref
                            type="external" target="http://esad.classics.ox.ac.uk/"
                            >http://esad.classics.ox.ac.uk/</ref></note> we aim to make explicit
                    some of the implicit mechanisms that contribute to the development of hypotheses
                    of interpretation by designing and implementing a web-based software offering
                    digital support for the hermeneutic task. This tool aims to record the
                    intermediary hypotheses of interpretation, thus keeping track of the rationale
                    and allowing easier and better revision when required. The model we have adopted
                    (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl6">Roued Olsen et al., 2009</ref>) is that of a network of percepts, where a percept is
                    defined as a minor interpretation that stems from perception and cognition
                    (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl8">Tarte, 2010</ref>). An understanding of expert knowledge and of how it is mobilised
                    is required to identify the crucial steps that allow us to reconstruct a
                    rationale. The level of the granularity at which we choose to provide support
                    also is essential to the usability of the software. Further, each percept, each
                    intermediary interpretation, each piece of evidence used either to support or to
                    invalidate a claim is potentially mutable. The implementation of an
                    Interpretation Support System (ISS) taking these considerations into account
                    poses the question of how to digitize or record a thought process; it is an
                    epitome of the ‘continuous-to-discrete’ (or ‘analogue-to-digital’) problem. In
                    the theoretical and life sciences, measurement devices are developed to sample
                    the signals of interest. Then, based on the discrete sampled signal, on an
                    underlying model of the behaviour of the signal, and on more general knowledge
                    of signal processing and information theory (e.g. the Nyquist-Shannon sampling
                    theorem), the continuous signal can be reconstructed with minimal deviation from
                    the original signal. Similarly, the ambition of our ISS is, based on an
                    appropriate model of the papyrological hermeneutic task, to allow the user to
                    capture the information necessary to the reconstruction of the rationale that
                    yielded a given interpretation. Two difficulties in sampling the interpretive
                    thought process are: (1) to take advantage and to beware of the sense of
                    scientific rigour that digitization conveys; and (2) to allow the digital
                    expression of uncertainty and mutability of percepts.</p>
                <p>In this paper, we explain how, while attempting to digitize the papyrological
                    interpretation act, we strive to avoid spurious exactitude and accommodate
                    genuine uncertainty. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Choosing what to digitize and how</head>
                <p>The papyrological model of reading developed by Terras (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl10">Terras, 2006</ref>) identified
                    ten levels of reading, corresponding to ten levels of granularity at which an
                    interpretation in progress is discussed. Tools stemming from web-based
                    technology (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl1">Bowman et al., 2010</ref>), image processing (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl9">Tarte et al., 2009</ref>) and
                    artificial intelligence can help support the digitization of the hermeneutic
                    task (<ref type="internal" cRef="fig1">see fig. 1</ref>). To illustrate how we
                    negotiate between spurious exactitude and genuine uncertainty, we focus here on
                    two specific stages of the digitization of the papyrological interpretation
                    process: how artefact digitization is being performed; and how, by identifying
                    the mechanisms that trigger the jumps between the ten levels of reading, we
                    propose to address the representation of uncertainty.</p>
                <figure xml:id="fig1">
                    <head>Figure 1: Model of the act of interpretation detailing the various levels of reading
                        based on (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl10">Terras, 2006</ref>) and the tools involved in the implementation of our
                        ISS.</head>
                    <graphic url="808_Fig1.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                        mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    <p>Note the deliberate choice of representation of the ten levels of reading as
                        star-shaped around a stylus tablet to convey the recursive nature of the
                        hermeneutic process. Although the levels of reading are defined according to
                        the granularity of the subject discussed, oscillations between levels of
                        reading constantly occur, and these oscillations do not necessarily take
                        place between adjacent levels of reading.</p>
                </figure>
                <div>
                    <head>Digitizing the text-bearing artefact</head>
                    <p>The problem of spurious exactitude is most prevalent at the stage where the
                        text-bearing artefact is digitized. For stylus tablets, for example,
                        high-resolution pictures are not enough. The materiality of the artefact
                        needs to be taken into account in a similar way as the experts exploit it in
                        the real-world. The guiding principle we choose to follow in this context is
                        mimesis. Indeed, when the papyrologists have physical access to such an
                        incised tablet, in order to see better the incised text, they lay the tablet
                        flat on their hand, lift it at eye level and expose it to raking light while
                        applying pitch-and-yaw motions to it. This signal enhancement strategy
                        exploits the shadow-stereo principle by which stronger and more mobile
                        shadows and highlights occur at the incisions than they do on the bare wood;
                        the text is thereby accentuated. Digitally imitating this process, we
                        capture series of images of incised tablets with varying light positions
                        (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl2">Brady et al., 2005</ref>), allowing users to reproduce digitally the visual
                        phenomenon they naturally exploit in the real-world. Note that, similarly to
                        signal measurement devices, we adopt a digitization process that is already
                        part of the interpretation process. And the intention behind artefact
                        digitization, as well as the intention behind signal measurement, is always
                        an implicitly set variable that affects downstream results.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Digitizing the thought process</head>
                    <p>When attempting to capture the milestones of the thought process that builds
                        an interpretation of an ancient or damaged text, we need to capture the
                        uncertainty of the intermediary percepts and their mutability. A numerical
                        approach to uncertainty such as bayesian networks could have been adopted,
                        but such a quantification of uncertainty usually presupposes that problems
                        are complete, i.e. that all the alternatives to a given situation are known
                        (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl4">Parsons &amp; Hunter, 1998</ref>). Instead, we have decided to turn to
                        argumentation theory (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl4">Parsons &amp; Hunter, 1998</ref>) and theory of
                        justification (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl3">Haack, 1993</ref>), and combine them to provide a formal, yet
                        invisible, epistemological framework that will allow us to point out
                        inconsistencies without forbidding them. Indeed, inconsistencies in an
                        unravelling interpretation naturally occur and can be rooted either in the
                        implicit expectations of the user or in the validity of the actual claims
                        (see <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl8">Tarte, 2010</ref> for an account of an inconsistency due to an implicit
                        assumption and its resolution). The balance to be found here (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl7">Shipman III
                        &amp; Marshall, 1999</ref>) is between on the one hand the usefulness of a formal
                        system as a backbone to support reasoning under uncertainty and make
                        implicit mechanisms explicit, and on the other the excess of formalism and
                        explicit formulation that can become a hindrance by creating for the user an
                        overhead disruptive to the interpretation process. Here again, our design
                        choice is based on the observation of the experts at work. We allow both
                        palaeographical and philological approaches in combination, through the
                        possibility of tracing the letters and of handling the text as a crossword
                        puzzle (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl5">Roued-Cunliffe, 2010</ref>); these are both approaches that we have
                        identified as the main strategies experts develop when interpreting
                        documents (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl8">Tarte, 2010</ref>). The expression of uncertainty is then made inherent
                        to the mode of interaction with the artefact, and the transposition of the
                        real-world tasks of drawing and crossword puzzle solving allows us to keep
                        the interface intuitive while, in the background, more formal mechanisms can
                        run routines such as consistency checks and consultation and constitution of
                        knowledge bases. In her doctoral work, Roued-Cunliffe (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl5">Roued-Cunliffe, 2010</ref>)
                        is currently concentrating on the crossword puzzle approach and combining it
                        to consultation of knowledge bases through web-services.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion: digitization is also interpetation</head>
                <p>Digital technologies can easily trick the mind into thinking that their use
                    confers an exactitude on the results obtained with their support. It is however
                    worth noting that in the sciences too, digitization is always made with an
                    intention. When looking to sample a continuous signal, be it a temperature as a
                    function of time, or a thought process as a function of time, the sampling
                    strategy is always adopted in the light of an intention. Digitization is actually
                    also an act of interpretation. To record digitally the continuous
                    papyrological interpretation process, we have to identify clearly our final aim,
                    and to adapt our sampling strategy accordingly. Here, our aim is to enable to
                    record, reconstruct, back-track if necessary, the interpretation process by
                    making explicit (some of) the epistemological evidence substantiating the
                    interpretation in progress; an added benefit to the software is that it will
                    also enable easier production of an edition of a text, as the evidence will have
                    been laid out clearly. Capturing uncertainty is vital to the recording process,
                    and being conscious that its very capture is also part of the hermeneutic task
                    is crucial to allow the software design to take on board the elements that are
                    core to the whole interpretation process.</p>
            <lb/><p><hi rend="bold">Acknowledgements</hi><lb/>This work was supported by the joint AHRC-EPSRC-JISC Arts and Humanities
                e-Science Initiative UK [grant AH/E00654X/1]. <lb/>The author wishes to thank Prof. Alan Bowman, Prof. Sir Michael Brady, Dr. Roger
                    Tomlin, Dr. Melissa Terras, Dr. Charles Crowther and Henriette Roued-Cunliffe for
                    their support, as well as the reviewers for their helpful comments.</p></div>
        </body>
        <back>
          
            <div>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl1"><author>Bowman, A. K.</author>
                        <author>Crowther, C. V.</author>
                        <author>Kirkham, R.</author>
                        <author>Pybus, J.</author>
                        <date>2010</date>
                        <title level="a">A virtual research environment for the study of documents
                            and manuscripts</title>
                        <editor>Bodard, G.</editor>
                        <editor>Mahony, S.</editor>
                        <title level="m">Digital Research in the Study of Classical
                            Antiquity</title>
                        <publisher>Ashgate Press</publisher><pubPlace>London</pubPlace></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl2"><author>Brady, M.</author>
                        <author>Pan, X.</author>
                        <author>Schenck, V.</author>
                        <author>Terras, M.</author>
                        <author>Robertson, P.</author>
                        <author>Molton, N.</author>
                        <date>2005</date>
                        <title level="a">Shadow stereo, image filtering and constraint
                            propagation</title>
                        <editor>Bowman, A. K.</editor>
                        <editor>Brady, M.</editor>
                        <title level="m">Images and Artefacts of the Ancient World</title>
                        <title level="s">British Academy Occasional Paper</title>
                        <publisher>Oxford University Press/British Academy</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace><biblScope type="vol">4</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">15–30</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl3"><author>Haack, S.</author>
                        <date>1993</date>
                        <title level="a">Double-aspect foundherentism: A new theory of empirical
                            justification</title>
                        <title level="j">Philosophy and Phenomenological Research</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">53(1)</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">113–128</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl4"><author>Parsons, S.</author>
                        <author>Hunter, A.</author>
                        <date>1998</date>
                        <title level="a">A review of uncertainty handling formalisms</title>
                        <editor>Carbonell, J. G.</editor>
                        <editor>Siekmann, J.</editor>
                        <title level="m">Applications of Uncertainty Formalisms</title>
                        <title level="s">Lecture Notes in Artificial Intelligence (Lecture Notes in
                            Computer Science)</title> 
                        <publisher>Springer</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Berlin / Heidelberg</pubPlace><biblScope type="vol">1455</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">8–37</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl5"><author>Roued-Cunliffe, H.</author>
                        <date>2010: forthcoming</date>
                        <title level="a">Towards a Decision Support System for Reading Ancient
                            Documents</title>
                        <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl6"><author>Roued Olsen, H.</author>
                        <author>Tarte, S. M.</author>
                        <author>Terras, M.</author>
                        <author>Brady, J. M.</author>
                        <author>Bowman, A. K.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">Towards an interpretation support system for reading
                            ancient documents</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">Digital Humanities’09</title>
                        <date type="conference">2009</date>
                        <biblScope type="pp">237–39</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl7"><author>Shipman III, F. M.</author>
                        <author>Marshall, C. C.</author>
                        <date>1999</date>
                        <title level="a">Formality considered harmful: Experiences, emerging themes,
                            and directions on the use of formal representations in interactive
                            systems</title>
                        <title level="j">Computer Supported Cooperative Work</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">8</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">333–52</biblScope></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl8"><author>Tarte, S. M.</author>
                        <date>2010: forthcoming</date>
                        <title level="a">Papyrological investigations: Transferring perception and
                            interpretation into the digital world</title>
                        <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl9"><author>Tarte, S. M.</author>
                        <author>Wallom, D.</author>
                        <author>Hu, P.</author>
                        <author>Tang, K.</author>
                        <author>Ma, T.</author>
                        <date>2009</date>
                        <title level="a">An image processing portal and web-service for the study of
                            ancient documents</title>
                        <title level="m" type="proceedings">2009 Fifth IEEE International Conference
                        on e-Science</title>
                    <date type="conference">2009</date>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl10">
                        <author>Terras, M.</author>
                        <date>2006</date>
                        <title level="m">Image to Interpretation. An Intelligent System to Aid
                            Historians in Reading the Vindolanda Texts</title>
                        <publisher>Oxford University Press</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace></bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="bibl11">
                        <author>Youtie, H. C.</author>
                        <date>1963</date>
                        <title level="a">The papyrologist: artificer of fact</title>
                        <title level="j">Greek, Roman and Byzantine Studies</title>
                        <biblScope type="issue">4(1)</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">19–33</biblScope></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
