<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<teiCorpus xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-815">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Digital Literacy for the Dumbest Generation - Digital Humanities Programs
                    2010</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Clement, Tanya</name>
                    <affiliation>Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities, <orgName>University of
                        Maryland</orgName>, <country>USA</country></affiliation>
                    <email>tclement@umd.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Jannidis, Fotis</name>
                    <affiliation>Institut für Deutsche Philologie, <orgName>Universität Würzburg</orgName>,
                        <country>Germany</country></affiliation>
                    <email>fotis.jannidis@uni-wuerzburg.de</email>
                </author>
                <author><name>McCarty, Willard</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>King's College London</orgName> <reg><country>UK</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>willard.mccarty@mccarty.org.uk</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-22</date>
                <name>CD</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <TEI>
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title/>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College
                        London</publisher>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <body>
                <p>Marc Baeurlein argues that undergraduates now and undergraduates to come soon are
                    “the least curious and intellectual generation in national history.”<note>Please
                        see <ref target="http://www.dumbestgeneration.com/home.html" type="external"
                            >www.dumbestgeneration.com/home.html</ref>.</note> Dubbing them “the
                    dumbest generation” and “mentally agile” but “culturally ignorant,” Bauerlein
                    decrees that The Web hasn’t made them better writers and readers, sharper
                    interpreters and more discerning critics, more knowledgeable citizens and
                    tasteful consumers” (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl1">Bauerlein, <hi
                            rend="italic">The Dumbest Generation</hi> 110</ref>). The crux of this
                    attack on digital culture lies in the link that Bauerlein and others (“Reading
                    at Risk” xii) make between paper and digital texts: “the relationship,”
                    Bauerlein explains, “between screens and books isn’t benign” (<ref
                        type="internal" cRef="bibl3">“Online Literacy is a Lesser Kind”</ref>). Like
                    Bauerlein and the authors of the NEA report, Sven Birkerts maintains that book
                    readers learn more because the book is a system that “evolved over centuries <hi
                        rend="italic">in ways that map our collective endeavor to understand and
                        express our world</hi>” and that “the electronic book, on the other hand,
                    represents—and furthers—a circuitry of instant access” (<ref type="internal"
                        cRef="bibl4">“Resisting the Kindle”</ref>). In contrast to this perspective,
                    scholars and educators in the digital humanities have spent decades working with
                    digital texts and arguing that advanced knowledge production is the primary
                    function of using computational methodologies in the humanities (<ref
                        type="internal" cRef="bibl6">Busa 1980, 89</ref>; <ref type="internal"
                        cRef="bibl20">Smedt 2002, 90</ref>; <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl14"
                        >McCarty 2005, 13</ref>). </p>
                <p>The three papers in this panel will give an overview on university programs
                    teaching digital humanities in the US, the UK and Germany. The first paper will
                    treat undergraduate programs, the second graduate programs and the third will
                    describe in depth one PhD program. Like others before us (<ref type="internal"
                        cRef="bibl8">McCarty, Orlandi, Terras, Unsworth, “The Humanities Computing
                        Curriculum”</ref>), we are especially interested in comparing these
                    programs, because this allows us to consider a common understanding of the
                    essential aspects of the work in digital humanities. On the other hand we are
                    interested in analyzing the differences and to explore as much as possible the
                    reasons for them. So an analytic charter of the curricula is complemented by a
                    closer look at the institutional affiliations of the programs and the people
                    mainly responsible for them. Undergraduate programs, for example, have to manage
                    the challenge to offer an introduction not only into <hi rend="italic"
                        >digital</hi> humanities but into the humanities in general while graduate
                    programs have to determine what kind of knowledge they demand from the students
                    entering them. Although our overall perspective on these programs is similar,
                    not only the personality of the three authors but also the specific problems of
                    the different forms of programs motivate quite different papers. Thinking about
                    the work that scholars do in the digital humanities from the perspective of the
                    work we need to do to produce culturally literate and critically savvy—that is,
                        <hi rend="italic">intelligent</hi>— students is essential.</p>
            </body>
        </text>
    </TEI>
    <TEI>
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title>An Undergraduate Perspective</title>
                    <author><name>Clement, Tanya</name>
                        <affiliation>Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities, University
                            of Maryland, USA</affiliation>
                        <email>tclement@umd.edu</email></author>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College
                        London</publisher>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <body>
                <p>The scholarship done by the digital humanities community demonstrates that
                    inquiry enabled by modes of research, dissemination, design, preservation, and
                    communication that rely on algorithms, software, and or the internet network for
                    processing data deepen and advance knowledge in the humanities. Marc Baeurlein
                    complains that undergraduates are passive consumers of “information,” that they
                    convert history, philosophy, literature, civics, and fine art into information,”
                    information that becomes, quite simply, “material to retrieve and pass along”
                        (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl3">“Online Literacy”</ref>). In contrast,
                    Wendell Piez and other digital humanities scholars insist that when we study
                    “how digital media are <hi rend="italic">encoded</hi> (being symbolic constructs
                    arranged to work within algorithmic, machine-mediated processes that are
                    themselves a form of cultural production) and how they encode culture in words,
                    colors, sounds, images, and instrumentation,” we are “far from having no more
                    need for literacy;” in fact, the cultural work done by and through digital media
                    requires that students “raise it to ever higher levels.” </p>
                <p>At this time, however, discussion concerning undergraduate pedagogy within the
                    digital humanities community remains limited and scattered. For instance, a
                    search for the word “undergraduate” in the past five years of abstracts from the
                    DH conference (or the joint ACH/ALLC conference) shows that there have been less
                    than five presentations specifically concerning undergraduate pedagogy (Jessop
                    2005; <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl12">Mahony 2008</ref>; <ref type="internal"
                        cRef="bibl11">Keating, <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi> 2009</ref>). This trend
                    may be linked to the notion that an undergraduate curriculum is more about
                    teaching and less about research (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl21">Smedt, <hi
                            rend="italic">et al.</hi> 16</ref>), but this answer is reductive if not
                    partially untrue. At the same time, if we believe that the work digital
                    humanists do “can help us to be more humanistic than before” (Busa 89), why
                    isn’t there more discussion within the DH conference and publications about this
                    essential aspect of undergraduate study?</p>
                <p>This paper will discuss work in place to lay the foundation for further (both in
                    terms of more and deeper) discussion about undergraduate education in the
                    digital humanities. First, this paper will present an updated and annotated
                    bibliography of current undergraduate programs that are inflected by the digital
                    humanities. Though Willard McCarty and Matthew Kirschenbaum’s list of
                    “Institutional models for humanities computing” is extensive, it does not
                    include an updated account of specifically undergraduate programs. That
                    undergraduate studies are not well discussed within the DH community is part and
                    parcel with the fact that it is a field that engages a wide range of
                    disciplinary perspectives and it is a field that is represented by programs of
                    study that are inflected by, but not necessarily called, Digital Humanities.
                    Because this annotated bibliography will be developed as the result of an
                    ongoing discussion with a disperse community, it will reflect a wide range of
                    programs that the community has itself defined as “inflected by digital
                    humanities.” Already, I have created an online list of undergraduate programs
                    generated through an informal survey conducted on <hi rend="italic"
                    >Twitter</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Humanist Discussion List</hi>, and the blog
                        U+2E19.<note>Please see Blog post “Digital Humanities Inflected
                        Undergraduate Programs” at <ref type="external"
                            target="http://www.palms.wordherders.net/wp/2009/11/digital-humanities-inflected-undergraduate-programs-2/"
                            >http://www.palms.wordherders.net/wp/2009/11/digital-humanities-inflected-undergraduate-programs-2/</ref>.</note>
                    To date, the website at King's College London still touts itself as “one of the
                    very few academic institutions in the world where the digital humanities may be
                    pursued as part of a degree” in undergraduate studies—a fact that is largely
                    still true—but there are many programs without formal degrees where important
                    pedagogy concerning digital culture happens. <note>At the time of this writing,
                        Martyn Jessop has written in the <hi rend="italic">Humanist</hi> Discussion
                        Group to clarify: “Sadly the . . . minor at King's College London has been
                        closed down” though they “still operate 'standalone' modules in digital
                        humanities for 1st and 2nd year students” (<ref type="internal"
                            cRef="bibl10">Jessop 2009</ref>). </note></p>
                <p>The fact that the list already includes a broad range of programs encompassing
                    information science, digital cultures, new media, and computer science reflects
                    the difficult nature of training an undergraduate student in the “methodological
                    commons” (McCarty 131) of the digital humanities, but it also reflects the
                    provocative nature of describing what that curriculum might look like. According
                    to Unsworth, “the semantic web is our future, and it will require formal
                    representations of the human record” requiring “training in the humanities, but
                    also in elements of mathematics, logic, engineering, and computer science”
                    (Unsworth). Patrik Svensson sees work in the digital humanities as a kind part
                    of a spectrum “from textual analysis of medieval texts and establishment of
                    metadata schemes to the production of alternative computer games and artistic
                    readings of nanotechnology” (Svensson). Smedt and his colleagues choose to limit
                    their definition of DH undergraduate programs in order “to concentrate on <hi
                        rend="italic">computing</hi> and to avoid the fields of information,
                    communication, media, and multimedia since these are generally considered as
                    social sciences rather than as humanities” (16). Just as asking the question
                    “What is Humanities Computing and what is not?” (Unsworth) generates more
                    questions, asking the community to identify programs inflected by the digital
                    humanities is sure to provoke more discussion concerning existing models. What
                    is important to teach these students? What is the core knowledge base
                    needed?</p>
                <p>When discussing current models, it is equally important to make transparent the
                    institutional and infrastructural issues that are specific to certain
                    universities. What works for one institution will not necessarily work for
                    another. By the same token, simply providing examples of existing programs would
                    belie the extent to which scholars and administrators shape these programs
                    (whether they grant degrees, certificates, or nothing at all) according to the
                    needs of their specific communities. Consequently, in order to make these
                    matters transparent and broaden discussion about the broad range of issues that
                    underpin the formation of an undergraduate curriculum, I will disseminate a
                    survey to the digital humanities community asking basic questions concerning how
                    an undergraduate program inflected by the digital humanities has been and might
                    be developed within a variety of university settings. These questions are based
                    on previous conversations (<ref type="internal" cRef="bibl7">Hockey 2001</ref>;
                        <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl19">Unsworth, Butler 2001</ref>), but this
                    previous work has focused primarily on graduate (or post-graduate) work. In my
                    attempt to update the conversation with a focus on undergraduate study, I
                    incorporate questions that concern curriculum and questions, which point to
                    infrastructural and institutional concerns that are specific to undergraduate
                    education: <xmt:oList rend="arabic">
                        <item>What are the aims and objectives of your undergraduate program?</item>
                        <item> How is the academic content of the program structured? What are the
                            core modules/courses? </item>
                        <item>What are the academic backgrounds of students accepted for the
                            program? Are there any particular requirements?</item>
                        <item>Does the program involve participation in research projects at area
                            institutions or centers? If so, what factors influence which projects
                            are chosen? How is participation monitored and assessed?</item>
                        <item> What is the program’s relationship to the larger undergraduate
                            community? Does the program include events, publications, or other
                            opportunities for outreach? Does the program include a residential
                            component, or other opportunities for community building?</item>
                        <item> Does the program grant a certificate or degree? What are the key
                            issues in establishing a certificate or degree for students in your
                            program?</item>
                        <item>How does the program fit into the overall structure of the
                            institution? </item>
                        <item>Are there classes already being taught at your institution? What are
                            the key issues in bringing these classes together under the rubric of a
                            single curriculum? </item>
                        <item>What technical facilities are needed for the program and how are these
                            supported?</item>
                        <item>What are other important infrastructural issues and challenges in
                            setting up a program within your institution? </item>
                    </xmt:oList>This paper will present and analyze the findings from this survey. </p>
                <p>Finally, this paper will conclude with a case study describing the development of
                    Digital Cultures and Creativity,<note>Please see <ref type="external"
                            target="http://dcc.umd.edu">http://dcc.umd.edu</ref>.</note> an
                    undergraduate living and learning program at the University of Maryland, College
                    Park (UMD) that we have designed for the 21st century student who was born into
                    the world of windows and the web. The result of a partnership between the
                    Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities (MITH) and UMD’s Arts and
                    Humanities College, DCC is part of the university’s new Honors College and will
                    commence in the fall of 2010 with classes run by faculty from the Computer
                    Science Department, the Information School, the Art Department and the English
                    Department. In an effort to make transparent how a program of this nature is
                    developed across disciplines within a large research university, this paper will
                    detail the various stages of development—curricular and administrative—we have
                    navigated during the 2009-2010 planning phase.</p>
                <p>In 2001, Steven Tötösy de Zepetnek observed that because undergraduates began
                    their research online, scholars should create more and better online resources
                    for academic study (Tötösy). A glance just at the last ten years of the journal
                    of <hi rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</hi>, the abstracts from
                    the annual Digital Humanities conference, and the first issues of the <hi
                        rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</hi> prove that the DH community
                    has worked hard to create these resources. Scholars in the digital humanities
                    are already teaching the next generation of students not only how to use
                    electronic resources, but how to create them, expand them, and preserve them.
                    Now is the time to make that work transparent and to provide a resource for
                    others who wish to continue, broaden, and support this work.</p>
            </body>
        </text>
    </TEI>
    <TEI>
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title>Graduate Programs</title>
                    <author><name>Jannidis, Fotis</name>
                        <affiliation>Institut für Deutsche Philologie, Universität Würzburg,
                            Germany</affiliation>
                        <email>fotis.jannidis@uni-wuerzburg.de</email>
                    </author>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College
                        London</publisher>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <body>
                <p>In the last five years new graduate programs for digital humanities have been
                    developed in Germany or are actively developed at the moment in four to five
                    universities. This could be understood as a sign that digital humanities have
                    been accepted as part of a modern university and its spectrum of disciplines. On
                    the other hand it may also point to the fact that in the context of the Bologna
                    process in Europe (i.e. recreating all programs in BA and MA formats to allow
                    students more freedom to change their place of study) Digital Humanities is seen
                    by many people in university administration as uncommon enough to provide the
                    possibility of contributing effectively to the profile of a university. For
                    some, Digital Humanities seems also to contribute a solution to the problem or
                    the tension between the self image of German universities as institutions which
                    are not tasked with providing practical knowledge immediately useful for any
                    profession, on the one hand, and the demands of students and the public in
                    general at least to diminish the gap between the knowledge taught at the
                    university and the demands of professional life outside it. </p>
                <p>This paper will give an overview of these new graduate programs in Digital
                    Humanities in Germany and will compare them to those in the US and the UK. As
                    some programs are in the process of being developed just now, there are no
                    definite results at the moment. The analysis will follow these questions: <xmt:uList>
                        <item>What previous knowledge is required by the programs, especially, in
                            respect to computer science, technical skills and the humanities?</item>
                        <item>How is the knowledge taught by the programs modeled: primarily as
                            practical, as conceptual, as theoretical, and what is the dominant
                            knowledge model for the program: for example computer science, some form
                            of applied science, humanities?</item>
                        <item>How is the program positioned institutionally: What school or
                            department does it and the larger part of its teaching staff belong to?
                            What kind of degree can students earn with the program? Can the program
                            be combined with others and from what kind of department?</item>
                        <item>How concrete or abstract is the program defined? Is there a detailed
                            course description or a syllabus of required texts?</item>
                        <item>What elements of the program can be found in more general humanities,
                            library science or computer science programs?</item>
                    </xmt:uList> There will be a systematic chart comparing the German programs with
                    a selected list of programs in the US and the UK based on the aspects mentioned
                    above and a systematic analysis of earlier research on digital humanities
                    education. But the paper will also include anecdotal evidence on the problems
                    and difficulties of developing and maintaining such a program. </p>
                <p>It will be of special interest to find communalities between all these programs.
                    It is to be expected to find some on the level of practical knowledge like text
                    encoding using XML and TEI, but it is an open question whether more abstract
                    competences like data modeling are shared by all or even most. The same is true
                    for knowledge and expertise usually associated with the humanities: the ability
                    to analyze fictional texts and art, in this case digital texts and digital art. </p>
                <p>It has been pointed out that in the long run the discussion on curricula is
                    probably more important for our conception of digital humanities than the
                    theoretical discussion about the topic or at least it is an important
                    contribution to the discussion (cf. <ref type="internal" cRef="bibl23"
                        >Terras</ref>). This paper also understands each curriculum as a statement
                    in this discussion, a statement not only directed at the digital humanities
                    community but also towards the humanities. This statement delineates what kind
                    of knowledge about the digital is taken for granted as part of the humanities
                    and what is (still?) marked as special knowledge not shared by most humanities
                    scholars. This borderline is also under discussion and an analysis of what kind
                    of modules and courses are taught by the staff mainly engaged in the digital
                    humanities program can show what point these negotiations have reached. </p>
                <p>At last some questions will be discussed which cannot be answered based on the
                    information available now: For example, what kind of professional profile will
                    students with degrees in those programs have? Will digital humanities as a
                    discipline recruit its academic teachers in future from these new programs? Even
                    if the answers cannot be given at the moment, maybe the discussion can
                    contribute to the reflection on question of what a successful graduate program
                    in the digital humanities would look like.</p>
            </body>
        </text>
    </TEI>
    <TEI>
        <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title>PhD in Digital Humanities, King's College London</title>
                    <author><name>McCarty, Willard</name>
                        <affiliation>King's College London</affiliation>
                        <email>willard.mccarty@mccarty.org.uk</email>
                    </author>
                </titleStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College
                        London</publisher>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
                </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
        <text>
            <body>
                <div>
                    <head>The PhD in the UK and at King's</head>
                    <p>In the United Kingdom the PhD (DPhil at Oxford) is normally a 3-4 year,
                        research-only degree (6-8 years part-time). No course-work or qualifying
                        examinations are required. At King’s College London the candidate enters
                        officially into an MPhil; after 9 months to a year he or she then applies
                        for an upgrade to PhD. To gain this upgrade the candidate must demonstrate
                        that he or she is producing work to the standards of a PhD. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The PhD in Digital Humanities at King's</head>
                    <p>The Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King’s College London, has
                        offered the PhD in Digital Humanities since 2005. Its first student dropped
                        out after approximately a year, but since then the programme has taken on a
                        further ten. Its first graduate will likely take his degree in Autumn 2010.
                        All of the students have come to the PhD from other institutions, 3 from the
                        U.K., 5 from elsewhere in the European Union, 1 from Norway and 1 from the
                        United States. Of the total 3 are enrolled part-time, the remainder
                        full-time. None has had prior degree-training in the subject. Currently 3
                        others are in process of developing their research proposals before
                        applying. Since the programme was created there have been in addition 41
                        serious enquiries, likely at least a dozen of which would have proceeded to
                        enrolment had adequate funding been available. </p>
                    <p>Apart from two studentships, one from the School of Humanities in 2006 and
                        another from the Arts and Humanities Research Council in 2009, the programme
                        has had no funding. Teaching assistantships are not available, but the
                        department has begun to offer limited part-time research positions for work
                        on collaborative projects. Lack of funding remains the most serious
                        impediment to growth of the programme. No serious efforts have yet been made
                        to advertise it. </p>
                    <p>The primary criterion for admission to the PhD in Digital Humanities is a
                        cogent research proposal supported by letters of recommendation. Usually the
                        applicant develops this proposal in consultation with the departmental
                        Director of Research (Professor McCarty). Proposals of sufficient quality
                        are accepted providing that the department, possibly in collaboration with
                        one or more other departments, can support the research adequately. In a
                        majority of cases to date (7 out of 10) supervision is cross-departmental: 3
                        with History, 1 with German, 1 with Portuguese, 1 with Computer Science, 1
                        with the Department of Education and Professional Studies, School of Social
                        Science and Public Policy. Of these 2 are associated also with the King’s
                        cross-school Centre for Language, Discourse and Communication. Usually the
                        balance of supervision is equally divided between the CCH and the other
                        department but can vary from 70% to 30%. </p>
                    <p>Of the current students, 8 out of 10 have come to the programme directly
                        rather than on referral from other departments. In other words, the PhD in
                        Digital Humanities is the primary attractor for those wishing to involve
                        computing as a major component in their research. </p>
                    <p>From 2009 students for whom living in London would pose a significant
                        hardship can with approval pursue a “semi-distance PhD”, with face-to-face
                        supervisory meetings according to an agreed schedule and meetings by Skype
                        as needed. Two students now take advantage of this arrangement, one
                        full-time, one part-time. </p>
                    <p>Apart from individual supervision, all students in the programme meet in the
                        monthly PhD Seminar, face-to-face or via the Internet, to present and
                        discuss their work. Some meetings are partly devoted to special topics of
                        interest to all. The PhD Seminar also includes students at the University of
                        Alberta and, in a special credit-course, students at the University of
                        Victoria, British Columbia, in real-time via Skype and Dimdim. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Development of the PhD in Digital Humanities</head>
                    <p>The PhD in Digital Humanities has been shaped primarily by the interests of
                        applicants rather than by a pre-conceived notion of what a doctoral degree
                        in the field should be. Technical competence at a level appropriate to
                        computer science or information science has not been assumed or required,
                        although critical thought on computing has been stressed from the beginning
                        through development of research proposals and required subsequently.
                        Practical work is strongly encouraged though it has not been required. A
                        central chapter on the relevant computing methods has become the norm, with
                        a thorough knowledge of the secondary literature attested in a survey or in
                        the citations. In a few cases students have needed and been given technical
                        support from within the department to develop an application of computing.
                        In equally many cases, however, students have come with a high level of
                        technical knowledge and skills. In two cases arrangements are being made to
                        provide specialised training, and in one the student separately obtained an
                        18-month paid fellowship to work abroad in a technical research institution
                        (some of this work with engineers to design and construct relevant
                        hardware). In brief, highest priority has been given to critical reasoning
                        with and about computing in a manner consistent with the interpretative,
                        problematizing disciplines of the humanities. </p>
                    <p>In all cases the subject of the research has been a problem within or
                        recognizable to one or more of these disciplines. We have assumed that those
                        who wish to practice computer science on material usually studied in the
                        humanities are altogether better served by that discipline, although we are
                        open to requests for collaborative supervision originating in computer
                        science. In general no decision has been made a priori to restrict primary
                        areas of investigation to the humanities. Students from elsewhere are most
                        welcome to apply, especially since they may well assist us in extending an
                        already broad church. </p>
                </div>
            </body>
            <back>
                <div>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl1"><author>Bauerlein, Mark</author>
                            <title level="m">The Dumbest Generation: How the Digital Age Stupefies
                                Young Americans and Jeopardizes Our Future (or, Don't Trust Anyone
                                Under 30)</title><date>2008</date>
                            <pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Jeremy P. Tarcher/Penguin</publisher>
                            <edition>Print</edition></bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl2">
                            <author>Bauerlein, Mark</author>
                            <title level="a">Introduction</title>
                            <title level="m">The Dumbest Generation</title>
                            <edition>Web</edition>
                            <date type="otehr">11 Nov 2009</date></bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl3">
                            <author>Bauerlein, Mark</author>
                            <title level="a">Online Literacy Is a Lesser Kind</title>
                            <title level="j">The Chronicle of Higher Education</title>
                            <date type="other">19 September 2008</date>
                            <edition>Web</edition>
                            <date type="visited">11 Nov 2009</date>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl4"><author>Birkerts, Sven</author>
                            <title level="a">Resisting the Kindle</title>
                            <title level="j">Atlantic Monthly</title>
                            <date type="other">2 March 2009</date>
                            <edition>Web</edition>
                            <date type="visited">15 Nov 2009</date></bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl5"><author>Burnard, Lou</author><title level="m"> Is
                                Humanities Computing an Academic Discipline? or, Why Humanities
                                Computing Matters</title>
                            <date>1999</date>
                            <edition>Web</edition>
                            <date type="visited">11 Nov 2009</date></bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl6"><author>Busa, Roberto</author>
                            <title level="a">The Annals of Humanities Computing: The Index
                                Thomisticus</title>
                            <title level="j">Computers and the Humanities</title>
                            <biblScope type="issue">14</biblScope>
                            <date>1980</date>
                            <biblScope type="pp">83-90</biblScope>
                            <edition>Print</edition></bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl7">
                            <author>Hockey, Susan</author>
                            <title level="m">MA Programmes for Humanities Computing and Digital
                                Media</title>
                            <date>2001</date>
                            <publisher>New York University</publisher>
                            <edition>Web</edition>
                            <date type="visited">11 Nov 2009</date></bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl8"><title level="m" type="proceedings">The Humanities
                                Computing Curriculum: The Computing Curriculum in the Arts and
                                Humanities</title>
                            <name type="venue">Malaspina University College, Nanaimo, British
                                Columbia, Canada</name>
                            <date type="conference">November 9-10, 2001</date>
                            <edition>Web</edition><date type="visited">15 Nov 2009</date></bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl9"><author>Jessop, Martyn</author><title level="a">In
                                Search of Humanities Computing in Teaching, Learning and
                                Research.</title>
                            <title level="m" type="proceedings">The International Conference on
                                Humanities Computing and Digital Scholarship, The 17th Joint
                                International Conference: Conference Abstracts (2<hi rend="italic"
                                    >nd</hi> Edition)</title>
                            <biblScope type="pp">91-93</biblScope>
                            <edition>Web</edition>
                            <date type="visited">15 Nov 2009</date></bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl10">
                            <title level="a">undergrad programmes</title>
                            <title level="m">Humanist Discussion Group</title>
                            <date type="other">27 Oct 2009</date>
                            <edition>Web</edition>
                            <date type="visited">11 Nov 2009</date>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl11"><author>Keating, John J.</author>
                            <author>Teehan, Aja</author>
                            <author>Byrne, Thomas</author>
                            <date>2009</date>
                            <title level="a">Delivering a Humanities Computing Module at
                                Undergraduate Level: A Case Study</title>
                            <title level="m"> Digital Humanities 2009 Conference Abstracts</title>
                            <biblScope type="pp">167-169</biblScope>
                            <edition>Web</edition>
                            <date type="visited">15 Nov 2009</date></bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl12">
                            <author>Mahony, Simon</author>
                            <title level="a">An Interdisciplinary Perspective on Building Learning
                                Communities Within the Digital Humanities</title>
                            <date>2008</date>
                            <title level="m">Digital Humanities 2008 Conference Abstracts</title>
                            <biblScope type="pp">149-151</biblScope>
                            <edition>Web</edition>
                            <date type="visited">15 Nov 2009</date></bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl13"><author>Mangen, Anne</author>
                            <title level="a">Hypertext Fiction Reading: Haptics and
                                Immersion</title>
                            <title level="j">Journal of Research in Reading</title>
                            <date type="other">31.4.2008</date>
                            <edition>Print</edition></bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl14"><author>McCarty, Willard</author>
                            <title level="a">New Splashings In The Old Pond: The Cohesibility Of
                                Humanities Computing</title>
                            <title level="j">The Alliance of Digital Humanities
                                Organizations</title><date type="other">16 October 2002</date>
                            <date type="visited">15 Nov 2009</date>
                            <edition>Web</edition>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl15"><author>McCarty, Willard</author>
                            <author>Kirschenbaum, Matthew</author>
                            <title level="a">Institutional models for humanities computing</title>
                            <date type="other">12 Dec 2003</date>
                            <edition>Web</edition>
                            <date type="visited">15 Nov 2009</date></bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl16"><editor>Nowviskie, B.</editor>
                            <editor>Unsworth, J.</editor>
                            <title level="m" type="proceedings">Is humanities computing an academic
                                discipline? An interdisciplinary seminar</title>
                            <date>1999</date>
                            <name type="venue">University of Virginia</name>
                            <date type="conference">Autumn 1999</date>
                            <edition>Print</edition></bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl17"><author>Piez, Wendell</author>
                            <title level="a">Something Called "Digital Humanities"</title>
                            <title level="j">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>
                            <date>2008</date>
                            <biblScope type="issue">2.1</biblScope>
                            <edition>Web</edition>
                            <date type="visited">11 Nov 2009</date>
                        </bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl18"><author>Orlandi, Tito</author>
                            <title level="a">Is Humanities Computing a Discipline?</title>
                            <date type="other">17 May 2002</date>
                            <title level="j">The Alliance of Digital Humanities
                                Organizations</title>
                            <edition>Web</edition>
                            <date type="visited">11 Nov 2009</date></bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl19"><author>Unsworth, J.</author>
                            <author>Butler, T.</author>
                            <title level="a">A Masters Degree in Digital Humanities at the
                                University of Virginia</title>
                            <date>2001</date>
                            <title level="m" type="proceedings">Session, ACH-ALLC 2001</title>
                            <name type="venue">New York University</name>
                            <date type="conference">June 13-16, 2001</date>
                            <edition>Web</edition>
                            <date type="conference">11 Nov 2009</date></bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl20"><author>de Smedt, Koenraad</author>
                            <title level="a">Some Reflections on Studies in Humanities
                                Computing</title>
                            <date>2001</date>
                            <title level="j">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>
                            <biblScope type="issue">17.1</biblScope>
                            <biblScope type="pp">89-101</biblScope>
                            <edition>Print</edition></bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl21"><editor>Smedt, Konrad</editor>
                            <editor>Gardiner, Hazel</editor>
                            <editor>Ore, Espen</editor>
                            <editor>Orlandi, Tito</editor>, <editor>Short, Harold</editor>
                            <editor>Souilliot, Jacques</editor>
                            <editor>Vaughan, William</editor><date>1999</date>
                            <title level="m">Computing in Humanities Education: A European
                                Perspective</title>
                            <pubPlace>Bergen</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>University of Bergen</publisher>
                            <edition>Print</edition></bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl22"><author>Svensson, Patrik</author>
                            <title level="a">Humanities Computing as Digital Humanities</title>
                            <title level="j">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>
                            <date>2009</date>
                            <biblScope type="issue">3.3</biblScope>
                            <edition>Web</edition>
                            <biblScope type="visited">11 Nov 2009</biblScope></bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl23"><author>Terras, Melissa</author>
                            <title level="a">Disciplined: Using Curriculum Studies to Define
                                'Humanities Computing</title>
                            <title level="m">Abstracts ACH/ALLC 2005</title>
                            <date>2005</date>
                            <edition>Web</edition><date type="visited">15 Nov 2009</date></bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl24"><author>Tötösy de Zepetnek, Steven</author>
                            <title level="a">The New Knowledge Management and Online Research and
                                Publishing in the Humanities</title>
                            <title level="j">CLCWeb: Comparative Literature and Culture</title>
                            <date>2001</date>
                            <biblScope type="issue">3.1</biblScope>
                            <edition>Print</edition></bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="bibl25"><author>Unsworth, John</author>
                            <title level="a">What is Humanities Computing and What is not?</title>
                            <title level="j">The Alliance of Digital Humanities
                                Organizations</title>
                            <date>2002</date>
                            <edition>Web</edition>
                            <date type="visited">11 Nov 2009</date>
                        </bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
            </back>
        </text>
    </TEI>
</teiCorpus>
