<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-817">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>A Data Model for Digital Musicology and its Current State – The Music
                    Encoding Initiative</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Kepper, Johannes</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>University of Paderborn</orgName> <reg><country>Germany</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>kepper@edirom.de</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-04-27</date>
                <name>AC</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <p>During the last 10 years, XML has gained general acceptance as a data model in the
                Digital Humanities. Actually, it even leveraged the success of digital projects in
                the humanities. Meanwhile TEI is the unchallenged standard for all projects in the
                fields of literature studies, epigraphy, linguistics, history sciences and so on.
                Many thoughts were invested to bring TEI and other related formats like EpiDoc to a
                level that suffices general scholarly needs.</p>
            <p>At first sight, things went differently in the field of music encoding. Around the
                year 2000 a couple of XML-based encoding schemes for music notation emerged, and
                within just a few years MusicXML became the best-known and most widespread music
                encoding format. It was intended to serve as an interchange format between different
                music applications, and even today it is virtually indispensable for this very
                important task. At the same time, this orientation of MusicXML requires a certain
                "simplicity" that facilitates implementations in various applications.</p>
            <p>The Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) went a different way. Not aiming at application
                support in the first place, an encoding model for <hi rend="italic">scholarly</hi>
                purposes was developed over years. Strongly influenced by the concepts of the TEI,
                Perry Roland as initiator of the format tried to transfer these concepts to the
                field of music encoding. For large parts, this is quite easy: music notation is a
                kind of text, and many unspecific modules of TEI can be reused for music encoding
                with only small changes. But then again, music notation itself offers a much higher
                complexity than other texts. It is multi-dimensional not only because of its layout
                of multiple vertically aligned staves, but also because of its simultaneity of
                harmonic and melodic progression. In music notation, the text itself consists of
                overlapping hierarchies and therefore demands a quite sophisticated data model. Most
                often, it is virtually impossible to preserve all possible meanings (or better:
                interpretations) of a musical text with reasonable effort. The reason is that the
                written text is only a part of the complete information. Every notation serves a
                certain purpose, and each composer or copyist uses only as many symbols as he needs
                to be explicit to his contemporaries. Besides this, the "rules" of music notation
                changed significantly over time, even though these developments often seem to be
                very subtle.</p>
            <p>All this leads to the problem that there is no absolutely fixed terminology in music
                notation. Some phenomena are still not completely understood or even defined, such
                as the problem of dots, strokes and hooks in scores from the classical period. The
                lack of a complete and well-defined terminology even for restricted repertoires
                makes the encoding of music notation on a scholarly level highly demanding, and, at
                the same time, the implementation and usage of such an encoding scheme is anything
                but trivial.</p>
            <p>The Music Encoding Initiative has chosen this way, and currently it stands on an
                important turning point: In a one-year project funded by the NEH and DFG the
                original model was revised and has proven to meet all essential scholarly
                requirements for such a format. In the next years, it needs to be disseminated in
                the fields of musicology, music information retrieval, music philology and digital
                humanities in general. A first step in this direction is the TEI's Special Interest
                Group on music encoding, whose members were actively involved in the recent
                developments on MEI, and who seek to find ways to bring MEI and TEI closer
                together.</p>
            <p>Due to the complexity of music notation – and thus music notation encoding too –
                application support for MEI is crucial to ensure its dissemination: Almost no
                traditional musicologist would be willing to work with a XML-editor like Oxygen.
                There are several projects currently working on such applications for MEI: The
                DiMusEd-Project, situated in Tübingen (Germany), uses SVG to render encodings of
                multiple sources of music notated with medieval neumes. Although this repertoire
                uses a limited set of symbols, this project already shows the benefits of a dynamic
                rendering from an encoding instead of engraved scores. The Edirom project, (Detmold,
                Germany) aims to establish workflows for digital scholarly editions of music. In the
                application for preparing such editions it is already using MEI to store all
                structural information about the musical text as well as the containing documents.
                For moving from basically facsimile-based editions to completely digital editions it
                is planned to offer complete encodings of all relevant sources including the
                rendering-facilities already demonstrated by the DiMusEd-project. In order to
                achieve this goal Edirom closely collaborates with the most ambitious of all ongoing
                MEI-related projects: TextGrid. A sub-project of this major German initiative, which
                is also located in Detmold, seeks to develop a limited scorewriter for MEI offering
                a graphical user interface for musicologists. In this case „limited“ means that the
                project neither intends to support MEI completely nor tries to keep up with the
                engraving quality of already existing scorewriters: the unambiguity of the output is
                more important than its beauty.</p>
            <p>All these German projects collaborate closely with the ongoing efforts in the US to
                further improve the format itself and to provide interchange to other relevant
                formats such as Humdrum and MusicXML. Depending on further funding by NEH and DFG
                respectively it is intended to provide reasonable collections of MEI encodings to
                facilitate further usage of the format. Although MEI will not find the wide
                acceptance MusicXML already has, all these components will help to disseminate MEI
                in the academic world, to promote interchange of high-quality data and to explore
                new methods for digital representations of written music.</p>
            <p>The talk will provide a short introduction to the current state of MEI – both the
                format itself and the projects and applications already working on and with it.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
