<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../schema/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
    xml:id="ab-876">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Xiakou: A Case Study in Digital Ethnography</title>
                <author>
                    <name>Flower, John</name>
                    <affiliation><orgName>Sidwell School</orgName>, Washington, D.C <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>FlowerJ@sidwell.edu</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Leonard, Pamela</name>
                    <affiliation>Independent Scholar</affiliation>
                    <email>pamleonard@hughes.net</email>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>Martin, Worthy</name>
                    <affiliation> Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities, <orgName>University of
                        Virginia</orgName> <reg><country>USA</country></reg></affiliation>
                    <email>wnm@cs.virginia.edu</email>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2010-05-01</date>
                <name>NG</name>
                <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="paper">
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>This story begins in a small Sichuan village over fifteen years ago as a
                    historian (John Flower) and an anthropologist (Pamela Leonard) began their study
                    of the cultural landscape of a contemporary Chinese village. The story evolves
                    as they strive to pioneer <hi rend="italic">digital ethnography</hi> and later,
                    in collaboration with The Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities
                    (IATH), build interactive presentation of focused, long-term fieldwork research
                    results in the form of an online monograph, media archive, and information
                    repository, entitled <hi rend="italic">Moral Landscape in a Sichuan Mountain
                        Village: A Digital Ethnography of Place</hi>.</p>
                <p>The original and ongoing field study explores the histories, beliefs,
                    livelihoods, and local identities in Xiakou Village, located in the mountains of
                    Ya'an County, in western Sichuan Province of the People's Republic of China. The
                    goal of the project is to understand Xiakou Village as an evolving <hi
                        rend="italic">cultural landscape</hi>, defined as the interwoven field of
                    physical environment, historical memory, and moral agency, in which particular
                    places gather a people’s sense of themselves and serve as sources of belonging
                    and identity. This understanding attempts to establish a basis to consider
                    questions such as: What does it mean to belong in a place? How do people
                    understand who they are in terms of where they live? What is the relationship
                    between history and place? How do memory and landscape inform the ways in which
                    people define their communities?</p>
                <p>The ethnography uses the new possibilities of digital technology to create
                    interleaving essays, primary source multimedia artifacts, and GIS maps. The
                    purpose of this digital form is to render more transparent the relationship
                    between source and interpretation, to open up non-linear narrative paths through
                    the ethnography, and therefore to more vividly reveal the interconnections among
                    different dimensions of village life that are the core content of the project.
                    Indeed, we revisit the village study model to highlight the overlapping fields
                    of interaction that link the village to broader regional, national, and even
                    transnational identities.</p>
                <p>Another fundamental aim of the project is to reframe modern Chinese history away
                    from the big narrative of the nation and toward local stories of the grassroots.
                    How do the villagers of Xiakou understand their history? What memories and
                    meanings from the past still animate their place, and how are they remembered
                    and explained?</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Moral Landscape in a Sichuan Mountain Village</hi> is
                    multidisciplinary, using the perspectives of history, anthropology, economics,
                    folklore, and religion to try to understand the interconnected facets of life
                    expressed in the village landscape. The common thread running through the
                    ethnography is the idea that the landscape holds moral values. When people in
                    Xiakou talked about place and history they were talking about what was good and
                    bad, right and wrong.</p>
                <p>We understand digital ethnography to be an online interactive monograph with
                    integrated archive and database. This digital format of the ethnography evokes
                    an understanding of place through interactive essays that localize the broad
                    trends of China's modern history in the lived experiences of Xiakou's villagers.
                    The interactive essays are the project’s main narrative tissue, interconnected
                    by a searchable archive of digital artifacts. These artifacts consist of
                    multimedia information—photographs, scanned documents, audio and video
                    recordings, GIS maps—contextualized in a thick setting of related metadata, and
                    shared across essays. The project’s digital format is essential for realizing
                    the rich potential of the ethnographic and historical content of the research: a
                    central database and interconnected xml content enable the transparency,
                    connectivity, and interactivity that comprise the key innovative characteristics
                    of this form of narrative. Transparency means that the ethnography will reveal
                    not simply &quot;what we know&quot; but also &quot;how we know it,&quot; by
                    providing the reader access to primary source materials in the database. The
                    architecture of the interactive interface will also use the database to
                    encourage connections across thematic categories, making it possible for the
                    reader to explore alternatives to a set, linear narrative. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Ways of belonging: new village studies and mapping the cultural
                    landscape</head>
                <p>What is a village in China? A wide range of scholarship has addressed this
                    central question, from the perspectives of regional systems analysis (Skinner
                    1964) to cultural landscape studies (Knapp 1992, Feuchtwang 1997). Our approach
                    tries to give priority to villagers' conscious representations, analyses, and
                    understandings of their relationship to &quot;their place&quot;. The resulting
                    geographical scope goes beyond the village itself to encompass the communities
                    along the North Road and, under some conditions, extends to include the broader
                    eight county Ya’an region.</p>
                <p>In <hi rend="italic">Moral Landscape in a Sichuan Mountain Village</hi> we
                    advocate a return to the ethnographic tradition of village studies, but using
                    new tools of the digital humanities that emphasize the ways in which place is
                    not simply a fixed and unchanging location, but rather a nexus of evolving
                    relationships and historical connections to other places. Thus, one of our goals
                    is to highlight the multiple, overlapping fields of interaction that link the
                    village to broader regional, national, and even transnational identities.</p>
                <p>We see our project as complementary to the much larger and comprehensive
                    initiatives that aim to create complete datasets, such as the China historical
                    GIS project (Bol 2006). In contrast, our project does not attempt to be
                    comprehensive, but rather celebrates the particularity of place. We hope that
                    our qualitative interpretation of landscape will provide the kind of unique
                    local portrait of place from which comprehensive projects can create a more
                    vivid broad tableau of China as whole.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Beyond Revolution: an inductive approach to local history</head>
                <p>Another fundamental goal of our project’s landscape approach is to reframe modern
                    Chinese history away from the master narrative of the nation and toward local
                    stories of the grassroots (Duara, Prazniak). How do the villagers of Xiakou
                    understand their history? What memories and meanings from the past still animate
                    their place, and how are they remembered and explained? How does that local
                    understanding of history reiterate or differ from historical narratives based on
                    the nation-state, China, as subject? While there are excellent village-based
                    histories (e.g. Chan, Madsen, Unger 1992; Selden, Friedman, Pickowicz 1991) that
                    focus on the local impact of national events, particularly the Chinese
                    revolution, in <hi rend="italic">Moral Landscape in a Sichuan Mountain
                        Village</hi> we try to adopt a more localized, inductive approach. The
                    historical scope of our project thus largely corresponds to the way villagers
                    mark the turning points in their past, based on their personal experiences in
                    local places and marking events that fall within their horizon of memory.</p>
                <p>Methodologically, we understand that the essays and artifacts represent <hi
                        rend="italic">our synthesis</hi> of a dialogue with local villagers and with
                    local historical source-materials on the topic of social and environmental
                    change. In confronting the subjective reality of fieldwork and analysis,
                    anthropologists have emphasized the need to be transparent in presenting the
                    politics of the research encounter. We believe digital technology allows us to
                    go further in meeting this aim. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>History, environment, and agency in the moral landscape</head>
                <p>In trying to understand the significance of the environmental changes that have
                    taken place in this valley, we frame issues of environment and economic
                    development within local cultural practices and historical knowledge. How do
                    local people draw on their historical understanding of place in adapting to
                    economic development policies introduced from outside? How do those development
                    policies in turn influence their livelihoods, and change their understanding of
                    the landscape?</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Structure, content, and logic of the digital ethnography</head>
                <p>The structure of the ethnography’s online monograph comprises eight chapters:
                    History, Landscape, Belief, Folklife, Authority, Work, Gazetteer, and Biography.
                    Chapters are not airtight divisions, but rather groupings that highlight the
                    dominant themes of the essays within them. There are three main types of content
                    within this chapter structure:<hi rend="italic"> essays, interactive maps</hi>,
                    and <hi rend="italic">artifacts</hi>. Essays are the basic interpretive building
                    blocks of the ethnography and are accessed through the chapters. The interactive
                    maps under the Gazetteer chapter will offer spatial representations of sites in
                    the cultural landscape, dynamically presented through GIS layers, sorted by kind
                    and historical period.</p>
                <p>Both the maps and essays are illustrated and documented by &quot;artifacts&quot;,
                    i.e., foci of evidence that link to multimedia content—photographs, video and
                    audio recordings, image maps, diagrams, supplemental texts, primary source
                    documents, and field notes. The artifact frames this multimedia content within
                    supplementary metadata and highlights thematic overlaps and interconnections
                    within the ethnography.</p>
                <p>The essay/artifact structure allows us to experiment with different approaches to
                    conceptualizing and presenting the ethnographic research. These
                    artifact-centered essays are intentional inversions of the more familiar
                    text-driven narrative presentation, and they point the way to readers who want
                    to engage the ethnography more interactively. To enable that level of
                    engagement, our goal is to code each artifact and each essay subsection with
                    selections from a finite set of keywords, making the whole site fully searchable
                    through the site’s integrated information structures. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Proposed Presentation</head>
                <p>We will discuss the information structures in which the base materials are
                    created and maintained. Then we discuss the interactive interface through which
                    those materials are accessed by scholars and the general public. Finally, we
                    will justify our claim that these techniques embody the methodologies expressed
                    above.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
