<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">A Project Demonstration of `Peripeteia': CAI Software
                    for Teaching Literary and Rhetorical Terms</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Anthony</forename>
                        <surname>Flinn</surname>
                        <affiliation> Department of English, <name type="org">Eastern Washington
                                University</name>
                            <email>aflinn@ewu.edu </email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Bergen</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bergen, Norway</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 1996</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Anne</forename>
                        <surname>Lindebjerg</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Espen</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                        <surname>Ore</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Øystein</forename>
                        <surname>Reigem</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>literature</item>
                        <item>rhetoric</item>
                        <item>terminology</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>My CAI software, called "Peripeteia," is an interactive database of literary and
                    rhetorical terms, their definitions, and sample text passages that exemplify
                    them. I've designed this software as a supplementary learning tool for the
                    literary studies and rhetoric programs in the EWU English department. This
                    software can be useful for virtually all literature and rhetoric students, from
                    the freshman to the graduate level. Faculty, too, can use it for quick reference
                    as well as course preparation.</p>
                <p>Central to the program's design is its pedagogical flexibility. Peripeteia
                    provides a multitude of access points, thereby addressing a range of learning
                    styles, levels of sophistication, and information requirements at the time of
                    access. This flexibility allows students a multitude of opportunities to think
                    inductively and deductively, moving from a series of examples to the literary or
                    rhetorical concept, or, conversely, moving from the concept to examples, if
                    desired.</p>
                <p>Students can run Peripeteia in three learning modes: quick reference, deductive
                    learning / testing, and inductive learning / testing. In each mode the software
                    displays iconic representations of the literary and rhetorical terms. These
                    icons serve primarily as mnemonic devices, but their designs also help clarify
                    the concepts for visual learners, who are typically exposed to terminology only
                    in verbal descriptions.</p>
                <p>Peripeteia is a highly interactive program, for each of the three modes requires
                    and responds to student actions. In the quick reference mode, students can
                    choose from among categories of terminology to terms within a particular
                    category to particular sample passages for each term. They can also display the
                    source of a currently displayed passage. In the deductive learning mode, in
                    which students must match terms to randomly displayed sample passages, they can
                    elect to skip particular terms and return to them later. Peripeteia permits two
                    attempts per term, and each attempt displays feedback that assesses the attempt,
                    prompts the next action, and, as necessary, provides hints. In the inductive
                    learning mode, students first select from a palette of icons the one
                    representing the concept suggested by the currently displayed set of sample
                    passages. After as many as two attempts, after which feedback alerts them to
                    their success or failure and identifies the correct term, students are then
                    prompted to type in their own definition for that term.</p>
                <p>Peripeteia's reporting and record keeping functions allow both the students and
                    their professors to monitor their progress. When students log in, they type
                    their name, social security number, and the class or classes in which they are
                    currently enrolled. A text file is then automatically created for each student
                    user. Each file is updated as the student proceeds through the two learning /
                    testing modes, recording the student's answers and success rate. In addition,
                    the student's attempted definitions in the deductive learning mode are
                    automatically added to his or her text file, along with the Peripeteia's
                    "correct" definitions for comparison and evaluation purposes.</p>
                <p>In its current design, Peripeteia functions by reading in the terms, definitions,
                    and samples from a text file and the iconic representations from a graphics
                    library file. Because the software is thus distinct from the database it draws
                    upon, Peripeteia can be adapted to serve virtually any other subject area
                    freighted with a range of discipline-specific terms or concepts.</p>
                <p>Peripeteia runs most effectively on a Macintosh Quadra or Power PC. It requires
                    at least a 13-inch screen and eight megabytes of RAM.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
