<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main"><emph rend="italics">Palimpsest</emph> for Windows: A
                    Tool for Computer Assisted Literary Translation Studies </title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jan-Mirko</forename>
                        <surname>Maczewski</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Göttingen</name>
                            <email>jan-mirko_maczewski@public.uni-hamburg.de </email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Bergen</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Bergen, Norway</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 1996</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Anne</forename>
                        <surname>Lindebjerg</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Espen</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">S.</forename>
                        <surname>Ore</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Øystein</forename>
                        <surname>Reigem</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>literary translation</item>
                        <item>literary and linguistic computing</item>
                        <item>corpus linguistics</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Abstract</head>
                <p>The <title level="m">Palimpsest</title> poster presentation is meant to
                    supplement the theoretical discussion provided by the session on Computer
                    Assisted Literary Translation Studies (CoALiTS). A first example of a Windows
                    application realizing aspects of the theoretical investigation presented in the
                    session, the presentation offers the opportunity to try out the latest version
                    of the <title level="m">Palimpsest</title> software and to discuss practical and
                    theoretical issues on the background of this "hands-on" experience.</p>
                <p>Drawing on established models and methods of comparative literary and linguistic
                    studies and fusing them with computer scientific resources, <title level="m"
                        >Palimpsest</title> has interdisciplinary discourse at its heart and
                    explores new technical as well as literary issues: the recursive process of
                    software design for literary purposes and the re-formulation of these purposes,
                    leading to a re-writing of the software, is expected to grant new insights into
                    theoretical and practical issues of multilingual text processing that are of
                    interest beyond literary translation as such.</p>
                <p>A decidedly experimental and open application, <title level="m"
                        >Palimpsest</title> currently divides into two parts: the pre-processors for
                    the creation of word- and phrase-based tables, and the main application with the
                        <title level="m">Palimpsest</title> Viewer and the statistics and
                    concordancing facilities. The presented version recurs to an already
                    pre-processed corpus of six texts, the first italicized passage of Virginia
                    Woolf's <title level="m">The Waves</title> and its three German and two French
                    translations. </p>
                <p>The central feature the <title level="m">Palimpsest</title> Viewer offers is the
                    multilinear display of the source text (ST) and its various destination texts
                    (DTs), based on the unit of the phrase as discussed in the session. The Viewer
                    offers to browse phrase by phrase through any of the texts, and to access a
                    specific phrase directly by searching for a particular word or lemma it
                    contains. Via an "Align" button, all other texts can be aligned to the selected
                    phrase. Apart from this, the Viewer screen offers a display of the existing
                    links between ST and DT which can be edited by a mouse click.</p>
                <p>Accessible via a pull-down menu, the statistical routines produce dBase tables
                    containing the word- or phrase-based, sentence or not-sentence-aligned output.
                    These files trace the interrelation of the texts by means of measuring the
                    relation of the word- or phrase-order of one text to the others, giving either
                    the accumulative effect in the not-sentence-aligned data or the sentence-aligned
                    results.</p>
                <p>Also activated via a pull-down menu, the concordancing routines produce a dBase
                    table containing a word- or phrase-based concordance relating the respective
                    units of the currently selected text to all others.</p>
                <p>Looking towards future developments, the as yet star-like organization linking
                    all DTs to the ST, but not to one another, will surely undergo reconsideration,
                    and the conversational form of the presentation during the ACH-ALLC conference
                    seems particularly appropriate to discuss such matters in interdisciplinary
                    conversation; also, the yet quite time-consuming task of manual pre-processing
                    might be eased significantly by co-operation with tagging projects which, in
                    return, could profit from some of the data a <title level="m">Palimpsest</title>
                    tagged multilingual corpus offers.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
