<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="panel">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">ALLC Special Session: Humanities Computing in the
                    Graduate Curriculum</title>
                <author>Chair: <name>
                        <forename type="first">Susan</forename>
                        <surname>Hockey</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Alberta</name> (ALLC Chair) <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>Speakers: <name>
                        <forename type="first">Harold</forename>
                        <surname>Short</surname>
                    </name><affiliation><name type="org">Kings College</name>,
                        London<email/></affiliation></author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Espen</forename>
                        <surname>Ore</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <name type="org">Norwegian Computing Centre for the Humanities</name>
                        <email/>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Willard</forename>
                        <surname>McCarty</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation><name type="org">King's College</name>,
                        London<email/></affiliation>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Geoffrey</forename>
                        <surname>Rockwell</surname>
                    </name>
                    <affiliation>
                        <name type="org">McMaster University</name>
                        <email/>
                    </affiliation>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>ALLC Special Session</item>
                        <item>humanities computing</item>
                        <item>graduate curriculm</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The session will include European and North American perspectives on the
                    development of graduate programmes in the humanities in which a computing
                    component has a significant role. A major Europe-wide project will be described
                    whose objectives are not only to gather information about the current situation
                    in European universities, but also to promote collaborative curriculum
                    development. Other panelists will describe initiatives under way in individual
                    British and North American universities.</p>
                <p>All the panelists will be emphasizing the issues that are shaping the development
                    of new graduate curricula rather than describing particular programmes in
                    detail. The main focus of the session is on general discussion, in which members
                    of the audience will be encouraged to contribute their experience and concerns.
                    Anyone whose home institution has or is contemplating a graduate programme with
                    a strong computing component is urged to attend and participate.</p>
                <p>Here are some issues that the session will address:<list>
                        <item>What should be the scope of an MA programme in humanities computing?
                            What should be taught? And how?</item>
                        <item>What would be the optimum format for an MA programme in humanities
                            computing? What would be the appropriate balance between course work,
                            project work and dissertation?</item>
                        <item>Should a graduate programme be closely allied with one discipline, for
                            example English? Or should it attempt to fit the needs of several
                            humanities disciplines?</item>
                        <item>How can project work be encouraged and also examined? What factors are
                            important in the assessment of a project?</item>
                        <item>What are the crucial topics and issues to be discussed in a graduate
                            programme in humanities computing? How can these be related to "critical
                            thinking" in humanities scholarship?</item>
                        <item>What institutional factors are important to encourage the development
                            of humanities computing in the graduate curriculum?</item>
                        <item>What would be the typical components of a PhD in humanities computing?
                            What kinds of thesis topics would be appropriate and how might they be
                            examined?</item>
                        <item>What would attract students to a graduate programme in humanities
                            computing?</item>
                    </list></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
