<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="panel">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Towards standards for lexicons and the linguistic
                    annotation of texts.</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Nicoletta</forename>
                        <surname>Calzolari</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Istituto di Linguistica Computazionale del CNR</name>
                            <email>glottolo@ilc.pi.cnr.it</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Antonio</forename>
                        <surname>Zampolli</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Istituto di Linguistica Computazionale del CNR</name>
                            <email>eagles@ilc.pi.cnr.it</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Ulrich</forename>
                        <surname>Heid</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">IMS-CL, Universitaet Stuttgart</name>
                            <email>heid@ims.uni-stuttgart.de</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Antonio</forename>
                        <surname>Sanfilippo</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Oxford University</name>
                            <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Ralph</forename>
                        <surname>Grishman</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">New York</name>
                            <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Catherine</forename>
                        <surname>McLeod</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">New York</name>
                            <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>linguistic annotation of texts</item>
                        <item>standardization</item>
                        <item>guidelines</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Motivation</head>
                        <p>As more and more machine readable text material becomes available, the
                            importance of linguistic annotation of this material is in steady
                            increase. This is true not only in the field of Natural Language
                            Processing (NLP) and Language Engineering, but as well in Humanities
                            Computing: for example, it is evident that linguistically informed free
                            text search and text retrieval (especially if these are written in
                            morphologically richer languages) is more precise (less noise) than
                            search in texts not linguistically pre-analyzed. Linguistic annotation
                                includes<list type="bulleted">
                                <item>the identification and tagging of word, sentence and paragraph
                                    boundaries;</item>
                                <item>the identification and tagging of the category (POS, word
                                    class) of word forms in running text;</item>
                                <item>the identification and tagging of morphological features
                                    (tense, number, person, etc.);</item>
                                <item>the identification and tagging of syntactic properties of
                                    predicates (syntactic subcategorization);</item>
                            </list>and many more.</p>
                        <p>Many corpus Linguistic Engineering companies and projects have designed
                            their own proprietary annotation schemes; broadly available common
                            schemes would have a number of advantages (easy availability,
                            documentation, exchangeability, etc.). The workshop will discuss the
                            need for standards for the above levels of linguistic description.</p>
                        <p>For the types of annotation listed above, the EAGLES project has
                            attempted to prepare annotation schemes and operational tagging
                            guidelines, to encode these as formal (or formally representable)
                            specifications, and to validate them in a number of application
                            experiments. EAGLES (Expert Advisory Groups on Linguistic Engineering
                            Standards) is an expert group with contributors from both industry and
                            academia from all over the EU aiming at the design of consensual
                            standards for key areas of Linguistic Engineering.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Workshop objectives</head>
                        <p>The workshop aims at presenting and discussing recent and ongoing work
                            towards standards for linguistic classification and annotation of word
                            forms in texts and lexicons; the second main objective is to gather the
                            feedback of the Humanities Computing scene with respect to the
                            standardization work.</p>
                        <p>Specific objectives include the following:<list>
                                <item>- Identify and discuss the need for and the problems related
                                    with standards in the field of linguistic resources (in
                                    particular lexicons and corpora);</item>
                                <item>- Discuss questions of the interaction between lexicon and
                                    corpus: if there is a common underlying classification of
                                    linguistic material, at the levels indicated above, interesting
                                    new possibilities for `compound' resources are opened up:
                                    dynamic links from the lexicon to the corpus, corpus-based
                                    lexicon validation, new possibilities for linguistic
                                    acquisition, etc.</item>
                                <item>- Describe the EAGLES approach to the definition of standards
                                    proposals, the representations used, and the mechanisms
                                    available for validation, consistency checking etc.</item>
                                <item>- Describe the existing proposals for syntactic (and possibly
                                    semantic) annotation in texts and lexicons, based on efforts in
                                    EAGLES and in the COMLEX project at NYU;</item>
                                <item>- Discuss the EAGLES proposals from the point of view of
                                    `users': if a lexicon design project or a corpus analysis
                                    project is set up, does the use of annotation standards
                                    contribute to the efficiency of the project?</item>
                            </list></p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>Standards for lexicons and corpora -- Areas, interaction between
                            lexicon and corpus, current state of EAGLES</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">Nicoletta Calzolari</p>
                        <div>
                            <p> When we highlight the complex structure of the interrelationships
                                between lexicon and corpus, we have to work on the assumption of an
                                interdependence between the two views, and we have to take into
                                account this interdependence in any lexical or corpus analysis or
                                application.</p>
                            <p>This was also the approach taken within the LRE EAGLES (see
                                Calzolari, McNaught, EAGLES Editors' Introduction, 1996) project
                                towards the development of standards both in Morphosyntax and
                                Syntax: the awareness of the interdependence between lexical
                                specifications on the one hand, and corpus tagsets/syntactic
                                annotations on the other, has guided the formulation of the
                                proposals for standards and recommendations in both the Corpus and
                                the Lexicon Work Groups of EAGLES. Corpus tagging/annotating was
                                considered as the first obvious application of a Computational
                                Lexicon. Therefore attention was given to the definition of
                                compatible sets of attributes and values.</p>
                            <p> The presentation will address problems of the interaction between
                                the two types of resources, corpora and lexicons, in particular from
                                the perspective of a standardization project.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>From specifications to tagsets and coding guidelines: EAGLES
                            morphosyntax annotations in lexicons and texts</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">Ulrich Heid</p>
                        <div>
                            <p> EAGLES has first established a core set of commonly agreed
                                annotations for morphosyntax, basically by collecting, comparing and
                                filtering existing annotation proposals from lexicons and tagsets.
                                Once the synthesis is available, how can it be put to use in both
                                lexicon building and text annotation work? This question is
                                addressed in our contribution.</p>
                            <p>We want the EAGLES morphosyntax annotation to be applicable in
                                different usage contexts, especially in both, lexicons for NLP and
                                text corpora. Moreover, other than in many tagsets for corpus
                                annotation, the classifications used must be strict: the classes
                                form a hierarchy, and any item to be described has to fall in one
                                branch of the hierarchy. Along with this structure, there is need,
                                however, for support for manual tagging: how can we make sure that
                                different people will classify the same facts in the same way?</p>
                            <p>In EAGLES, we have tried to come close to solutions for some of the
                                requirements stated above. We have defined a typed class hierarchy,
                                to specify the classifications underlying our language-specific
                                morphosyntactic coding systems. These hierarchies can be mapped onto
                                lexicon codes as well as onto corpus tagsets, the latter is even
                                automatic. For a subset of languages, we have written guidelines for
                                manual annotation, which contain discussions of borderline cases,
                                tests and a large collection of examples, to support manual coders.
                                We have applied the tagset and guidelines to the manual coding of
                                60.000 word reference corpora for German and Italian.</p>
                            <p>The contribution will summarize the experiences gained in this
                                exercise, and we will point to the ressources and tools produced
                                therein.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="EmbeddedDoc">
                    <div>
                        <head>The Comlex Syntax Lexicon and the Eagles Subcategorization
                            Standard</head>
                        <p rend="presenter">Ralph GRISHMAN/Catherine McLEOD</p>
                        <div>
                            <p>Comlex Syntax is a broad-coverage English lexicon which was developed
                                specifically for natural language processing and includes detailed
                                information on complements for verbs, nouns, and adjectives. The
                                information we seek to capture is similar to that of EAGLES
                                syntactic lexicons, but our focus on a single language has allowed
                                us to define a fixed set of complement classes. These classes are
                                defined in the dictionary as combinations of standard syntactic
                                constituents.</p>
                            <p>Comlex Syntax is accompanied by a corpus with tagged examples of the
                                subcategorization patterns of various high-frequency verbs. Our
                                definition mechanism for complement classes allowed us to readily
                                add new classes for previously unseen and rare complement
                                structures. The tagging has also required additional features
                                (besides those in the lexicon) to account for subcategorization
                                patterns in context.</p>
                            <p>We are currently extending Comlex Syntax to include information on
                                nominalizations. This is requiring us for the first time to link
                                subcategorization frames from different parts of speech.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>

</TEI>
