<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Tailoring a formal grammar for efficiency without
                    compromising its linguistic motivation</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Nelleke</forename>
                        <surname>Oostdijk</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Nijmegen</name>
                            <email>oostdijk@let.kun.nl</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>syntactic corpus analysis</item>
                        <item>formal grammar</item>
                        <item>ambiguity</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>Corpus linguistics can be characterised as the formalized approach to
                        descriptive linguistics. Its main objective is the study of actual language
                        use and variation therein on the basis of text corpora. A corpus is not just
                        any amount of textual data; rather, a corpus is a balanced collection of
                        language data and is constituted by samples of connected discourse, usually
                        in a single dialect. In its raw form, the corpus serves as a test-bed for
                        the linguistic hypotheses laid down in a formal grammar. Once annotated (in
                        accordance with the grammar), the corpus constitutes a database that may be
                        consulted in order to obtain information about linguistic structures, their
                        frequency of occurrence and distribution, as well as to gain insights into
                        co-occurrence restrictions (cf. e.g. Oostdijk and de Haan, 1994). In this
                        approach, the formal grammar plays a central role: the grammar both contains
                        the formalized description of the language under investigation, which is
                        validated in the process of annotating the corpus, and it is also used to
                        automatically derive the parser that is employed to annotate the corpus.</p>
                    <p>The formal grammar is originally conceived on the basis of the linguist's
                        intuitions and any information found in sources such as grammatical
                        handbooks (for English, for example, Quirk et al. 1985) and linguistic
                        monographs. Through a process of iterative testing on the corpus and
                        augmenting the description contained in it, the formal grammar is developed
                        until it reaches a satisfactory level of descriptive and observational
                        adequacy. From the point of view of the (descriptive) linguist, the added
                        value of the corpus linguistic approach then lies in the fact that the
                        description that results is explicit, exhaustive, objective and validated,
                        this in contrast with other, traditionally informal accounts.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Current practice: an evaluation</head>
                    <p>While the annotation of corpora can serve a dual purpose, so far the creation
                        of databases has been given priority over the advancement of descriptive
                        theory. The reason for this is simply that this continues to be the most
                        urgent task, since corpora that have been annotated with detailed linguistic
                        information are still rare. Therefore, at present grammars are being
                        constructed for the purpose of analysing corpora that, once analysed, can be
                        used by the general linguistic community. It goes without saying that the
                        linguistic descriptions contained in these grammars should adhere to the
                        standards set by the discipline. In effect this means that the descriptions
                        must conform to a large extent to what is familiar and traditional.</p>
                    <p>The corpus linguistic approach described above to the linguistic annotation
                        of corpora can be said to be a rather ambitious one, as the parser should
                        produce for each corpus sentence (at least) the one contextually appropriate
                        analysis. Since the knowledge incorporated into the formal grammar is for
                        various reasons insufficient, overgeneration is unavoidable. This has a
                        negative impact on the efficiency of the analysis process. With the present
                        orientation towards the production of annotated corpora that can serve as
                        databases for further linguistic reseach, it is required that for each
                        corpus sentence the database should contain ONLY the one analysis that is
                        contextually appropriate. In a situation in which the parser is permitted to
                        overgenerate, human intervention then becomes necessary (van Halteren and
                        Oostdijk, 1993). This not only slows down the analysis process even further,
                        but also the consistency in the analyses is no longer warranted (as it would
                        be if the analysis process were to run fully autonomously).</p>
                    <p>So far the idea has always been upheld that overgeneration is unavoidable.
                        The overall effects overgeneration has on the analysis process and the
                        quality of the output are perhaps more far- reaching than is desirable.
                        While it is undoubtedly true as Aarts et al. (1996) point out that
                        "consistency is mainly endangered if the human analyst takes the initiative
                        in the analysis process" and that therefore it is better "to have the
                        linguist only react to prompts given by automatic processes, by asking him
                        to choose from a number of possibilities presented by the machine", the
                        negative effects of the interaction with the human analyst in terms of loss
                        of consistency and efficiency remain. With regard to our short term goal,
                        what we see is that there still is a great demand for corpora that have been
                        annotated with detailed linguistic information, while the rate at which such
                        corpora are being produced is far too low. Our long term goal, the
                        advancement of descriptive linguistic theory through iterative testing and
                        augmenting the description contained in the formal grammar, cannot be
                        achieved if we do not succeed in shortening the time-span that is needed to
                        complete a single iteration.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Tailoring the grammar</head>
                    <p>In theory, there are two possible solutions to the problem of overgeneration.
                        The first solution is to resort to underspecification, a strategy which is
                        widely adopted both in tagging and in parsing. The portmanteau tags in
                        various tagsets are typical examples of underspecification. In the PENN
                        Treebank approach (Marcus et al., 1993) for instance the portmanteau
                        part-of-speech tag IN is assigned to both prepositions and subordinating
                        conjunctions. Underspecification is also found at all levels of English
                        Constraint Grammar (ENGCG, Karlsson et al. 1995). The major drawback of
                        underspecification is of course the loss of information. An alternative
                        solution can be found in incorporating into the grammar the knowledge that
                        is now brought into play in the analysis process in the interaction with the
                        human analyst. The nature of this information is diverse and includes
                        knowledge about semantics, pragmatics, discourse and syntax. Now at this
                        stage it would be too unrealistic to propose to incorporate all these types
                        of knowledge. However, closer examination of the overgeneration found in the
                        corpus we have (syntactically) analysed yields the following picture: (1)
                        not all knowledge that we have as far as syntax is concerned has as yet
                        found its way into the grammar, and (2) the knowledge we have incorporated
                        in our grammar so far has not been used to the full. The two points are
                        obviously related. They both have to do with the fact that while
                        constructing the formal grammar, it was not at all clear what knowledge and
                        what detail were required. The construction of the formal grammar so far has
                        amounted to formalizing what knowledge we were aware of and which was deemed
                        linguistically relevant.</p>
                    <p>The present paper reports the results of an investigation into the nature of
                        the overgeneration as found in the analysis results obtained in the process
                        of annotating a corpus of Modern British English by means of a rule-based
                        parser. As these results show, there is sufficient reason to believe that it
                        should indeed be possible to tailor the grammar for efficiency without
                        compromising its linguistic motivation. Moreover, the nature of (some of)
                        the adaptations is such that they must be considered relevant not only with
                        respect to the specific parser used in the experiment, but that they can
                        also be of importance in a broader context.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Aarts</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">H.</forename>
                                    <surname>van Halteren</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">N.</forename>
                                    <surname>Oostdijk</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">The TOSCA analysis system</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">H.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Koster</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">E.</forename>
                                    <surname>Oltmans</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Proceedings of the First AGFL Workshop</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Nikmegen</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>CSI</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">181-191</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">H.</forename>
                                    <surname>van Halteren</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">N.</forename>
                                    <surname>Oostdijk</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Towards a linguistic database: the TOSCA analysis
                                system</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Aarts</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>de Haan</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">N.</forename>
                                    <surname>Oostdijk</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">English Language Corpora: Design, analysis and
                                exploitation</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Amsterdam - Atlanta</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Rodopi</publisher>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">145-161</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">F.</forename>
                                    <surname>Karlsson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Voutilainen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Heikkilä</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Anttila</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Constraint Grammar. A Language-Independent System for
                                Parsing Unrestricted Text</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Berlin - New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Mouton de Gruyter</publisher>
                                <date when="1995">1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <surname>Marcus</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">B.</forename>
                                    <surname>Santorini</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">M.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Marcinkiewicz</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Building a large annotated corpus of English: The Penn
                                Treebank</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Computational Linguistics</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">19</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">313-330</biblScope>
                                <date when="1993">1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">N.</forename>
                                    <surname>Oostdijk</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">P.</forename>
                                    <surname>de Haan</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Clause patterns in Modern British English. A
                                corpus-based (quantitative) study</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">ICAME Journal </title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">18</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">41-80</biblScope>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Quirk</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">S.</forename>
                                    <surname>Greenbaum</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <surname>Leech</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Svartvik</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">A Comprehensive Grammar of the English Language</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Longman</publisher>
                                <date when="1985">1985</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
