<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="panel">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Institutional Support in the Advancement of Technology
                    in the Humanities: Roles, Models, and Collaboration</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Robert</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">E.</forename>
                        <surname>Wright</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">National Humanities Center</name>
                            <email>wright@ga.unc.edu</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Willard</forename>
                        <surname>McCarty</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">King's College London</name>
                            <email>Willard.McCarty@kcl.ac.uk</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Susan</forename>
                        <surname>Saltrick</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Addison Wesley Longman</name>
                            <email>Susan.Saltrick@harpercollins.com</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>support</item>
                        <item>role</item>
                        <item>model</item>
                        <item>collaboration</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>While the rapid advancement of technology in the humanities in recent
                    years--particularly with the advent of the World Wide Web and the increasing use
                    of multi-media--has been no doubt dramatic, even revolutionary, the progress has
                    thus far tended to be dependent on the work of individuals or groups of
                    individuals, with or without substantial institutional support, rather than
                    systemic and institution-wide. Colleges and universities, with varying levels of
                    resources and success, are moving to provide technological access and services
                    for their faculty, graduate and undergraduate students, and other constituents,
                    but the impact on departments of the humanities is most often uneven, at best.
                    Specialized programs and organizations have developed effective means of
                    addressing their own constituents' particular concerns, but the problems of
                    integrating these into larger institutional and professional structures have yet
                    to be resolved. Moreover, the distinctive roles of different types of
                    institutions--colleges and universities, research libraries, professional
                    organizations, and institutes for advanced study--and the nature of
                    collaboration among them in this new technological environment have yet to be
                    defined, even as economic and other forces press for increased clarity of
                    purpose and of productivity.</p>
                <p>In the absence of existing models, it is imperative that these broad
                    institutional issues be addressed if the advancement of technology in the
                    humanities is to fulfill its greatest promise in a manner that is both effective
                    and timely. Specifically, the role of different types of institutions must be
                    more clearly defined (for their own interests, as well as those of higher
                    education at large), effective models of performance must be developed, and an
                    unprecedented level of creative, technological collaboration among institutions
                    with different missions must be established.</p>
                <p>The proposal for this session grows out of a planning meeting held in May 1996 at
                    the National Humanities Center, a private, independent institute for advanced
                    study located in Research Triangle Park, North Carolina. A total of thirty-seven
                    people, including this session's panelists, participated in that meeting, with
                    representatives of universities in the United States and Canada, libraries,
                    information officers, technology programs in the humanities, professional
                    organizations in the humanities, and philanthropic organizations in the United
                    States and Europe. The two-day meeting, "Scholarly and Educational Applications
                    of Advanced Technology," explored the range of issues involved with technology
                    in the humanities, progressing through several sessions: Advanced Technologies,
                    Resources, and Access; Scholarship, Publication, and Scholarly Communications;
                    Teaching and Curricular Applications; Institutional, Professional, and
                    Disciplinary Issues; Setting the Agenda--The Role of Colleges and Universities,
                    Research Libraries, Professional Organizations, and Institutes for Advanced
                    Study; and The Role of the National Humanities Center--Mission, Goals, Specific
                    Initiatives, Infrastructure, and Timetable.</p>
                <p>The session proposed for ACH-ALLC '97 would draw upon themes and proposals put
                    forth at the earlier meeting, with particular emphasis on the following sets of
                    questions from two of the sessions:</p>
                <p><emph rend="italics">
                        <emph rend="bold">Institutional, Professional, and Disciplinary
                            Issues</emph>
                    </emph>: What are the forces that are either driving or resisting the use of
                    advanced technology in higher education? How does technology help to address
                    economic and other challenges facing colleges and universities? What are the
                    likely and desirable effects on higher education in the twenty-first century?
                    What is the impact of work with advanced technology--in scholarship,
                    publication, and teaching--on the appointment, promotion, and tenure process for
                    faculty in the humanities? Should the definition of what "counts" as scholarship
                    in the humanities change and, if so, how and under what conditions is it likely
                    to do so? How is advanced technology affecting the relationship between the
                    humanities and other disciplines, and among the humanistic disciplines
                    themselves? In what fields of the humanities is the use of advanced technology
                    having the most impact, and why? What fields have the greatest potential for its
                    use in the foreseeable future? How is advanced technology changing the
                    relationships between and among faculty, librarians, technologists, designers,
                    students, and others?</p>
                <p><emph rend="italics">
                        <emph rend="bold">Setting the Agenda--The Role of Colleges and Universities,
                            Research Libraries, Professional Organizations, and Institutes for
                            Advanced Study</emph>
                    </emph>: What are the varying roles of these different types of institutions of
                    higher education with regard to advanced technology in the humanities? What are
                    the most important agenda to be set for the next three to five years, and how
                    can that process of advancement best be accomplished? What institutions are
                    doing the most effective work with advanced technology, and which have the most
                    potential? How can these different institutions most productively interact and
                    work together as we enter the twenty-first century? How can philanthropy and
                    other sources of financial support assist these various institutions in meeting
                    their highest goals with regard to the use of advanced technology?</p>
                <p>The panelists for the proposed ACH-ALLC '97 session, all of whom have agreed to
                    participate, would bring to it varying and complementary perspectives, as
                    follows:</p>
                <p><emph rend="italics">
                        <emph rend="bold">Robert E. Wright</emph>
                    </emph> is Vice President for Communications and Development at the National
                    Humanities Center, a private, independent institute for advanced study in all
                    fields of the humanities, which each year supports some thirty-five Fellows in
                    residence from across the United States and abroad. A medievalist by training
                    with ten years experience in fundraising and administration for institutions of
                    higher education, he would address the broad issues involved in the advancement
                    of technology in humanistic scholarship and teaching, as well as the challenges
                    of securing financial support.</p>
                <p><emph rend="italics">
                        <emph rend="bold">Willard McCarty</emph>
                    </emph> is Senior Lecturer in Humanities Computing, King's College London, and
                    Editor of <emph rend="italics">Humanist</emph>. Trained as a Miltonist, for the
                    last decade he has specialized in humanities computing and Ovidian studies. He
                    would represent humanities computing at a British institution that has recently
                    founded an academic department in the field, bringing with him a comparative and
                    international perspective. He would address the integrity of the field as an
                    area of study, its essential roles within an institution of higher education,
                    and various models by which these roles are currently played. </p>
                <p><emph rend="italics">
                        <emph rend="bold">Susan Saltrick</emph>
                    </emph> is Vice President and Director of New Media at Longman, a division of
                    Addison Wesley Longman, focused on publishing educational materials for the
                    humanities, education, and the behavioral and social sciences. Last summer, she
                    led the Summer Program in Multimedia for Higher Education at New York
                    University's Interactive Telecommunications Program, in which she also served as
                    producer, working with Robert Hollander of Princeton University, for the
                    prototype of the Multimedia Dante project. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
