<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The Electronic Archive of Early American Fiction
                    (1775-1850)</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">David</forename>
                        <surname>Seaman</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Virginia</name>
                            <email>etext@virginia.edu</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>SGML</item>
                        <item>archival imaging</item>
                        <item>early American Fiction</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>This 125,000-page project takes the University of Virginia Library into a
                        level of archival-quality text and image production rarely seen in rare
                        books archives. In preparing for this project we have tackled issues of
                        funding, production-level digital equipment and practices, partnerships with
                        commercial publishers to disseminate the results, and large-scale storage
                        issues. This paper will outline the project, explain the workflow,
                        equipment, and text and image standards that we think appropriate for
                        creating data of long-term viability, and explore the lessons we are
                        learning (and expect to learn) regarding the economics of undertaking a
                        cost-recovery process.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Scope</head>
                    <p>The Early American fiction project will create electronic texts for the 425
                        titles (582 volumes) which are in the Barrett and Taylor collections at the
                        University of Virginia Special Collections Department. The list includes
                        major works of Edgar Allan Poe, James Fenimore Cooper, Nathaniel Hawthorne,
                        and Washington Irving but also includes many lesser known authors such as
                        Anne Newport Royall, Samuel Benjamin Judah, and Charles Frederick Briggs. By
                        including the lesser known works and authors we hope to represent the fabric
                        and context of early American literature, making available to teachers and
                        researchers what Americans were reading during the first 75 years of the
                        history of our nation.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Digital Formats</head>
                    <p>The project will combine high-quality color page images of all 125,000 pages
                        (including covers and spines) with TEI-encoded text versions, allowing
                        scholars all over the world a rare sense of the physical reality of the
                        volumes being studied as well as providing a fully-searchable SGML database.
                        All images will be scanned with a digital camera at approximately 400 dpi,
                        24-bit color, and archived as TIFF files. The paper will cover the
                        challenges of managing this vast amount of data, and the necessity for such
                        large page-image files. JPEG derivatives will be generated for on-line
                        use.</p>
                    <p>All the text will be encoded in TEI. The conversion to tagged ASCII text will
                        be done under contract with a keyboarding company, who will also add some of
                        the markup. The texts will be completed and parsed at UVa., and mounted on
                        the web. The paper will report on this workflow, and outline the lessons we
                        learn in handling large quantities of TEI text and color TIFF images.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Economics</head>
                    <p>A key part of this project will be a structured measurement of usage of the
                        e-texts created in the project, and a comparison of that usage with the
                        usage of original rare books. In addition to the economics of use, there
                        will be a report on our cost-recovery assumptions, which include a
                        partnership with a commercial publisher to market a CD version of the
                        database.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Conclusion</head>
                    <p>The Electronic Archive of Early American Fiction project presents the
                        opportunity to study scholarly use of original rare books and of their
                        computer simulacra, and to determine the extent to which electronic texts of
                        rare books can serve scholars and teachers, and to compare the usage and
                        costs of electronic texts and of original paper texts of rare books. This
                        paper will outline the scope of the project and report on what we have
                        learned to endorse or challenge our initial assumptions about workflow,
                        cost, level of tagging, commercial interest, and image quality.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
