<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="panel">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">ACH Special Session: ACH and NINCH</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Michael</forename>
                        <surname>Neuman</surname>
                        <affiliation>(President of <name type="org">ACH</name>), Chair <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">David</forename>
                        <surname>Green</surname>
                        <affiliation>(Executive Director of <name type="org">NINCH</name>),
                            Presenter <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">John</forename>
                        <surname>Unsworth</surname>
                        <affiliation>(Member, <name type="org">ACH Executive Council</name>),
                            Respondent <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>ACH special session</item>
                        <item>ACH</item>
                        <item>NINCH</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>The ACH-ALLC joint conference protocol welcomes special sessions proposed by
                    chief executives of the two organizations and by the local organizers of the
                    conference. The session described here was proposed by the President of ACH to
                    announce the recent inclusion of the Association for Computers and the
                    Humanities in the constellation of institutions and organizations that comprise
                    the National Initiative for a Networked Cultural Heritage (NINCH) and to explore
                    ways in which the affiliation could work to the mutual advantage of the two
                    organizations.</p>
                <p>NINCH is described on <ref target="http://www-ninch.cni.org/">its home page</ref>
                    as a broad coalition of arts, humanities, and social science organizations
                    formed to promote participation of the cultural sector in the new digitally
                    networked environment. NINCH began in 1993 as a collaborative project of the
                    American Council of Learned Societies, the Coalition for Networked Information,
                    and the Getty Information Institute. The two dozen affiliated organizations
                    include national organizations (including ACLS), professional societies (such as
                    the American Historical Association and the College Art Association),
                    universities, and cultural institutions (including the Smithsonian).</p>
                <p>The mission of NINCH is to advocate the inclusion of the cultural sector in all
                    policy deliberations on the future of the information infrastructure and to
                    educate policymakers, coalition members, and the general public about the
                    critical importance of translating the vision of connected, distributed, and
                    accessible collections of cultural knowledge into a working reality. Strategies
                    include community building, advocacy, and communications and education -- each
                    of which is described in more detail on the web site.</p>
                <p>Among the projects and initiatives planned by NINCH, several may be of interest
                    to members of ACH, especially those on Fair Use and Education, Cultural
                    Diversity and Cultural Heritage (and featuring Web-based "pavilions" on
                    educational themes aimed at secondary and post-secondary students), a series of
                    Advocacy Working Groups on such issues as copyright and metadata, and
                    cross-sectoral interactions such as collaborations between computer scientists
                    and humanists or public- private collaborations to digitize works from our
                    cultural heritage.</p>
                <p>The format for the conference session on the ACH-NINCH affiliation will consist
                    of an introduction by the President of ACH on the expertise offered and the
                    opportunities to be gained by the members of ACH, a presentation by David Green
                    (the Executive Director of NINCH) on the mission of the Initiative and the
                    potential role for ACH, a response by a member of the ACH Executive Council, and
                    open discussion among attendees.</p>
                <p>At this point in its history, the Association for Computers and the Humanities is
                    seeking to expand its membership, to increase recognition of its members'
                    expertise and its organization's contributions to research and teaching with
                    digital resources, to extend its purview to additional disciplines and
                    additional forms of humanities computing, and to add its voices to the debates
                    currently being waged on issues at the intersection of technology, culture, and
                    policy. This session is designed to explore ways in which an affiliation with
                    the National Initiative for a Networked Cultural Heritage would advance ACH
                    towards those objectives while promoting the cultural, educational, social, and
                    political mission of NINCH. All conference participants are welcome.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
