<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">A Digital Library System for Japanese Classical
                    Literature</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Shoichiro</forename>
                        <surname>Hara</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">National Institute of Japanese Literature</name>
                            <email>hara@nijl.ac.jp</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Hisashi</forename>
                        <surname>Yasunaga</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">National Institute of Japanese Literature</name>
                            <email>yasunaga@nijl.ac.jp</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>SGML</item>
                        <item>Japanese classical text</item>
                        <item>multimedia database</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>1. Overview</head>
                    <p>The National Institute of Japanese Literature (NIJL) has been designing,
                        building, managing, and maintaining the databases on Japanese classical
                        literature for academic researchers both in Japan and foreign countries. The
                        NIJL's database system is comprised from a computer and inter-network, and
                        provides three catalogue databases (i.e., the Catalogue of Holding
                        Microfilms of Manuscripts and Printed Books on Japanese Classical
                        Literature, the Catalogue of Holding Manuscripts and Printed Books on
                        Japanese Classical Literature, and the Bibliography of Research Papers on
                        Japanese Classical Literature). A feature of the NIJL's computer system is
                        that all data processing from data compiling, data correction, database
                        service, and to publishing is executed on a main frame computer system.
                        However, during more than ten years, NIJL's database system has had many
                        problems awaiting solution from the view of software and hardware. To solve
                        these problems, NIJL has started the new project of the digital library for
                        Japanese classical literature. This project downsizes the main frame
                        computer system and reconstructs it as the so-called distributed computer
                        system over several years. The key words of this project are
                        "standardization of data," "data independent from systems" and "multimedia
                        oriented." At present, following this definite policy, we are reconstructing
                        catalogue databases and full text databases, and from this year, we start
                        constructing the new image database of Holding Manuscripts and Printed Books
                        on Japanese Classical Literature.</p>
                    <p>During few years of experiment, we recognize that a digital library alone
                        cannot always contribute to research activities of humanities scholars. A
                        digital library is only a bank of raw material data, on the other hand,
                        valuable results are produced under the individual research environments.
                        Thus, we feel better and effective software tools, linking with digital
                        libraries for downloading raw data and uploading research results can assist
                        research skill done by the researchers. We begin new study of software for
                        humanities as a "Digital Study System."</p>
                    <p>In the following, chapter two describes "On Going Project" of the digital
                        library, chapter three describes the new project of the image database.
                        Finally, new study of the "Digital Study System" for humanities is described
                        in chapter four.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2. On Going Projects</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>2.1 SGML as the Basis of Data Description</head>
                        <p>There are a several languages or standards for describing text
                            structures, including SGML (Standard Generalized Markup Language), TeX,
                            PostScript, and ODA (Open Document Architecture). Among these, SGML is
                            the only language that can describe the logical structure of text. As it
                            is established as ISO and JIS (Japanese Industrial Standard) standard,
                            many applications have been developed.</p>
                        <p>At present, we are under reconstruction of catalogue databases and full
                            text databases. Both data can essentially be considered as nested string
                            fields with variable length. SGML can describe the complicated text
                            structure such as repeating groups, nests, an order of appearance, and
                            number of appearances. If a data search is regarded as "a search for a
                            specific string in text data," constructing database system that uses a
                            string searching device is possible. Actually, in research on Japanese
                            literature, search by string is more common way than search by
                            numbers.</p>
                        <p>Meanwhile, fast string search devices and software are being developed
                            and sold; all of the products are capable of handling SGML data.
                            Consequently, we have done some projects based on SGML.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>2. 2 Catalog Databases</head>
                        <p>Catalogue data is used for various purposes such as on-line database
                            service, publishing in printed form, publishing in CD-ROM and so on<note
                                n="1">[1]Keiko KITAMURA, Hisashi YASUNAGA: <title level="a">Data
                                    Base Delivery for Japanese Literature by CD-ROM'</title>, <title
                                    level="m">Joint International Conference ALLC/ACH Conference
                                    Abstract</title>, pp.261-265, 1991.</note>. This database system
                            was designed more than 10 years ago based on devices at that time. As
                            the latest computer system cannot support these devices, taking this
                            opportunity, we begin reconstructing whole database systems. Reviewing
                            old systems, we make new system policy of independence data from
                            hardware and software, definitely speaking, we introduced SGML to
                            describe the data<note n="2">[2] Shoichiro HARA, Hisashi Yasunaga:
                                    <title level="a">On the Text Based Database Systems for Public
                                    Service</title>, <title level="m">Joint International Conference
                                    ALLC/ACH Conference Abstract</title>, pp.43-45, 1995.</note> As
                            the original data was prepared and compiled by librarians from their
                            points of view, some researchers are not satisfied with the contents for
                            their research purposes. We adopt their advices to expand data structure
                            while reconstructing the systems.</p>
                        <p>Based on the ideas described above, we began reconstruction of new
                            catalogue database systems. Specifically, we have:<list>
                                <item>1) Created DTD (Data Type Definition) for new catalogue
                                    data.</item>
                                <item>2) Converted original data to SGML data.</item>
                                <item>3) Test-produced a database system using a string searching
                                    tool.</item>
                                <item>4) Converted SGML data to LaTeX data and output in printed
                                    form.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The tools used in this project were MARK-IT for the data conversion and
                            structure analysis, and OPEN-TEXT for the string searching engine.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>2.3 Full Text Database</head>
                        <p>At the beginning of our full-text database construction, the movement of
                            standardization of the text data description was not active in Japan. We
                            considered SGML as a favorable standard for defining text structure and
                            describing text data. However, its Japanese standard was not
                            established, and the worse, there were no applications to manipulate
                            Japanese language. For these reasons, we had to establish our own text
                            description rules based on SGML. We call these rules as KOKIN rules
                            (KOKubungaku (Japanese literature) INformation)<note n="3">[3]Hisashi
                                Yasunaga: <title level="a">Data Description Rule and Full-text
                                    Database for Japanese Classical Literature</title>, <title
                                    level="m">Joint International Conference ALLC/ACH Conference
                                    Abstract</title>, pp.234-239,1992.</note></p>
                        <p>As KOKIN rules were designed to be easy to understand and to use, they
                            have been favored by humanities researchers. However, as they are
                            independent rules from another standard, there are no good tools to
                            parse and check the KOKIN-based texts. SGML was originally developed as
                            the document markup language for publishers, but recently, it has been
                            regarded as an encoding scheme for transmission of data among the
                            systems. From this background, we believed our text data should be
                            converted to SGML-based one from the point of effective data
                            circulation. Recently, as SGML has become popular in Japan, we began the
                            project to construct a new full-text database based on SGML<note n="4"
                                >[4]Shoichiro HARA, Hisashi Yasunaga: <title level="a">SGML Markup
                                    of Japanese Classical Text -A Case Study-</title>, <title
                                    level="m">Joint International Conference ALLC/ACH Conference
                                    Abstract</title>, pp.131-134,1996.</note> We used "the Anthology
                            of Storiette" as a sample. This is the collection of the short stories
                            of the citizen in "Edo" period and this text have been already
                            transcribed by one of our co-worker in NIJL, and it is also marked up by
                            KOKIN rules. This text has complex structures such as editorial
                            corrections, side notes, Japanese rendering and so on. We conducted the
                            following experiments of: <list>
                                <item>1) Creating DTD for "the Anthology of Storiette."</item>
                                <item>2) Converting the original data to the SGML data.</item>
                                <item>3) Constructing the database system using a string searching
                                    tool.</item>
                                <item>4) Converting SGML data to LaTeX data and printing a
                                    block-copy manuscript.</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The tools used in this experiment were the same as for the above
                            project.</p>
                    </div>
                    <!-- suspect following section should be numbered 2.4 -->
                    <div>
                        <head>2.3 Image Database for the Study of Japanese Classical
                            Literature</head>
                        <p>One of the main dissatisfactions sent from database users is that "the
                            catalogue databases are undoubtedly useful to find the existence of
                            materials, but accessing materials themselves is difficult for distant
                            uses (especially for foreign users)." To respond to the request, we
                            begin the new project of constructing the "Image Database for the Study
                            of Japanese Classical Literature" receiving a grant-in-aid from the
                            Ministry of Education, Science and Culture.</p>
                        <p>This image data is derived from the microfilms of the "Holding
                            Manuscripts and Printed Books on Japanese Classical Literature" as for
                            getting around the copyright problems and for speedy construction. The
                            image is sampled with 1 bit gray scale and 600 DPI resolution,
                            compressed by G4 method, and stored in a TIFF format.</p>
                        <p>The image database will be linked with the new catalogue database as
                            mentioned above. Database users first consult the catalogue database to
                            search for their objective material, then they will access its image
                            data by following the link between two databases (this link is based on
                            the call-number of the materials in both databases).</p>
                        <p>We make an ingenious device in image data for linking both databases in
                            opposite direction. That is, as we write the call-number of an original
                            materials in each image data file (tag 0x10d of "Document Name" is used
                            for this purpose), then a viewer program can access the corresponding
                            catalogue information automatically by matching the call-number. Using
                            this device, database users first glance at the image database to find
                            an interesting material, then they will access its catalogue information
                            following the link in the opposite direction.</p>
                        <p>We will digitize about four hundred thousand frames of microfilms within
                            1996. If the project progresses satisfactorily, we will finish
                            digitizing all materials ( about one million frames of microfilms) in
                            1998.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <!-- online abstract does not have a section 3 -->
                <div>
                    <head>4. A Digital Study System</head>
                    <p>Above "On Going Projects" become on the right track. By the way, these
                        systems are the systems for center functions such as to store and supply
                        data, but not always for research support functions such as to analyze text.
                        During few years experiment, we recognize the need of better and effective
                        software tools. In the reviews of past information systems, we begin a
                        software development. At present, the following software are under
                        construction or in a draft stage.</p>
                    <div>
                        <head>4.1 Image Annotation Program</head>
                        <p>This program allows researchers to attach annotations (by text) to a
                            certain position and/or area on an image. This program is intended to
                            support a transcription process of humanities researchers. If a
                            researcher attaches some keywords or codes to images, he or she can
                            access specific images by searching specific string in annotations
                            attached to images. In the same way, a researcher can collect images on
                            a specific subject. Furthermore, linking images of different materials
                            is possible, for example, a researcher can compare a specific sentence
                            between authentic text and its variants if he or she put same keywords
                            or codes to several materials.</p>
                        <p>Another use for this program might be image retrieval. As it stores a
                            text with its associated coordinate on the image, calculating the
                            locational relation of annotations is easy. Thus, if the appropriate
                            annotations are attached to images, the image retrieval such as "the
                            images of the mountain in the center of the images with lakes at the
                            foot (under) of it" might be possible.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>4.2 Version Control Mechanism</head>
                        <p>As mentioned in 2.3, we are compiling full text data. However, it is
                            impossible to transcribe all materials by ourselves. One way for swiftly
                            increasing of the amount of full texts is to gather full text data from
                            the public. The problems pointed out to this way are quality control,
                            difficulty of source identification, and so on.</p>
                        <p>One solution to these problems is the version control mechanism, that is,
                            the text data that passes the NIJL data systems must have a kind of
                            "header" that includes the version information such as an original
                            source, a reviser, a summary of revision and so on. The version control
                            mechanism constructs the version tree to show the history of data
                            development. By reviewing the history, users can assess the quality of
                            the data.</p>
                        <p>This mechanism is in planning level. We are considering to use the TEI
                            header for this mechanism<note n="5">[5]C.M.Sperberg-McQueen, Lou
                                Burnard: <title level="m">Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding
                                    and Interchange (TEI P3)</title>, 1994.</note></p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>4.3 Lexical Analyzer</head>
                        <p>One of the main studies on text is vocabulary analysis, where attribute
                            information such as inscription and reading should be added to each word
                            to organize useful data. There are many convenient text analyzing tools
                            for European languages. However, most of these tools cannot be
                            applicable to Japanese text. As there are no spaces between words in
                            Japanese sentences, words shall be written with space by manual to
                            prepare for further analysis. Moreover, Japanese words have a
                            word-forming characteristic to form compound words, which makes it
                            difficult to separate a sentence into words automatically. And, as the
                            style of a sentence is different from work to work, genre to genre, and
                            period to period, thus methods of preparation, management and use of a
                            vocabulary index are different. These make Japanese text difficult to
                            introduce convenient text analysis tools such as TACT.</p>
                        <p>Thus a lexical analyzer to divide the sentence into elements (words) is
                            very important for Japanese text analysis. Recently, there are several
                            large electronic dictionaries and some software tools to analyze
                            vocabulary. We examine these tools to construct more useful lexical
                            tools.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>5. Conclusion</head>
                    <p>NIJL is under reconstruction of databases using SGML to cope with the
                        multimedia age. These reconstructions become on the right track. We begin a
                        software development to support the individual research environment.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
