<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Symbolic Technologies: Challenges and Dangers for the
                    Humanities</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Merlin</forename>
                        <surname>Donald</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Queen's University</name>
                            <email>donaldm@psyc.queensu.ca</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>Queen's University</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Kingston, Ontario</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ACH/ALLC 1997</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name type="org">the secretarial staff in the Department of French Studies at
                        Queen's University</name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Lessard</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>

                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>symbolic technologies</item>
                        <item>keynote paper</item>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Our distinctively human ways of thinking and remembering have evolved almost
                    entirely during the past 2.5 million years. Prior to that time, our remote
                    ancestors were, for all intents and purposes, very much like modern apes. The
                    first major transition period in our biological evolution was approximately 2.5
                    to 1.8 million years ago, with the speciation of <emph rend="italics"
                        >Homo</emph>. A second major transition occurred 250 to 100 thousand years
                    ago, with the speciation of <emph rend="italics">Homo sapiens</emph>. Both of
                    these transitions brought major changes to the brain and mind, giving hominids
                    two distinctively new modes of representation, mimesis and language, that served
                    as the cognitive foundation for our communicative cultures. The modern human
                    mind has additional skills that have been formed quite recently, in close
                    symbiosis with symbolic technologies.</p>
                <p>Broadly defined, symbolic technologies encompass a variety of devices that have a
                    direct impact on thought and memory. These technologies emerged early in human
                    prehistory, initially taking the form of inscribed objects, tokens, amulets,
                    mnemonic devices, pictorial representations, and simple measuring instruments.
                    More elaborate technologies have appeared over the past five thousand years,
                    including powerful systems of writing and numeration, timekeeping devices,
                    navigational devices, and a number of complex cognitive artifacts and
                    institutionalized procedures for entrenching certain habits of thought. The rate
                    of change has steadily increased over this period, culminating in the powerful
                    electronic technologies of the late 20th century. Each new technology has
                    imposed new requirements on the brains that use that technology.</p>
                <p>Taken together, symbolic technologies have brought two major changes to the human
                    cognitive process. First, there has been a constant elaboration of symbolic
                    literacy skills, especially those needed for numerous forms of visual decoding,
                    including writing, mathematics, graphic representation and a variety of other
                    forms of representation. These have placed significant new demands on the human
                    brain, in the form of new cognitive "architectures" that are difficult to
                    acquire, and must be imposed by extensive education. Second, there has been a
                    gradual externalization of human memory. This has changed the way we think,
                    remember, and communicate. There is potential for even more radical change in
                    the future. This is evident in comparing the properties of "exograms," or
                    external memory records, with "engrams," or internal memory records. Exograms
                    introduce changes in every aspect of memory, including what can be stored, what
                    format it may have, and how it can be retrieved. They drastically change the
                    potential number and size of memory records, the ways in which memory records
                    may be organized and transmitted, and especially, how they may be displayed (the
                    display and viewing options for our strictly "biological" memory systems are
                    very limited). These are not trivial changes, in cognitive terms; they have
                    altered all of the parameters by which psychology classifies and measures
                    memory. In some cases, the changes are qualitative.</p>
                <p>Taken together, symbolic technologies have brought two major changes to the human
                    cognitive process. First, there has been a constant elaboration of symbolic
                    literacy skills, especially those needed for numerous forms of visual decoding,
                    including writing, mathematics, graphic representation and a variety of other
                    forms of representation. These have placed significant new demands on the human
                    brain, in the form of new cognitive "architectures" that are difficult to
                    acquire, and must be imposed by extensive education. Second, there has been a
                    gradual externalization of human memory. This has changed the way we think,
                    remember, and communicate. There is potential for even more radical change in
                    the future. This is evident in comparing the properties of "exograms," or
                    external memory records, with "engrams," or internal memory records. Exograms
                    introduce changes in every aspect of memory, including what can be stored, what
                    format it may have, and how it can be retrieved. They drastically change the
                    potential number and size of memory records, the ways in which memory records
                    may be organized and transmitted, and especially, how they may be displayed (the
                    display and viewing options for our strictly "biological" memory systems are
                    very limited). These are not trivial changes, in cognitive terms; they have
                    altered all of the parameters by which psychology classifies and measures
                    memory. In some cases, the changes are qualitative.</p>
                <p>The greatest impact of these technologies may not have been felt yet. While it is
                    dangerous simply to extrapolate trends from our evolutionary history, it seems
                    likely that the impact of computers and other communication technologies will be
                    a mix of good and bad, depending on what one values. The "good" effects are
                    fairly easy to describe: greater freedom, the democratization of information,
                    more rapid access, more powerful forms of representation, and so on. The "bad"
                    effects are less obvious, but potentially quite worrisome, especially to those
                    who cling to traditional Humanistic values. These may include the disintegration
                    of traditional culture, increased dependency on cognitive technology, and less
                    autonomy for the individual mind. The mastery of traditional culture was a
                    relatively simple matter, even a century ago, defined in terms of its cognitive
                    demands. This is no longer true. External storage has dwarfed and overwhelmed
                    individual memory. Methods of external memory retrieval are gaining even greater
                    dominance, in relative terms, over the speed and accuracy of biological memory
                    retrieval. The new technology of imagination--virtual reality, television, and
                    cinema--threatens to outweigh individual imagination, and programmed corporate
                    agendas already outstrip the individual thought process in many kinds of work.
                    In many areas, the creative process itself is being "managed" by institutions
                    and corporations, employing the latest technology. The trend is clearly towards
                    technological, corporate, and institutional control over the individual mind. </p>
                <p>When these effects are mapped out against our current models of cognition, it
                    becomes clear that they reflect <emph rend="italics">structural</emph> changes
                    in the human cognitive process itself, rather than the actions of any ideology
                    or interest group. Therefore they are unlikely to be prevented by the actions of
                    ideologies or interest groups. Moreover, the rate of change is completely out of
                    line with the slower evolutionary process that led up to the modern era. The
                    explosion of new communication technologies presents the Humanities with an
                    extraordinary challenge: new opportunities and tools for research, many new
                    cultural phenomena to analyse, and formidable threats to its historic values.
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
