<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="poster/demo">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">XSL - Characteristics, Status, and Potentials for Text
                    Processing Applications in the Humanities</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Wendell</forename>
                        <surname>Piez</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Mulberry Technologies</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>What XSL Is</head>
                    <p>The Extensible Style Language (XSL) is a specification currently being
                        finalized (May 2000) by the W3 Consortium, the vendor consortium that
                        proposes recommendations for web standards including HTML, CSS and now XML
                        and its related technologies. XSL's immediate purpose is to support various
                        kinds of presentation of arbitrarily marked-up documents in XML format. In
                        an XSL system, any well-formed XML document could be formatted for print,
                        displayed in hypertext (including on the web), or presented in other media,
                        more easily and more effectively than is currently the case, and in a
                        standards-based way. In a networked environment, processing documents for
                        display on screen could happen on either server or client.</p>
                    <p>In order to support its task of <emph rend="italics">presenting XML</emph>
                        (that is, applying to an arbitrary tag set a formatting description for a
                        user interface such as screen or printer), XSL evidently has to provide for
                        granular access to markup structures, so as to be able, for example, to
                        derive tables of contents, text for running heads, indexes, and other common
                        (presentational) expressions of underlying document architecture. In the
                        course of working out XSL it became increasingly clear that (as is often the
                        case with computer data processing problems) this problem was more easily,
                        and more powerfully, addressed, if it was treated as a special case of a
                        more general capability, namely the "transformation" of one markup structure
                        into another.</p>
                    <p>Accordingly, XSL is formally divided into two parts:<list>
                            <item><emph rend="underscore">"XSL Transformations" (XSLT):</emph> on a
                                standalone basis, provides a language to describe many of the kinds
                                of rearrangement and filtering of markup structures that a
                                reasonably powerful XML presentation language requires.</item>
                            <item><emph rend="underscore">"XSL Formatting objects" (XSLFO):</emph>
                                provides a vocabulary for describing, in a standard and abstract
                                way, formatting of text for visual display in print or on screen
                                (and possibly for alternative media presentation).</item>
                        </list></p>
                    <p>XSLT was accepted as an "official" W3C recommendation in November 1999. XSLFO
                        is expected to be completed in mid-2000. The relative maturity of the
                        specifications is reflected in the tools available: already by the end of
                        1999 a number of tools supporting XSLT were available on the Net for free.
                        As of this writing, tools supporting XSLFO (which could, for example,
                        convert XML via XSL into PDF format) are less mature.</p>
                    <p>XSLT, on the other hand, was instantly in use by mid-1999, primarily (though
                        not exclusively) as a way of converting XML into HTML. Because XML becomes
                        instantly useful as soon as HTML can be reliably created out of it, this has
                        in effect jump-started the XML presentation industry, at the price of
                        keeping on-line published versions of XML source documents limited to the
                        capabilities of HTML, the current state of the art in browsing on the web.
                        As a result, even before the ink is dry, we are beginning to get a sense of
                        XSLT's capabilities for processing - while at the same time we are still
                        unclear as to what XSL's own "design language" (its formatting objects) will
                        look like.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>XSLT's Capabilities</head>
                    <list>
                        <item><emph rend="bold">-Presentational XSLT</emph><lb/> XSLT is already
                            used to convert XML into HTML. In this, it is a ready alternative to a
                            scripting approach (Perl, Omnimark etc.) or to the ISO standard DSSSL -
                            and easier to learn than either. It also compares favorably in price:
                            tools for XSLT conversions are free.</item>
                        <item><emph rend="bold">-Analytic XSLT</emph><lb/> XSL processing is
                            dependent on markup in the source text for navigation as opposed to
                            (say) character offsets or line numbers. While very good at presenting
                            information encoded in markup, it is not good at recognizing or
                            construing implicit information such as character patterns. It does no
                            tokenizing, hence cannot recognize "word" boundaries. By default, string
                            processing and matching in XSLT is case-sensitive, and cannot readily be
                            configured otherwise.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>Somewhat surprisingly, however, XSL is nevertheless useful for certain kinds
                        of analytical functions, including certain kinds of XML validation (cf. Rick
                        Jelliffe's "Schematron"). For example, one could write an XSL stylesheet
                        that would check the conformance of an instance of a TEI Header to a certain
                        model, that went beyond the DTD to specify element dependencies - for
                        example, reporting a warning (or providing defaults) if the publication
                        statement were not filled out according to house standards. This could be
                        done with a stylesheet and would not require altering the DTD.</p>
                    <p>And because it can perform testing on strings, XSLT can also be used for
                        generating rudimentary concordances. A concordancer in the form of an XSL
                        style sheet will be demonstrated as a part of this presentation.</p>
                    <p>The thing to keep in mind about any computer-facilitated analytic work is
                        that, without being supported by information from an external source (such
                        as a thesaurus of terms or a morphological dictionary), no algorithm is able
                        to reveal something about a text that is not implicit in the text already.
                        That is, while a computer can rearrange information in a text, and therefore
                        perform such operations as counting incidences or providing indexes, it
                        cannot actually add any "knowledge". What it does, is present a text, and
                        information derived about the text, in such a way that a careful reader can
                        come to conclusions about it that would otherwise be very difficult to
                        demonstrate. This is merely to point out that, for example, a concordance is
                        not an analysis, and by itself makes no argument, although it may facilitate
                        the development of one.</p>
                    <p>XSLT-based analytic work is no different, and since XSLT is not designed
                        specifically with analytic work in mind, it is in some respects an
                        unexpected benefit if it can support this work at all. Even given its fairly
                        rudimentary capabilities, however, XSLT has certain incidental advantages:<list>
                            <item><emph rend="bold">1. It leverages investments made in
                                    markup:</emph><lb/>Many repositories have XML texts, or texts
                                readily convertible into XML. These are all ready for XSL
                                processing, and can be enhanced to support more sophisticated
                                processing.</item>
                            <item><emph rend="bold">2. It produces "publishable" results as a
                                    natural work product:</emph> Since the end result of an XSL
                                transformation can be HTML or an XML format ready for further
                                processing, it is easy to generate results in a form that can be
                                displayed as is.</item>
                            <item><emph rend="bold">3. An investment in XSL is worth making for
                                    other reasons:</emph> Since XSLT processors are so inexpensive
                                (free), the real investment is in time to learn it. And XSLT is so
                                portable and versatile, it pays off this investment in expertise
                                fairly quickly.</item>
                            <item><emph rend="bold">4. It can be combined with other methods:</emph>
                                An XSLT stylesheet can also be used to prepare XML texts for other
                                kinds of work. An XSLT stylesheet can generate COCOA encoding from
                                XML, that can be used to support TACT or another tool that takes
                                advantage of COCOA markup of events in a text stream (such as
                                chapter breaks or shifts in narrative voice). [An XSL stylesheet
                                that creates COCOA markup from an XML TEI source can be
                                demonstrated.]</item>
                        </list>
                    </p>
                    <p>Or, an XSLT stylesheet can be used to derive SVG (Scaleable Vector Graphics)
                        files from descriptive XML source. SVG is a graphics format which is
                        expected, by some, to revolutionize distribution of graphics for certain
                        kinds of applications on the web. Graphic representations of phenomena
                        accessible to XSL transformations can be already displayed in prototype SVG
                        viewers. [SVG frequency distribution graphs of strings in an XML file can be
                        demonstrated.]</p>
                    <p>These are only two examples of ways XSLT can be applied to help prepare XML
                        texts for a variety of further uses. The basic principle being applied is a
                        layered architecture: the source data is maintained in a stable format, such
                        as TEI XML, useful over the long term. Applied "on top" of this repository
                        layer a separate process can expose a "view" or presentation of the source
                        data (some readers may be familiar with the "model-controller-view" model of
                        computer application design), ready for the special format requirements of
                        an arbitrary application.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Role Of XSL/XSLT In The Future</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>- Possibilities for XSL extension:</head>
                        <p>The XSL specification also provides allowance for its extension.
                            Extension functions, in Java or an alternative scripting language, could
                            be made available to an XSL processor. Tokenizing functions,
                            sophisticated string processing and matching, database-integration
                            services (for retrieving data such as morphological variants or checking
                            values against an authority list) could all be addressable, given a good
                            API, from within XSL stylesheets.</p>
                        <p>It is unlikely, however, that such extensions (at least, those especially
                            suited for the types of analysis academic humanists are interested in)
                            would be developed in the private sector - not that they would be
                            without profitable application there. But academic researchers, with
                            clear focus on their own functional requirements, have to lead the way.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>-An XSL browser as "analytical engine":</head>
                        <p>XSL's potentials in these respects suggest that it could play a role in
                            the markup-aware "analytical engine" that many of us keep envisioning
                            (cf. the ELTA initiative). An XML browser that supported XSL stylesheets
                            could be integrated with an editing environment allowing on-the-fly
                            emendation of the stylesheets, and/or the extension functions they call.
                            Stylesheets and function libraries could be pulled "off the shelf," or
                            written especially to address local problems and questions. Specialized
                            functions would have the capability of integrating XSL's
                            presentation/analytical capabilities with other tools such as databases
                            or network applications.</p>
                        <p>Not only would such a system be very versatile; also, in it, research
                            results could take the form of ready-made publishable material, in HTML
                            or any other markup-based form. Since it would basically be an XML web
                            browser, it could also be readily networked, especially as concerns the
                            XML source text (the text under analysis), which could be located
                            anywhere on the Internet. Analytical stylesheets in XSL would be
                            portable and applicable to any text that conformed to the same
                            (sufficiently constrained) document model.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Present Advantages [as of the end of 1999]</head>
                        <div>
                            <head>-XSL tools are freely available:</head>
                            <p>As of this writing, free XSLT processors are available in Java, and
                                are not difficult to set up and run. Learning the stylesheet
                                language itself is the biggest barrier to entry, and there are free
                                and inexpensive resources for this as well.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>-XSL is easy to get going with:</head>
                        <p>By design, XSL is a declarative language, abstracted at a fairly high
                            level. As a result, it is not difficult to learn, at least for most
                            ordinary operations, and is very portable (making it easier to learn
                            from others' work).</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Present Disadvantages [as of the end of 1999]</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>-XSL is somewhat arcane:</head>
                        <div>
                            <p>Although the rudiments of XSL are not difficult, some users take to
                                it less easily than others. It is a "functional" and "declarative"
                                language unlike most scripting languages, so expertise in other
                                computer languages is not readily applicable to it. Naïve users seem
                                to have less trouble learning it than experts. The model of the text
                                on which it operates, the "document tree," although it leverages
                                document markup in a very simple and powerful way, is not a
                                self-evident approach to developers used to looking at text as a
                                stream of characters.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>-XSL processing is XML-based; requires well-formed XML to
                                start:</head>
                            <p>Obviously, XSL requires an XML text to operate on. Either this is a
                                problem, or it isn't.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head>-Tools are rudimentary (although improving):</head>
                            <p>Strong support for internationalization, for example, is envisioned
                                by the specification but not yet widely implemented in interfaces or
                                tools.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <p>As mentioned above, it is unlikely that the private sector would, on
                                its own initiative, develop function libraries that would provide
                                for all the kinds of functions wanted by scholars in the Humanities.
                                (Some, like support for sorting texts in major European and Asian
                                languages, can be hoped for, although not necessarily for free.)</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Conclusions</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>-What XSL will be good for:</head>
                        <p>Presentation, filtering/rearrangement, markup-based processing such as
                            indexing supported by markup. Some kinds of validation. Especially
                            extended or in combination with other methods, XSL will also be capable
                            of supporting sophisticated analytical functions on text marked up in
                            XML.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>-What the emergence of XSL tells us about our markup projects:</head>
                        <list>
                            <item>1. the up-front investment in the text (editorial work) remains
                                the most difficult, interesting and important phase of work. Much or
                                most further processing "down stream," and the types of processing
                                possible, are directly dependent on the features of the text
                                represented through its markup.</item>
                            <item>2. investments in valid SGML/XML formats are demonstrating their
                                resilience through readiness for new applications</item>
                        </list>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Web Site </head>
                        <p>A web presentation of this paper will be made available at &lt;<ptr
                                target="http://www.mulberrytech.com/papers/achallc2000"/>&gt;</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
