<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="panel">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The Role of the Scholarly Associations in Humanities
                    Education</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Harold</forename>
                        <surname>Short</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">King's College London</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Elisabeth</forename>
                        <surname>Burr</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Duisburg</name>, Germany <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">László</forename>
                        <surname>Hunyadi</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Debrecen</name>, Hungary <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Susan</forename>
                        <surname>Hockey</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University College London</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Stuart</forename>
                        <surname>Lee</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Oxford University</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Lisa</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">Lena</forename>
                        <surname>Opas-Hänninen</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Joensuu</name>, Finland <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Allen</forename>
                        <surname>Renear</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Brown University</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">David</forename>
                        <surname>Robey</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Reading University</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p rend="presenter">Chair: Harold Short</p>
                <p rend="presenter">Elisabeth Burr</p>
                <p rend="presenter">László Hunyadi </p>
                <p rend="presenter">Susan Hockey </p>
                <p rend="presenter">Stuart Lee </p>
                <p rend="presenter">Lisa Lena Opas-Hänninen </p>
                <p rend="presenter">Allen Renear </p>
                <p rend="presenter">David Robey</p>
                <p>The use of computer-based resources and techniques in higher education in the
                    humanities disciplines is growing rapidly. Scholarly associations such as ALLC
                    and ACH have played and continue to play a part in this, although the main
                    imperatives are, of course, much more broadly based.</p>
                <p>This session aims to provide a forum for open discussion of the role or roles,
                    formal and informal, that scholarly associations such as ALLC and ACH could
                    and/or should have in the future development and practice of learning and
                    teaching in higher education in the humanities, specifically with reference to
                    the inclusion of advanced computing, both as part of the curriculum and of
                    teaching methodology.</p>
                <p>From an ALLC perspective, this question has an immediate and direct relevance.
                    The ALLC has been formally a partner in the ACO*Hum Project, and indeed has
                    played a leading role in it, with a number of members of the ALLC Committee
                    serving on one of the main working groups of the project, concerned with
                    'Textual Scholarship and Humanities Computing'. ACO*Hum is a 'thematic network'
                    funded by the European Union as part of its SOCRATES programme. It is now
                    approaching the end of its funding, and discussions are in progress about what
                    should happen next. The ALLC is taking an active part in these discussions,
                    including at national and European Union level.</p>
                <p>Members of the panel will report on the work of ACO*Hum and will give their
                    perspectives on the future development of computing in humanities education.
                    They will address specifically (but briefly) the questions surrounding what
                    role(s), if any, should be played by scholarly associations such as ALLC and
                    ACH. A number of possible roles have been suggested, from continuing support for
                    initiatives and projects such as ACO*Hum through to a formal role in the
                    validation or accreditation of courses and diplomas. Allen Renear will present
                    North American and ACH perspectives on the issues raised.</p>
                <p>The brief presentations by each of the panelists will be followed by open
                    discussion in which all those attending will be invited to comment on what the
                    panelists have had to say, or to raise any additional issues they believe to be
                    relevant. From the ALLC perspective, the session is a significant opportunity
                    for dialogue on a range of issues that are important to the associations, and on
                    which the coming months will offer opportunities and the need for decisions.
                    Viewed in a wider context, now is a critical time for fundamental thinking, and
                    for initiatives to be taken unless the associations decide they have no role to
                    play.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
