<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">Solutions for the Delivery of Thematically-Tagged
                    Text</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Terry</forename>
                        <surname>Butler</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Alberta</name>, Canada <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Greg</forename>
                        <surname>Coulombe</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Alberta</name>, Canada <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sue</forename>
                        <surname>Fisher</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Alberta</name>, Canada <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Text Encoding</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>The Orlando Project has developed prototype delivery software which gives end
                        users access to our literary history textbase. Richly-tagged SGML data is
                        automatically converted to XML, and presented to users through a custom
                        application (which runs locally on their machine, and communicates with a
                        back-end XML server). The design of the user interface has been developed
                        through a formal user needs analysis, conducted with a local Pilot Users
                        Group. In the process, we have learned a great deal about how to exploit the
                        richness of a heavily-tagged textbase, and how to present this information
                        selectively to end users (meeting their information requirements without
                        overburdening them with complexity).</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The Goals of our Project</head>
                    <p>The Orlando Project is applying state-of-the-art software technology to
                        traditional fields of study in the humanities. We are writing a literary
                        history of women's writing in Britain, as both a conventional published text
                        and as an SGML tagged textbase. At present (November 1999) we have documents
                        on 850 British women writers and documents on 590 other writers. For each
                        author we have a pair of interdependent documents - a biography and a
                        writing life history. This material is supplemented by 13,600 events, which
                        are discrete dated items providing the further essential and enriching
                        political, social and cultural background to the work. Events vary in their
                        depth of coverage, but are in every case in one way or another related to
                        the literary history which we are writing. Here are three examples of
                        events:</p>
                    <p><emph rend="underscore">1863: Selective chronology: British Women
                            writers:</emph> Florence Nightingale privately printed an anonymous
                        pamphlet, <emph rend="italics">Note on the supposed protection afforded
                            against venereal disease by recognizing and putting it under police
                            regulation</emph>. [keyword: law and legislation] [keyword: body/health
                        - venereal disease]</p>
                    <p><emph rend="underscore">August 1863: Selective chronology: British Women
                            writers:</emph> Florence Nightingale corresponded with Harriet
                        Martineau, outlining the case against the Contagious Diseases Acts. (Vicinus
                        441)</p>
                    <p><emph rend="underscore">by 1871: Comprehensive chronology: Social
                            climate:</emph> The Royal Commission on the Contagious Diseases Acts
                        rejected a suggestion that soldiers and sailors be required to submit to the
                        same regular examinations required of the prostitutes they frequented. The
                        commission believed "there is no comparison to be made between prostitutes
                        and the men who consort with them. With the one sex the offence is committed
                        as a matter of gain; with the other it is an irregular indulgence of a
                        natural impulse." This illustrates the double standard that held women to be
                        sexually unresponsive and men to be prey to strong desire; paradoxically,
                        this belief coexisted with the notion that women were emotional and
                        irrational, while men were more enlightened and controlled.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Delivery Plans</head>
                    <p>The Orlando Project received SSHRC funding in 1994. Our grant proposal at
                        that time argued that SGML was the only feasible means to capture and encode
                        the complex thematic approach to literary history which the project
                        required. As to the ultimate means of delivery for this information, we
                        anticipated that the technology landscape would be utterly changed 5 years
                        on. We believed that there would be ways to deliver SGML to end users at the
                        very end of the 20th century (we were also aware, in 1994, that there were
                        perfectly acceptable ways of converting and delivering SGML information). We
                        have found that XML is the means to the end which we hoped would appear. XML
                        is a rapidly developing W3 Consortium standard, which will permit the direct
                        delivery of tagged information to end users. An XML audit of our textbase,
                        carried out in 1998, showed us that (for delivery purposes) our textbase
                        could be transformed from SGML to XML without any loss of its intellectual
                        value. We are able today to deliver our richly-tagged information to a
                        client program (running in an XML browser, such as Internet Explorer 5; or
                        in a custom application which support XML though third party software such
                        as IBM's XML toolkit.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>User Needs</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Assessment</head>
                        <p>Having received a great deal of positive encouragement from the scholarly
                            community that the information we are developing is of considerable
                            interest to them, we began a formal process of user needs assessment. A
                            richly-tagged textbase such as ours can be exploited by end users in a
                            wide variety of ways:<list type="bulleted">
                                <item>subject-specific searches can create customized chronologies
                                    and research texts for reading</item>
                                <item>imposing chronological limits can highlight issues and create
                                    connections which standard "period" labels obscure</item>
                                <item>consistent tagging allows one or more documents to be compared
                                    "side-by-side", to reveal new insights about authors and their
                                    context</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The most important issue for us was to "bridge" between the complex tag
                            set which we have created and the terminology and information
                            expectations which will characterise our end users. The strengths of our
                            tagging are their rigour, and the highly detailed descriptions of their
                            meaning. Their deficiency (from the point of the end user) is that this
                            knowledge is locked up in a single tag name which may be opaque (such as
                            our Cultural Formation tag) or dangerously obvious (such as our Name
                            tag, which has a precise meaning and occupies a specific niche in a
                            constellation of about a dozen "personal name" tags). In order to drive
                            the development of the software from the users' point of view (rather
                            than our own), we struck a Pilot Users Group. This group (about a dozen
                            people) were drawn from representative communities who we expect will be
                            interested in accessing our information, including: <list
                                type="bulleted">
                                <item>professors, graduate students, and undergraduate
                                    students</item>
                                <item>scholars in fields such as English literature and
                                    History</item>
                                <item>librarians and information scientists</item>
                            </list></p>
                        <p>The program for this group was devised in order to elicit their
                            expectations and desires for our software, without raising the question
                            of what the software would look like or how it would work. We began with
                            meetings where the group were given only written and oral accounts of
                            our Project's goals and content; we elicited the group's own
                            descriptions and terminology for our areas of interest. In the fall of
                            1999, building upon our team's sense of what kinds of access we could
                            provide to end users, the Pilot Users Group was asked to comment on an
                            on-screen mock-up of our delivery software. These sessions were
                            conducted as formal focus groups [Greenbaum; Jordan]; the sessions were
                            recorded and team notetakers wrote down the comments and suggestions
                            from the users group. Because the software on-screen was truly "throw
                            away", we are able to genuinely encourage the users to critique it and
                            explore their preferences and expectations. We also surveyed the
                            computer equipment and level of experience of the user group; we will
                            expand this survey, to make sure we create delivery software which our
                            target users can run, and which they will be able to learn to use
                            effectively.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Software Architecture</head>
                        <p>Our prototype delivery software is being written in a client/server
                            fashion. The client end is a Java program which uses XML-aware code to
                            request XML documents from the server to process them (by sorting,
                            selecting, and sub-setting), and then displays them using XSL (the XML
                            stylesheet language). Although it is technically possible to execute
                            this part of the process inside an XML-capable browser, the nature of
                            our textbase and the kinds of interaction which we wish to provide are
                            rather unlike the Web-page metaphor. Our textbase can be queried to draw
                            together coherent document sub-sections from many documents at once,
                            which can be presented to the user in various forms, such as a
                            customised chronology or a synoptic view of relevant sections from the
                            lives or works of many authors at once. For this reason we feel the
                            creation of an independent delivery program is desirable. A similar
                            consideration operates with respect to linking within our textbase. We
                            are implementing a much richer form of linking that the web at present
                            provides; a great deal of the linking which end users will be able to
                            explore will be generated automatically through the carefully and
                            consistently tagged text. Users who are viewing text of interest will be
                            able to pursue that interest by traversing automatic links which will
                            open up from our elaborately tagged text. The server side of this
                            architecture will make available our tagged textbase (as an XML document
                            collection) which will respond to user queries by selecting and sending
                            XML documents to the client program. We have explored various
                            technologies to provide this searching and delivery on the back-end,
                            including Java and CGI formats (using both Perl and SGREP to handle the
                            searching). The obvious advantage of this approach is that the server
                            can be implemented in more than one way (and be revised and extended as
                            new technologies appear), while the front end client program remains the
                            same (or is extended and improved on an independent trajectory). We are
                            making extensive use of standard technologies, such as XML, XSL, and
                            HTTP (for the communication between client and server). This will aid
                            the process of generalising this software to meet the needs of other
                            users who wish to present SGML or XML text to users without "rendering
                            it down" to display-only formats like HTML.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Issues</head>
                        <p>XML is an emerging standard. The software support for XML is beginning to
                            appear; our strategy will be more effective as XML becomes ubiquitous
                            and a variety of robust XML-capable tools emerge.</p>
                        <p>The current effort is a "prototype"; the exercise of deploying it will
                            have both successes and failures, from which we will learn.</p>
                        <p>We have been very careful to avoid using the "Web" metaphor - our
                            textbase can be delivered in ways which are much more dynamic and more
                            informative that a Web delivery metaphor would imply. This ambition is
                            to some extent undercut by the expectations of our Pilot Users Group,
                            who came to the material with "Web on the brain". A classic case of this
                            was the specific comment that we ought not to use a certain shade of
                            blue for text if it was not a link, because "blue means link".</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Thomas</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Greenbaum</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">The Handbook for Focus Group Research</title>
                            <edition>Second edition</edition>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>Sage Publications</publisher>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Patrick</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Jordan</surname>
                                </name> et al </author>
                            <title level="m">Usability Evaluation in Industry</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>Taylor &amp; Francis</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Steve</forename>
                                    <surname>McConnell</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Rapid Development</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher>Microsoft Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Terry</forename>
                                    <surname>Butler</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Sue</forename>
                                    <surname>Fisher</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Orlando Project: Issues when Moving from SGML to XML
                                for Delivery of Content-Rich Encoded Text</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">Presentation at Markup Technologies '98, Chicago, Nov.
                                12-13, 1998</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Terry</forename>
                                    <surname>Butler</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Can a Team Tag Consistently? Experiences on the Orlando
                                Project</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Presentation given at ACH-ALLC 1999, Charlottesville
                                VA, June 1999</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
