<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main"> Ekphrasis and the Internet: Connecting the Verbal and
                    the Visual with Computer-mediated Student Projects in an Undergraduate
                    Humanities Class</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Donna</forename>
                        <surname>Reiss</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Tidewater Community College</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Art</forename>
                        <surname>Young</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Clemson University</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>The Electronic Classroom</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>In her exploration of ekphrasis, the relationship between visual and verbal arts,
                    Amy Golahny reminds us that references to the interconnectedness of the language
                    of pictures and words date at least from the fifth century B.C. when Simonides
                    said, "as in painting, so in poetry". In the first century B.C., Golanhy adds,
                    Horace said that "painting is mute poetry and poetry a speaking picture".
                    Further consideration of the concept of ekphrasis by Murray Krieger and W.J.T.
                    Mitchell brings our attention to this verbal-visual relationship up to date.
                    However, at the end of the twentieth century, most undergraduate education in
                    the humanities continues to approach these art forms separately or to focus on
                    student-generated text alone for developing and communicating ideas.</p>
                <p>The ease with which the Internet now allows students to exchange, create, and
                    manipulate text and images offers new opportunities for engagement with the
                    composing process. Because our goal as teachers of undergraduate writing and
                    literature classes is creative as well as critical communication and because our
                    pedagogy emphasizes active learning processes, we introduce our students to
                    computing in and about the humanities. Dialogic writing within and beyond their
                    classes enables students to enter into new discourse communities and to explore
                    collaboratively the concepts of their courses. Creating, selecting, and
                    manipulating visual images alone or in conjunction with text introduces students
                    to expanded and contemporary composing processes. Publication of their
                    compositions on the Internet provides them with an audience of other learners.
                    They need not strive to be professional poets or painters to be makers of poems
                    and paintings as a way to learn.</p>
                <p>Although our students may read Blake at a Website or in an edition illustrated by
                    his own drawings or read Auden's "Musée des Beaux Arts" accompanied by a
                    reproduction of Brueghel's <title level="m">Landscape with the Fall of
                        Icarus</title>, the relationship between the visual and verbal has not been
                    emphasized in undergraduate higher education, where science textbooks are likely
                    to have more illustrations than literature anthologies. How do humanities
                    teachers dramatize the connection between the visual and verbal for our students
                    and thus help our students understand the interrelatedness of the linguistic and
                    graphical arts? How do we revive their own creativity and cognitive skills with
                    words and pictures? After all, our students probably illustrated their own words
                    in elementary school but are seldom invited to do so in college.</p>
                <p>New technologies, in particular the World Wide Web, are bringing words and
                    pictures together for us and our students in ways that might bring those
                    connections back to our college classrooms. Document design now extends beyond
                    the one-inch margin requirements of MLA student manuscripts. Instead, our
                    students are learning with us about screens and color and negative space and
                    visual communication as integral to rather than decoration for the word.</p>
                <p>We will describe undergraduate literature and writing projects in which
                    student-generated words and graphics are central to communication of ideas. In
                    these projects, publication of their compositions on the Internet encourages
                    students to reflect on the connections between technology and art, word and
                    image, private and public writing, and their own creative and critical
                    processes. These projects give students opportunities to perceive and to
                    communicate visually, orally, textually, kinesthetically - in other words, they
                    provide multisensory learning experiences.</p>
                <p>Theoretical foundations for student-generated compositions in this project come
                    not only from Golahny, Krieger, and Mitchell but also from chapters on teaching
                    in <title level="m">Learning Literature in an Era of Change: Innovations in
                        Teaching</title>. Terri Pullen Guezzar ("From Short Fiction To Dramatic
                    Event: Mental Imagery, The Perceptual Basis of Learning in the Aesthetic Reading
                    Experience") applies the theories of Rudolf Arnheim and Allen Paivio, who argue
                    that privileging the verbal over the visual limits our cognitive development and
                    that separating verbal from visual perception fragments our understanding of and
                    communication about literature. Pedagogical theory is featured in "Figuring
                    Literary Theory and Refiguring Teaching: Graphics in the Undergraduate Literary
                    Theory Course," where Marlowe Miller maintains, "Graphics help students
                    conceptualize complex and abstract theories so that they can identify the
                    central concepts and assumptions of those theories."</p>
                <p>Two accessible resources for teachers thinking about integrating new media into
                    undergraduate education also are useful for encouraging colleagues to
                    incorporate the Internet as a learning environment and to make computer-mediated
                    student projects integral to the learning process. In <title level="m">Seven
                        Principles for Good Practice in Undergraduate Education: Implementing with
                        Technology</title>, Arthur W. Chickering and Stephen C. Ehrmann describe
                    ways the following tenets can be incorporated into computer-mediated
                    instruction: contacts between students and faculty, reciprocity and cooperation
                    among students, active learning techniques, prompt feedback, time on task, high
                    expectations, respect for diverse talents and ways of learning. Cooperation
                    among students and active learning techniques as well as respect for diverse
                    learning styles all are supported by multisensory student online publications in
                    which students create original works of art or combine text and images to learn
                    and to communicate their learning.</p>
                <p>Additional encouragement for teachers and students comes from <title level="m"
                        >Engines of Inquiry: Teaching, Technology, and Learner-Centered Approaches
                        to Culture and History</title> by Randy Bass, director of the American
                    Crossroads Project, Georgetown University. Bass identifies "six kinds of quality
                    learning" that "information technologies can serve to enhance": distributive
                    learning, authentic tasks and complex inquiry, dialogic learning, constructive
                    learning, public accountability, and reflective and critical thinking. Once
                    again, collaborative student-generated projects are emphasized as effective
                    learning strategies.</p>
                <p>Teaching at two quite different types of institutions, Donna at a large
                    multicampus urban-suburban open admissions community college on the Atlantic
                    coast of Virginia and Art at a selective land-grant university emphasizing
                    agriculture, engineering, science, and technology in the foothills of South
                    Carolina, we both have found that opportunities to compose and share text and
                    images has enriched learning for undergraduates. Examples from the work of our
                    own students and of our colleagues' students will demonstrate some ways that
                    novice scholars learn "from the inside out" by creating, selecting, combining,
                    and manipulating text and images in electronic environments.</p>
                <p>Using either a live Internet connection (preferable) or files on disk displayed
                    through a Web browser as well as an overhead projector, we will present and
                    analyze student work that illustrates the conjunction of visual and verbal
                    knowledge and its significance for introducing undergraduate students to the
                    artistic life of their community and to computer-mediated composing as well as
                    for fostering their creative and cognitive development.</p>
                <p>&lt;<ptr
                        target="http://onlinelearning.tc.cc.va.us/faculty/tcreisd/projects/achalc2k/"
                    /> &gt;</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Rudolf</forename>
                                    <surname>Arnheim</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Visual Thinking</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Berkeley</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>University of California Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1980">1980</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Randy</forename>
                                    <surname>Bass</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="u">Engines of Inquiry: Teaching, Technology, and
                                Learner-Centered Approaches to Culture and History</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1998">16 Oct. 1998</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr
                                target="http://www.georgetown.edu/crossroads/guide/engines3.html"
                            />&gt;.</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Arthur</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Chickering</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Stephen</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">C.</forename>
                                    <surname>Ehrmann</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Implementing the Seven Principles: Technology as
                                Lever</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j"/>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol"/>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp"/>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.aahe.org/technology/ehrmann.htm"
                            />&gt;.</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Arthur</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Chickering</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Zelda</forename>
                                    <surname>Gamson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Seven Principles for Good Practice in Undergraduate
                                Education</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">AAHE Bulletin</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol"/>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp"/>
                                <date when="1987">March 1987</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Amy</forename>
                                    <surname>Golahny</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">The Eye of the Poet: Studies in the Reciprocity of the
                                Visual and Literary Arts from the Renaissance to the Present</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Terri</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">Pullen</forename>
                                    <surname>Guezzar</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">From Short Fiction To Dramatic Event: Mental Imagery,
                                The Perceptual Basis of Learning in the Aesthetic Reading
                                Experience</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Dona</forename>
                                    <surname>Hickey</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Donna</forename>
                                    <surname>Reiss</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Learning Literature in an Era of Change: Innovations in
                                Teaching</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Sterling, VA</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Stylus</publisher>
                                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">74-86</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Murray</forename>
                                    <surname>Krieger</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Ekphrasis: The Illusion of the Natural Sign</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Baltimore</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1992">1992</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Marlowe</forename>
                                    <surname>Miller</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Figuring Literary Theory and Refiguring Teaching:
                                Graphics in the Undergraduate Literary Theory Course</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Dona</forename>
                                    <surname>Hickey</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Donna</forename>
                                    <surname>Reiss</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Learning Literature in an Era of Change: Innovations in
                                Teaching</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Sterling, VA</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Stylus</publisher>
                                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">61-73</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">W.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">T.</forename>
                                    <surname>Mitchell</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Picture Theory</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>University of Chicago Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1995">1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Allan</forename>
                                    <surname>Paivo</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Imagery &amp; Verbal Processes</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Mahwah, NJ</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates</publisher>
                                <date when="1971">1971</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
