<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main"> Academic Collaboration On Line: The SOL as a Case
                    Study</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="middle">Ross</forename>
                        <surname>Scaife</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Kentucky</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Raphael</forename>
                        <surname>Finkel</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Kentucky</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">William</forename>
                        <surname>Hutton</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">College of William and Mary</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Elizabeth</forename>
                        <surname>Vandiver</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Maryland</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Patrick</forename>
                        <surname>Rourke</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Nashoba Valley Technical Vocational High School</name>,
                            USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Digital Resources</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>Despite the Herculean labors and remarkable achievements of the Perseus Project,
                    today many essential resources for the study of the ancient Mediterranean world
                    still remain accessible only to a few specially trained researchers because they
                    have never been translated into modern languages or provided with sufficiently
                    convenient interpretive materials. Our current work represents the first step in
                    an attempt to address that problem by engaging the efforts of scholars
                    world-wide in the production of substantial translated and annotated texts that
                    will be made available exclusively through the internet. The text with which we
                    have chosen to begin is the Byzantine encyclopedia known as the Suda, a 10th
                    century C.E. compilation of material on ancient literature, history, and
                    biography. A massive work of about 32,000 entries, and written in often dense
                    Byzantine Greek prose, the Suda is nevertheless an invaluable source for many
                    details that would otherwise be unknown to us about Greek and Roman antiquity,
                    as well as an important text for the study of Byzantine intellectual
                    history.</p>
                <p>The sheer size of the Suda (the most up-to-date printed edition runs to four
                    hefty and tightly-printed volumes) and its lack of literary charm are sufficient
                    to explain why no individual scholar has committed his or her career to
                    translating it. Many scholars, each taking responsibility for selected entries
                    or series of entries, can get the job done more effectively. Moreover, the vast
                    breadth of subject matter covered by the Suda would challenge the expertise of
                    even the most widely competent modern scholar. By sharing the load, individual
                    translators can focus on those entries from the Suda that pertain to their area
                    of expertise, thus producing better translations and more informed
                    annotations.</p>
                <p>Begun in January of 1998, the Suda On Line (SOL) already involves the
                    contributions (or promised contributions!) of nearly seventy scholars throughout
                    the world. The general plan of the project is to assemble an SGML-encoded
                    database, searchable and browsable on the web, with continuously improved
                    annotations, bibliographies and hypertextual links to other electronic resources
                    in addition to the core translation of entries in the Suda. Individual work
                    becomes available on the web as soon as possible, with only the minimum
                    necessary proofreading and editorial oversight. A diverse board of area
                    specialists will eventually edit every entry, altering and improving the content
                    as needed. The display of each entry will include an indication of the level of
                    editorial scrutiny it has received. We want to encourage the greatest possible
                    participation in the project and the smallest possible delay in presenting a
                    high quality resource to a wide public readership.</p>
                <p>Collaborative efforts always generate questions about how to allot proper credit
                    to individual contributors. Given the searchable database format of the SOL it
                    is a simple matter for translators and editors to print out their own
                    peer-reviewed work for inclusion in, for example, promotion and tenure dossiers.
                    Moreover, we anticipate that translators will establish hypertextual links
                    directly from their on-line rèsumès to their contributions in the SOL.</p>
                <p>Our choice of the web as the medium for publishing the SOL is crucial to the
                    project's conception. This format has many advantages, of which accessibility
                    and ease of use are perhaps the most obvious. Users can access the project's web
                    page and search the database in various ways: by strings in a full text search,
                    with Boolean combinations, by keyword, by translator, etc. The display for each
                    entry includes the headword in English and Greek (options for displaying Greek
                    suit the requirements of different systems), the translation, footnotes and
                    other annotations, and bibliographical references (where available and/or
                    appropriate). The SOL's interface automatically generates links to the complete
                    Greek text of the entry from the database of the Thesaurus Linguae Graecae and
                    to the relevant entries in Liddell and Scott's Greek Lexicon (via the Perseus
                    Project); further links to both external and internal resources can be created
                    in the text of the translations and the annotations.</p>
                <p>The on line format also allows for continuous editing and updating, which is
                    crucial to our conception of the SOL as an evolving work forever subject to
                    improvement by many hands. We believe that the specific ways in which we have
                    enabled the process of editorial control and our plans for further enhancements
                    are among the most sophisticated now available in any on-line scholarly
                    resource: every aspect of communication among contributors is handled via
                    web-based forms and dynamically generated e-mail. Any work goes onto the web
                    immediately; individual authors do not have to wait for publication until the
                    entire project is finished (as in the case of a print format). Thus, the project
                    can be immediately useable even while the bulk of the work remains to be done.
                    Furthermore, entries can be updated immediately whenever new information
                    arises.</p>
                <p>Perhaps the most exciting aspect of a web-based publication such as the SOL,
                    however, is the potential for interoperability with other projects. The SOL is
                    one of many projects involved in a consortial arrangement at the Stoa, which is
                    actively exploring ways to promote the interconnection of distributed projects.
                    Although our goal is to have as much annotation and documentation as possible
                    within the SOL database itself, our translation takes advantage of the natural
                    capacity of web-based documents to be linked with other sources of electronic
                    information. We want the SOL to be one important model for a new generation of
                    hypertext commentary on ancient texts; a SOL fully outfitted with links to other
                    electronic resources will provide not only the Greek text of the Suda and its
                    translation, but also a wide variety of links to other relevant Suda entries, to
                    the ancient vitae of any major authors or other figures mentioned in the text,
                    to all the testimonia, and to essays by various scholars (both public-domain and
                    new essays written specifically for this project). The same model may be used
                    for on-line commentaries for other ancient works, which may in turn be linked to
                    relevant entries in the SOL. The prospects for the on-line production of true
                    variorum editions are vast and exciting.</p>
                <p>This copious annotation and hypertextuality will ensure that the on-line Suda is
                    useful not only to classical scholars and historians, but to a much wider
                    audience as well. Students at various levels will be able not merely to read the
                    translated Suda entries but to understand their wider context. A bare
                    translation would be of little use to most non-specialists, but a translation
                    provided with a rich supply of links to other ancient works and to modern
                    scholarship will open a whole world of information to the interested beginner
                    and can still be a valuable research tool for the trained specialist.</p>
                <p>The goal of the SOL is not just to be a useful tool for researchers, but to
                    provide a sophisticated model for the kind of scholarship made possible by open
                    source technology and the internet, scholarship that is cooperative rather than
                    solitary, communal rather than proprietary, worldwide rather than localized and
                    evolving rather than static. Accordingly we aim at two principal results: in
                    addition to our development of the Suda On Line itself as a respected scholarly
                    resource, we plan to make a generalized, well-documented version of our software
                    freely available for other scholars to adapt for their own purposes.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References:</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">A.</forename>
                                    <surname>Adler</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Suidae Lexicon</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">(5 volumes)</biblScope>
                                <pubPlace>Stuttgart</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1928">1928-1938</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">Perseus: An Evolving Digital Library of Ancient Greece </title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/"/>&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">The Stoa: A Consortium for Electronic Publication in
                                the Humanities</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.stoa.org/"/>&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">The Suda On Line</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.stoa.org/sol/"/>&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">Thesaurus Linguae Graecae</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr target="http://www.uci.edu/~tlg"/>&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>

</TEI>
