<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">ACAD - a Cambridge Alumni Database</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">John</forename>
                        <surname>Dawson</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Cambridge</name>, UK <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Digital Resources</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>1. Introduction</head>
                    <p>From 1922-27 Venn published the four volumes of Part I of <title level="m"
                            >Alumni Cantabrigienses, a biographical list of all known students,
                            graduates and holders of office at the University of Cambridge, from the
                            earliest times to 1751</title>. This was followed from 1940-54 by the
                        six volumes of Part II, covering 1752-1900. Subsequent archival research
                        unearthed much more detail, and many more names, for the period up to 1500,
                        and in 1963 Emden published his two-volume <title level="m">A Biographical
                            Register of the University of Cambridge to 1500</title>. Together, these
                        twelve volumes cover approximately 180000 names, with some overlap.</p>
                    <p>It goes without saying that all this information is of the utmost importance
                        for historical research, covering as it does a large proportion of the
                        religious, legal, administrative, medical, academic, and royal appointments
                        in Britain, the Empire, and the Colonies, as well as many other countries. A
                        good deal of social history is also included, albeit patchily.</p>
                    <p>However, all these publications have a great defect for research: there is no
                        index. Also, since Venn's work, many corrections and additions to the
                        information have come to light, and without the incorporation of this new
                        material it is easy to be misled by the original books. So, to find all the
                        Vicars of Trumpington mentioned by Venn and Emden requires an exhaustive
                        search of twelve large volumes and many card indexes of Addenda and
                        Corrigenda.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2. Database</head>
                    <p>We therefore set about the creation of an on-line database to make all this
                        information accessible. Other sources, such as the Tripos Lists (lists of
                        degrees awarded), and College Registers (especially those of the women's
                        colleges, which were ignored by Venn) have been included. It is envisaged
                        that the database will be made freely available for public searching on the
                        World Wide Web, though it is not yet clear what mechanism for searching will
                        be provided.</p>
                    <p>Similar projects, based on Emden's Registers for Oxford and Cambridge, were
                        undertaken in the 1970s.[3] In those studies, the data was highly coded to
                        allow easy cross-tabulation. Several important articles using results from
                        the studies have appeared.[1][2][4] There is, however, no resource for
                        Oxford comparable to that of Venn for the later period.</p>
                    <p>For many years we were unable to find a simple and reliable way to put the
                        data into machine-readable form. Venn's books are in small hand-set type,
                        printed on thick rough paper, and are full of italics, all of which proved
                        completely intractable to the OCR packages available until recently.</p>
                    <p>By chance, just as we had found suitable technology to cope with Venn's
                        printing, we discovered that Ancestry.com had already prepared
                        machine-readable versions of most of the volumes of Part II.</p>
                    <p>Negotiations between Cambridge University Press (the copyright holders) and
                        Ancestry.com soon led to an agreement to share this data, as their product
                        and ours are for essentially different purposes, theirs being mainly
                        accessed for genealogical information. Ancestry.com are also planning to put
                        the remaining volumes of Venn into the computer, and to make the data
                        available to us.</p>
                    <p>Emden's <title level="m">Biographical Register</title>, the Tripos Lists, and
                        the registers of the women's colleges have proved relatively easy to read
                        using OCR and the services of an excellent methodical proofreader.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3. Structural Analysis</head>
                    <p>A typical entry from Emden looks like this (with references abbreviated):<lb/>
                        <eg>Dawson, John (Dauson).* 
                            Entered in C.L. ET 1484;
                            grace that study for 6 yr in C. and Cn.L. suffice for entry in Cn.L. gr. 1488-9;
                            Inc. C.L., adm. June 1490 [Ref_1];
                            D.C.L. 
                            R. of Debden, Essex, clk, adm. 17 May 1484; 
                            till death [Ref_2].
                            Died 1492. 
                            Will dated 10 Aug. 1492; proved 12 Feb. 1493 [Ref_3]. 
                            Requested burial in S. Michael's, Cambridge.</eg><lb/>
                        and has the following structure:<lb/>
                        <eg>heading 
                            event 1 
                            event 2 ... </eg><lb/> 
                        where each event in general comprises:<lb/>
                        <eg>topic 
                            type 
                            place 
                            date(s) 
                            reference(s)</eg></p>
                    <p>The initial form of the database is an SGML-tagged text, from which
                        subsequent databases and searching/sorting structures can easily be
                        obtained.</p>
                    <p>My first attempts at analysis were written in Perl, a widely available
                        string-handling language which allows complex regular expressions. (A
                        regular expression is just a pattern which is used to match parts of the
                        data and extract those parts which can vary.) It soon became apparent that
                        the complexity of the regular expressions needed for the recognition of
                        large-scale structures such as these entries uses too much memory in Perl,
                        and the programs frequently failed.</p>
                    <p>At Cambridge we have a locally-written programmable text editor called NE
                        which has good regular expression handling. It may seem a retrograde step to
                        use a one-off local program like NE in preference to a widely used standard
                        such as Perl, but in our case only the <emph rend="italics">product</emph>
                        (the database) is useful; the <emph rend="italics">process</emph> used to
                        make the product is different for each text analysed, so the ephemeral
                        nature of the analysis programs is not significant.</p>
                    <p>Events will in general be split over several input lines, so it was first
                        necessary to combine the lines of a complete paragraph into a single line,
                        then to split them at punctuation such as semicolons, and to put references
                        on separate lines.</p>
                    <p>It was clear that some type of formal, structured, but readable output would
                        be needed in the first instance. This could then be converted automatically
                        as input to any required database package. SGML provides an adequate
                        structure for these needs, and is widely used by publishers of
                        machine-readable databases.</p>
                    <p>First attempts at analysis were very heuristic, but served to clarify the
                        problems in my mind. Writing a DTD for the SGML structure was then very
                        helpful, as it forced me to take decisions about nesting of fields, etc. </p>
                    <p>Initially, my regular expressions tried to match complete events, including
                        place names and dates, but two problems arose: the programs ran out of time
                        or store, or NE's regular expression processor found the structure too
                        complex to analyse. Automatically pre-tagging identifiable structures such
                        as dates and place names enabled simpler regular expressions to be written.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>4. Results</head>
                    <p>A discussion of the complete DTD and the analytical processes used will be
                        presented. Various types of results will be used to illustrate the
                        processing, including complete updated entries amalgamated from all sources,
                        and statistics about certain types of event such as religious appointments.
                        The Figures (see below) are based on only part of the data (one volume of
                        Venn), as the analysis is not yet complete. The Figures should be used with
                        care, because although they represent approximately ten thousand
                        individuals, they are constrained by having surnames beginning 'Abbey' to
                        'Challis', so a preponderance of one family attending one college may skew
                        the results.</p>
                    <p>Figure 1 will show the range of ages at admission to all colleges, and holds
                        no surprises. Age at admission is given in only about half of the entries in
                        Venn. Most of the older admissions are men who have already been ordained. </p>
                    <p>Figure 2 will show the admissions to the two largest colleges, Trinity and St
                        John's, between 1752 and 1900, and illustrates the general increase in size
                        of all the colleges, and hence the whole university, in that period.</p>
                    <p>Figures 3 and 4 will show the admissions to other colleges during that period
                        (except Downing, Selwyn, and the women's colleges, which were not founded
                        until the nineteenth century). The outstanding feature of Figure 4 is the
                        dramatic increase in admissions at Queens' College from 1821-1830.</p>
                    <p>Figure 5 will show the number of religious appointments (Curate, Vicar, or
                        Rector) per county.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>5. References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="1">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >H.</forename><surname>Ashton</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Oxford's Medieval Alumni</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Past &amp; Present</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">74</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">3-35</biblScope>
                                <date when="1977">1977</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="2">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >H.</forename><surname>Ashton</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">G.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >D.</forename><surname>Duncan</surname></name></author>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">T.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >R.</forename><surname>Evans</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">The Medieval Alumni of the University of
                                Cambridge</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Past &amp; Present</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">86</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">1</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">9-86</biblScope>
                                <date when="1980">1980</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter" n="3">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <surname>Evans</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">The Analysis by Computer of A.B. Emden's Biographical
                                Registers of the Universities of Oxford and Cambridge</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">N.</forename>
                                    <surname>Bulst</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.-P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Genet</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Medieval Lives and the Historian: Studies in Medieval
                                Prosopography</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Kalamazoo</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Medieval Institute Publications, Western Michigan
                                    University</publisher>
                                <date when="1986">1986</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter" n="4">
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">R.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle"
                                    >B.</forename><surname>Dobson</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Recent Prosopographical Research in Late Medieval
                                English History: University Graduates, Durham Monks, and York
                                Canons</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">N.</forename>
                                    <surname>Bulst</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">J.-P.</forename>
                                    <surname>Genet</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Medieval Lives and the Historian: Studies in Medieval
                                Prosopography</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Kalamazoo</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Medieval Institute Publications, Western Michigan
                                    University</publisher>
                                <date when="1986">1986</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
