<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">SMART Project: Methods for Computer-based Research of
                    Premodern Chinese Texts</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <surname>Wittern</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Chung-Hwa Institute of Buddhist Studies</name>, Taiwan
                            <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item>Stylistics</item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p>This presentation will start with a look at some of the problems encountered so
                    far in a number of projects that tried to apply TEI [TEIP3] markup to premodern
                    Chinese Buddhist texts. I have been working with the TEI Guidelines for more
                    than seven years and published the first text, rather heavily marked up in TEI
                    fashion, in 1995<note n="1">1. The Chan-Buddhist genealogical history <title
                            level="m">Wudeng Huiyuan</title> (first printed in 1253) on the ZenBase1
                        CD-ROM, see [App et al 95]. </note>. Since then I became involved with some
                    other projects digitizing Chinese Buddhist texts, most prominently the work by
                    the Chinese Buddhist Electronic Texts Association (CBETA)<note n="2">2. The
                        CBETA project website (mostly in Chinese) is at &lt;<ptr
                            target="http://ccbs.ntu.edu.tw/cbeta."/>&gt;</note>. We now have about
                    200 MB of texts basically marked up<note n="3">3. This basic markup follows the
                        general ideas lined out in [Wit96].</note> according to the Guidelines.</p>
                <p>All of these projects worked from printed editions published 80-100 years ago.
                    One of the most obvious problems we encountered is the large amount of
                    non-standard characters found in these texts, but TEI and SGML in general is
                    quite able to handle this elegantly - nevertheless there are some important
                    details that should be noted<note n="4">4. I will not go into detail for this
                        audience, but some references to these problems can be found in the work by
                        the Chinese Characters Analysis Group. More recently, we based our efforts
                        on the work done by the Mojikyo Font Institute in Japan &lt;<ptr
                            target="http://www.mojikyo.gr.jp"/>&gt;.</note>. Some of the more subtle
                    problems involve structural elements specific to texts of the sphere of Chinese
                    cultural influence. Examples of these elements include the notion of a scroll,
                    that is carried over from the time when the documents were actually written on
                    scrolls, but still mark divisions in the printed editions. Being based on the
                    physical medium, they fall into a similar category as the LB, PB and MILESTONE
                    elements in TEI, but they are usually associated with some other heading-like
                    text, colophons and the like. While this could be taken care of with the FW in
                    some way, we decided to come up with our own solution, which was to introduce a
                    new element, JUAN, (Chinese for scroll) and encode the information therein.
                    Other structural elements that presented difficulties include colophons or other
                    backmatter-like text at the end of a scroll, but in the middle of a DIV element
                    that continued on the next scroll and sound glosses in the text.</p>
                <p>A second part of this presentation will give an overview of the recent
                    developments in the SMART (System for Markup and Retrieval of Texts)
                        project<note n="5">5. The project website is at &lt;<ptr
                            target="http://www.chibs.edu.tw/~chris/smart/"/>&gt;.</note>. This
                    project aims at providing a working environment for research and markup on East
                    Asian texts by utilizing the TEI Guidelines (see also [SpMcQ91]) and other
                    international, open standards. The environment tries to enable network based
                    collaboration and layered, private markup added to a central repository of
                    texts, but it is intended to make it possible to use it on stand-alone machines
                    without a live connection to the Internet. So far, the basic framework has been
                    outlined and some of the utilities built. Originally, the plan was to develop
                    this into a collection of open modules, that can interact through an open
                    protocol in the spirit of presentations at ACH/ALLC 1999 by Michael
                    Sperberg-McQueen, Jon Bradley and others. However, since such a protocol
                    specification is far from being finalized, I found that I would rather have a
                    concrete implementation to play with and to iron out problems. I therefore
                    recently decided to build the tools I would need on top of the Zope<note n="6"
                        >6. For more information on Zope see &lt;<ptr target="http://www.zope.org"
                        />&gt;.</note> Web-Application platform. This is an OpenSource&amp;trade;
                    project build mainly with Python, implementing an object-oriented database and a
                    complete framework for developing dynamic Web-Applications. It has a strong
                    support for XML and related standards and thus seems especially suited for the
                    purpose at hand. All the methods are exposed through a URL-based interfaced, but
                    also callable through XML-RPC.</p>
                <p>The presentation in the context of the ALLC/ACH conference aims at contributing
                    to a discussion of how such an open framework can be implemented, while at the
                    same time showing some of the problems that arise when dealing with East Asian
                    languages (see [ApWi96] and [CCAG80-85]). East Asian languages do not normally
                    mark the word boundaries and even the definition of a word is highly disputed
                    among linguists. In this situation, a list of all occurring words in the manner
                    of a word-wheel cannot be applied. Additionally, the texts used here contain
                    markup of textual variants, which complicates the creation of an index.
                    Furthermore, different representations of the same character in machine-readable
                    encodings have to be accounted for. An indexing method that takes these problems
                    into account and also provides an abstraction from indexing of actual low-level
                    locations in the text has been developed<note n="7">7. More information can be
                        found in [Wit99]</note>.</p>
                <p>The SMART project will be utilized in two different contexts:<list>
                        <item>1. As a retrieval and interface engine for the Buddhist text database
                            produced by the Chinese Buddhist Electronic Text Association. SMART will
                            allow for retrieval with enhanced queries, and add markup based on these
                            queries, thus providing a powerful way to gradually enrich the
                            markup.</item>
                        <item>2. As the central research platform for a research project of texts of
                            the Chan school in Chinese Buddhism. A smaller corpus of texts is here
                            used for building not only text with rich markup, but also supporting
                            databases of proper names, sites and historical dates to allow for
                            knowledge-base centered retrieval of the texts.</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>A demonstration of both applications will be given in this presentation.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>References</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="[ApWi96]">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Urs</forename>
                                    <surname>App</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                                    <surname>Wittern</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">A New Strategy for Dealing with Missing Chinese
                                Characters</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Humanities and Information Processing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">10</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">52-59</biblScope>
                                <date when="1996">February 1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="[App et al 95]">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Urs</forename>
                                    <surname>App</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Fujimoto</forename>
                                    <surname>Kumiko</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                                    <surname>Wittern</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>

                            <title level="m">ZenBase CD1</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Kyoto</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>International Institute for Zen Buddhism</publisher>
                                <date when="1995">1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book" n="[CCAG80-85]">
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name type="org">Chinese Character Analysis Group</name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Chinese Character Code for Information
                                Interchange</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">Vol. I-III</biblScope>
                                <pubPlace>Taipeh</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1980">1980</date>
                                <date when="1982">1982</date>
                                <date when="1985">1985</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="[CaZa91]">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Nicola</forename>
                                    <surname>Calzolari</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Antonio</forename>
                                    <surname>Zampolli</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Lexical Databases and Textual Corpora: A Trend of
                                Convergence between Computational Linguistics and Literary and
                                Linguistic Computing</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Research in Humanities Computing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">1</biblScope>
                                <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Clarendon</publisher>
                                <date when="1991">1991</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">273-307</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book" n="[Lanca91]">
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Ian</forename>
                                    <surname>Lancashire</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">The Humanities Computing Yearbook 1989-90 A
                                Comprehensive Guide to Software and other Resources</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Clarendon</publisher>
                                <date when="1991">1991</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="[Latz92]">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Hans-Walter</forename>
                                    <surname>Latz</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Entwurf eines Modells der Verarbeitung von
                                SGML-Dokumenten in versionsorientierten Hypertext-Systemen Das
                                HyperSGML Konzept</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <edition>Diss.</edition>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Technische Universität Berlin</publisher>
                                <date when="1992">1992</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter" n="[Neum96]">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Michael</forename>
                                    <surname>Neuman</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">You Can’t Always Get What You Want: Deep Encoding of
                                Manuscripts and the Limits of Retrieval</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Research in Humanities Computing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">5</biblScope>
                                <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Clarendon</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">209-219</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter" n="[Rob94]">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Peter</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">M.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">W.</forename>
                                    <surname>Robinson</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Collate: A program for Interactive Collation of Large
                                Textual Traditions</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="m">Research in Humanities Computing</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">3</biblScope>
                                <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Clarendon</publisher>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">32-45</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter" n="[SpMcQ91]">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">Michael</forename>
                                    <surname>Sperberg-McQueen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Text Encoding and Enrichment</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Ian</forename>
                                    <surname>Lancashire</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">The Humanities Computing Yearbook 1989-90 A
                                Comprehensive Guide to Software and other Resources</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
                                <date when="1991">1991</date>
                                <biblScope type="pp">503f</biblScope>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book" n="[TEIP3]">
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">C.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">Michael</forename>
                                    <surname>Sperberg-McQueen</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <editor>
                                <forename type="first">Lou</forename>
                                <surname>Burnard</surname>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and
                                Interchange</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Chicago, Oxford</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="[Wit93]">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                                    <surname>Wittern</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Chinese Character Encoding</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Electronic Bodhidharma</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">Nr. 3</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">44-47</biblScope>
                                <date when="1993">July 1993</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="[Wit94]">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                                    <surname>Wittern</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Code und Struktur: Einige vorläufige Überlegungen zum
                                Aufbau chinesischer Volltextdatenbanken</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Chinesisch und Computer</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">Nr. 9</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">S. 15-21</biblScope>
                                <date when="1994">April 1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="[Wit95a]">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                                    <surname>Wittern</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">The IRIZ KanjiBase</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Electronic Bodhidharma</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">Nr. 4</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">58-62</biblScope>
                                <date when="1995">June 1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle" n="[Wit95b]">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                                    <surname>Wittern</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Chinese character codes: an update</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Electronic Bodhidharma</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">Nr. 4</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue"/>
                                <biblScope type="pp">63-65</biblScope>
                                <date when="1995">June 1995</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="[Wit96]">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                                    <surname>Wittern</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Minimal Markup and More - Some Requirements for Public
                                Texts</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">Conference presentation at the 3rd EBTI meeting on
                                April 7th, 1996 in Taipei, Taiwan</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="[Wit99]">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                                    <surname>Wittern</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">SMART: Format of the Index Files</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first"/>
                                    <surname/>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m"/>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace/>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1999">1999</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>Technical note published on the Internet at &lt;<ptr
                                target="http://www.chibs.edu.tw/~chris/smart/smindex.htm"/>&gt;.
                            (First published July 20th, 1999, last revised January 10th, 2000)
                        </note>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct n="[Yas96]">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Koichi</forename>
                                    <surname>Yasuoka</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Yasuko</forename>
                                    <surname>Yasuoka</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Kanjibukuro</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Kyoto</pubPlace>
                                <publisher/>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <note>&lt;<ptr
                                target="http://m-media.kudpc.kyoto-u.ac.jp/~yasuoka/kanjibukuro/"
                            />&gt;</note>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
