<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/remote/homed/saschmid/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">The Style-Marker Mapping Project: a Rationale and
                    Progress Report</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Joseph</forename>
                        <surname>Rudman</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">Carnegie Melon University</name>, USA <email/>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2000">2000</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Glasgow</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2000</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Jean</forename>
                        <surname>Anderson</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Amal</forename>
                        <surname>Chatterjee</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                        <surname>Kay</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Margaret</forename>
                        <surname>Scott</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <head>Introduction</head>
                    <p>This paper explicates the what, why, and how of a substantially completed but
                        ongoing project to identify and categorize all style-markers in written
                        English that are quantifiable (e.g. type/token ratios, word length
                        distributions, word length correlations, hapax legomena).</p>
                    <p>Section I treats the what - defining the project - and then addresses the why
                        - the rational for the project. Section II outlines the how. Section III
                        gives a status report of the project.</p>
                    <p>Although the final mapping will have value in various disciplines (e.g.
                        stylistics, corpus linguistics, computational linguistics, and computer
                        science), the impetus for the project is from non-traditional authorship
                        attribution studies. Non-traditional attribution practitioners define style
                        in the seemingly narrow framework of only those stylistic traits that are
                        quantifiable.</p>
                    <p>The main hypothesis behind this project (and all non-traditional authorship
                        attribution studies) is that every author has a verifiably unique style. If
                        we look at style as an organism, style-markers are its genetic material -
                        making this project analogous to the human genome project. This analogy is
                        somewhat of a stretch because each style-marker is analyzed by an
                        independent study, whereas all of the loci of an autoradiogram are obtained
                        in one scientific analysis.</p>
                    <p>The identification of a quantifiable style-marker does not necessarily mean
                        that that particular style-marker should be included in an authorship study
                        (e.g. the orthography might be dictated by an editor or typesetter).</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Section I</head>
                    <p>This section treats the what - defining the project - and then moves into the
                        why of the project.</p>
                    <p>A short overview of what is in this section follows:</p>
                    <p>The style-marker mapping project is a study to identify every style-marker in
                        written English that can be quantified. The project began in a preliminary
                        fashion in 1983 when I started recording the various style-markers that were
                        used in non-traditional authorship attribution studies so that I could use
                        them in my studies of the canon of Daniel Defoe. The project continued in
                        this vein (along with a few attempts on my part to come up with "new"
                        style-markers) until five years ago when I realized the importance of
                        identifying all of the quantifiable style-markers.</p>
                    <p>There is no one style-marker or even a combination of several style-markers
                        that have proven to be a definitive discriminator in all non-traditional
                        authorship studies. What works in one case often does not work in others.
                        Word length distributions and sentence length distributions are two examples
                        of style-markers that seemingly work in some cases but not in others. The
                        idea is to look at style as a combination of all of the quantifiable
                        style-markers and then to do the analysis as if each style-marker were a
                        locus in the autoradiogram (See RUDMAN for a more detailed explanation). </p>
                    <p>Another reason for using all of the quantifiable style-markers is to
                        eliminate any charges of statistical cherry-picking.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Section II</head>
                    <p>This section treats the how. References to all of the literature and
                        techniques will appear in the final report. For example, HOLMES, DELCOURT,
                        and ELLIOTT AND VALENZA are three of the references under non-traditional
                        authorship studies.</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>1) Search the literature, e.g.:<list type="bulleted">
                                <item>Stylistics</item>
                                <item>Grammar</item>
                                <item>Non-traditional Authorship Attribution Studies</item>
                                <item>Linguistics<list type="bulleted">
                                        <item>Computational</item>
                                        <item>Corpus</item>
                                        <item>Text</item>
                                    </list></item>
                                <item>Rhetoric</item>
                                <item>Discourse Analysis</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>2) Query the practitioners in all of the above fields, e.g.:<list
                                type="bulleted">
                                <item>Professor Erwin R. Steinberg of Carnegie Mellon for
                                    stylistics,</item>
                                <item>Professor Paul G. Hopper of Carnegie Mellon for Grammar - all
                                    of the active practitioners in the non-traditional authorship
                                    studies.</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>3) Establish a clearinghouse on a web page that allows anyone to query
                            the up-to-date mapping and allows anyone to suggest "new" quantifiable
                            style markers that would be added by the curator. This will lead to a
                            continually updated list. Negotiations are under way to make this site
                            an extension of the Carnegie Mellon University English Web Site.</item>
                        <item>4) Use various strategies to identify new style-markers. This is where
                            the innovative work supplements the drudge work, e.g.:<list
                                type="bulleted">
                                <item>Neural networks</item>
                                <item>Pattern searching programs</item>
                                <item>Brainstorming sessions</item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Section III</head>
                    <p>This section gives a status report of the project and reports a timeline for
                        its "completion." References will be given for all of the style-markers in
                        the final report, e.g. MOSTELLER AND WALLACE is one of the function word
                        references. Only a few representative examples of each section are listed
                        for this abstract.</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>1) META-WORD<list type="bulleted">
                                <item>Paragraph</item>
                                <item>Sentence</item>
                                <item>Phrases</item>
                                <item>Clauses</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>2) WORD<list type="bulleted">
                                <item>Part of speech</item>
                                <item>Ratios</item>
                                <item>Positions</item>
                                <item>Function Words</item>
                                <item>Most frequent words</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>3) SUB-WORD<list type="bulleted">
                                <item>Syllables</item>
                                <item>Letters</item>
                                <item>Phonemes</item>
                                <item>Morphemes</item>
                            </list></item>
                        <item>4) OTHER<list type="bulleted">
                                <item>Punctuation</item>
                                <item>Imagery</item>
                                <item>Rhetorical Devices<list type="bulleted">
                                        <item>Zeugma</item>
                                        <item>Chiasmus</item>
                                    </list></item>
                            </list></item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Conclusion</head>
                    <p>The questions, "Can this project ever be completed?", and, "Is the number of
                        style-markers infinite?", are addressed.</p>
                    <p>The success of this project will not solve all of the problems of
                        non-traditional authorship studies. This project does not address the
                        problems that gender, genre, time constraints, or conscious vs. unconscious
                        style bring to the table. Nor does it treat the problem of lemmatization. </p>
                    <p>Identifying the style-markers is only a small part of the overall problems
                        with non-traditional authorship attribution studies. The statistics that
                        should be used in any study for each of these style-markers and the
                        statistics for combining all of the markers into a "final" answer is the
                        subject of another ongoing project.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="biblioraphy">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <author><name><forename type="first">Christian</forename>
                                <surname>Delcourt</surname></name></author>
                            <title level="a">Stylometry</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="u">ALLC-ACH 1994, École Normale Supérieure de Lettres et Sciences Humaines, Paris, 14-15</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace></pubPlace>
                                <publisher></publisher>
                                <date when="1994">1994</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr></biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Ward</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">E.</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">Y.</forename>
                                    <surname>Elliott</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Robert</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">J.</forename>
                                    <surname>Valenza</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">And Then There Were None: Winnowing the Shakespeare
                                Claimants</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Computers and the Humanities (CHum)</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">30</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">3</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">191-245</biblScope>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">David</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">I.</forename>
                                    <surname>Holmes</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">The Analysis of Literary Style - A Review</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Journal of the Royal Statistical Society, Series
                                A</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">148</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">Part 4</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">328-341</biblScope>
                                <date when="1985">1985</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Fredrick</forename>
                                    <surname>Mosteller</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">David</forename>
                                    <forename type="middle">L.</forename>
                                    <surname>Wallace</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Applied Bayesian And Classical Inference: The Case Of
                                The "Federalist Papers."</title>
                            <edition>2nd Edition</edition>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Springer-Verlag</publisher>
                                <date when="1984">1984</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="journalArticle">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Joseph</forename>
                                    <surname>Rudman</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">The State of Authorship Attribution Studies: Some
                                Problems and Solutions</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">Computes and the Humanitis (CHum)</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">31</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="issue">4</biblScope>
                                <biblScope type="pp">351-365</biblScope>
                                <date when="1997">1997</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
