<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="file:/Users/saraschmidt/Desktop/teiConferenceAbstracts.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" rend="paper">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title level="a" type="main">That Was Then: Canonicity in the Trésor</title>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Susy</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">C.</forename>
                        <surname>Santos</surname>
                        <affiliation>
                            <name type="org">University of Manitoba</name>
                            <email>umsant06@UManitoba.CA</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
                <author>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Paul</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Fortier</surname>
                        <affiliation>Centre on Aging, <name type="org">University of Manitoba</name>
                            <email>Fortier@cc.umanitoba.ca</email>
                        </affiliation>
                    </name>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <date when="2002">2002</date>
                <publisher>
                    <name>University of Tübingen</name>
                </publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tübingen</pubPlace>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title level="m">ALLC/ACH 2002</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>editor</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Harald</forename>
                        <surname>Fuchs</surname>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <forename type="middle"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first"/>
                        <surname/>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>encoder</resp>
                    <name>
                        <forename type="first">Sara</forename>
                        <forename type="middle">A.</forename>
                        <surname>Schmidt</surname>
                    </name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="http://hcmc.uvic.ca/teiJournal/topicKeywords/">
                    <list>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                        <item> </item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <p>The Trésor de la Langue Française (TLF) corpus (<ptr
                            target="http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/efts/ARTFL/databases/TLF/index.html"
                        />) was set up almost half a century ago. When one reads the description of
                        how this was done, the distance becomes evident. Professor Imbs quite openly
                        admits that the goal is to reflect "elite" usage of the French language;
                        texts were chosen after consultation of histories of literature, some of
                        which were quite dated even then (Imbs 1971, I, xv-xl). Considerations of
                        inclusiveness, of representativity, as discussed in Scholes (1992) or von
                        Hallberg (1984), do not seem to have concerned the committee which finalized
                        the corpus. One is entitled to wonder to what extent this corpus represents
                        the interests of scholars of French literature a half century later.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Purpose</head>
                    <p>It is legitimate to evaluate the extent to which the texts included in the
                        TLF database do represent important trends in French literature, as judged
                        by what interested scholars at the time it was constituted, and as reflected
                        by what has interested scholars of the present.</p>
                    <p>More specifically, it is possible to see whether the choices embodied in the
                        TLF reflect what scholars of the time judged important by comparing the
                        choices of texts in a given genre - the novel - to the number of lines
                        dedicated to the authors chosen for the TLF found in the <title level="m"
                            >Oxford Companion to French Literature</title> (Harvey &amp;
                        Heseltine 1959).</p>
                    <p>Similarly, the <title level="m">MLA Bibliography</title> (<ptr
                            target="http://www.mla.org/publications/bibliography"/>) provides online
                        data showing the number of publications in the modern languages and
                        literatures for the periods 1963-90 and 1991 to the present. A comparison
                        between the number of publications mentioning a novelist found in this
                        bibliography and the number of texts by the same novelist in the TLF will
                        show the extent to which choices made by the TLF group have been confirmed
                        by the interest of later scholars. Given the volume of data involved these
                        questions must be dealt with using statistics.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Data</head>
                    <p>A subset of the TLF database was chosen for analysis: novels published
                        between 1789 and 1954 (See Table 1). The name of the novelist (Author) and
                        the number of novel texts included in the database for each writer (Texts)
                        was recorded, along with the publication date of the text included in the
                        database (Pub Date). When more than one novel by a given author is in the
                        TLF Pub Date records the date of the earliest one published. In cases where
                        authors were better known for other genres rather than prose fiction, they
                        were removed from the test data, because they would be a source of
                        ambiguity.</p>
                    <p>These numbers were compared to three series of test data. The column OxC in
                        Table 1 records the number of lines devoted to the novelist and to the
                        included novels by that author which are found in the <title level="m"
                            >Oxford Companion to French Literature</title> (Harvey &amp;
                        Heseltine 1959), a volume contemporary with the formation of the TLF
                        database. Columns MLA 1 and MLA 2 record the number of articles mentioning
                        the novelist or work(s) found in the MLA online bibliography of learned
                        articles dealing with language and literature. MLA 1 covers the period
                        1963-1990 and MLA 2, 1991-2000.</p>
                    <p>For analysis the entire set of 128 frequencies concerning novels was used.
                        Subsequently subsets of roughly equal numbers of authors were generated,
                        covering the periods 1789-1859 (33), 1860-1907 (35), 1908-23 (25), and
                        1925-54 (35).</p>
                    <table rows="13" cols="6">
                        <row>
                            <cell role="label">Author</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Pub Date</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Texts</cell>
                            <cell role="label">OxC</cell>
                            <cell role="label">MLA 1</cell>
                            <cell role="label">MLA 2</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Abellio</cell>
                            <cell>1946</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>0</cell>
                            <cell>9</cell>
                            <cell>0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>About</cell>
                            <cell>1857</cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>14</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Adam</cell>
                            <cell>1902</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>25</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>4</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Alain-Fournier</cell>
                            <cell>1913</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>93</cell>
                            <cell>29</cell>
                            <cell>4</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Ambriere</cell>
                            <cell>1946</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>0</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>0</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Aragon</cell>
                            <cell>1936</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>25</cell>
                            <cell>445</cell>
                            <cell>305</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Arland</cell>
                            <cell>1929</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>0</cell>
                            <cell>37</cell>
                            <cell>4</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Ayme</cell>
                            <cell>1933</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>7</cell>
                            <cell>38</cell>
                            <cell>9</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Baillon</cell>
                            <cell>1927</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>0</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                            <cell>6</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Balzac</cell>
                            <cell>1824</cell>
                            <cell>16</cell>
                            <cell>577</cell>
                            <cell>1986</cell>
                            <cell>781</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Barbusse</cell>
                            <cell>1916</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>16</cell>
                            <cell>52</cell>
                            <cell>13</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Barres</cell>
                            <cell>1888</cell>
                            <cell>5</cell>
                            <cell>87</cell>
                            <cell>93</cell>
                            <cell>72</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Method</head>
                    <p>A glance at the frequencies of the texts recorded for individual authors
                        shows a large number of authors with one text, and a very small number of
                        authors with ten or more, a distribution pattern quite familiar to people
                        who work with word frequencies in natural languages. These data do not form
                        the familiar bell-shaped curve typical of the Gaussian or normal
                        distribution.</p>
                    <p>Since the data are not normally distributed, Pearson's product-moment
                        correlation analysis cannot legitimately be used on them. Similarly these
                        data would produce a very high proportion of predicted values smaller than 5
                        in a contingency table for a chi-squared analysis, so this method cannot be
                        employed. The usual way of handling such a problem (grouping the data) is
                        not appropriate, since it is the treatment of individual authors which is of
                        interest.</p>
                    <p>Spearman's rank correlation analysis does not require normally distributed
                        data nor predicted frequencies greater than five; it has been chosen as the
                        primary analytic technique and applied in pairwise fashion to the data, and
                        to the four subsets of the data. At the same time, jackknifed outlier
                        analysis provided by JMP-IN (Sall &amp; Lehman 1996) has been used to
                        identify authors whose distribution varies the most from the trends in the
                        data.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Results</head>
                    <p>Taken as a whole, the data show a high degree of correlation among the number
                        of texts in the TLF database, the number of lines in the <title level="m"
                            >Oxford Companion</title>, and the two sets of MLA Bibliographic data
                        (See Table 2). There is no measurable probability that these correlations be
                        the result of chance alone.</p>
                    <table cols="4" rows="7">
                        <head>Table 2: Nonparametric Measure of Association</head>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Variable by</cell>
                            <cell>Variable</cell>
                            <cell>Spearman Rho</cell>
                            <cell>Prob&gt;|Rho|</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>OxC</cell>
                            <cell>Texts</cell>
                            <cell>0.5528</cell>
                            <cell>&lt;.0001 </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>MLA_1</cell>
                            <cell>Texts</cell>
                            <cell>0.4475</cell>
                            <cell>&lt;.0001 </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>MLA_1</cell>
                            <cell>OxC</cell>
                            <cell>0.6101 </cell>
                            <cell>&lt;.0001 </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>MLA_2</cell>
                            <cell>Texts</cell>
                            <cell>0.4047</cell>
                            <cell>&lt;.0001 </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>MLA_2</cell>
                            <cell>OxC</cell>
                            <cell>0.5918</cell>
                            <cell>&lt;.0001</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell>MLA_2</cell>
                            <cell>MLA_1</cell>
                            <cell>0.9084 </cell>
                            <cell>&lt;.0001</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>The data divided into four sections show a higher correlation in the earlier
                        period than in the later, and outliers in the earlier two periods tend to be
                        the greats of French literature, like Balzac, Stendhal and Zola, whereas in
                        the later periods they tend frequently to be novelists whose literary
                        fortunes are less obvious, like Simenon or Giono.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Conclusion</head>
                    <p>The analysis carried out on the number of novel texts included in the TLF
                        database shows that the texts included tend to be about the same as what
                        might have been included if a different team of scholars had drawn it up in
                        the late 1950s. Similarly the works included do correspond - particularly
                        for the period up to 1908 - to what scholars of our day find sufficiently
                        interesting to be included in their published studies.</p>
                    <p>It is thus reasonable to conclude that the TLF database is a valid
                        representation of important French literary texts for the period from 1789
                        to 1954. As more and more databases become commercially available, the
                        method presented here for validating the representativity of a database
                        using readily-available online bibliographical information would seem to
                        have a significance which goes beyond modern French literature.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                    <p>The research reported here has been supported by the Social Sciences and
                        Humanities Research Council of Canada (SSHRCC) under grant number
                        410-98-1348.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Bibliography</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Paul</forename>
                                    <surname>Harvey</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <forename type="first">J.</forename>
                                <forename type="middle">E.</forename>
                                <surname>Heseltine</surname>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">The Oxford Companion to French Literature</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>Oxford UP</publisher>
                                <date when="1959">1959</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Paul</forename>
                                    <surname>Imbs</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Le Trésor de la Langue Française: Dictionnaire de la
                                langue du XIXe et du XXe siècle</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <biblScope type="vol">16 vols.</biblScope>
                                <pubPlace>Paris</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>CNRS</publisher>
                                <date when="1971">1971</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">John</forename>
                                    <surname>Sall</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Ann</forename>
                                    <surname>Lehman</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">JMP Start Statistics</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Belmont, Ca.</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>SAS Institute</publisher>
                                <date when="1996">1996</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="bookChapter">
                        <analytic>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Robert</forename>
                                    <surname>Scholes</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="a">Canonicity and Textuality</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <editor>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Joseph</forename>
                                    <surname>Gibaldi</surname>
                                </name>
                            </editor>
                            <title level="m">Introduction to Scholarship in Modern Languages and
                                Literatures</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>MLA</publisher>
                                <date when="1992">1992</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                    <biblStruct type="book">
                        <monogr>
                            <author>
                                <name>
                                    <forename type="first">Robert</forename>
                                    <surname>von Hallberg</surname>
                                </name>
                            </author>
                            <title level="m">Canons</title>
                            <imprint>
                                <pubPlace>Chicago</pubPlace>
                                <publisher>U of Chicago P.</publisher>
                                <date when="1984">1984</date>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
